<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>96dc4904b9cc00a0a3f39a11a714f8115dc232de3e927fe59bfae3f4d3de6512</job>
    <base_name>62po</base_name>
    <doi>10.1002/dir.20046</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 1</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER o ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">MOHANBIR SAWHNEY</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">GIANMARIO VERONA</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">AND EMANUELA PRANDELLI</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6" confidence="possible">I n the networked world, firms are recognizing the power of the Internet as a co-creation.We has for platform customer impacted for co-creating the engagement, outline process the value of distinctive collaborative including with customers.We capabilities interactivity, r o innovation—a of focus the enhanced Internet key on how process reach, as the a platform Internet in persis- value tence, Internet-based ry process to collaborative involvement engage case speed, studies (back customers (high innovation and end mechanisms. to flexibility, illustrate reach vs. in front collaborative vs. at different high the and end We integrated suggest discuss richness).We stages) stages product how h t and that and of these for firms present the innovation systematic differing New mechanisms can two Product use through detailed levels usage these Development can of of capabilities a explorato- customer variety Internet- facilitate of © JOURNAL based for industry 2005 managerial Wiley collaborative and OF Periodicals, INTERACTIVE Eli practice Lilly from innovation Inc. and the and MARKETING academic pharmaceutical Direct mechanisms—Ducati Marketing research VOLUME A u Educational industry. on 19 / collaborative NUMBER We Foundation, from derive 4 / the AUTUMN innovation. implications Inc. motorbike 2005 Published online in Wiley InterScience (www.interscience.wiley.com). DOI: 10.1002/dir.20046</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8" confidence="possible">MOHANBIR SAWHNEY is the McCormick Tribune Professor Technology at the Kellogg School of Management, Northwestern University; e-mail: <email id="7">mohans@kellogg</email>. northwestern.edu GINAMARIO VERONA is an Associate Professor of Management at Bocconi University and Senior Lecturer at SDA Bocconi School of Management, Milan, Italy; e-mail: gianmario.verona @sdabocconi.it EMANUELA PRANDELLI is an Associate Professor of Management at Bocconi University and Senior Lecturer at SDA Bocconi School of Management, Milan, Italy; e-mail: emanuela.prandelli@ sdabocconi.it</abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx9">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62po.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62po.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="10">1</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="11">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="12">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="2" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="2" column="1">In an increasingly dynamic business environment, firms are realizing the importance of collaboration for creating and sustaining competitive advantage. Collaboration with partners and even competitors has become a strategic imperative for firms in the networked world of business (Brandeburger &amp; Nalebuff, 1996; Gulati, Nohria, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Zahere, 2000</xref>; Iansiti &amp; Levien, 2004). More recently, scholars in strategy and marketing have focused on collaboration with customers to co-create value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Prahalad &amp; Ramaswamy, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Thomke &amp; von Hippel, 2002</xref>). While collaboration with customers can span several business processes, one of the most important is collaborating to create value through product innovation. In this paper, we examine how the Internet can serve as a powerful platform for enabling collaborative innovation with customers. While customer interaction has always been important in new product development (von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 1988</xref>), the widespread deployment of the Internet has greatly enhanced the ability of firms to engage with customers in the product innovation process (Dahan &amp; Hauser, 2002). By creating virtual customer environments (Nambisan, 2002), firms can tap into customer knowledge through an ongoing dialogue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Sawhney &amp; Prandelli, 2000</xref>). The Internet enhances the ability of firms to engage customers in collaborative firms interactions Through ties, customer tomers and through it the to allows with the the transform scope knowledge shared into use creation firms innovation of of a persistent independent the interests. to episodic tap shared of firm’s virtual in into dialogue several And and among the customer third-parties customer it social one-way extends ways. with groups h t dimension interactions customers. communi- the It customer to of allows reach reach cus- of non-customers—competitors’ customers. Firms nisms mechanisms product ful they best for, practice enable. can to and development facilitate use the While firms differ a nature variety are in optimistic collaborative process terms leveraging of the of customers of that Internet-based claims customer the the they innovation. stage Internet abound or are u A interactions prospective of most the on mecha- to These use- how con- new nect with customers, there is little formal research on collaborative innovation. We take a first step in this area by identifying several Internet-based mecha-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> nisms for collaborative innovation. We present detailed case studies to show how best-practice firms are using these mechanisms to improve the speed, cost, and quality of their new product development process. Through these in-depth case studies, we o derive as The trasting the paper implications lessons traditional is organized for organization for perspectives academics as follows. and on and customer We strategy, managers. begin involve- by as well con- ment in the new product development process with the emerging perspective on customer collaboration in virtual environments. Next, we describe a number of Internet-based mechanisms for engaging cus- P tomers vance product customer studies of in of innovation these product best involvement. mechanisms practice innovation, process, firms We and at then that and different for have highlight present different implemented stages two the levels of rele- case the of some of these mechanisms—Ducati Motor from the motorcycle industry, and Eli Lilly from the pharmaceutical industry. We conclude by summarizing implications for academics and managers.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="2" column="2">CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION: THE TRADITIONAL PERSPECTIVE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="2" column="2">In literature and in practice, product innovation is generally conceptualized as a five-stage New Product Development (NPD) process—ideation, concept development, product design, product testing, and product introduction (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Ulrich &amp; Eppinger, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Urban &amp; Hauser, 1993</xref>). Firms use varied techniques to solicit customer input in order to create better new products faster. In the front-end stages of the NPD process (ideation and concept development), firms use market research techniques like focus groups, customer surveys and quantitative techniques like conjoint analysis to create, test, and refine new product concepts. At later stages in the NPD process, firms use quality function deployment, prototyping, product testing, and test marketing to design and improve products and marketing strategies for new product introduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Urban &amp; Hauser 1993</xref>). While firms have always sought to hear the “voice of the customer,” customers have traditionally tended to play a passive role as recipients of the firm’s innovation activities. Firms seek to improve fit between their<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> offerings and customer needs by surveying customers and importing knowledge from leading-edge customers into the firm (von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 1988</xref>). Drivers of the firm’s innovation success include the firm’s market sensing ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Day, 1994</xref>), effective R&amp;D and manufacturing routines right 1999). ment implicitly balance The (Hayes, traditional of views organizational Wheelwright, value perspective creation &amp; competences Clark, on and customer 1988) innovation o (Verona, engage- and the as a firm-centric activity, with most information flowing in a one direction from the customer to the firm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Prahalad &amp; Ramaswamy, 2004</xref>). When customers are viewed as passive recipients of innovation, the firm has a oped there and like limited enhance participant within is little understanding their ideas. emphasis observation specific Further, on of contexts customer iterative if one (Leonard excludes of dialogue knowledge experience; P &amp; costly Rayport, to devel- refine tools and 1997), there is little opportunity to engage communities of customers to tap into the social aspects of knowledge. Finally, the firm tends to be biased towards listening to its current customers, and even among these, to its most important customers.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="26" page="2" column="2">2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="27" page="2" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28" page="3" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 3</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="29" page="3" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="34" page="3" column="1">CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN VIRTUAL ENVIRONMENTS: THE CO-CREATION PERSPECTIVE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="3" column="1">The Internet is an open, cost-effective and ubiquitous network (Afuha, 2003). These attributes make it a global medium with unprecedented reach, contribut- ing to reduce constraints of geography and distance (Cairncross, 1997). Further, the Internet potentially allows firms to overcome the trade-off between richness and reach because it is interactive in nature ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Evans &amp; Wurster, 1999</xref>). In the physical world, com- municating (and absorbing) rich information requires physical proximity or personal interactions with customers. These constraints limit the number of customers that the firm can dialogue with. On the other hand, the firm can interact with a large number of customers through customer surveys, but this type of interaction does not allow for a rich dialogue. However, Internet-based virtual environments allow the firm to engage a much larger number of customers without significant compromises on the richness of the interaction. Virtual environments also increase the speed and the persistence of customer engagement. Due to cost and<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> effort limitations, traditional market research techniques like focus groups and surveys are limited in terms of the frequency with which firms can engage with customers, and the time taken to solicit customer input. In virtual environments, customer interactions can happen in real-time, and with a much higher frequency. The physical and cognitive effort needed for the firm as well as customers is far lower in virtual environments, so the interactions can be more frequent and more persistent. The key con- straint is the willingness of customers to participate in interactions and privacy concerns that may limit the depth of information that customers may be will- ing to share with the firm. Virtual environments also enhance the firm’s capacity to tap into the social dimension of customer knowledge, by enabling the creation of virtual communities of consumption (Kozinets, 1999). Customers self- select themselves and participate in spontaneous conversations. This makes them highly involved in a joint experience of co-creation. Finally, the Internet increases the flexibility of customer interactions: customers can vary their level of involvement over time and across sessions. For instance, customers partici- pating in a discussion group or a community can choose their level of involvement (Hagel &amp; Singer, 1999; Hoffman &amp; Novak, 1996). Firms can allow customers to interact with them at different levels of h t commitment payoffs level over The persistence, virtual benefits extended time. of environments from participation for collaborative increased based interaction, reach, on enhanced as combine speed, their their innovation and interests and commitment they to interactivity, higher produce can with and modify flexibility customers: three perceived increases greater their key of u A scope The knowledge two-way about groups increases (a) and the richness direction of and of direction the dialogue because customers. import audience learn of of the of interaction helps virtual from to communication; interaction; (Table The an firms individual richness interactive communities 1). evolves to and progressively of (b) (c) customers the dialogue. from of the the interaction customers intensity size one-way learn This and and help firms to tap into social knowledge in addition to individual customer knowledge. Virtual customer communities allow the firm to immerse itself into the<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> experiential contexts of customer consumption on an ongoing basis, rather than on an episodic basis that characterizes traditional ethnographic customer research. Further, the size and scope of the audience increases because the firm can participate in interactions mediated by third parties that are able to reach non-customers or prospective customers who may not have the virtual by rather well directly helping firm as any than environments as social as relationship firms well having knowledge knowledge, as to through a engage biased augment with import, customers third-party and point the customer to firm, to of gather involve view. in or mediators. conversations h t may collaboration individual In customers summary, perceive as</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="38" page="3" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="39" page="3" column="2">3</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="40" page="4" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 4</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="4" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="4" column="1">MAPPING INTERNET-BASED COLLABORATION MECHANISMS TO THE NPD PROCESS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="4" column="1">Internet-based collaboration mechanisms can be mapped to the NPD process based on two important dimensions—the nature of customer involvement that is needed, and the stage of the NPD process at which the customer involvement is desired. In terms of the nature of customer involvement, Internet-based collaboration mechanisms can be classified into mechanisms that emphasize reach versus mechanisms that emphasize richness of the interaction. While the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> reach-versus-richness trade-off is not as severe on the Internet as it is in the physical world, it still is a deci- sion that the firm needs to make. The firm may want to emphasize richness over reach if it is interested in generating ideas and insights, while it may value reach over richness if it is interested in validating hypotheses with a representative sample of customers. Internet-based collaboration mechanisms may also be classified in terms of their usefulness at different stages of the NPD process: some mechanisms are more relevant at the front-end stages of the process (idea generation and concept development stages), while others are better applied to enhance the back-end stages of the process (product design and testing). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> shows a variety of Internet-based mechanisms classified on these two dimensions. u A Mechanisms NPD tomers instance, ideas well tion) its customer Web as in process for can site. a services Ben dedicated new advisory contribute Firms that &amp; include products Jerry (especially are can panels area useful their allows also suggestion (prepackaged called to engage own at packaging customers solicit the “Suggest-a-Flavor” innovative customers early boxes customers’ ice and to stages where contribute cream) ideas. distribu- through of feed- cus- For the on as back on a systematic basis, such as those created by Hallmark (the Hallmark Idea Exchange) and by Procter &amp; Gamble (the P&amp;G Advisors program). To<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> make suggestion boxes and customer advisory panels effective, it is essential for the firm to establish clear rules regarding intellectual property rights, so that the company can use the innovative ideas suggested by customers, while customers can benefit through financial or non-monetary incentives. Well-designed incentives have been found to remarkably improve collaborative idea generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Toubia, 2004</xref>). New product development at the early stages can also benefit from online virtual communities, which bring together users who have common interests and engage in online conversations to share their experiences with like-minded people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Hagel &amp; Armstrong, 1997</xref>; Kozinets, 1999). Virtual communities are a rich source of socially generated knowledge. This socially generated knowledge provides insights that complement the knowledge generated from individual customer interactions. These insights cannot be gleaned from one-on-one interactions with customers. To facilitate customer participation in virtual communities, the firm may rely on intangible incentives like recognition and opinion leadership in consumer-oriented markets, while it may need to provide economic incentives in business-to-business market settings. Members of virtual communities often show a high degree of involvement and often even specific technical competence—as in the case of communities of<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> video game enthusiasts (e.g., www.Idsoftware.com) and networking engineers (e.g., Cisco Networking Professionals Forum). Reward mechanisms can also be introduced to encourage the most competent users to compete in Internet-based innovation market- o places 2003). third communities parties, to These solve of marketplaces because experts. specific of problems Examples their are ability typically (Nalebuff of such to innovation hosted aggregate &amp; Ayres, by marketplaces include HelloBrain (www.hellobrain. com), Experts Exchange (www.experts-exchange. com), NineSigma (www.ninesigma.com) and Yet2.com (www.yet2.com). P Turning front simplest collaborative Rangaswamy, end to and of mechanisms innovation—are the most &amp; Gupta, NPD traditional process, that 2001). provide a use In popular online the of validation the search surveys—the tool Internet (Burke, for at suc- the for cessful new product ideas, firms seek to reduce uncer- tainty by interacting directly with customers to understand their needs and preferences. Online surveys are most useful for understanding articulated or explicit customer needs and in situations where the firm can accurately identify target audiences for its offerings. Firms can create online concept labs to test customer reactions to new products that are current- ly under development, as Volvo has done with its Volvo Concept Lab (www.conceptlabvolvo.com). And h t firms that boards instance, allow tomer to development. uncover monitor can firms buzz to firms harness identify for trends to millions Another monitor specific like online trends that IntelliSeek of technique product customer blogs, market may in customer Web be categories (www.intelliseek.com) that intelligence sentiment useful sites, is behavior. useful and for and and services bulletin product brands at cus- For the early stages is the technique of listening in (Urban &amp; u A Hauser, ing and tomers needs. accuracy, among based been information virtual done implementations To attributes identify 2004), consumers the in experts same industries which product exchanged of new end who can involves concepts of and product be provide ranging conjoint between asked with recording concepts that advice a to from analysis, higher individual make best to and cameras using meet trade-offs help degree analyz- as users Web- their cus- has to of toys (Dahan &amp; Hauser, 2002). For instance, General Motors has created a Web-based tool (www. autochoiceadvisor.com) that helps customers to<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> choose the right automobile for them, based on their preferences. This tool allows GM to collect quantitative data on customer preferences from hundreds of thousands of customers on an ongoing basis, at very low incremental cost. This data helps product develop- ers ing the Moving to development with understand to changing the later and how market stages refinement customer of conditions, the preferences NPD of new process, and o concepts. can are virtual evolv- guide environments allow customers to directly participate in designing and developing new products. Toolkits for user innovation can be created to exploit new technolo- gies such as computer simulation in order to make NPD 2002). online an Using online faster toolkit For tools example, design from and called less the environment Webench National Webench costly (Thomke (webench.national.com), Semiconductor site, for circuit circuit &amp; P von designers. designers offers Hippel, an can design and test new circuits, and can have proto- type power supply kits delivered anywhere in the world in 48 hours. Customer toolkits can be expanded to allow customers to customize products and even develop them through mechanisms of repeated trial and error. They can even be used to get customer suggestions on patents for finished products. And customer toolkits can be used by communities of customers to build upon designs that have been created by other customers, as in the case of designing new games for mobile concept op expression communities dreds to (von collaboratively new Krogh and phones products of peer-to-peer even in &amp; run the (Piller, von thousands concept by develop form Hippel, and Ihl, customer of has for Fuller, open-source new of 2003). the found individual products collaboration users &amp; its In Stotko, most that these mechanisms— h t and contributors allow significant 2004). systems, to services devel- hun- The individual users do not develop the product by them- selves—as the ual effort. Moving the several uct tions individual contributions and back-end involve options to market in mechanisms stages the level. to testing. mass to application engage a Rather, of community-based the customization The that customers NPD they most facilitate of customer make process, advanced to small support u A validation of development firms toolkits products applica- individ- prod- have at at (Randall, Terwiesch, &amp; Ulrich, 2004), such as the personalized sneakers that can be purchased on Nike’s<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Web site. Digital environments can also significantly contribute to simplifying and making the new product testing stage more efficient before launching a product on the market, as Google does by beta testing new ideas in the Google Labs section of its Web site. Web- based beta testing is very common in the software, e-commerce, and video game industries. New tech- nologies such as rapid prototyping, simulation, and combinatorial methods make it possible to generate and test different product versions quickly and cheap- ly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Thomke, 1998</xref>). The Internet makes it possible to simultaneously test different product configurations (virtual product testing) as well as different marketing mixes to complement the supply (virtual market testing) in order to choose the best solution with direct collaboration of the end-customers (Dahan &amp; Srinivasan, 2000).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="47" page="4" column="2">4</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="48" page="4" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49" page="5" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 5</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50" page="5" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="51" page="5" column="1">Applicability to Stage of New Product Development Process Collaboration Deep/ High Richness Web-based Suggestion Virtual Advisory (Ideation communities Front-end panels and Box idea Concept) markets (Product Toolkits Open-source Web-based for Design Back-end users f o patent mechanisms and innovation markets Testing) Information Pump Nature of Broad/ Reach High Market Web-based Listening On line intelligence survey in techniques conjoint services analysis Virtual Mass Web-based product customization product r prototyping testing of the Virtual market testing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="52" page="5" column="1">FIGURE 1 Mapping Internet-Based Collaboration Mechanisms Based on Nature of Collaboration and Stage of NPD Process</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="57" page="5" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="58" page="5" column="2">5</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="59" page="6" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 6</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="60" page="6" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" page="6" column="2">CASE STUDIES ON INTERNET- ENABLED CUSTOMER COLLABORATION IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="6" column="2">There is a paucity of academic literature on the experiences of firms that have successfully used the Internet as a platform for collaborative innovation. Hence, we adopt an exploratory approach to derive patterns and implications. We follow the logic of grounded theory (Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967), by employ- ing a multiple-case-study methodology (Eisenhardt, 1989; Miles &amp; Huberman, 1994). In the tradition of other qualitative approaches used in business research, we rely on a small number of highly visible examples of the object of our inquiry to develop our insights (Pettigrew, 1990). The two companies we study are a European firm in the automotive industry and a U.S. firm in the pharmaceutical industry. We selected these companies because they are leading- edge practitioners of Internet-based collaborative innovation. The case studies were informed by in- depth interviews with senior managers and a detailed search of publicly available information from financial statements, internal documents and industry publications. Interviewees within each firm were chosen on the basis of their specialized knowledge and experience, following a key informant approach (Kumar, Stern, &amp; Anderson, 1993; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Philipps, 1981</xref>). In- depth interviews with executives and managers were conducted during 2003 and early 2004 at Ducati and<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Eli Lilly. The approach was nondirective, based on individual semi-structured interviews (McCracken, 1990) that are flexible yet are controlled (Burgess, 1982). We used an open-ended approach to question- ing so that we could identify emergent themes in collaborative innovation.<marker type="block"/> In the motorcycle industry, companies create competitive advantage not only based on technical product superiority, but also on their ability to interact with their customers and create deep customer relationships Motorcycles motorcycle munity innovative across among product companies are their the a features. entire customers lifestyle-intensive need lifecycle to foster in addition a of sense P product, ownership. to offering of com- so Ducati Motor, a manufacturer of motorcycles head- quartered in Italy, was quick to realize the potential for using the Internet to engage customers in its new product development efforts. The company set up a Web division and a dedicated Web site, www.ducati. com, in early 2000, inspired by the Internet sales of the MH900evolution, a limited-production motorcycle. Within 30 minutes, the entire year’s production was sold out, making Ducati a leading international e-commerce player. Since then, Ducati has evolved its site that Community Ducati keting” and be the a Internet “fan.” to major had that create and 160,000 Ducati asset management “customer” management to a enhance robust of considers registered the company virtual with the has has the replaced “fan the users become customer community and words experience.” as it the of strives so h t “community” words community July central of fans Ducati to “mar- 2004. use at to involves its fans on a systematic basis to reinforce the places, Ducati community uct munity Ducati well as opment well development as life uses as broad the process directly at style function events, Web-based the customer and (Figure back-end and influences Ducati’s and is the tightly mechanisms 2). engagement, the fan stages desired people involvement connected product of its brand to that at support product development. with the u A express in image. front-end the the rich devel- prod- com- The the as Virtual communities play a key role in helping Ducati to explore new product concepts. Ducati has promoted<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and managed ad-hoc online forum and chats for over three years to harness to strong sense of community among Ducati fans. Over 200 messages are posted every day on Ducati forums. The most popular discussion is about products and the biking experience. These conversations are highly relevant for Ducati to better understand customer needs and gain insights into new products and services. Ducati also realized that a significant number of its fans spend their leisure time not only riding their bikes, but also main- taining and personalizing their bikes. As a result, Ducati fans have deep technical knowledge that they are eager to share with other fans. To support such knowledge sharing, the company has created the “Tech Cafè,” a forum for exchanging technical knowledge. In this virtual environment, fans can share their projects for customizing motorcycles, provide suggestions to improve Ducati’s next generation products, and even post their own mechanical and technical designs, with suggestions for innovations in aesthetic attributes as well as mechanical functions. To support their ideas, they can attach text or graphics files. In the customer service area of the Web site, individual bikers can self- signal their technical competencies and solve mechanical problems posted by other Ducati fans. These technical forums help Ducati to benefit from spontaneous customer knowledge sharing, and help the company to glean suggestions for improving its marketing, engineering, and customer support. They have also significantly reduced the number of calls coming into<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> the company’s call centre, resulting in significant sav- ings on customer support. While not all fans participate in the online forums, those who do participate provide rich inputs for exploring new product concepts and technical solutions. tomer buy mandated products These loyalty, the forums they because involvement helped also its help to fans of create. all Ducati are the more Ducati’s company’s to o enhance motivated CEO prod- cus- has to uct engineers in customer relationship management activities. They are required to periodically interview selected Ducati owners from the company’s online database of registered fans—adding a physical dimension attempts gather Ducati and bulletin community ideas to to go boards from the beyond managers as hosted online broad its customer on interaction. an monitor independent audience base relevant P Ducati as in Web an possible. forums effort sites, also such as the community of American Ducati fans hosted on Yahoo!. Ducati community managers take part in these forums, sometimes identifying themselves and remaining anonymous at other times, based on the nature of the topics and the sensitivity of the audience to privacy concerns. Ducati managers also monitor vertical portals created for bikers, including Motorcyclist.com and Motoride.com; micro-sites that aggregate specific segments of interest to Ducati’s. These include sites that aggregate women bikers— the cling—as Ducati munities Ducati partnership to members. tap fastest into brand. fans.” well that Through their growing with And For as have the community “girlfriends, Ducati instance, these demographic apparel lifestyle monitors diverse Ducati fashion and wives, associations interact group other has “listening company and entered h t virtual in mothers with with motorcy- DKNY posts,” into their com- the of a Ducati tries to ensure that it expands its peripheral vision tomers The nisms not broader insights, product ences. ideas necessarily As beyond we it market concepts Ducati a can describe and testimony reach its insights uses for own represent and are directly Ducati online to customers, rich to that the quantify and ability by products. customer emerge the itself. creative, and preferences of customer from Ducati beyond To surveys u A but validate the to the they mecha- prefer- of to create cus- test the its do an ongoing customer dialogue and create a sense of engagement with its fans, Ducati gets extraordinary<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> response rates, often in excess of 25% when it surveys its customers. Ducati uses customer feedback for activities that go beyond product development. The layout and functions of Ducati’s Web site are shaped by customer feedback, and the guests for live chats on the Web site are also chosen based on customer input. To encourage customers to participate in online surveys, Ducati has created a sophisticated incentive system based on both tangible and intangible payoffs. For instance, every week Ducati launches a competition called “Name the picture”: participants have to guess what part of the bike an image shows to enter the “Hall of Desmohead-Fame.” In these events, technical knowledge becomes a passport to enter a highly qualified virtual community of fans. Ad-hoc surveys are also created to get feedback about specific products and strategic directions for marketing activities like new product concept selection. For instance, three concepts for the new Ducati Sport Classic were presented on October 2003 simultaneously at the International Exhibition of Tokyo as well as on Ducati’s Web site. No engineering components had been developed yet at that time. Fans were asked to provide their feedback about the opportunity to produce the new Sport Classic. Almost 15,000 answers were collected in five days, with more than 96% rec- ommending the production of all the three models. Ducati’s new Web site, which went online in September 2004, features a new registration form where fans can share personal information about their experience with Ducati motorbikes and allows them to provide suggestions for accessories that can complement the biking experience. Similar features are also featured on the customized MyDucati pages that each fan can create and personalize. Ducati also pursues Internet-based customer collaboration at the back end of its NPD process. Virtual communities play an important role at the product design and market testing stages. For instance, in early 2001, the community managers of Ducati.com identified a group of customers on its Web site that had particular- ly strong relationships with the company. They decid- ed to transform such customers into active partners, involving them in virtual teams that cooperate with professionals from R&amp;D, Product Management, and Design of Ducati Motors. These virtual teams of customer work with the company’s engineers to define attributes and technical features for the “next bike.”<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Through this mechanism, Ducati recognizes opinion leadership and provides recognition for members within its customer community. Contests are also used in order to enhance and reward customer involvement. For instance, the company created a competition called “Design lenged by ning offering ideas to Your interpret artistic were Dream selected as in well Ducati,” any by as form a technical team where their that “Dream fans ideas. o included were The Ducati,” chal- win- the CEO, the chief manager of the Design Department, and the Creative Director. Future contests will focus on specific areas of interest for the company, to solicit solutions to specific mechanical market. and instance, annual and offline gathering aesthetic The during mechanisms company the of problems—a Ducati World also for plans fans customer Ducati form from to integrate of Week all engagement. Web-based over P (WDW), the its online world idea For an in Italy, the company organizes the Ducati Garage Challenge. The purpose of this gathering is to allow bike owners to show how they transformed their Ducati based on their skills and creativity. In the 2004 gathering, more than 20 motorcycles constructed by Ducati were remodelled by the imagination of customers who worked in their workshops to transform their dreams into reality. The winners are selected through votes cast by official Ducati riders, as well as by the company’s technical and styling directors. Notwithstanding product er sands Ducati current review tested sample of online proposed motorbikes. designs and pages of future customers. in illustrating are the the product reviewed Ducati form Within origin Ducati’s of modifications the of bike virtual the and the mechanical owners tested virtual fans “next prototypes. can bike,” with h t that discuss community, features surf a all can broad- thou- They new and be of can can and personalizing answer technical even also can such ask experts vote personalize questions, Ducati to their reject within bikes technicians products the proposed the Internet to company. their to modifications. for their division preferences. suggestions u A preferences, relies They on on To<marker type="block"/> Eli Lilly The pharmaceutical industry relies heavily on innovation to sustain competitive advantage. The average cost to discover and develop a new drug is more than<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> $500 million, and the average length of time from discovery to patent is 15 years. Eli Lilly, an Indianapolis-based pharmaceutical firm, has created an Internet-based platform to support collaborative innovation involving its customers—patients, doctors, clinicians, researchers, and health care providers. The company employs more than 35,000 people worldwide, and markets medicines to treat depression, schizo- phrenia, diabetes, cancer, osteoporosis, and many other diseases in almost 140 countries. Like its competitors, Eli Lilly invests heavily in R&amp;D, consistent with the philosophy of its founder, who referred to research as “the heart of the business, the soul of the enterprise.” In recent years, the company has sought to make its innovation processes more widely distributed by leveraging the Internet. In the late 1990s, the company created a new division, e.Lilly, dedicated to using the Internet to manage customer interactions with the explicit purpose of supporting R&amp;D activities. e.Lilly focused on engaging potential creative partners, including customers, in a dialogue to explore new ideas and strategies for growth. e.Lilly aimed to create new and unanticipated connections among patients, doctors, and employees, because these connections facilitate creative solutions to innovation problems. e.Lilly is responsible for two main streams of Web-based activities—generation of new drugs and creation of new patient solutions. Each stream of activities is pursued through a specific Web site and ad-hoc mechanisms of customer engagement, selectively applied at the early stages and later stages of the innovation process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>).<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> In order to collaboratively explore new solutions to problems of patients suffering from diseases, the company invites them to participate in specialized forums where they can socialize their experiences and share advice. Ad-hoc forums allow the medical community and engage cific to the health patients company in a shared condition, affected in experience order while by to the providing creatively of same learning useful pathologies drive o about insights its a idea spe- to generation process. To enhance its validation activities at the front end, Lilly educates and involves patients on a broader basis, through the corporate Web site (www. elililly.com) such lillywom apy offered is as on enhanced the enshealth.com). the and Lilly Web its Center and through direct feedback Patient for links customized Women’s sessions. to involvement related Health P The information Web purpose in (www. sites, ther- is to empower patients to choose their personal treatment options by providing them with information about diseases as well as potential therapies. At the same time, Lilly is able to generate valuable feedback about new product concepts from a representative sample of customers through online polls and surveys. Eli Lilly also uses the Internet as a platform for involving scientists in the innovation process, by directly engaging them in innovation-related problem solving. The company has created a venture called InnoCentive as are competitive InnoCentive and solve scientific a traded communities Web-based innovation problems and is (Innovation problem to market related participation enable of for experts solution collaboration where problems. solving. Incentive) who by is solutions qualified enhanced The InnoCentive have with that h t purpose expertise to lead scientists, functions problems through users posts to of without ground. scientists tions find engage basis been broadened third the spun party and to experts best The regard facilitate to then off its that find solution. InnoCentive.com as mission from work connects to an problems its geography, independent around independently R&amp;D InnoCentive to “solvers” acting that the efforts. match time Web world company, as with allows InnoCentive or an site zones, on their collaborate “seeker” u A independent a encourages Eli contingent and qualifica- or Lilly it back- com- has has to to panies in a variety of industries including biotechnol- ogy, agribusiness and consumer products.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> A key issue in facilitating customer involvement in innovation is the design of appropriate reward mechanisms for customers. In the case of InnoCentive, scientists are offered cash rewards that are explicitly defined on the Web site. Scientists work and submit solutions with the understanding that only the best solution will receive the financial award. InnoCentive is a cost-effective, convenient, and speedy mechanism for Eli Lilly to tap into the broad and rich base of distributed knowledge among the world’s scientists. It allows Lilly to expand its scientific research and development capacity, without adding to its employee costs. To understand the power of this Internet-based distributed innovation platform, consider an example of an innovation challenge—to improve the manufacturing process of a chemical called 4-(4-hydroxyphenyl) butanoic acid. After Eli Lilly’s internal R&amp;D organization had spent 12 person-months of work on this problem, the result was a five-step process that needed expensive starting materials and produced low yields. The goal was to devise a two-step process that had a starting cost of less than $100 per kilogram and produced a better yield. The problem was posted on InnoCentive’s site in June 2003. It soon received several submissions, including a promising approach suggested by Werner Mueller, a retired senior scientist from Hoechst Celanese. At the end of November 2003, Mueller’s fifth submission was accepted and he was awarded $25,000 by InnoCentive. In less than five months, one scientist had solved a problem that had eluded a team of researchers at Eli Lilly. By the end of 2004, more than 70,000 leading scientists and scientific organizations in more than 165 countries had registered to solve problems on InnoCentive’s Web site. InnoCentive has also signed up several companies including BASF, Dow Chemical, and Procter &amp; Gamble to post scientific problems confidentially on the InnoCentive Web site. Eli Lilly also engages its customers at later stages in the NPD process. Doctors are engaged through advisory programs aimed at supporting continuous feedback on specific solutions to selected pathologies, in order to better anticipate market evolution and identify the most appropriate period to launch a new treatment on the market. An extension of these programs has driven to the Supplier Diversity Development (SDD), aimed at broadening participation of minority and women-owned businesses—often<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> managed by the same company’s clients, such as researchers and clinicians—in the Lilly supplier base to levels more reflective of the diverse business community. And patients are involved in customizing the treatments and therapies the company provides them, their same, reflect disease but based the the individual on conditions. therapy their history preferences is personalized The and basic experience. and drugs the case o specifics can by case be the to of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="67" page="6" column="2">6</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="68" page="6" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="69" page="7" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 7</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="70" page="7" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="72" page="7" column="1">Ducati Motor</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="73" page="7" column="1">Applicability to Stage of New Product Development Process r o o f Collaboration Nature of Deep/ Broad/ Richness High Reach High Polls by Advisory Tech Website My Technical Ducati On (Ideation product Ducati line &amp; Café Service feedback survey programs Front-end Forum engineers and to Concept) &amp; sessions improve supported Chat the (Product Mass Focalized Web-based product Design Virtual Ducati customization Teams Garage Your Design Back-end contest product Dream Challenge and testing of Ducati Testing) the Virtual scenarios</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="75" page="7" column="2">FIGURE 2 Ducati’s Internet-Based Collaborative Innovation Initiatives</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="77" page="7" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="78" page="7" column="2">7</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="79" page="8" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 8</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="80" page="8" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="83" page="8" column="2">8</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="84" page="8" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="85" page="9" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 9</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="86" page="9" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="91" page="9" column="2">Applicability to Stage of New Product Development Process Front-end Back-end (Ideation and Concept) (Product Design and Testing) Specialized customer Advisory programs with Collaboration Deep/ Richness High InnoCentive forums Supplier Development selected Diversity doctors of On line polls &amp; surveys Customization of treatments Nature Broad/ Reach patients Feedback and sessions doctors with High Educational programs</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="92" page="9" column="2">FIGURE 3 Eli Lilly’s Internet-Based Collaborative Innovation Initiatives</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93" page="9" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="94" page="9" column="2">9</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="95" page="10" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 10</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="96" page="10" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="10" column="2">10</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="100" page="10" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="101" page="11" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 11</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="102" page="11" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="11" column="1">DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" page="11" column="1">The purpose of this paper was to highlight how the Internet can serve as a powerful platform for collaborative innovation with customers. While customer knowledge has always played a key role in managing product innovation, today’s competitive environment demands going beyond merely importing the “voice of the customer” through traditional market research mechanisms. The Internet allows firms to engage customers more broadly, more richly, and more speedily. It allows firms to create ongoing customer dialogue, absorb social customer knowledge, and scan knowledge of potential or competitors’ customers. By estab- lishing direct, persistent, and interactive dialogue, the firm can access knowledge at low cost from individual customers as well as from communities of communities. In virtual environments, it can better select lead users or, better, let them self select. In addition, the firm is neither constrained by geographical boundaries nor by the boundaries of its served markets in the selection of lead users. While this exploratory inquiry needs to be followed up with further empirical analysis, our study contrasts the traditional perspective on customer involvement in innovation against the emerging perspective of co- creation facilitated by the Internet. We illustrate how the characteristics of the medium—interactivity, reach, speed, persistence, and flexibility—permit firms to explore new frontiers in co-creation of value. We also outline a variety of Web-based mechanisms for customer collaboration, and provide a framework for classifying the mechanisms in terms of the nature of the collaboration (deep versus broad) and the applicability to stages in the NPD process (front end versus back end). Our case studies reveal three themes in Internet- based collaboration with customers to support new <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> product development, relating to (a) the absorption and integration of complementary forms of knowledge through different mechanisms; (b) organizational transformation as a prerequisite for the success of collaborative innovation and; (c) the emergence of mediators who facilitate collaborative innovation. The first theme we observe is that the Internet should be used as an integrated platform for engaging customers in multiple ways for different purposes. Both Ducati and Eli Lilly selectively use a diverse portfolio of Internet-based mechanisms to support different stages of the NPD process, and to acquire different types of knowledge. For instance, Ducati uses P its and relies ideas erate virtual tap by on successful into involving specific communities the polls competencies “next larger to bikes.” numbers verify to enhance of the These lead of soundness customers idea users, polls generation but of achieve to these then gen- extraordinary response rates, because the sense of belonging to the community increases individual commitment and brand loyalty. A similar virtuous cycle enacts within the Eli Lilly Web site, where patients develop trust and commitment towards the company because it provides them with information on their specific diseases, and committed customers, in turn, help the company to improve its treatments and, hence, further increase their loyalty. Eli Lilly’s ability to integrate patients’ experiences shared in the forums h t hosted contributions an best Internet-based the support dimension, important content approaches in new its knowledge-sharing and role corporate through product mechanisms to process in marketing defining the development. Web dimensions InnoCentive site new positively the processes with treatments. treatments of On the venture knowledge impact the at scientists’ a and content social plays both the to u A level experiential the knowledge traditional dimension, forms activities. munities increases firm generate of enables individual customer A to that there strong research contexts. gain knowledge would strong is sense insights participation customers’ a techniques. not These resonance of social be that belonging into possible virtual relationships, is willingness socially in rooted On among the to contexts to the virtual glean in company’s generated different to process specific which share using allow com- their knowledge with the company. Conversely, the ability to develop personalized relationships with<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> individual customers has a positive impact on their trust and involvement with the firm. The higher involvement in turn enhances customers’ intention to participate in communities managed by the company or even by independent third parties. The various Internet-based collaboration mechanisms are synergistic, and therefore can be employed simultaneously as part of an integrated innovation strategy, and not as independent “silos” for customer dialogue. Firms should strive to integrate all these channels to create an integrated portfolio of mechanisms that they can use to pursue different forms of knowledge, for different purposes, to support different stages of the NPD process. More specifically, the tools for front-end stages and deep customer engagement (suggestion boxes, advisory panels, virtual communities, Web-based idea markets) are more relevant to the ideation and concept development stages. Consider, for example, the Tech Cafè, technical forums, Ducati service area, and customer advisory programs run by Ducati; and the specialized customer forums and the InnoCentive Web site managed by Eli Lilly. The tools in the front-end stages and broad customer engagement (online surveys, market intelligence services, Web-based conjoint analysis, listening-in techniques) are more useful at the concept-testing phase, while the tools in the back-end stages and broad customer engagement (toolkits for users innovation, open-source mechanisms, Web- based patent markets) are better suited to improve the product design phase (e.g., contests like “Design Your Dream Ducati” and virtual teams organized by Ducati; as well as the advisory programs with selected doctors run by Eli Lilly). Finally, the tools related to the back-end stages and broad customer engagement (mass customization, Web-based prototyping, virtual product testing and virtual market testing) are most relevant at the product and market testing stages in the NPD process. In summary, the synergistic usage of different tools supporting different phases of the new product development is an important factor in enabling successful Internet-based collaborative innovation with customers. The second theme we observe from the case studies relates to the organizational changes that need to accompany the adoption of collaborative innovation with customers. While customer engagement in product development has received a lot of attention in<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> recent years, there is little academic research on the organizational adoption of such mechanisms. An interesting finding in our case studies is that both companies we studied underwent significant organizational transformation as they embraced collabora- o tive keting and function also innovation. department tightly with the linked Ducati around division the reorganized the community in community charge its management of entire the function, NPD mar- process. Specific organizational roles have been created to support continuous customer knowledge sharing within the company, selectively distributing the knowledge garnered through the Internet to spe- P cific tion. organization efforts. encourage departments Eli And Lilly innovative it to had created manage that to create can the its thinking benefit collaborative InnoCentive e-Lilly from as and a the new innovation spin-off to informa- hybrid allow to InnoCentive to become an independent Web-based innovation marketplace serving other companies. We believe that true co-creation will require a funda- mental redesign of marketing processes and the marketing organization to support continuous dialogue with customers, as well as to systematically share the knowledge generated through this dialogue within the firm in a way. The final theme that we find is the emergence of autonomous Web-based innovation marketplaces. h t Third an laborative peripheral own provide from site. important Web its These parties Ducati loyal site. innovation, vision intermediaries role like and Similarly, with as beyond InnoCentive enthusiastic intermediaries knowledge allowing its vertical allow own the and fans it customers portals firm in could firms NineSigma on facilitating to its not expand for to own and gather access bikers play Web col- its its prospects and competitors’ customers, who are unlike- u A ly Third as allowing edge, beyond Prandelli, complements vation to knowledge interact and party controlled the firms to &amp; firm’s Web-based gain the directly Verona, brokers to traditional insights immediate by access the with 2003). (Hargadon innovation unbiased individual into the processes field This firm opportunities of mediated marketplaces &amp; customer in view firm. conversations. Sutton, of direct (Sawhney, Mediated that process knowl- 1997) inno- act lie activities of innovation represent an interesting and profitable extension of the traditional business of information intermediaries.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="107" page="11" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="11" column="2">11</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109" page="12" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 12</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="12" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="113" page="12" column="2">12</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="114" page="12" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="115" page="13" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 13</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="116" page="13" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" page="13" column="1">Evans, P., &amp; Wurster, T. (1999). Blown to Bits: How the New o f Gladwell, Glaser, Can Economics Harvard B., Make M. &amp; Business Strauss, (2000). a of Big Information Difference. The School A. (1967). Tipping Press. Transforms Boston: The Point. Discovery Little, How Strategy. Little Brown of Grounded Boston: Things &amp; Co. Theory. Chicago: Aldine.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" page="13" column="1">Hagel, J., III, &amp; Armstrong, A.G. (1997). Net Gain: r Hagel, Boston: Expanding Markets J., III, Harvard when &amp; Markets Singer, Customers Business through M. School (1999). Make Virtual Press. Net the Worth: Rules. Communities. Shaping Boston: Harvard Business School Press. Afuha, A. (2003). Redefining Firm Boundaries P in the Face of Hargadon, Hauser, Harvard Administrative and J.R., Innovation A., Business &amp; &amp; Clausing, Sutton, Science Review, in R.I. a D. Quarterly, Product-Development (1990). (1997). May–June, The Technology 42, 716–749. House 63–73. of Brokering Quality. Firm. the Internet: Are Firms Really Shrinking? Academy of Hayes, R.H., Wheelwright, S., &amp; Clark, K. (1988). Dynamic Management Review, 28(1), 34–53. Manufacturing: Creating the Learning Organization. Brandenburger, A., &amp; Nalebuff, B. (1996). Co-opetition. New New York: New York Free Press. York: Doubleday. Hoffman, D.L., &amp; Novak, T.P. (1996). Marketing in Burgess, R. (1982). The Unstructured Interview as a Hypermedia Computer-Mediated Environments: Burke, George Rethinking Wind Sourcebook Conversation. R.R., &amp; Allen V. Market Mahajan and Rangaswamy, and In Field R. Unwin. Research Burgess (Eds.), Manual A., R. Digital in (Ed.), (pp. the &amp; Gupta, Digital 107–110). Marketing. Field o r World. Research: S. London: (2001). Global In J. A Iansiti, Kozinets, Implications Harvard 50–68. Conceptual M., R. Business (1999). &amp; Foundations. Levien, of Virtual E-Tribalized Review, R. Communities (2004). Journal March, Marketing? Strategy 1–10. of Marketing, of Consumption. The as Strategic Ecology. 60(4),</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">[AQ:1] Cairncross, Dahan, Cooper, Boston: Communication Publishing. 226–255). Strategies the Process R.G. E., Harvard &amp; F. (2001). New Hauser, from from (1997). York: Winning Business Revolution Idea the J.R. The John to World’s (2002). Death Launch, at Wiley School New will Leading The &amp; of Products: Press. 3rd Sons. Change Distance: Virtual Edition. h t Experts Accelerating our Customer. How Perseus Lives. (pp. the Kumar, McCracken, Leonard-Barton, Innovation Interoganizational Anthropological European Academy Review, N., November–December, Stern, G. of Management through Management (1990). D., L., Perspective. Culture Empathic &amp; Research &amp; Anderson, Journal, Rayport, Journal, and Design. 102–113. Using Journal Consumer 17(3), J. 36(6), J.F. (1993). Harvard Key 252–264. of (1997). 1633–1651. Behavior: the Informants. Conducting Business Market Spark An Journal of Product Innovation Management, 19, Research Society, 32(1), 3–11.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="123" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">[AQ:2] Day, Downes, Dahan, Digital Harvard 332–353. Internet-Based Depiction Organizations. Management, G. E., L., (1994). &amp; Strategies Business &amp; and Srinivasan, Mui, Animation. 17, Journal Product The C. 99–109. School (1998). for V. Capabilities of Concept (2000). Market Press. Journal Marketing, Unleashing The Testing of Dominance. Predictive Product of 58, the Market-driven u A 37–52. Using Killer Innovation Power Boston: Virtual App: of Nalebuff, Nambisan, Miles, CA: Environments Boston: Everyday Theory. Analysis. 392–413. M.B., Sage B., Harvard Academy Publications. &amp; S. An Ingenuity &amp; Huberman, Ayres, (2002). Expanded for Business New of to I. Product Designing (2003). Solve Management A.M. Sourcebook. School Problems (1994). Why Development: Press. Virtual Not? Qualitative Thousand Review, Big How and Customer Toward to Small. 27(3), Oaks, Data Use a Eisenhardt, K.M. (1989). Building Theories from Case Pettigrew, A. (1990). Longitudinal Field Research on Study Research. Academy of Management Review, 14(4), Change: Theory and Practice. Organization Science, 3, 532–550. 267–292.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" page="13" column="2">Gulati, R., Norhia, N., &amp; Zahere, A. (2000). Strategic Networks. Strategic Management Journal, 21, 203–215.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="14" column="1">Philipps, L.W. (1981). Assessing Measurement Error in Key Informant Reports: A Methodological Note on Organizational Analysis in Marketing. Journal of Marketing Research, 18 (November), 395–415.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="14" column="1">Piller, F., Ihl, C., Fuller, J., &amp; Stotko, C. (2004). Toolkits for Open Innovation—The Case of Mobile Phone Games.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="14" column="1">Prahalad, Proceedings Conference Experiences: Journal C.K., of Interactive on The &amp; System of Ramaswamy, the New Marketing, Sciences. 37th Practice Hawaii V. 18(3), in (2004). Value 5–14. o International Co-creation Creation. Randall T., Terwiesch C., &amp; Ulrich K.T. (2004). User Design of Customized Product. Marketing Science, forthcoming.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" page="14" column="1">Sawhney, M., &amp; Prandelli, E. (2000). Communities of Creation: Managing Distributed Innovation in Turbulent</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="14" column="1">Sawhney, Shapiro, Markets. of 44(2), Innomediation. 77–82. C., M., California &amp; Prandelli, Varian, Management MIT H.L. E., &amp; Sloan (1998). Verona, Management Review, Information G. (2003). P 42(4), The Rules. 24–54. Review, Power A Strategic Guide to the Network Economy. Boston: Harvard Business School Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="14" column="1">Thomke, S.H. (1998). Managing Experimentation in the Design of New Products. Management Science, 44(6), 743–762.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="14" column="2">Thomke, S.H., &amp; von Hippel, E. (2002). Customers as Innovators: A New Way to Create Value. Harvard Business Review, 80(4), 74–81.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="14" column="2">Toubia, O. (2004). Idea Generation, Creativity, and Incentives. Working Paper. Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Boston, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="14" column="2">Ulrich, K.T., &amp; Eppinger, S.D. (2003). Product Design and Development. New York: McGraw Hill/Irwin.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="14" column="2">Urban, G.L., &amp; Hauser, J.R. (1993). Design and Marketing of New Products. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="14" column="2">Urban, G.L., &amp; Hauser, J.R. (2004). “Listening In” to Find and Explore New Combinations of Customer Needs. Journal of Marketing, 68(April), 72–87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" confidence="possible" page="14" column="2">Verona, G. (1999). A Resource-Based View of Product Development. Academy of Management Review, 24(1), 132–142.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="14" column="2">von Hippel, E. (1988). The Sources of Innovation. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="14" column="2">von Hippel, E. (2001). Perspective: User Toolkits for Innovation. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 18, 247–257. [AQ:8]</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="14" column="2">von Krogh, G., &amp; von Hippel, E. (2003). Special Issue on Open Source Software development. Research Policy, 2.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" page="13" column="1">In conclusion, co-creation of value is an important source of competitive advantage in the network econo- my (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Prahalad &amp; Ramaswamy, 2004</xref>). While co-creation is a compelling notion, it needs to be described and analyzed for every specific marketing process, including development, munications, paper customer provided customer and relationship useful brand insights support, building. management, into sales, We co-creation marketing hope o new that product in com- this virtual environments to support one key marketing process—developing new products. We also hope that our work stimulates further investigation into other processes for collaboration, including collaborating with customers to define value propositions, deliver value, share value, and communicate value.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="120" page="13" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="124" page="13" column="2">[AQ:3]</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="126" page="13" column="2">[AQ:4]</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="127" page="13" column="2">COLLABORATING TO CREATE: THE INTERNET AS A PLATFORM FOR CUSTOMER ENGAGEMENT IN PRODUCT INNOVATION</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="128" page="13" column="2">13</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="129" page="14" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 14</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="130" page="14" column="1">Journal of Interactive Marketing DOI 10.1002/dir</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="133" page="14" column="1">[AQ:5]</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="134" page="14" column="1">[AQ:6]</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="137" page="14" column="1">[AQ:7]</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="149" page="14" column="2">14</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="150" page="14" column="2">JOURNAL OF INTERACTIVE MARKETING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="151" page="15" column="1">DIR194_440_20046.qxd 08/23/2005 05:55 PM Page 15</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="152" page="15" column="1">AUTHOR QUERIES AQ3: AQ2: AQ4: AQ1: provide This This This This is is is is not not not not the cited cited cited cited publisher’s in in in in the the the the text. text. text. location. text. Insert Insert Insert Insert f o o citation citation citation citation or or or or delete delete delete delete reference. reference. reference. reference. If you add a text citation to this, please AQ5: Please provide the publisher’s name and location. AQ6: Please update this reference. AQ8: AQ7: This This is is not not cited cited in in the the text. text. Insert Insert P citation citation or or delete delete reference. reference.</region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
