<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>b4f47bc7889e684e2f72db2f45c1272742c3d532222d55ee578a7b91ef116457</job>
    <base_name>62fa</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1117/12.246699">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/21573727.2014.970177</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">The Politics of Participation in Interaction Design (early draft)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Frederick M.C. van Amstel (fred@usabilidoido.com.br)</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" confidence="possible">participatory design, interaction design, design politics</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" page="1" column="1">In response to market needs, researchers and designers in Interaction Design are experimenting new ways of enabling user participation in information systems development. However, the same conceptualization of the participant as a user already reduces his possibility of participation. The user are not capable of designing, so there is a need for experts that can translate their needs into design defnitions. Even though participatory design exercises involving users are being promoted, the goal is not to autonomize participants to their own new technology development, but instead to generate user representations in order to improve targeting new products. It ́s an abstract inclusion and concrete exclusion, that legitimates technological dependence of a particular social group. Participatory Design as in the scandinavian tradition proposes that this perverse logic should be questioned in the design process, with the goal of generating alternatives that really promote participant ́s social development. This participatory approach can lead Interaction Design beyond the microstructures of interaction: interfaces, technics, tasks and other intrinsic details that don ́t comprehend the cultural density of the process.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="5" page="2" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="6" page="2" column="1">1</outsider>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="2" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" page="2" column="1">The process of interaction design becomes complex when we establish the multiple social forces that permeate through it. The adequacy of information systems is not a mere technical problem but a social issue of increasing relevance to the extent that society uses computation to mediate it's activities. At the beginning of computing, the main purpose for computers was to calculate large numbers, but today, the purpose for new systems is the interpersonal communication that information processing allows. More than new interfaces, these systems creates "interspaces" where people live much of their lives (Winograd, 1997). Although computers are used in this way for decades, many projects in this area still keeps the focus on the interface, providing only superfcial changes to existing systems. In the classical formulations of Human-Computer Interaction (Dix et al, 1998), the interaction is reduced to exchanges between the computer and its human operator, which occur through interfaces (input and output devices, linguistic codes, manuals and other resources). In Interaction Design, the proposal is to go beyond interfaces (Saffer, 2007), however, there remains a passive conceptualization of people that participate on the interaction. In fact, they are considered only users of the interfaces and not effective participants on it's design, hence the need for experts to defne what can and can not be done through interfaces. The Participatory Design praxis goes against this conceptualization, confguring itself as an alternative mode of production (Asaro, 2000;). In Participatory Design, the interface is just the tip of the iceberg. The main theme for the discussions are the possibilities of using the system, ie, for what it will be useful, how it could be appropriated for each participant and how the social organization will be affected by it. In this sense, the Participatory Design approach can be a way to overcome the traditional boundaries that the product type imposes on Design (eg Graphic User Interface Design, Software Design, Web Design), which leads to focus on micro-structures. When there are only discussions about the intrinsic values of a designed object, you lose the possibility of innovations in the structures of social activities (Crabtree, 2003:138). The participatory approach in Interaction Design could be a way to implement in practice the broad scope the area defnes for itself, at least in the words of Saffer (2007): “designing interactions between human-beings”. We will, in this article, discuss some principles and endeavors to enable participation in Interaction Design from Communication, Management, Information Systems, and Anthropology perspectives.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="9" page="2" column="1">2</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="2" column="1">Active Reception</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="2" column="1">The linear communication model, based on the scheme of sender / message / receptor, prevents us from seeing the bidirectionality of the communication process and its relationship with the social context in which it operates. To overcome such limitations, Martín-Barbero (1997) proposes that reception is taken not as a step in the communication process, but as a place from which to rethink communication research, that is, to change the starting point from the mass media mechanisms to the social mediations that constitute everyday life. Jesus Martín-Barbero (1997) identifed two predominant threads in Communication Studies during the 1960's and 1970's: the ideologism and informationism. The frst "focused on the goal of discovering and reporting (...) the strategies by which the dominant ideology penetrates the communication process" (p.280), while the second one "equates the process of communication to the transmission of information" (p.283), free from any infuence of power and other social forces. In both ideologism and informationism, the receiver role is to process the information or to internalize the ideologies propagated by the media. Unexpected reactions from the receivers are considered the result of noise in the channel or inconsistencies in the speech. Martín-Barbero brings back the subjectivity onto the communication process, giving the receiver the ability to not only re-semanticize messages, but also to convert them into new forms of mediation in its social loci. The television melodrama becomes quickly a material for discussion within neighborhood <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> conversations, not necessarily in the explicit sense of the television show, but towards the negotiated sense between the variegated social histories of the neighbors. The concept of reception is extensively discussed by Martín-Barbero because it outlines the production and research processes in Communication. The opening up of radio and television for public participation would not be possible without a change in the receiver status, which shall be considered capable of producing. This epistemological change, endorsed also by other authors and, especially, as demanded by social movements, created conditions for the emergence of New Media, horizontal networks for capturing, editing and distribution of content that mix roles and connections constantly (Manovich, 2001), such as the Internet, mobile telephony and others. In spite of Interaction Design being involved with the development of such networks, the informationist receiver conception is predominant, or as it is commonly referred to, the user. Starting from the “user modeling”, the designer translates the system functionalities into interface signs that could be understood as expected. Few authors have ventured into considering unexpected actions from the receiver as creative rather than dull. The literature, in general, recommends that the system prevents the user from making errors (Nielsen, 1993), using constraints and forcing functions (Norman, 2006:164). Production and reception are taken separately in informationist approaches, being the frst of which that determines the second. At the receiver, or user, there is nothing left but to receive, or use what was designed. Although different theoretical approaches questioned these assumptions before, it is after the advent of New Media that this issue gained prominence in Interaction Design. In New Media, people can be active producers of content and choose what they want to consume. It's enjoyment is an ongoing process of overlapand not switchingbetween production and reception. The inadequacy of the information processing model to analyze this scenario has stimulated the search for new insights in many different felds of knowledge.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="12" page="3" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 3</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14" page="3" column="1">3</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="15" page="3" column="1">Co-creation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="3" column="1">In Management Science, von Hippel (1986) proposed lead user studies for product design. The method's aim is to harness the creativity of advanced users of related products. Together with designers, engineers and facilitators from the organization, lead users participate in collective workshops, ranging from the conceptualization stage of the product to its technical specifcation. The method assumes that lead users have better knowledge of the situation than outside experts. This method ignores users that do know the context, but are not advanced users from any related product. Also from Management, Prahalad and Ramaswamy (2004) had a more inclusive vision. For the authors, the creation (and extraction) of value, the main purpose for capitalist enterprises, can't occur within companies. The value comes from the interaction between companies and consumers. From the standpoint of the consumer, the value is not the product she consumes but the experience it provides. So if the company improve this value co-creation, it can increase its proftability. Co-creation is not restricted to the production process, as proposed in von Hippel, but also occurs during consumption, support, sales or any other point of interaction. The change in conceptualizing the consumerfrom passive to activehas challenged the dominant logic of value creation within the frm (process optimization, innovation, internal), but Prahalad and Ramaswamy (2004) cite examples of fnancial successful business that provides experience programs, mass customization and consumer communities. The appropriation of co-creation by the market is not, however, motivated by democratic ideals or social justice. This is just an adaptation of business model for the economic realities of late modernity, characterized by widespread fragmentation. Martín-Barbero does not believe that the market is able to meet the demands for identifcation of individuals in the current scenario: The market can not settle traditions, because all it produces "melts into air" due to its structural tendency to a rapid and widespread obsolescence not only of things, but also the forms and institutions.(MARTÍN- BARBERO, 1997:15) <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> The growth on consumer choices and media participation that these new business models brought us do not necessarily imply in greater democratization of society. If, on the one hand, one can assemble a cultural schedule containing only what he likes, on the other hand, he loses contact with different tastes. Instead of expanding his cultural horizons, the individual may be subject to shrink them by virtue of their own desires, being oblivious to the public interests. Often, technologies are implemented to give new forms to old content, while maintaining the same underlying logic of domination. According to Martín-Barbero (1997), the possibility of innovation lies not in the implementation, but in the appropriation of the technology by communities, especially in Latin American nations, which heavily import technologies from other countries.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="17" page="4" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 4</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19" page="4" column="1">4</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="20" page="4" column="1">Technological Appropriation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" page="4" column="1">The interaction among cultures promotes many types of hybridization: between languages, between genders, between identities and also between technologies. If technology is considered part of the culture, one can not ignore its commitment to certain practices, cultural codes or collective and individual intentions. This cultural density makes technology a crucial aspect of intercultural interaction, either in collaboration, competition or confict. Therefore, technology is also subject to the processes of hybridization identifed by Burke (2003). Among them, we highlight the appropriation, ie the incorporation of elements of another culture within a particular practice, becoming a recreation of the new element itself. Most often than not appropriation occurs in the dominated culture as a form of resistance, subversion or survival. However, changes can be re-appropriated by the dominant culture as a way of maintaining control over practice. Bar et al (2007) identify three modes of technology appropriation within Latin American cultures: baroque infltration, creolization and cannibalism. Baroque Infltration happens when objects are customized with symbols from the local culture, as in the case of tropical fruit ornaments carved on sixteenth century's Catholic Churchs in Brazil. Creolization refers to the bricolage of elements provided by one or more objects in order to enable new social uses. In Brazil, the use of steel sponges to expand the capacity of TV antennas is an good example of creolization. And cannibalism is the direct confrontation with power relations embedded in the object, subverting them. The limits are trepassed to achieve unexpected, unwanted or illegal uses. Cloned cellphones, energy stealing, video game and printers unlock, software piracy are common examples of cannibalism in Brazil. In Brazil, creolization and cannibalism are well known by the popular nickname gambiarra, defned by Boufeur (2006:25) as "The procedure required for setting up an improvised device. The practice of gambiarra involves always an alternative intervention, which also could be defned as a `technical 're-appropriation of the material: a way to use or build artifacts through an attitude of differentiation, improvisation, adaptation, adjustment, alteration or adaptation needed by a material resource available, often with the goal of solving a specifc need." Analyzing different practices and discourses in this regard, Rodrigo Boufeur (2006) recognizes a close relationship between gambiarra and the jeitinho brasileiro, a loose way for solving problems that Brazilians are pride for being good at. This association refects the crucial role of appropriation on the identity constitution of the Brazilian people. "Everything indicates that the routine use of these two terms is a recent phenomenon, and that it has intensifed with the growing awareness of the Brazilian people and their culture, origin and identity." (Boufeur, 2006, p.28) Given the cultural homogenization, adverse social conditions and scarce resources, Brazilians must improvise to survive and, in the impromptu, build their identities. Boufeur (2006) believes that the popular practice of gambiarra may inspire changes in design, emphasizing the importance of recycling materials, intuition and co-creation. The commitment to industrial production prevents Design to incorporate such categories immediately. Encouraging creolization and cannibalism of products would be incompatible with current industrial rationality. However, companies cannot ignore such practices, especially when they reproduce in large proportions, threatening their business models. Bar et al (2007) reported cases of companies that responded to creolization creating new services, which incorporated the popular practice in an</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="22" page="5" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 5</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">institutional context, for example, mobile banking services created from the popular practice of exchanging prepaid cards in Africa.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="24" page="5" column="1">5</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="25" page="5" column="1">Ethnographic Studies</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="5" column="1">Technology companies recently begun to invest in ethnographic studies to closely monitor usage and consumer behavior. They send researchers to places where they can not obtain information through conventional means (newspaper clipping, distribution channels, call centers and others) to observe the daily lives of users and, from this type of observation, generate new product concepts that ft into their daily life (Blom et al, 2005). This approach reduces design to the creation of technical solutions to social problems, disregarding their overlaps with culture (Dourish, 2006). Technologies created in developed countries are imported and deployed as if they could "save" the peripheral countries from their social problems with the help of researchers that would know the territory better than its own inhabitants. As part of such ethnographic studies, group activities are promoted by researchers seeking to capture insights from users. As such, Participatory Design is reduced to a research technique, becoming an isolated exercise of refection, without, however, be committed to the group own social ambitions. In this way, Participatory Design serves the instrumental rationality from organizations that dominate the production of technologies, wich are not interested in empowering participants to produce their own. The Finnish handset maker Nokia had promoted one such exercise in 2007 in Mumbai (India), Accra (Ghana) and Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) that was called Nokia Open Studio (NOS). It was conceived as a competition in which participants drew the cell phone of their dreams. At the end of some weeks, the team elected and rewarded the winners with a new phone. The exercise was part of a larger study that explore the impact of mobile connectivity in the context of global urbanization. "The purpose of the NOS was not to generate ideas that could be bought into the design process. Rather, the research method aimed to generate inspirational and cross-referential material about the role of future technologies in participant’s lives by giving residents the opportunity to articulate their needs and aspirations, and present these in the context of their everyday life.. " (Jung e Chipchase, 2008:22) In fact, such initiatives establish a closer dialogue with communities that are distant from the technology production centers, however, it limits participation to modeling representations of their daily life, with which technicians will develop new systems. As anthropologists create representations of people and cultures to help society cope with them, "Ethnographies in Information Systems (...) the role of the systems designer, or at least one role of a member of a design team, as being fundamentally that of an anthropologist—to produce a representation of the practices of a work culture which can be used as a basis for systems design. "(Asaro 2000:282). According to Asaro (2000), the practice of participatory design emerged precisely because the representations that technicians did for their users were often inadequate, which threatened the adoption of new systems. With pre-defned objectives, however, the creation of representations tends to be reductionist, eliminating extraneous issues to the system and relying on behavior generalization. In participatory design sessions or in feld studiessuch as those described by Crabtree (2003), participants are invited to describe their activities, their goals, their instruments, their environment. The researchers cross these descriptions with their observations and classify people, according to demographics (age, sex) or by their role in activities. Subjects are diluted by cultural stereotypes to become simple abstractions: the police arrest criminals, waiters serve customers and secretaries answer the phone. Both ignore the simultaneous overlap of activities when doing several things at once or playing multiple roles, and the resulting deviations from the formalization of the activity (instructions and standards) and from the cultural stereotypes (prejudices and schemes). The other of design "ethnography" is transformed into abstraction because the goal for design practice is to generate a single solution (technical) to different problems from a particular community or segment of the population. Instead of considering the subjects able to solve their problems by themselves, design conceptualizes them as victims of "bad design" or lack thereof (Spinuzzi, <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> 2003). Within Latin America, Martín-Barbero calls this ruse "an anthropological operation": the reactivation of the evolutionary logic that reduces now easily and without cracks, the other to the straggler, that converts what is left of identity in other cultures into mere refex identityhas no value except to enhance, by contrast, the identity of the hegemonic cultureand negatively: what constitutes us is what we lack, what constitutes us is scarcity. And what we lack, what else is missing in today would be this: the technology produced by central countries that would allow us to fnally take the fnal leap into modernity. (Martín-Barbero, 1997. P. 257) As the frst ethnographies were used to improve the social control from colonial imperialist nations, the participatory design that treats the other as primitive – lay person, end user, consumerserves a new form of colonialism, the technological colonialism (Asaro, 2000 ). This fnding is not new: "The techno-apartheid is interwoven in a complex piece of historical segregation and shaped by cultural and socioeconomic and educational inequalities." (Garcia Canclini 2005:236). Technology does not reverse or dilute these relations, by contrast, makes them more visible. Luddites were not naivette when destroying machinery in protest. They saw them a symbol and instrument of rationality that dehumanized labor and degraded living conditions. Taking classic examples like this, technicians maintain their representations in the name of economic rationality. "Therefore, on the transition from political to economic, it becomes clear the central mechanism: abstract inclusion and concrete exclusion, namely, the legitimation of social differences." (Martín-Barbero, 1997:34) If, on the one hand, ethnographic and participatory design exercises promotes a peripheral involvement in production process — at least as ideal, on the other hand, it maintains the dependency and technological barriers from socio-economic factors.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="27" page="6" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 6</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="29" page="6" column="1">6</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="6" column="1">Participatory Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="6" column="1">As seen, the issue of participation in design is not only methodological, but primarily political. On the crisis of representation systems and the rise of participatory media, Martín-Barbero said that "what we are living is not the dissolution of the politic, but the reconfguration of the mediations in which they interpellate subjects and the representations that binds a society. "(2004:320) Participatory Design spread, although limited, is the result of this reconfguration. According to Asaro (2000), the Participatory Design in system development has its origins in the Scandinavian School of Information Systems, which developed a series of projects to the democratization of technology involving researchers and worker unions between 1960 and 1970. Infuenced by the Scandinavian studies, but with different objectives, researchers at Xerox PARC and IBM have developed a different favor of Participatory Design in the United States. Despite the differences, Asaro identifes the same basic concern among the two strands: how to deal with the political deadlock on technological mediated work organization? This is not about reaching a consensus for what (political) purposes technology should be employed, but to uncover and negotiate the inherent political nature of technology: what it allows and not allows us to do? How it mediates the activities? What commitments do we make for it? How individual knowledge and skills can be recognized and valued by technology? And more recently, specially on work unrelated projects (Sanders and Dandavate, 1999): what new uses do we invent in everyday activites? What narratives technology enables us to build, remember and tell? What it tells us and help us to say about who we are or who we want to be? All these issues are also political, if we consider politics as something that is done in the everyday and not only in offcial settings. Asaro (2000) emphasizes that technology should be treated as an active agent in the political discourse. Technology is a material discourse, but, being so, it is never completely infexible nor adaptable. You need to experience the strength of both discourse and materials that sustains it to be aware of it's limits. There are certain uses that is prohibited or discouraged by social norms or licenses, while others are simply impossible by physical limitations. The best way to understand the technology property is engaging into prototyping activities. "When the technological artifact itself becomes part of the interaction, the practical consequences of design and materials are reworked in the process" (Asaro, 2000:284). Going forward, Sanders (1999) reports that co- creation with simple tools can help people who can not express themselves in spoken words, articulating feelings, desires and needs in a tangible way. The use of concrete tools (prototypes) rather than abstract (conceptual models, formalisms) activates tacit knowledge, facilitating the <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> visualization of alternative futures, including organization's own social activity (Crabtree, 2003). Given the political, cultural and technological issues that emerge and it's diverse and situated nature, there is no general formula for dealing with them. "Besides promoting abstract democratic values generally and in the design process, there would seem to be no specifc, formal or structural prescriptions available for the democratization of work through design, and such a view ignores the possible limits of technological capabilities."(Asaro, 2000:286) We have to, as proposed by Martin-Barbero, "grope forward, without a map or having only a nightly map." (1997:290)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="7" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 7</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="34" page="7" column="1">7</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="7" column="1">Concluding Remarks</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="7" column="1">Aforementioned authors quotes at different perspectives the inextricable nature of production and reception processes. Following them, we argue that one can not predict nor produce a design process as this will be produced when executed by the participants themselves. We cannot predict nor produce what a user will do with a designed object. Despite of any object having it's own limits, the usage is socially produced and negotiated in the face of multiple factors that are found outside of the object itself. It's not possible even to produce what is expected nor produce automatic forecasts, because technology has limited agency (Trapp, 2005). An outlet for developing a realistic design might decreasing the belief in technological rationality and opening artifact production and use processes for other rationalities, other cultures, other people. If we intend to propose or highlight something in this paper is that Interaction Design Research should expand its focus from artifact interface characteristics to the social interaction it provides. While restricted to the human-artifact interface, Research deepen onto relevant micro-structures, but without knowing the social context, the resulting knowledge is another fragment in the theory or rather a usability recommendation or else a useless artifact. To make sense from microstructures, we need to see them being reproduced in real processes of production and use, articulating cultural ways of living, ways of interacting among individuals and collectivities. The shape of a interface button is not only determined by its relationship with other interface elements, but for a genre whose history includes the changes in ways of operating and building machines, ways of living and organizing the home and ways of relating to friends (From Rouchey, 2009). In future projects we intend to explore the mediation map outlined by Martin-Barbero (1997) to work Interaction Design together with Communication, Culture and Politics. The map draw process in two axis: short term (synchronic axis) and long term (diachronic axis), allowing to realize the negotiations behind production and use and the genres transformation alongside social history. The mediations between the axes are of particular interest to Interaction Design, as they give thickness to the fabric of relationships between people, institutions, techniques and signs. Making the circuit in both directions, Interaction Design Research can achieve the intention to go beyond the artifact, which is, according Saffer (2007), the particular contribution of Interaction Design in relation to other approaches within Design. <marker type="block"/> Referências Asaro, Peter, 2000. Transforming society by transforming technology: the science and politics of participatory design. In: Accounting, Management and Information Technologies, Elsevier. Bar, F; Pisani, F; Weber, M, 2007. Mobile technology appropriation in a distant mirror: Baroque infltration, creolization, and cannibalism. In: Seminario sobre Desarrollo Economico, Desarrollo Social y Comunicaciones Moviles en America Latina. Buenos Aires. Blom, J; Chipchase, J. Lehikoinen, J, 2005. Contextual and cultural challenges for user mobility research. In: Communications of the ACM, ACM Press. Boufeur, Rodrigo, 2006. A questão da gambiarra: formas alternativas de desenvolver artefatos e sua relação com o design de produtos. Dissertação (Mestrado — Área de concentração: Design e Arquitetura), FAU, USP. Crabtree, Andy, 2003. Designing Collaborative Systems: A Practical Guide to Ethnography.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> London: Springer. De Rouchey, Bill, 2009. The History of the Button. In: Push. Click. Touch. &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.pushclicktouch.com/category/historyofthebutton/" id="39">http://www.pushclicktouch.com/category/historyofthebutton/</ext-link>&gt; Acesso em 14/04/2009 Dix, A; Finlay, J; Abowd, G; Beale, R, 1998. Human-Computer Interaction. Nova Iorque: Prentice Hall. Dourish, Paul, 2006. Implications for design. In: Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human Factors in computing systems. New York. Fischer, G., 2001. User Modeling in Human-Computer Interaction. In: User Modeling and User- Adapted Interaction, Springer. García Canclini, Néstor, 2005. Diferentes, desiguais e desconectados. Rio de Janeiro: Editora UFRJ. Hippel, Eric von, 1986. Lead Users: A Source of Novel Product Concepts . In: Management Science, JSTOR. Jung, Younghee; Chipchase, Jan, 2008. Nokia Open Studio: Engaging Communities. In: &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://younghee.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2008/10/nokiaopenstudio_fnal_20081030.pdf" id="40">http://younghee.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2008/10/nokiaopenstudio_fnal_20081030.pdf</ext-link>&gt; Manovich, Lev, 2001. The Language of New Media. Cambridge: MIT Press. Martín-Barbero, Jesús, 2004. Ofício de Cartografo: Travessias latino-americanas da comunicação na cultura. São Paulo: Edições Loyola. Martín-Barbero, Jesús, 1997. Dos Meios às Mediações: Comunicação, Cultura e Hegemonia. Rio de Janeiro: Editora UFRJ. Nielsen, Jakob, 1993. Usability Engineering. : Morgan Kaufmann. Norman, Donald, 2006. O Design do Dia-a-dia. : Rocco. Prahalad, C; Ramaswamy, V, 2004. The Future of Competition: Co-Creating Unique Value with Customers. : Harvard Business School Press. Saffer, Dan, 2007. Designing for interaction: creating smart applications and clever devices. Berkeley: New Riders. Sanders, E.B.N; Dandavate, U., 1999. Design for experiencing: New tools. In: Proceedings of the First International Conference on Design and Emotion. . Spinuzzi, Clay, 2003. Tracing Genres Through Organizations: A Sociocultural Approach to Information Design. Cambridge: MIT Press. Trapp, M, 2005. The Infuence of Unpredictability on Multiple User Interface Development. In: 2nd Workshop on Multi-User and Ubiquitous User Interfaces. . Winograd, Terry, . From Computing Machinery to Interaction Design. In: Denning, Peter; Metcalfe, Robert. Beyond Calculation: The Next Fifty Years of Computing. : Springer-Verlag.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="38" page="8" column="1">| Participatory Politics in Interaction Design| 8</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
