<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>a1c7e58e97ae8687bc0b41878d2d0fb8c3ca9dc282705dfd3171991eaf637156</job>
    <base_name>62s3</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/desi_a_00207</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Co-Design as a Process of Joint Inquiry and Imagination Manuscript of an article that was accepted for publication in Design Issues (May 2012). For personal and academic use only. See Guidelines Marc Steen</article-title>
      </title-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="2" page="1" column="1">Many innovation projects are currently organized as co-design processes, that is, as processes of creative cooperation. The term co-design can, for example, refer to the organizing open innovation, in which people from different organizations share and 1 combine ideas and knowledge, or to involving users or customers as participants in the 2 design process. One might even argue that design is always co-design, since design is 3 inherently a social process. Co-design comprises diverse approaches, ranging from research-oriented approaches (such as applied ethnography) to design-oriented approaches (such as the use of generative tools), and—if we focus on user involvement—ranging from approaches in which researchers and designers move towards users (such as usability testing) to approaches in which users move towards 4 researchers and designers (such as participatory design). Co-design often builds upon 5 the tradition of (Scandinavian) participatory design. Below, I will follow Sanders and Stappers’s usage of the term co-design to ‘indicate 6 collective creativity as it is applied across the whole span of a design process’. A useful definition is also provided by Kleinsmann and Valkenburg, who described co-design as ‘the process in which actors from different disciplines share their knowledge about both the design process and the design content ... in order to create shared understanding on both aspects ... and to achieve the larger common objective: the new product to be 7 designed’. This definition draws attention to the sharing and combining of knowledge and to developing shared understanding—issues that will be discussed below. Diverse benefits are associated with organizing co-design, ranging from improving processes of idea generation and service or product development, to improving decision making and promoting cooperation and creativity, to longer-term improvement of users’ 8 and customers’ satisfaction and loyalty. Despite the popularity of co-design, it receives 9 little scholarly attention and the ideas behind it are rarely discussed critically. This may also be caused by the popularity of labelling projects as co-design and the conceptual dilution or confusion that may result from this. In this essay, I will explore how philosophical pragmatism can help to better understand and to effectively organize co-design processes.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="3" page="1" column="1">–1–</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="4" page="2" column="1">Abduction or design thinking</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" page="2" column="1">A first move in this exploration is to remark that (co-)design proceeds via a particular form of logic and that it cannot be adequately understood as a form of science or of engineering. Science is typically concerned with describing and understanding past or current situations and with discovering ‘facts’, whereas design is concerned with envisioning and realizing alternative situations, and with both facts and values. Furthermore, engineering is typically concerned with solving a problem that is given beforehand and finding one ‘best’ solution, whereas design is concerned also with exploring alternative problem definitions and with exploring alternative solutions. I added ‘typically’ in order to acknowledge the fact that scientists’ or engineers’ actual practices can be rather different from how these practices are ‘typically’ described or prescribed in textbooks or in management discourse. Numerous studies have shown that, in science and engineering practices, facts and values are often intertwined and are dealt with simultaneously, and that problem-setting and solution-finding proceed via 10 explorative and iterative processes. What happens in (co-)design can be understood more adequately as a process of abduction—a term coined by pragmatist philosopher C.S. Peirce, which refers to a type of reasoning that is different from deduction or induction: ‘deduction proves that something must be; induction shows that something actually is operative; abduction 11 merely suggests that something may be.’ These three types of reasoning can be illustrated with the following examples: In deduction, one starts with two or more premises and then draws a conclusion, for example, one starts with premises ‘All humans are mortal’ (p→q) and ‘Socrates is a human (p), and then deduces that ‘Socrates is mortal’ (q); this type of reasoning is typical for mathematics and logic. In induction, one starts with a series of observations and then speculates about a pattern, for example, one observes ‘if copper is heated, it expands’ (p1→q1), ‘if steel is heated, it expands’ (p2→q2), et cetera, and then induces that ‘if metal is heated, it expands’ (p→q); this type of reasoning is typical for natural science and social science. In abduction, one can start with experiencing a specific current situation as problematic (p), and then one simultaneously and iteratively imagines ways to approach and frame the situation (p→q) and imagines possible 12 solutions for the problem (q); this type of reasoning is typical for design. <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 13 Likewise, Dorst recently argued that abduction is at the ‘core’ of design thinking. Dorst understands deduction as the process to move from knowing ‘what’ and ‘how’ to the ‘result’ (e.g. if one knows about stars and about their movements, one can deduce their locations), and induction as the process to move from knowing ‘what’ and ‘result’ to possible options for ‘how’ (e.g. if one knows about stars and their locations, one can induce possible working principles), and two forms of abduction. In abduction-1 (closed problem solving) one develops an object (‘what’), based upon a given desired outcome (‘result’) and a given working principle (‘how’), and in abduction-2 (open problem solving) one starts with a desired outcome (‘result’) and develops both an object (‘what’) and a working principle (‘how’). The latter is associated with design thinkin and with the notion of framing. Framing refers to an approach of iteratively developing frames, which refers to combinations of a result and a working principle, and developing possible solutions, and thus creatively moving between “result”, “how” and “what” during the design process. In design thinking, problems and possible solutions are explored and developed and evaluated simultaneously in an iterative process: a ‘design process involves finding as 14 well as solving problems’ so that ‘problem and solution co-evolve’. Design thinking is 15 needed to cope with ‘wicked problems’, that is, with problems which cannot be clearly defined using ‘facts’ at the start of a project and which cannot be solved by selecting a ‘best’ solution—that is, with many real problems in the real world. In the case of co-design, diverse people participate in this process of design thinking. Below, I will argue that co-design can be understood and organized as a process of collaborative design thinking, or—drawing from the ideas of pragmatist philosopher John Dewey—as a process of joint inquiry and imagination.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="6" page="2" column="1">–2–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="3" column="1">Dewey’s Pragmatism</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11" page="3" column="1">This exploration’s second move is to turn to philosophical pragmatism. Philosophical pragmatism emerged in the USA in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, with William James, C.S. Peirce and John Dewey as key figures. A key theme in pragmatism is its focus on people’s practices and experiences, rather than on abstract theories. I will focus on texts by Dewey (1859-1952) because his ideas are especially relevant to 16 technology, engineering and design, and have been used productively in these fields. Many people in the field of design are familiar with Dewey’s ideas on experience 17 and aesthetics, and Dewey’s ideas appear in Schön’s notion of reflective practice, <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> which he uses to discuss the ways in which professionals combine practice and reflection—not surprisingly so, since Schön wrote his dissertation on Dewey’s theory of 18 inquiry. Moreover, the usage of Dewey’s ideas to discuss co-design is in line with Dewey’s ambition to make his ‘scholarly work’ relevant and applicable to ‘practical 19 affairs’. Dewey saw philosophy as a way to develop tools that people can use to cope with real problems in the real world, and he aimed for a ‘recovery of philosophy’, so that philosophy ‘ceases to be a device for dealing with the problems of philosophers and 20 becomes a method, cultivated by philosophers, for dealing with the problems of man’. Dewey’s pragmatism has two key themes: it focuses on people’s concrete practices, their personal experiences and the role of practical knowledge, and it aims at promoting 21 cooperation and at empowering people so that they can improve their situations. These two themes will be briefly discussed below.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="10" page="3" column="1">–3–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Practices, Experiences and Knowledge</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="4" column="1">Dewey distinguished between primary experiences of ‘gross, macroscopic, crude subject-matters’, that is, experiences ‘as the result of a minimum of incidental reflection’, and secondary experiences of ‘refined, derived objects of reflection’, that is, 22 experiences ‘in consequence of continued and regulated reflective inquiry’. Furthermore, Dewey promoted an ‘empirical method’ of moving back and forth 23 between practices (primary experiences) and reflections (secondary experiences) in order to develop practical knowledge: knowledge that is based on practices and that is practically applicable. In addition, Dewey’s held that knowledge needs to be ‘particular’ or ‘contingent’, which is rather different from traditional philosophy or mainstream 24 science, where knowledge is typically viewed as ‘universal’ or ‘necessary’ . Dewey held that ‘thinking and acting are just two names for a single process—the process of making our way as best we can in a universe shot through with contingency’, and that ‘knowledge is a by-product of activity: people do things in the world, and the doing results in learning something that, if deemed useful, gets carried along into the 25 next activity’ . Similar ideas—on the generation of knowledge in relation to design 26 practices—have been expressed by, for example, Stappers and Van der Lugt .</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Communication, Cooperation and Change</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="4" column="1">Dewey believed that ‘the specific conditions which exist at one moment, be they 27 comparatively bad or comparatively good, in any event may be bettered’. He <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> emphasized people’s abilities to communicate and to cooperate as ways to jointly bring about positive change: ‘The heart of language is not “expression” of something antecedent, much less expression of antecedent thought. It is communication; the establishment of cooperation in an activity in which there are partners, and in which the 28 activity of each is modified and regulated by partnership.’ This engagement with communication, cooperation and change is rather different from a ‘spectator conception 29 of knowledge’ , which is typical for traditional philosophy or mainstream science and which refers to describing an external reality and a stable state of affairs. Dewey promoted processes in which people are empowered to jointly reflect on their practices and experiences, to communicate and cooperate and to improve their own 30 or other people’s situations. This ‘melioristic motive’ can also be found in the works 31 of Papanek and Margolin and, more recently and in this journal, in the works of 32 Bonsiepe, Dong, Nieusma and Oosterlaken.<marker type="block"/> Dewey viewed knowledge as instrumental, in that he proposed that knowledge should be concerned with exploring alternative futures, with promoting communication and cooperation, and with organizing positive change. These are also key themes in co- design, which makes Dewey relevant indeed to a discussion of co-design. These topics—practices, experiences and knowledge, and communication, cooperation and change—are intimately intertwined through Dewey’s concept of 33 inquiry . Dewey advocated organizing processes of joint inquiry, in which people jointly explore, discuss and define a problem and jointly explore, develop and evaluate possible solutions. In very general terms, he envisioned inquiry as a process that starts from a problematic situation, and that moves—by productively combining doing and thinking—to a resolution: ‘Inquiry is the controlled or directed transformation of an 34 indeterminate situation into ... a unified whole.’ In such an inquiry process, the aim is not to develop universal knowledge that represents some external reality, but to bring people together so that they can jointly explore, try-out and learn, and bring about change in a desired direction.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="16" page="4" column="1">–4–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="19" page="5" column="1">Exploring Ethics</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="5" column="1">A third move in this exploration is a turn towards ethics. Based on Dewey’s pragmatist philosophy, I will argue that co-design has inherent ethical qualities. <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> For Dewey, moral experiences were his starting point and the empowerment of people to cope with moral questions was his primary goal: ‘For Dewey, social and 35 political philosophy—and not metaphysics or epistemology—is First Philosophy’. Dewey held that people, throughout their daily lives, continuously engage in ethics, especially when they interact with each other. People have moral experiences and need to cope with moral questions whenever they think and feel, whenever deliberate and act, 36 whenever they communicate and cooperate, whenever make plans and decisions. For Dewey, ‘moral concerns permeate much of experience and require nearly constant 37 deliberation and choice of action, whether issues are minute or momentous.’ Dewey saw daily life, with both its minor issues and its major questions, as inherently ethical. Moreover, Dewey saw deliberation as a social process, ‘not only in the sense that we must take consequences for others into consideration but also in the sense that 38 conversation with others provides the means for reflection.’ I would like to propose that when people engage in a co-design process, they also engage in ethics—in a process with ethical qualities. These ethics become manifest, for example, when co-design participants express and share their personal experiences, when they empathize with others, when they discuss current or problematic situations, when they envision possible or desirable situations, when they develop and evaluate possible solutions, or when they make decisions and bring about change. Co-design can be understood as an instance of ‘moral inquiry’: ‘a reflective response—intervening with analysis and imaginative deliberation—when action is frustrated’, where deliberation may ‘proceed by dialogue, visualization, imagining of motor responses, and 39 imagining how others might react to a deed done.’ 40 Similarly, Devon and Van de Poel argued that design is inherently a social activity and quintessentially an ethical process—‘Ethics is not an appendage to design but an integral part of it’—and advocated using moral imagination to bring the ethical qualities 41 in design processes to the fore. In addition, Lloyd argued that design and ethics are similar in that they are both concerned with envisioning and developing possibilities and with evaluating and choosing between possibilities. Pragmatist ethics provides an alternative to two dominant schools in ethics: consequentialist ethics, which tends to search for general rules to maximize the positive consequences of one’s actions, and deontological ethics, which tends to search for general rules based on one’s duties and obligations. ‘Pragmatist ethics turn away from such rigid abstractions [like the ‘general rules’ just mentioned] and returns to the<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> ordinary life-experiences of inherently social, embodied, and historically situated 42 beings.’ If some may find it somewhat awkward to use the term ethics in the context of co- design, we can instead use the term ethos and discuss the ethos of co-design, that is, the moral ideas and attitudes of participants in a co-design process.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21" page="5" column="1">–5–</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="6" column="1">–6–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="25" page="7" column="1">Joint Inquiry and Imagination</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" page="7" column="1">Below, I will discuss Dewey’s ideas on organizing processes of joint inquiry and 43 imagination. He argued that such processes consists of five phases, which are intimately related and which are ideally addressed in an iterative process.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Exploring and Defining the Problem (Phases 1 and 2)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="7" column="1">1. ‘The indeterminate situation’: A specific and concrete situation is experienced as problematic, without yet knowing what is precisely problematic about it. Dewey stressed that personal and subjective experiences are critical for the start of an inquiry process, to make the situation ‘questionable’, and that expressing and sharing these experiences are critical: ‘inquiry is not a purely logical process—feeling is a useful and 44 orienting presence throughout each phase’. 2. ‘Institution of a problem’: A provisional problem definition is formulated, which can later be restated and refined in an iterative process. It is important to be aware of the importance of the wording: ‘The way in which the problem is conceived decides what specific suggestions are entertained and which are dismissed’. This intimate relationship between problem-setting and solution-finding is also found in design thinking. The ethics of co-design occur in the ways in which and in the extent to which participants are able to express and share their experiences and to empathize with others, for example, by engaging in storytelling, and in the ways in which they are able to draw from their own and other people’s experiences when they explore and define the problem. Ideally, these processes are carefully organized, so that participants can engage with questions such as: What do I find problematic about this situation? What are other people’s experiences? or In what direction should we look for possible solutions?—questions which Dewey would have found ethical.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="29" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Perception of the Problem and Conception of Possible Solutions (Phase 3)</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="30" page="7" column="1">–7–</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="8" column="1">3. ‘The determination of a problem-solution’: In an iterative process, the problem and possible solutions are simultaneously explored and further defined—similar, again, to design thinking: ‘Observations of facts and suggested meanings or ideas arise and 45 develop in correspondence with each other’. Dewey proposed that problems are best explored and defined using perception—one’s capacities to see, hear, touch, smell and taste current situations (what is)—and that solutions are best explored and developed using conception—one’s capacities to imagine and envision alternative situations (what could be). Ideally, perceiving the problem and conceiving possible solutions are 46 productively combined. Different or more precise ways to perceive the problem help to conceive different or more concrete solutions, just like the conceiving of different or more detailed solutions helps perceiving the situation differently or more precisely. The ethics of co-design occur in the ways in which and in the extent to which participants can use their capacities for perception, for example, by engaging with visuals that are related to the problem and by empathizing with the people involved, and can use their capacities for conception, for example, by using tools that foster joint 47 creativity and the generation of innovations. Such perception and conception ideally 48 involve ‘moral imagination’ or ‘dramatic rehearsal’ , in which co-design participants imagine or rehearse current and problematic situations or alternative and desirable situations, using both their thoughts and their feelings. In such deliberation, ‘we singly or collectively hunt for ways to settle difficulties and ambiguities by scoping out alternatives and picturing ourselves taking part in them. Imagination continues until we are stimulated to act by a course that appears to harmonize pressing interests, needs, and 49 other factors of the situation.’ This combination of perception and conception, and the ways in which co-design participants cooperate productively would enable them to address questions such as:</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="32" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">How does this problematic situation feel like? How can we generate solutions for this problem? How is this solution better than the current situation?—questions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">that we</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="34" page="8" column="1">or can consider, again, as ethical.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Trying-out and Evaluating Solutions (Phases 4 and 5)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="8" column="1">4. ‘Reasoning’: One should not jump to conclusions or accept a solution too quickly. The relationships between the tentatively-defined-problem and different suggestions- for-solutions need to be evaluated in order to assess how different solutions can help to solve the problem. Ideally, participants can explore and define the scope and boundaries <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> of a project and critically discuss means and ends, and the relationships between means and ends. This can promote systems thinking, since participants become more aware of the scope and boundaries of their project, and a systems perspective can help them to generate innovative ideas and solutions. 5. ‘The operational character of facts-meanings’: This phase is concerned with practically trying-out solutions, for example, by organizing experiments or tests with users or customers. The project becomes more real and the stakes get higher, and it is therefore critical that the people involved continue to cooperate constructively. They may need to express and discuss their respective roles and interests, which may cause 50 conflicts between them, but which is necessary for developing a shared understanding of what needs to be done and how they need to cooperate. They need to jointly generate solutions that will work practically. If their roles and interests remain unexamined, there is a risk that one role or one interest dominates the project, which can lead to solutions that are less viable or less feasible. Ideally, co-design participants can deal creatively 51 and productively with even ‘deep-seated and fundamental value conflicts’ and develop solutions that work for all of them. The ethics of co-design occur in the ways in which and in the extent to which the people involved are able to try-out different solutions, to critically discuss the project’s scope and boundaries, and to negotiate their different roles and interests. This would help them to explore ethical questions such as: What should be our project’s scope? or</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="37" page="8" column="1">–8–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">What solution will work for me? And for the other participants or stakeholders?</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="9" column="1">Imagination is key throughout the process outlined above. Fesmire discussed two roles 52 of imagination: 1) imagination as ‘empathic projection’, as a way to respond directly and empathically to others and their feelings and thoughts; and 2) imagination as a way to escape current patterns and imagine alternatives. Imagination is then ‘a capacity to 53 engage the present with an eye to what is not immediately at hand’. In sum, we can understand co-design as a process of joint inquiry and imagination, that is, as ‘a reflective activity in which existing tools and materials (both of which may be either tangible or conceptual) are brought together in novel and creative 54 arrangements in order to produce something new’. In such a process, people use ‘the power of intelligence to imagine a future which is the projection of the desirable in the 55 present, and to invent the instrumentalities of its realization’.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="41" page="9" column="1">–9–</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="42" page="10" column="1">An Example</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="10" column="1">56 In order to illustrate this argument, I will discuss one project: TA2. In this research and innovation project, some forty researchers, designers and developers from fourteen organizations (ranging from international corporations and small enterprises to universities and research institutes) cooperated for four years (2008-2012) on developing and evaluating a series of innovative telecommunication, multimedia and gaming applications. The project’s goal was to better understand how such technologies can help groups of people to engage in social communication when they are separated in space and in time—TA2 stands for Together Anywhere, Together Anytime. TA2 focused on group-to-group communication, as an alternative to many projects and products that facilitate one-to-one communication. The project followed a co-design approach and promoted multidisciplinary teamwork, early user involvement and an iterative approach of research, design and evaluation. Below, I will discuss some of the co-design activities in TA2 and focus on the ways 57 in which project-team members engaged in joint inquiry and imagination.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Exploring and Defining the Problem (Workshops)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="10" column="1">The original project plan contained a drawing of pyramid ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>), which represents the project’s goal, that is, to make ‘communications and engagement easier among groups of people separated in space and time’, which will ‘help in the nurturing of social relationships’ (in the top of the pyramid), and what needs to be done in order to realize that goal: the development of technologies, components and applications, and knowledge on, for example, user experience and business modelling (in the bottom of the pyramid).<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> Implicitly, it is suggested that there is something problematic about the current focus on one-to-one communication in many products and services, and that products and services for group-to-group communication need to be developed. In order to make the process of problem exploration and definition more explicit and more into a collective effort, several co-design workshops were organized. Three months into the project, key project-team members participated in a Scenario Workshop. They were invited to empathize with different groups of (imaginary) people and to take them as a starting point for developing scenarios. They wrote five short narratives in which people use the TA2 applications in specific situations. Writing these scenarios helped them to empathize with (imaginary) users and their experiences, and to more vividly imagine the sort of problems that TA2 aims to solve. In the tenth month of the project, it appeared that people had slightly different ideas on the project’s overall goal. In order to improve shared understanding, a Togetherness Workshop was organized. All project-team members were invited to express their personal experiences in relation to togetherness and to engage more personally with this key theme. This workshop further helped project-team members to empathize with people’s experiences, by expressing and sharing their experiences in relation to the theme of togetherness. These workshops brought to the fore the ethics of co-design in that they helped project-team members to express and share their own experiences and to empathize with other people and their experiences—which helped to ground the project’s problem definition in people’s concrete experiences.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="47" page="10" column="1">Improved relationships Project between groups Vision Concept Editing grammar for demonstrators video communication User Architectures Multimedia Essential understanding and platforms composition Outputs Analysis and A/V transmission Interaction Business interpretation chain modelling language modelling Key Enablers Narrative Experience Interaction Evaluation Social representations design design methods methods science methods Existing Standards Component technologies Design Social science Knowledge RTP, H.264, SIP, AAC Ambulant, NSL best-practice theory</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="48" page="10" column="1">Figure 1: Overview of TA2 goals and enablers.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="49" page="10" column="1">– 10 –</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="51" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Perceiving the Problem and Conception of Possible Solutions (Storyboards)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" page="11" column="1">Next, the five scenarios were developed into five storyboards, in an iterative process between key project-team members and a professional illustrator. Each storyboard consisted of five to ten drawings with accompanying narratives. One example is MyVideos ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>): a software application that helps people to use video recordings of a social event, for example, a school concert (left), to create a video compilation, using one’s own and other people’s footage (middle), and to share these video compilations with others, for example, a family member abroad (right). MyVideos is intended to facilitate togetherness by enabling people to share the experiences of a shared activity.<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> Jointly developing the storyboards helped the project-team members to be more specific and precise, and to productively discuss how the project overall goal and ideas for specific solutions relate to each other. Moreover, the five storyboards were used to organize focus groups with people from five corresponding target groups, in order to talk with them about the applications as early as possible—before any prototypes were built. These focus groups helped to better understand people’s daily lives, their needs, expectations and preferences in relation the TA2 applications. Creating these storyboards and discussing them with potential users helped the project-team members to combine technology perspectives (the ambition to create technology) and users’ perspectives (the ambition to help people). It promoted a multidisciplinary and iterative process in which project-team members were able to discuss different solutions in the context of the overall project goal. Creating and discussing the storyboards brought to the fore the ethics of co-design in that both project-team members and users were able to perceive the problem (the project’s goal), and to conceive possible solutions (specific applications), and to move between perception and conception in an iterative process, for example, when project- team members listened to users talking about their problems and when they jointly tried to find solutions for these problems.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="54" page="11" column="1">– 11 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62s3.page_012.image_01.png" thmb="62s3.page_012.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="56" page="12" column="1">Figure 2. Drawings of a storyboard for MyVideos.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="58" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Trying-out and Evaluating Solutions (Prototypes)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" page="12" column="1">In the second and third year of the project, project-team members worked together to develop several prototypes and they discussed the viability and feasibility of the various technologies and applications. Moreover, these prototypes were tried-out evaluated in realistic situations in close cooperation with potential users, in field trials in people’s homes or in laboratory experiments. For example, for MyVideos, project-team members cooperated with two groups of parents with children in two high schools. First, a group of parents with children in a <marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> high school in The Netherlands participated in focus groups in which they discussed their current practices of recording, editing and viewing video material vis-à-vis the ideas for MyVideos. Some months later, they made video recordings of a concert in which their children performed and participated in user tests, in which they evaluated a first prototype of MyVideos to view and edit the video material recorded at that concert. Next, they participated in focus groups to discuss different options for further development, which directly impacted the development of a second prototype of MyVideos. Next, parents with children at a high school in the UK participated in further evaluation. At a concert in their school, they made video recordings of their children performing and some of them participated in user tests to evaluate the second prototype of MyVideos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>). In these experiments, people’s experiences with using the application were studied by conducting interviews and filling-out questionnaires before, during and after the experiments.<marker type="block"/> The ethics of co-design happen in so far as the participants are able to jointly achieve concrete results and, at the same time, to critically discuss these results—and to learn from this confrontation, for example, when solutions do not work as planned or when problems turn out unexpectedly.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="60" page="12" column="1">– 12 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62s3.page_013.image_02.png" thmb="62s3.page_013.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="64" page="13" column="1">Figure 3: Prototype and user test of MyVideos.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="66" page="13" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="13" column="1">My argument has been that co-design can be understood as a process of collaborative design thinking: a process of joint inquiry and imagination in which diverse people jointly explore and define a problem and jointly develop and evaluate solutions. A process in which participants are able to express and share their experiences, to discuss and negotiate their roles and interests, and to jointly bring about positive change. Co- <marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> design participants combine inquiry, a move from the outside world and others to the inside world, so that they can be curious and jointly learn, and imagination, a move from the inside world to the outside world and others, so that they can be creative and jointly bring about change. Moreover, I have argued that the process of co-design has inherent ethical qualities. These ethics come to the fore in the ways in which and in the extent to which participants are actually able to express and share their experiences, to discuss and negotiate their roles and interests, and to jointly bring about positive change. The ethics 58 come to the fore, for example, in the process of framing , in which participants creatively and iteratively move between problem-setting and solution-finding. Ideally, co-design participants are able to jointly and carefully engage with ethical questions such as: How do I perceive this problem? How do others perceive it? How would I go</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="68" page="13" column="1">– 13 –</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">about solving it? How can we jointly develop solutions?</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="14" column="1">This view is supplementary to other views on co-design, which typically emphasize the generation and combining of knowledge, in that it brings to the fore the importance of combining thinking and feeling, facts and values, of combining doing and reflecting, and divergence and convergence. In the spirit of pragmatism, I would like to advocate organizing co-design more accordingly to these ethics—to its ethos, which often remains implicit. We can do this by making these ethics more explicit, for example, by promoting reflexivity: by helping co-design participants to be more aware of their thoughts and feelings, and of their own roles and interests. By becoming more aware of their involvement, participants can organize their co-design more effectively, so that they can jointly learn and jointly create, address problems in the real world, and develop solutions that work.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="72" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="14" column="1">This paper was written within the TA2 project, which received funding from the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under grant no. ICT-2007-214793. I would like to thank Pieter Jan Stappers for his enthusiasm for the idea to read Dewey to understand co-design, and Larry Hickman for his enthusiasm for an early draft of this paper.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74" page="14" column="1">– 14 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">1 H.W. Chesbrough, Open innovation: The new imperative for creating and profiting from new technology (Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press, 2003); and H.W. Chesbrough,W. Vanhaverbeke, and J. West (eds.), Open innovation: Researching a new paradigm (Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press, 2006). 2 S. Kujala, User involvement: A review of the benefits and challenges, Behaviour and Information Technology, vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 1-17, 2003; H. Rohracher (ed.), User involvement in innovation processes: Strategies and limitations from a socio-technical perspective (München, Germany: Profil Verlag, 2005); and B. Edvardsson, A Gustafsson, P. Kristensson, P. Magnusson, and J. Matthing (eds.), Involving customers in new service development (London, UK: Imperial College Press, 2006). 3 L. Bucciarelli, Designing engineers (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1994). 4 E. B.-N. Sanders and P. J. Stappers, Co-creation and the new landscapes of design, CoDesign, vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 5-18, 2008; and M. Steen, Tensions in human-centred design, CoDesign, vol. 7, no. 1, pp. 45-60, 2011. 5 D. Schuler and A. Namioka (eds.), Participatory design: Principles and practices (Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum, 1993). 6 E. B.-N. Sanders and P. J. Stappers, Co-creation and the new landscapes of design, CoDesign, vol. 4, no. 1, pp. 5-18, 2008. 7 M. Kleinsmann and R. Valkenburg, Barriers and enablers for creating shared understanding in co-design projects, Design Studies, vol. 29, no. 4, pp. 369-386, 2008. 8 M. Steen, M. Manschot and N. De Koning: Benefits of co-design in service design projects, International Journal of Design, vol. 5, no. 2, pp. 53-60, 2011. 9 With the exception of work by, for example, Sanders, Stappers, Kleinsmann, Valkenburg and Van der Lugt (referenced), and work in the Scandinavian Participatory Design tradition, by people like E. Beck, G. Bjerknes, T. Bratteteig, S. Bødker, P. Ehn, J. Greenbaum, M. Kyng, R. Markussen, and more recently, K. Battarbee, J. Buur, J. Fulton Suri, J. Gulliksen, I. Koskinen, S. Kujala, T. Mattelmäki and E. Stolterman. 10 B. Latour and S. Woolgar, Laboratory life: The construction of scientific facts (2nd ed.) (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1986); B. Latour, Science in action: How to follow scientists and engineers through society (Milton Keynes, UK: Open University Press, 1987); S. Woolgar (Ed.) Knowledge and reflexivity: New frontiers in the sociology of knowledge (London, UK: Sage, 1988); M. Ashmore, The reflexive thesis: Wrighting sociology of scientific knowledge (Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1989), K. Knorr Cetina, Laboratory studies: The cultural approach to the study of science, In S. Jasanoff et al. (Eds.), Handbook of Science and Technology Studies (140-166) (London, UK: Sage, 1995); and B. Latour, Aramis, or the love of technology (Translated by Catherine Porter) (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1996). 11 C.S. Peirce, quoted in: N. Cross, ‘Discovering design ability’, Discovering design: Explorations in design studies. R. Buchanan and V. Margolin (Eds.) (Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1995), p. 110. 12 See also: N.F.M. Roozenburg and J. Eekels, Product design: Fundamentals and methods (Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1995).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="76" page="15" column="1">– 15 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">13 K. Dorst, The core of ‘design thinking’ and its application, Design Studies, vol. 32, no. 6, pp. 521-532, 2011. 14 B. Lawson, How designers think: The design process demystified (4th ed.) (Amsterdam: Elsevier, 2006), p. 125; and N. Cross, Designerly ways of knowing (London: Springer-Verlag, 2006), p. 80. See also: K. Dorst and N. Cross, Creativity in the design process: Co-evolution of problem-solution, Design Studies, vol. 22, no. 5, pp. 425-437, 2001; N. Cross, Design thinking (Oxford: Berg Publishing, 2011); and J. Kolko, Abductive thinking and sensemaking: The drivers of design synthesis, Design Issues, vol. 26, no. 1, pp. 15-28, 2010. 15 H.W.J. Rittel and M.M. Webber, Planning problems are wicked problems, in Developments in design methodology, N. Cross, ed. (Chichester: Wiley, 1984); R. Buchanan, Wicked problems in design thinking, Design Issues, vol. 8, no. 2, pp. 5-22, 1992; R. Coyne, Wicked problems revisited, Design Studies, vol. 26, no. 1, pp. 5-17, 2004; and K. Dorst, Design problems and design paradoxes, Design Issues, vol. 22, no. 3, pp. 4-17, 2006. 16 L.A. Hickman, John Dewey's pragmatic technology (Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 1990); L.A. Hickman, Philosophical tools for technological culture: Putting pragmatism to work (Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 2001); J. Keulartz, M. Schermer, M. Korthals, and T. Swierstra, Ethics in technological culture: A programmatic proposal for a pragmatist approach, Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, vol. 29, no. 1, pp. 3-29, 2004; G.A. Emison, The complex challenges of ethical choices by engineers in public service, Science and Engineering Ethics, vol. 12, no. 2, pp. 233-244, 2006; P. Dalsgaard, Designing engaging interactive environments: A pragmatist perspective (PhD dissertation) (Aarhus University, 2009); S.A. Moore, ed., Pragmatic sustainability: Theoretical and practical tools (London: Routledge, 2010); and R. Sennett, The craftsman (London: Penguin Books, 2008). See also: G. Melles, New pragmatism and the vocabulary and metaphors of scholarly design research, Design Issues, vol. 24, no. 4, pp. 88-101, 2008; and C. DiSalvo, Design and the construction of publics, Design Issues, vol. 25, no. 1, pp. 48-63, 2009. 17 J. Dewey, Art as experience (New York: The Berkley Publishing Group, 2005 [first published in 1934]). 18 D.A. Schön, The reflective practitioner: How professionals think in action (New York: Basic Books, 1983); and D.A. Schön, Design: A process of enquiry, experimentation and research, Design Studies, vol. 5, no. 3, pp. 130-131, 1984. 19 D. Hildebrand, Dewey: A beginner’s Guide (Oxford: Oneworld, 2008), p. 3. 20 J. Dewey, The need for a recovery of philosophy, in Creative intelligence: Essays in the pragmatic attitude. J. Dewey, ed. (New York: Henry Holt and Co., 1917), p. 65. 21 D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), pp. 4-6. 22 J. Dewey, Experience and nature (La Salle: Open Court Publishing, 1965), pp. 3-4. 23 J. Dewey, Experience and nature, p. 5-9. 24 J. Dewey, Reconstruction in philosophy (New York: Henry Holt and Co., 1920), p. 78. 25 L. Menand, The metaphysical club: A story of ideas in America (New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2001), pp. 360 and 322.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="78" page="16" column="1">– 16 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">26 R. Van der Lugt and P.J. Stappers, Design and the growth of knowledge (Delft University of Technology, 2006); and P.J. Stappers, Doing design as a part of doing research, in Design research now: Essays and selected projects, R. Michel, ed. (Basel: Birkhäuser Verlag, 2007), pp. 81-91. 27 J. Dewey, Reconstruction in philosophy, p. 178. 28 J. Dewey, Experience and nature, p. 179. 29 J. Dewey, Reconstruction in philosophy, p. 156. 30 D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), p. 5. 31 V. Papanek, Design for the real world: Human ecology and social change (2nd ed.) (Thames &amp; Hudson, London, 1991) and V. Margolin, The politics of the artificial: Essays on design and design studies (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2002). 32 G. Bonsiepe, Design and democracy, Design Issues, vol. 22, no. 2, pp. 27-34, 2006; A. Dong, The policy of design: A capabilities approach, Design Issues, vol. 24, no. 4, 76-87, 2008; D. Nieusma, Alternative design scholarship: Working towards appropriate design, Design Issues, vol. 20, no. 3, pp. 13-24, 2004; and I. Oosterlaken, Design for development: A capability approach, Design Issues, vol. 25, no. 4, pp. 91-102, 2009. 33 L.A. Hickman, Dewey’s theory of inquiry, in Reading Dewey, L.A. Hickman, ed. (1998), pp. 166-186; and D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), pp. 40-62. 34 J. Dewey, Logic: The theory of inquiry (New York: Henry Holt and Co., 1938), pp. 104-105. 35 J.J. Stuhr, Dewey’s social and political philosophy, in Reading Dewey, p. 85. 36 D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), pp. 63-93; and G.F. Pappas, Dewey’s ethics: Morality as experience, in Reading Dewey, L.A. Hickman, ed. (1998), pp. 100-123. 37 D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), p. 63. 38 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination: Pragmatism in ethics (Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 2003), p. 82. 39 D. Hildebrand, Dewey (2008), p. 77. 40 R. Devon and I. Van de Poel, Design ethics: The social ethics paradigm, International Journal of Engineering Education, vol. 20, no. 3, pp. 461-469, 2004. See also: R. Devon, Towards a social ethics of technology: A research prospect, Techne: Research in Philosophy and Technology, vol. 8, no. 1, pp. 99-115. 41 P. Lloyd, Design, ethics and imagination (or: Why we don’t need to teach ethics to designers, but why we should teach philosophers to design), presented at an Ethics Seminar at the Open University, 16 November 2006. 42 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination, p. 58. 43 This section is based on: J. Dewey, Logic: The theory of inquiry, pp. 101-119. 44 D. Hildebrand, Dewey, p. 57.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="80" page="17" column="1">– 17 –</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">45 J. Dewey, Logic: The theory of inquiry, pp. 109. 46 There is a looking backward when perceiving a problem and a looking forward when conceiving solutions. This looking backward and looking forward can be recognized in Dewey’s phrase warranted assertibility, which he used to describe the role of knowledge in inquiry: warranted ‘points backward in time toward something that has been accomplished’ and assertibility ‘points forward in time towards something yet to be done’ (L.A. Hickman, Dewey’s theory of inquiry, 166-167). 47 F. Sleeswijk Visser, Bringing the everyday life of people into design (PhD dissertation) (Delft University of Technology, 2009); and E. B.-N. Sanders, Generative Tools for Co-designing, in Collaborative Design: Proceedings of CoDesigning 2000, S. A. R. Scrivener, L. J. Ball, and A. Woodcock, eds. (London: Springer-Verlag, 2000), pp. 3-12. 48 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination, pp. 55-91. 49 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination, p. 70. 50 M. Kleinsmann and R. Valkenburg, Barriers and enablers for creating shared understanding in co-design projects, Design Studies, vol. 29, no. 4, pp. 369-386, 2008. 51 J. Keulartz, M. Schermer, M. Korthals, and T. Swierstra, Ethics in technological culture: A programmatic proposal for a pragmatist approach, Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, vol. 29, no. 1, pp. 3-29, 2004. 52 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination, p. 65. 53 S. Fesmire, John Dewey and moral imagination, pp. 67. 54 L.A. Hickman, Dewey’s theory of inquiry, p. 169. 55 J. Dewey, The need for a recovery of philosophy, p. 69. 56 See also: www.ta2-project.eu 57 M. Steen, J. Buijs and D. Williams: The role of scenarios and demonstrators in promoting shared understanding in innovation projects, International Journal of Innovation and Technology Management, vol. x, no. x, pp. x-x, 2012 (forthcoming). 58 K. Dorst, The core of ‘design thinking’ and its application.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="82" page="18" column="1">– 18 –</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
