<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>7a53b32f2a37d2647dbdb1a76f7b40c347a1595613553f52d59f0a0d3322da51</job>
    <base_name>62mk</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/016224399101600402</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Flexible Sketches and Inflexible Data Bases: Visual Communication, Conscription Devices, and Boundary Objects in Design Engineering</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx2">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62mk.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Flexible Sketches</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Inflexible Data Bases: Visual Communication</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Conscription Devices</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Boundary Objects in Design Engineering Author(s): Kathryn Henderson Source: Science</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Technology</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Human Values</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">Vol.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="10">No. 4 (Autumn</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="11">)</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="12">pp. 448-473 Published by: Sage Publications</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="13">Inc. Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/689803 . Accessed: 18/11/</name>
          <aff id="14">:</aff>
          <aff id="15">18</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">of Use, available at .</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="17">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19">discover, use, and build upon a wide range of increase productivity and facilitate new forms</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="21" confidence="possible">. JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="20">support@jstor.org</email>.</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23">Sage Publications, Inc. is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Science, Technology, &amp;Human Values.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx24">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62mk.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="26"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="25">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="27">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="28">FlexibleSketches and Inflexible DataBases:VisualCommunication, Conscription Devices, and Boundary Objectsin DesignEngineering</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible">Kathryn Henderson TexasA&amp;MUniversity</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="30">Engineeringsketchesand drawingsare the technologicaldesign and production.These visual representations act as the design to productionprocess, hence serving as a "social glue" both between individuals and The authordiscusses two main capacities such visual representations serve in facilitating distributed team design work.As conscriptiondevices, they enlist and organize group participation~ As boundaryobjects, they facilitate the reading of various groups involvedin the design process. The introduction of computer-aided design into relationships betweenworkersin ways thatcan these crucial capacities to takeplace. The data are drawnfroma studyof the daily practices of engineersengaged in redesigninga participant observation.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31">A professional model maker, unable verbally to describe what he is working on, walks across the room to fetch a drawingso he can point to its various parts. A senior drafter,recently promotedto engineer, fights with managementto get her drawingboardback, stating,"I can't thinkwithout my drawingboard."A field engineer,explainingthe workings of a turbine</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" confidence="possible">AUTHOR'SNOTE: I wish to expressmy appreciation to the engineers,staff, andmanagement at "Selco" for their patience with my presence and my their hectic work schedules. The helpful comments of Leigh Star, Bruno Latour, Michael Schudson, Joe Gusfield, Chuck Nathanson,JudithPerrolle,Jon Guice, Eric Palmer,Neelam Sethi,andthe anonymousrefereeshave contributed to the increasing clarity of this its errorsare,of course, my own. Because of the need to protectproprietary design information, representations that would have servedas illustrations were unavailablefor publication. An earlier version of this article was presented at the American Sociological Association Atlanta,August 1988.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="33">Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, Vol.16 No.4, Autumn 1991 448-473 ? 1991SagePublications, Inc. 448</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx34">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62mk.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="35">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36">Henderson/ Design Engineering 449</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45">engine in multiplelanguagesto ThirdWorldusers, says, "ThankGod for the drawings," which he coded to show functionsusing colored pencils. This is a visual culture-the world of design engineers.1 Here, sketchingand drawing arethebasic componentsof communication; words arebuiltaroundthem, but the drawingsareso centralthatpeople assembledin meetingswait while individualsfetch visual representations left in theiroffices or sketchfacsim- iles on white boards. Coordinationand conflict take place over, on, and throughthe drawings.These visual representations shape the structure of the work,who may participate in the work,andthe final productsof design engi- neering.They are a componentof the social organizationof collective cognition and the locus for practice-situated and practice-generated knowledge. Contrary to the still-persistentmythology of the so-called scientific age that has long attributedtechnological accomplishmentsto the virtue of "scientific truth"addressedto humanneeds, it is the mundaneinteractions of actors,machines,and paperthatconstructtechnologicalinnovation.The researchevidence in this articlejoins others(Laudan1984; Mackenzie and Wajcman1985; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Winner 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Law 1986</xref>; Latour 1987; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Bijker, Pinch, and Hughes 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Law and Callon 1988</xref>) in challenging scientific-formula- drivenviews of technology.Engineeringsketchesanddrawingsarethebuild- ing blocks of technologicaldesign and production.Moreover,because they are developed and used throughinteraction, these visual representations act as the means for organizingthe design to productionprocess, hence serving as a social glue between individualsand between groups.The drawingsand sketches themselves structure the work process as well as its product. While a good numberof technology studies have looked at historical materialsand the majorityof studies of representational practice in contem- poraryscience have concentratedon the physical and biological sciences, this study looks at the role of visual representations in present-dayengineer- ing practices.The study is based on participant observationof day-to-day practicesin a contemporary industrialsetting among engineers engaged in the actual process of designing a turbineengine package. It focuses on the way the introductionof a CAD/CAM system (computerassisted design/ computerassisted manufacture)destroyed traditionalboundariesbetween design engineersandthe shop floor,therebyrestructuring social relationsand generatingresponsesto that restructuring. The destructionof important situated practices within the visual conventions of design activity lies in an elementarymisunderstanding of both the practicesthemselves and their interactive character.These fundamentalmisunderstandings are constructed into the CAD/CAM system, whose designers assume a linear theory of innovationthatprojectsa straightforward process from idea, to drawing,to prototype,to production.This articleillustrates,as Latourand Knorr-Cetina<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> among others have argued,thatsuch rigid models are seriously misguided. While such models integrate well with and are even prerequisiteto the constructionof an integratedcomputersystem, the assumptionson which they arebased and the very "efficiency"of theirintendeduse dis-integrates the social communication practicesthatnormallyserveto repairtheproblems and misunderstandings that arepartof the work process.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx42">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62mk.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="43">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="44">450 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="46" confidence="possible">Concepts</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73">A centralfocus of this articleis thecrucialroleplayedby boundaryobjects (Star1989) as agentsthatsocially organizedistributed cognition.Aboundary object allows membersof differentgroupsto readdifferentmeaningspartic- ular to their needs from the same material.This is possible because the materialremainsflexible in group use and more focused in individualsite use ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Star 1989</xref>; StarandGriesmer1989). Cognitionis distributed, as it were, as variousforms of nonverbalknowledge are elicited and capturedto some degree throughinteraction with sketchesand drawings.The visual represen- tationshelp coordinatedistributed cognition since they allow for the manip- ulationof tacitknowledgebetween individuals.The capacityof engineering sketches and drawingsto be flexible for various uses and users and thus to facilitate differentialreadingsqualifies them as boundaryobjects in Star's terms. Investigationof the social construction of technologynecessarilyleads to the examinationof the daily processes involved in the work itself.2Scholars in the sociology of scientific knowledge view the science-technologyrela- tionshipas egalitarianand interactive. To get closer to the technicalcontents of discovery, experimentation, replication,argumentation, and representation as they occur in the processes of knowledge production,a numberof these researchers have incorporated constructivist and ethnomethodological approaches into theirwork, includingparticipant observation,in-depthinter- views, and analysis of informal "shop talk" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Latour and Woolgar 1986</xref>; Knorr-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Cetina 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Lynch 1985a</xref>; Collins 1985). The data presentedhere, based on similar participationin the everyday activities of designers and drafters, illustratethe social andpracticalconsequencesof replacinginterac- tive social practices with technical equipment. The normally occurring interaction in this case dependson the social organization of tacitknowledge, accomplishedthroughthe use of visual conventionsto constructand negoti- ate the collective cognition intrinsicto team design work. The role of tacit knowledgehas become a growing concern in practice- orientedstudies of science and technology.3I am using the termhere in the<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> broadestsense, that is, to signify knowledge that is not verbalized,in some cases because it cannotbe, but in othercases because it may simply be taken forgrantedor regardedas too trivialto warrant verbalization. The generation and elicitation of all types of tacit knowledge is intrinsically linked to practice.Withinthe broadresidualcategoryof tacit knowledge, two particular types of nonverbal knowledge are pertinent here. These are visual knowledgeand kinestheticknowledge.4Engineeringdrawingsand sketches do not capturethe full arrayof tacit knowledge used in practice,but like indexicalsthey standfor or point to morecomplex stocks of tacit knowledge and provide a loose, broad frame for them, so that individualsand groups may index differentinformation or knowledgefromthe same representation or portionof it.5 Recent work in cognitive science (Hutchinsforthcoming) suggests that it is a mistake to assume groupcognitive action is the same as thatof individuals.6 Drawings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="55" class="deo:Reference">and sketches serve the social organizationof distributedcognition in a manner similar to that described by Suchman (1988)</xref> for white boards.The predominant differencebetweenthe engineers' representational practice and thatof the cognitive scientistsis thatengineers rely more heavily on the purelyvisual format.The contrastis significantbe- cause of the link betweenvisual information and nonverbaltacitknowledge. Representational practice in science has recentlybecome an intensefocus in examining the productionof scientific knowledge. Studies in this area focus on what LatourandWoolgar(1986) have termed"inscriptions," which take the form of visual or verbal devices such as intentionallyarranged, trimmed,and filteredsamples;carefullycroppedphotographic records;and edited charttracings(Latour1986; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Lynch 1985b, 1988</xref>; Gilbert<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="57" class="deo:Reference">and Mulkay 1984; Woolgar 1988</xref>; Amann and Knorr-Cetina1988; Knorr-Cetinaand Amann1990; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Pinch 1985</xref>; Shapin1984; Bowker 1988; Rudwick1976).7The view of technologicalpracticetakenin this articlesimilarlyshows technology as a social process, simultaneouslysocially shapedandsociety shaping. Studies of the social constructionof technology by Law (1986, 1987), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Law and Callon (1988)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Bowker (1987)</xref>, Latour (1988), and Mackenzie and Spinardi(1988), to name a few, illustratethe view that the received con- structedenvironmentis not the only possibility and that the processes of inscription,construction,and persuasionover time must be understoodas part of the productionof any technological artifact.I join these and other scholars(Barnes1982; Barnesand<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Edge 1982</xref>;Bloor 1976;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Garfinkel, Lynch, and Livingston 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Woolgar 1985</xref>, for example) in science studies in the convictionthatall knowledgeandknowledgeclaims aresocially constructed and in the argument for a nonreductionist,interactive approach to the machinein context.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> This article goes beyond current studies of visual representationsin science, however, in that it reveals the role of engineering sketches and drawingsas devices thatsocially organizethe workers,theworkprocess,and the concepts workers manipulatein engineeringdesign. Visually oriented inscriptiondevices particular to engineering,which I have termedconscrip- tion devices, enlist the participationof those who would employ them in either the design or productionprocess, since users must engage in the generation,editing, and correctionof drawingsduringtheir constructionif the design is to serve its intendedfunction. Historians of technology have documented the vital aspect of visual informationin the technological practices of engineers from the fifteenth century forward.The earliest drawingscarriedthe whole task of building informationwith little verbal or mathematical elaboration(Ferguson1976, 1985; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Hindle 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Booker 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Baynes and Pugh 1981</xref>). The more recent applicationof computer-generated graphicsto engineeringdesign work has generated interest in the contrastof design engineers' actual practice and engineeringschool protocols(Ullman,Stauffer,andDietterich1987). Some authorshave suggested thatthe process of creatingdrawingsmay be as importantto design as the drawingsthemselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Bly 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Tang and Leifer 1988</xref>). My examinationof visual communicationpracticesin the world of technologicalinnovationis based on a case study of the visual communications thatstructure the processof designingan industrial applications engine package and focuses on what happensto the structureof the interactionof actorsand artifactswhen computer-aided design is broughtinto the process. In this case study,the introduction of a CAD/CAMsystem into the visual culture of engineering drawings hampers the flexibility crucial to their function, particularly because the computer-generated drawingsare linked to several otherdatabases, overextendingthe capacityof drawingsto act as boundaryobjects. This happensbecause they become less flexible but also because of the assumptionsof the linearprocesses of design work built into the programs themselves.The social activitiesrestructured most significantly by the introduction of CAD/CAMarethe processesof sketchinganddrafting designs. CAD/CAM is meantto allow engineersto design on the computer. This means thatthey must reorganizea system of visual representation.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx52">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62mk.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="53">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54">Henderson/ Design Engineering 451</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx65">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62mk.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="67">452 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible">Method and Context</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83">Serving as technicalwriterat an engineeringfirm in southernCalifornia for over a year allowed me to observe and participatein the daily activities of engineerswho were in the processof designinga new turbine engine pack- <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> age. My access to the site was a negotiated exchange for my work as a technicalwriter;all those I talkedwith knew me as the residentsociologist. I attended design meetings, questioned design and mechanical engineers, drafters, illustrators, and technicalwritersconstantly,viewed trainingvideo- tapes, interviewedmanagersin depth, and observed the interactionsof de- signersandshop workersbothduringthe planningof the newengine package andduringthe buildingof the prototype.As a participant observerI was able to learn members'practices and meanings, specifically the visual conventions in the world of turbineengine design. Daily work activities do not take place in a vacuum; rather,they are situatedin an environment influencedby a company'shistoryand economic healthand by members'views of the effect of those factors on themselves andtheirjobs. Before a designmeetingever takesplace, actorsmakepolitical andpower moves and allianceswithin the companyand in the world of the market.Selco, a pseudonymfor the mid-sized,mid-techcompanyI studied,8 builds a line of large engines for industrialapplications.The company has been shrinkingfor almost two decades since the collapse, first, of the aero- space industryand then of the oil and gas industries.Companymanagers undertookyet anotherreorganization, includingextensive layoffs, in 1984. While Selco has been experiencing some success with "co-generational" products that produce energy and make by-product heat available for a secondaryapplication,they mustalso workto staycompetitivewith Japanese companiesin their market. Turbineengines, and most technologicalproducts,are not designedfrom scratchbut are amalgamations of various partsof earliertechnologies with new ideas incorporated.9 The design group I worked with was redesigning the package support structurefor a new model of one of the company's smaller engines with the goal of increasingits outputfrom 8,000 kilowatts to 10,000 kilowattswhile manufacturing it at a lower cost. The old version sold for $550,000 with 50% profitability. The goal for the new version was a 20% reductionin the $225,000 cost. I will referto this projectas the Vul- can MarkIV. The name, changedhere for anonymity,refers to the size and capacityof the engine. Selco also buildsthreelargerengines, all with Greco- Romandeity names that suggest heavenly bodies, a leftover from the aero- space era. The "Mark" numberrefersto consecutive designs of a given engine, MarkIII being the previousdesign designation. Engineersdifferentiate between the actualturbineengine and the system that supportsit. The designersI workedwith were in the "packaging" division. Packagingincludesthe lubrication, oil, gas, andelectricalsystemsalong with the structuralframe that contains and supportsthese systems and the engine. One underlyingdesign conceptfor the new enginewas to makecom-<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> ponents of the supportingsystems modular,that is, self-contained,so they could be easily removed for maintenance and repair work without the necessityof dismantlingotherpartsof themachine.Thiswas to be doneusing cheaperand lightermaterialsto keep costs down and profitsup, while maintaining the company's reputationfor the productionof very high quality, heavy duty turbineengines. Shrinkagein theirmarkethas meantthatSelco no longerdevelops single products for a largemarketsuch as militaryapplications but, rather, produces specializedproducts for single customers.Thishas meanta short-range focus on doing the particular job at hand,rather than attention to keepingup a large database for repetitiveuse. In today's world of international engineering,visual communicationis just as importantas in earlierperiods.Engineeringis intrinsicallylinked to visual communicationfrom the first steps of the design process, through production and sales, to the training of customer personnel. Computer graphicssystems such as CAD/CAMarebeing introduced in manufacturing companiesaroundthe globe in hopes of circumventingrepetitionsof visual renderingsand thus cutting time and labor costs. A subgoal of the team designing the MarkIV was to integratecomputergraphicsmore fully into the design and productionprocess. Thus they were counting on formal proceduresroutedthroughthe database and CAD/CAMsystem to facilitate communicationand coordinationbetween departments. However, as I will illustrate,some substantialgaps occurred.The constraintsof this article do not permit a full discussion of all of the modes of visual communicationI observed as a new design went into production.I have discussed these elsewhere(Henderson1989). I will confine my discussionto those at the two ends of the design process:sketches,the buildingblocks of design, andfixed drawings,the officially recognizedcarriers of design information, actuallya set of officially released drawings. Both sketches and fixed drawings are inscriptiondevices as well as boundaryobjects but differ from one another in the scope of the boundariesthey serve.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx76">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62mk.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="77">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="78">Henderson/ Design Engineering 453</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx80">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62mk.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="81">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="82">454 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible">Boundary Objects and Conscription Devices</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="86">Latour and others use the term inscriptions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Latour and Woolgar 1986</xref>;</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="129">Latour1986, 1987) for images thathave been extractedfrom the laboratory that appearlater cleaned, redrawn,and displayedas figures in supportof a text. The essentialcharacteristics of inscriptionsarethatthey aremobile,pre- sentable,readable,combinablewith one another, and immutable.The immu- <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> table qualityof an inscriptionrefersto its translation into a formatof optical consistency with thatof the originalsource so thatthe internalpropertiesof the subject representedare not modified (Latour1986, 7). In visual modes this is accomplishedthroughsome device such as the illusion of perspective or the conventions of map making or drafting.All types of engineering drawings share these characteristics with inscriptionsbut differ slightly in directionality. Lynch and Woolgar(1988) describe directionalityof representations in the practiceof science as "a movementof an assemblyline" in the musterof the full range of literaryand artisticconventions available to build up the scientist's argument visibly. These authorscontrastsuch argument assembly to any actual"movementaway fromor towardan originaryreality." Further, they point out thatthe use of "mere"metaphor, similarity,or surfaceresem- blance in representations is regardedas inadequatein science, to be aban- doned in favor of "deep,""genetic,"or "mathematical" reconstructions of a phenomenon'sorganization, which illustrate"penetration" into the depthsof the phenomenon,its unraveling,its dissection (1988, 105). The character of engineeringdrawings is similar but needs furtheranalysis, since drawings must be put into productionaftertheir own construction.Visual representations in engineeringmust capturethe buildingup of the phenomenonrather than its dissection or disassembly, yet these representations, too, require visual articulationof a minutely detailed nature,which reveals the inner structureand workings of the object represented. While representations in science are assembled in the course of a text to constructthe end product cumulatively-a convincing argumentin the mannerof the "movementof an assembly line"- engineering drawings must accumulateand articulate information for the assemblyline. Engineeringdesigns are built up through a cascadeof representations and re-representations to constructa final design, as Latour(1986) suggests is the case with other cascades of inscriptions. However, at this point the directionality turns, andthe constructeddesign in which "things" were turnedinto papermust now be used to turnpaperback into things. Since in most cases someone other than the designers must physically constructthe objectthatthe designershave socially constructed, conventions of representation have developed in the draftingtrade to attemptto make explicit the knowledge requiredto producethe object.Thatthey fail to make all nonverbalknowledge explicit, of course, does not alterthe intentionof their endeavor, which acknowledges the importanceof tacit knowledge. Scientists may dismiss tacit knowledge as the trivial craftsmanship of the laboratory, mystify it as "art" or "magic," or intentionallywithhold it from<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> other scientists in order to maintain an edge in areas of new Conscientiousengineeringdesignerswho consultwith shop workersas well as with other designers, however, succeed in incorporatingat least some levels of tacit knowledge in theirdesigns. The importanceof interactivepractice surroundingthe drawings in the elicitation of such knowledge must not be underestimated.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Lave (1988)</xref>, drawingon recentdevelopmentsin the social anthropology of cognitionand the syntheses fermenting in social theorygenerally,arguesthatknowledge- in-practice,constitutedin the settings of practice, is the locus of the most powerfulknowledgeabilityof people in the lived-in world.~ She arguesthat the whole person in action-acting with the settings of that activity-is a more appropriate unit of analysis thanthe one used in reductivetheories,in which "theindividualis reducedto a self-containeddisembodiedtechnology of cognition,knowledge is reducedto scientific 'discoveries,'and society to a set of actors whose lives are structured only by self-interestedmotives." On the basis of her studies of cognitive activity in everyday settings, she<marker type="block"/> school is the main prerequisitethat makes cognitive skills available for transferacross situationsand for everydayuse.'2 Similarly,my point is that it is not school-learneddraftingconventionsor school-learnedmathematical formulasused in engineeringthatfacilitateandconstructengineeringdesign work and knowledge. Ratherthe everydaypracticesof sketching,drawing, and draftingactively constructnot only the new technologies that emerge from designers but also the collective knowledge and interactionsof the design engineers. To accentuatethe role of engineering drawings as network-organizing devices and draw attentionto the process of theircreation,I have termeda subgroup of inscription devices conscriptiondevices, in thatthey enlist group participation and arereceptaclesfor knowledgecreatedandadjustedthrough group interactionaimed towarda common goal. To participateat all in the design process,actorsmustengage one anotherthroughthe visual representation of the conscriptiondevice. They focus their attentionand their communicationswith one anotherby referringto it. The conscriptivequalityof these visual representations is so strongthat participants find it difficult to communicateaboutthe design at all withoutthem. If a visual representation is not broughtto a meeting of those involved with the design, someone will sketch a facsimile on a white board (presentin all engineeringconference rooms) when communicationbegins to falter,or a team memberwill leave the meeting to fetch the crucialdrawingsso group memberswill be able to understand one another.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> As products bearing knowledge that means one thing to some group memberswho use themandsomethingelse to othermembers,these conscription devices serve as boundaryobjects. Accordingto Star(1989), boundary objectsare"objectswhich arebothplasticenoughto adaptto local needs and constraintsof the several parties employing them, yet robust enough to maintaina common identity across sites." Detail renderingsare one of the tightly focused portionsthatmake up the more flexible whole of a drawing set. For example, the depiction of a welded joint may stand for partof the supportstructure to the designerandstandfor laborexpendedto those in the shop. If the designerconsultswith workerswho suggest a formationthatwill save welds and then incorporatesthe advice, collective knowledge is cap- turedin the design. One small partof the welders' tacit knowledgecomes to be represented visually in the drawing.Hence the flexibility of the sketch or drawing as a boundaryobject helps in enlisting the aid and knowledge of additionalparticipants. On a cognitive level, Hutchins(forthcoming)suggests thatthe cognitive propertiesof groupsmay differ from those of individualsand thus may depend on the social organizationof individualcognitive capabilities.In his examinationof the social organizationof distributed cognition in reference to navigation,he points out thatit is "simply an implementation of the eth- nographer's fantasy"to assumethatall the individualsin a sharedinteraction have exactly the same schematafor a given situation.In accountingfor a particular ship collision, he notes<marker type="block"/> My point is thatwhetherthe sharedinformation is on a piece of paperin front of the participants or a schematawithin the mind, the flexibility that allows for multipleinterpretations is a crucialqualitythatfacilitatesthat sharing. The way engineeringdesign participants focus their attentionand their communicationswith one anotherin referenceto the conscriptiondevice as boundaryobject is similarto the approach that Suchman(1988) describesin her analysis of cognitive scientists'groupuse of the white board.Although not every detailedaspect of cognitive scientists'white-boarduse is identical with engineers' use of drawingsand sketches, there are outstandingparal- lels.13Suchman,for example, characterizes the white boardas structuring a "sharedinteractionalspace" and a "second interactional floor which is co- extensive and sequentially interlockedwith talk." The co-extensive and<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> interlockingnatureof the link between visual representationsand talk is probablyeven strongerin engineeringinteractions than in those of cognitive scientists. In engineeringdesign meetings conversationcenters around,on, and throughvisual representations to the extent, as previously noted, that speech actuallybegins to fail. Participants may even resortto handgestures or drawingin the air if a sketchingsurfaceand some sort of markerare not present. Engineers'drawings,like cognitive scientists' white boards,"achieve a conceptualorderingbetween items," althoughthe orderingin engineering drawingswill be a spatialordering.Both the drawingsand the white boards may be "delineatedinto owned territories or inhabitedjointly."The joining of individuallyowned and interpreted territories as well as jointly inhabited ones into a largerjointly inhabitedframeis the very point of the functionof representations as boundaryobjects. It is this aspect that, like that of the cognitive scientists' white boards, allows engineers' visual representations theflexibility"tobecome a settingforthe production and resolutionof design dilemmas." Finally,just as the white boardis "embeddedin a networkof activities" and "servesas an unfoldingsetting for the work at hand"and as an index of past and horizonof futureactivities,so, too, the engineeringdrawingsrepre- sent the tangiblebut unmalleablemachineof the past in a mannerin which it can be manipulatedon paper. Yet even the final paper rendition that representsthe end productdesign will be the point of departure for subse- quent phases of futureiterations.Of course, the major differencebetween cognitive scientists'representations and those of designengineersis the more explicitly visual dimensionof engineeringdesigns, which are more depen- dent on the manipulation of line thanon the manipulation of words. At any phasethe enlistingdrawingmustremainsufficientlyflexible if the transferof knowledge is to take place. Latour(1986) cites the historiccon- tributionsof linear perspective and descriptive geometry to engineering draftingin maintaining "opticalconsistency"andthusfacilitatingthe change of scale from large machineto flat renditions.Representational conventions in contemporaryengineering incorporateeven more techniquesto embed information into flat renditions.These includean entirelexicon of schematic symbols that designate types and specific functions of componentparts of the machinebeing designed.In this pictographic lexicon, an abstract symbol representsa functionalcomponentand additionalvisual codes elaboratethe basic shape to give more specific information.For instance,if two triangles designate a basic valve, the additionof a thirdtrianglecan indicatea three- way valve. The lexicon allows the schematic drawingsto remainflexible enough that engineerscan readthe coded functionsin the layout and under-<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> stand the interrelations of the various functionalcomponentsof the whole project. This holds even when the main concern of an individualengineer may be more tightly focused on the aspects of the design applicable to her or his own area of expertise, for example-for an electrical engineer- electricalcomponentsand functions. The ability of schematic layout drawings that utilize this pictographic lexicon to picture the entire relationshipof functional components while giving detailed informationfor those working on a specific aspect of the design nicely illustratesStar's definition of boundaryobjects as "weakly structured in common use," and "stronglystructured in individual-siteuse." At the same time, this very definitionreveals the problemof CAD-CAM at Selco. There the set of official fixed drawings is so strongly structured, because of its many interlocking computerdata bases, that its ability to function as a boundaryobject is impaired.I discuss this in more detail in a later section. First, it is necessaryto look at the buildingblocks used in the process of constructinga set of officially released,fixed drawings.<marker type="block"/> Sketches are the real heartof visual communication.They are probably the most important carriersof visual knowledge because they serve both as an interactivecommunicationtool and as an individualthinkingtool. The flexibility of sketches to serve in both these capacities allows these two functions to overlap when designers collaborate,so that sketches become group thinkingtools of distributedcognition. For example, Selco management was sold on the design of the Mark IV by a model generatedfrom conversations between Cap, the senior engineer known as "the guru of piping,"and a hobbyist model builderin management who became project engineer for the enterprise.The new design combined some of the best aspectsof previousdesigns along with new ideas. Before the model could be built, these ideas had to be conveyed throughrough sketches accompanied by conversation. In their early draft stages drawings also are used by designersas an interactivetool, in that they may be alteredor correctedby someone otherthanthe personwho drewthem. Sketchingis connectedwith thoughtsthatarein visual format.As an interactivetool sketchesarethe most directway for an engineerto help form a concept in the mind of a colleague by giving form to concepts picturedin her or his own mind. The importance of sketches as individualthinkingtools is illustrated by a design engineer who said that when she was promoted from drafterto engineer,they took her draftingboard away.T4 She askedfor it back, stating,<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> "Ican't thinkwithoutmy draftingboard."As a thinkingtool the renditionof the visual image onto paper is analogous to the accomplishmentsof the writtenworkin the historicaldevelopmentof literacy.A physicalpicture,like writing,becomes the carrierfor a concept, allowing it to traversetime and space independentof its author.The tangible shape or form of the concept rendered onto paperalso allows for criticalanalysisnot possible when it was only a visualizationin someone's mind. Sharonstates,"As soon as you start drawingit, you have ideas andchanges.You'reerasingit andimprovingit." And later,"Butwhen you startlaying it out, that'swhere, you know, 80%of the problemscome out." In the early stages this is a rapidprocess duringwhich the sketch serves as notes or the outlinefor a piece of writing.Sharonnotes, "Theysay the best designers startdrawingright from the beginning."Like note taking, quick sketchinggets fleeting ideas down before they disappearfrommemory.The sketchcapturesthem in a concreteformatandform-literally giving ideas a potentialshape that is a first approximation of the actual form objects will take. Sketchingalso serves anotherpurpose,which is to understand the param- eters of the project itself better:"You'rejust trying to get a size, trying to understand it ... to get an understanding of the system, almostbuilding up your self-confidence so you know the task you've been assigned."Sharon illustratesthe sketch's use both as an individual thinking tool and as a conscriptiondevice, showing its flexibility from one to the other in her statement: "As soon as you have something,you can take it to someone else and say, 'Look this is what I have, how can I improve on it?' or 'Did you have a problemin this areatoo?' " At the interactivelevel, sketches serve as boundaryobjects and assist communicationto refine ideas further. As boundaryobjects servingto assist shared cognition concerning the packaging of a turbineengine, sketches capturepertinent knowledgefrommanysources.Cap,the seniordesigneron the Mark IV, points out that these conscriptiondevices are used not only between design engineersbut also to facilitateconsultationbetween designers and those in the productioncycle. He discusses his ideas early in the design process with people in "structures," the unit that does welding. He states:"I usuallytake my layouts rightafterI've started,afterI do my initial layouts,before they're ever dimensioned." This allows him to plan a design thatis the most efficientto build:"It'sjust a matterof 'is this thebest possible way to do this particular thing' and usually it's peripheral, but a lot of times they'll say, ah, 'Well, gee, if you did this, over here, this would save one weld.' "<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> An example of sketches as boundary objects-strongly structuredin individualsite use but weakly structured for use in common-is illustrated in Cap's dependenceon sketches afterthe layout is finished and the project moves to production.Detailed visual informationis initially providedonly in a layout format-a "top-down"view that shows the placementof parts like a map.Detaileddepictionsof how the finalprojectshould"look"or how partsfit togetherare not available on the shop floor duringthe assembly of a first package. (When the project goes into standardproduction,a build book, generatedout of the process of the first assembly and integrated with assembly instructionsfrom parts vendors will be available for the shop.) Because he knows from experiencethatthe initial conscriptiondevices can easily be misinterpreted, Cap is on the shop floor duringthe first assembly of his designs and provides additionalvisual information when needed. He acknowledgesthat for workers,workingfrom the two-dimensionallayouts, "theystill may not make as much sense in one area,so you circle a line on it and make a little hand sketch off to one side there to clarify the thing." Pointingto a vague areain a layout he says:<marker type="block"/> While not all designersfollow throughas thoroughlyas Capdoes, his use of visual communication throughhandsketchesfacilitatesboththe earlydesign process during its conceptualstates and the actualrealizationof the design during its final production.He moves back from the weak structureof the layout drawingto the strengthof its building blocks, sketches, to fill in the site-specific detail. The informalvisual communicationof sketching is essential to getting ideas across; Sharonsays you never "get two designers who just sit down andjust talk,"adding,"Everybody draws sketchesto each other." Cap points out that a meeting with people in structures, where the package is actually built "workswrong if you can't communicate." He takeshis drawingsto "sit and talk," so others understand what he is trying to do. Likewise he draws sketchesfor workersso they can understand what they are supposedto do to create what he has in his mind that may not be clear in their minds from looking only at layoutdrawings.This interactiveuse of conscriptiondevices as boundaryobjects knits together the input of people with expertise from shop experience such as the welders in the "structures" division with the<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> combined knowledge of various designers. It taps individual expertise in piping, electrical circuitry,lubricationsystems, and so on to socially constructa machinebuilt throughorganized,distributed cognition.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx88">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_008.image_09.png" thmb="62mk.page_008.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="89">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="90">Henderson/ Design Engineering 455</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx92">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_009.image_10.png" thmb="62mk.page_009.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94">456 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="95">research.TM</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="98">challenges the view that explicit, general knowledge of the sort taught in</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx100">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_010.image_11.png" thmb="62mk.page_010.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="101">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="102">Henderson/ Design Engineering 457</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="104">In the ship collision situation,it the mate shared the schematafor motion of other ships. But, consensus on schematais not the same of events. Two individualscould have the same schema for the same phenomenonand still of events.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx106">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_011.image_12.png" thmb="62mk.page_011.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="107">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="108">458 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx110">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_012.image_13.png" thmb="62mk.page_012.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="112">Henderson/ Design Engineering 459</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="114">The Importance of Sketches</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx116">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_013.image_14.png" thmb="62mk.page_013.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="117">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="118">460 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx120">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62mk.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="121">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="122">Henderson/ Design Engineering 461</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="124">Forinstance,like whereit's blackherein thisarea,theysee a dottedline coming down on there?"I'm liable to just go off with the pencil and go make a little handsketch off to one side just to make it clearer to the guys doing it at the time but it wouldn't be as a permanent anything.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx126">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_015.image_16.png" thmb="62mk.page_015.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="127">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="128">462 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible">The Fixed Drawing as Boundary Object and Conscription Device</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="144">The most complex conscriptiondevice is the fixed drawing,the official document that is credited with conveying visual informationfor a given project.Although called a "drawing," the fixed drawingis actually a set or several sets of drawingsthat become official carriersof informationwhen they are "released" by the projectengineer.Releasing a drawingmeans it is in its final form and can be distributed to the varioususer groups.However, it is widely used as a conscription device beforethispoint,as I havediscussed underthe subjectof sketches.The set thatmakesup the drawingconsists not only of the layoutdrawingsof the objectitself. It also includesan installation layout, detail views, electrical diagrams,the highly codified schematics of the functionalcomponentsof the machines(discussedpreviously),and also a partslist. The drawingsarereadlike maps.Eachparthas a letterandnumber code, so it can be easily foundwithin the drawing.This indexing is done in the same mannerthat streetsor towns are found on a road map by locating the intersection of thenumberandlettergridlines. The formaldrawingserves not only in the design andfabrication stages of the productbut in marketing, sales, inventory control, and accounting. Every minute part of the final productis indexed on the drawingsand matchedto a partnumberkept in a computerfile. This multifunctioning of the fixed drawingas a conscription device means it enlists an even largernumberof participants. As a boundary object, it is of much largerscope than the sketches from which it is built. It encompasses many more boundaries,in thatit is integrated with othercomputerizeddata bases: the partsindexed to the drawingare also partof inventoryand sales records.Thisis too muchoverlapforone boundary object, becauseit hampers the flexibility of boundaryobjects(weakly structured in common use). The interlockingdatabases of cost accountingandinventorycontroloverloadthe boundaryobject and make it appearinflexible, so that employees at Selco become intimidated by it andlook for ways to work aroundit. To understand this intimidation a closer look at the social contextof the historyof computerassisted design at Selco is helpful. <marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> The Mark IV project was the first attempt on the part of designers, management,and CAD/CAM operatorsto capturethe design on the computergraphicssystem early in the process ratherthan completely after-the- fact as merely a record-keeping operation- its usualuse up to this point.The package design managerdescribedits use: "Wedesign things on paperand then we hand it over to the CADs system. We use the CADs system as a recordkeeping and ratherexpensive, fast eraser." He also noted thatthis is not regardedas the conventionalway to use a computergraphics system, stating,"Wego backwards.Insteadof buildinga picture,andthentakingthe detail pieces off, we often end up going the other way around-which is wrong." Selco management initially triedto interesttheirdesignengineersin using the new graphicssystemwhen it was firstinstalledin the 1970s. Classeswere offered on a half-day basis: four hours of regularwork and four hours of instructionfor a periodof two weeks. A senior designerstated:"A lot of us went throughthe course in CADs, but a crash two-week course in CADs could just leave you totally confused." He further pointed out that by comparingnotes on course contentwith outside-trained "CADs"operators, he foundthatthe operators had spent"six months,eight hoursa day"learning the same applications.Althougha numberof courseswere offeredto designers, not enough time was allowed for the designers to practiceand "play" with the abilities of the equipmentsince they also had to keep up with their regularwork.15 Moreover,if they did try to do theirwork using the graphics system, the initial bugs in the system in the early periodresultedin the loss of hoursof work. Engineersbecame disenchantedand "infrequent users" of the technology, thus making its use a time-consumingchore ratherthan an efficient technology. Hand drawingremainedmore time and cost effective for experienceddesigners.This was the main argumentdesignershad used with management.Management,having to meet deadlines,backed off to a certainextent,decidingthatimplementation of computergraphicswas going to be generational;the next generationof design engineers would use the system. Since the companyhas been in a shrinkingmode, however,the only "new designers"who work on CAD/CAM systems are actually serving as draftersand detailers,not conceptualdesigners. While the subgoal of the MarkIV design team was to "do it right"this time by integrating the computergraphicsystem earlyin the process,this did not include designing on the computersystem. Ratherit meant digitalizing<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> the design into the system before the packagewas built ratherthan after,so that the graphicscapabilitiescould serve as more than merely an after-the- fact, record-keeping device. Of course this extrastep in copying lends itself to the potentialfor more frequenthumanerrorsuch as transposednumbers and errorsin dimensioning.While some errorsof this type did occur, these kinds of errorsare common in design work and not particular to computer graphics. A moresignificantproblemat the Selco site was basedin the formalization of the drawingin its role as a boundaryobject. The fluidity and flexibility that is part of the loose structure of boundaryobjects was paralyzedby the fact that the whole system was computerized.The problemwas manifestin workers'reactionsto the monolithiccomputerizeddata base. The huge size and complexity of the interlockingsystems intimidatedpeople. Employees were afraidif they adjustedinformation in theirpartof the system and made a small error such as the misplacement of a decimal point-a common error-that monumentalconsequencescould result,such as the orderingof excess inventory. This could resultin astronomical costs to the companyand the loss of theirjobs. This fearwas not unfounded,since the shrinkageof the company had alreadymeant many layoffs, leaving workers nervous about job security.Technicalwritersat Selco mentionedthat it was difficult even to obtainthe information they neededfor technicalmanualsbecauseemploy- ees, in fear of replacementsand layoffs, had become excessively secretive about their knowledge. Employees attemptedto use the methods workers have always used to really get things done-personal contacts, short cuts, avoidanceof official forms.The informaland the formalinformationstruc- tures and flows, operatingside by side, meant that communicationsbroke down for those depending on the integratedformal system to make sure everythingwas readywhen the new design went into production. As an example of social impacton engineering,Latour(1987) cites from Kidder'sSoul of a New Machine the example of a computerdesign team's principalengineer'stakingaparta competingproductandremarking that the design reflects the organizationalproblems of the company that built it. Similarly at Selco, the organizationalpolitics and confinement of under- standingto one's own department was reflectedin the design of and interaction with the data base. The system was treated as the designer was. As companyfolklore tells it, this designerwas overly particular in his applications proceduresfor computerizingdata; he even wrote a book and gave outside lectureson computerization in industrialapplications.A fastidious organizer, he was not well-liked anddid not go far in his careerat Selco. He was sent off on "specialassignment," officially isolatedfromthe areawhere<marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> his ideas were employed.When the special assignmentwas over, he was told that therewere no openings back in the mainstreamat that time. Company folklore attributeshis demise to two factors: insufficient political clout and a design thatwas too meticulous.The status of the formal data base is like that of the designer:weak midmanagement,a position that managers can override and workers can circumvent.The methods used are informal processes. The problemwas furthercompoundedby attemptsto cut down on paper- work.The companyhadchangedfromanold formthatcouldbe used initially to notify departments of upcomingneeds andto show corrections. In the new form, called a PCA (preliminarychange authority),informationwas pre- defined from the database, and changes had to be made to this information to initiate action. The new form was supposed to follow an authorization signaturerouting,so thatall departments affectedby a changewere notified. While this could be very efficient, in fact it was not. Few employees under- stood the interlocking relationship of the variousdepartments throughout the companyon the detailedlevel of the database. Because they did not understand how a change they made would affect the larger system, they were intimidatedby theirworst fears of the unknownand by the gross impactof slight errors.Thereforethey resortedto "hipshooting"in companyjargon- informalmethodslike skippingofficial paperwork. Forms like the PCAwere sometimes not routed to other departmentsinforming them of upcoming needs.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx132">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_016.image_17.png" thmb="62mk.page_016.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="133">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="134">Henderson/ Design Engineering 463</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="135">The Use of CAD at Selco</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx137">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_017.image_18.png" thmb="62mk.page_017.image_18-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="138">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="139">464 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx141">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_018.image_19.png" thmb="62mk.page_018.image_19-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="142">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="143">Henderson/ Design Engineering 465</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" confidence="possible">Failure of CAD/CAM as a Boundary Object</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154">Failureto generateformsthatwould modify the integrated data base was exactly what happenedin the case of the MarkIV. When the frame left the structuresdepartment, where it had been welded, and arrivedon the shop floor, assembly of the package could not start.Standardpartssuch as nuts, bolts, washers,and basic fittings used on all packageswere in shortsupply, as were more sophisticatedpartssuch as gauges and valves specific to the package. Since interactionwith inventoryhad been circumvented, the parts had not been ordered. Paradoxically,it was the drawingsproducedby the CAD/CAM system, including schematics and parts lists, that employees came to use as their informal alternative,althoughnot without problematicconsequences. The boundary-objectdrawing producedby the CAD/CAM operatorsallowed employees to see the projectat handin a kindof totality.Since the distributed <marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> informationwas seen as coming from the CAD/CAM system operators group,they became the liaison to productionwithout the inputof the design engineers. Hence, as common errorswere detected on the shop floor and correctionswere made, design engineerscould no longer check alterations; they lost control. An engineer sketched out a hypotheticalexample: If the welding group found an errorin the official drawing (such as transposed digits resultingin an erroneouspartnumberor the potentialinterferenceof one partwith anotherbecause a dimensionwas too short or too long), that department would suggest a changeandthe CAD system operator would put it back into the computersystem without consulting the design engineers. Such hip shooting-the instigationof change withoutproperdistribution- circumventsanalysis of the impactof changes on the design contentand on productioncosts. It can create disastrousresults.What looks like a simple change to someone who is not a design engineeror does not understand the integrateddatabase may have significantconsequenceson the stressfactors of one moving partinteracting with anotheror may add unforeseencosts by requiringa more expensive partto make everythingfit together. In the meticulouslyplannedsystem at Selco, the cost of keeping open a system designedto be closed was thata chunkhad to fall out of the circle of bricks.Thatchunkwas communication with design engineers.The drawings as boundaryobjects have the crucialrole, at least on the projectat hand,of standing in for integrationbetween the confusing details of many departments. Their flexibility is illustratedby the fact that employees have been able to substitutethem for the closed data base system to which they are indeed linked. A project managerwho had been working in liaison with various departmentsat Selco for eight years noted that probably twenty meetings a year addressedthe properadministrative handlingof design and productionchanges. He added that these meetings always became heated because of lack of understanding of the totalsystemof interaction on the part of the participants;people got bogged down and lost in the details. He claimedto understand the interlockingdatabase andwould have liked others to sharehis view of the design-to-production process, which he perceivedto be "as simple as an organizational flow chartembellished with variables." But when managers were arguing,he said, they could not makethe firstflow chart.Thus the difficulties employees encounteredin interactingwith the data base reflected the difficulties departments had in interactingwith one another. Aboundaryobjectthattriesto encompassthe totalityof interlocking information in such a settingmusteitherdictatethe restructuring of thewhole setting (a position advocatedby many computergraphicsdepartment man-<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="block"/> agers,who would necessarilyadvanceto the level of a vice-presidentunder this scenario)or they must maintainmuch more flexibility.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx147">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_019.image_20.png" thmb="62mk.page_019.image_20-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="148">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149">466 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx151">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_020.image_21.png" thmb="62mk.page_020.image_21-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="152">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="153">Henderson/ Design Engineering 467</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible">Conclusion</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160">Engineersneed informalvisual practices to think and to constructnew designscollectively.This need is illustrated here in the importance of visually oriented conscription devices as organizing devices, thinking tools, and boundaryobjects.I am looking at the resultof design engineers'fight against the formalreorganization of theirwork by a computergraphicssystem. This is no mere Ludditeresistanceto new technology. Because visual practices are so importantto problem solving, design engineers find ways to shield thesepracticesfromthe formalizinginfluencesof the CAD/CAMsystem and hence create a division of laborbetween company-dictated proceduresand informalwork practices.These resultsshow the intersectionof concerns in the new science studies, directedto the messy,visually orientedprocesses in the laboratoriesof technoscientists,with the point of view, exemplified by Shaiken's(1985) close examinationof machineshoppractice,directedat the threatof automationin deskilling the worker.16 My focus on the way CAD/ CAM is simultaneouslyincorporated and resistedshows the need andimpor- tance of messy day-to-dayvisual practices,which make the applicationof fully integratedformal and rationalsystems problematic.Divided thinking on the partof designershas deployed computer-graphics technology so that it worksto integratedesign andproduction on some levels butis intentionally isolated on others. Under the presentsystem, attemptsby the company to computerizethe design-to-production process, because they were imposed on informalem- ployee practices,have led to communicationbreakdownand a shop unpre- paredto assemble the new machine.Nevertheless,engineers,management, and sales keep up the appearance that computergraphicsand official docu- mentationhave accomplishedthe task rationallyand efficiently throughthe use of illustrationspreparedusing graphic displays. Marketingdistributes these illustrationswith their "high-tech" look, such as the sculptedgridlike web of "wiremodel"drawings,to customersand top management.In practice, however,conscriptiondevices such as sketcheswork togetherwith formal drawingsto get thejob done, andso-calledcomputer-generated graphics are recordedand correctedafterthe fact. The networks of individuals involved in the day-to-day activities of engineering practice place visual representationdevices at what Latour <marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="block"/> (1987) would call a "centreof calculation."This is a place where representationsand re-representations are collected togetherin forms that allow the holding of a piece of informationwithout the thing itself-for example, a mapof a harbor, which is not actuallandandwater).The cascadeof sketches that ultimately are made concrete in the final turbine design representa- tions-like Latour'sexample of the map of Sakhalin'sharbor, broughtback to Europeforthe use of futurenavigationsto China- depend on the mobility, stability, and combinability of the representations in order to extend the network of the participantsand tie the informationand the participants together. There are no one-way relationshipsbetween actants, mental models, representations, and the constructed technology.Rather, interactive practices contribute to the mutualandsimultaneousconstruction of each by the others. The representations are the productof and resourcesfor situatedpractice. The destruction of such visually oriented situated practices may occur because of a fundamental misunderstanding of theircrucialrole in the social organization of distributedcognition in team design work. When such fundamentalmisunderstandings are built into inflexible computergraphics programsdesigned with the misleading idea of a definable linear process from concept to design to production, then the social mechanisms that ordinarilyrepairfrequentlyoccurringproblems are left out of the process with potentiallydisastrousresults.This study is a first step in understanding such interactivesocial mechanismsassociatedwith the visual conventions of engineering.Perhapswith more researchfocused on the visually situated practiceof engineeringdesign work we will eventuallybe able to construct better-informed and more useful computertools. When the messiness of the job is finished, it is not the pure logic, clean formulas,or computer-generated drawings,all of which aretoo often singu- larly creditedin technological achievement,thatget a new turbinepackage built. It is, rather,social construction accomplishedthroughthe use of rough drawingsand sketches acting as conscriptiondevices and boundaryobjects thatget the job done. The traditionof sketches,the buildingblocks of technical design, which enlist participationand serve as boundaryobjects be- tweenparticipants with differingagendasandexpertise,facilitatethecapture, formation,negotiation,and final cognitive and physical structure of shared knowledge embeddedin the official drawingset. These documentsareaided in theirfunctionas boundary objects notby computergraphicsandintegrated databases butby yet moresketchesthatglue togetherthe social environment of the actors and artifactsthatultimatelyconstructthe physicalversion of a new turbineengine or any othernew technologicalartifact.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx157">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_021.image_22.png" thmb="62mk.page_021.image_22-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="158">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159">468 Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx161">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_022.image_23.png" thmb="62mk.page_022.image_23-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="162">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="163">Henderson/ Design Engineering 469</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="164">Notes</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible">1. A visual cultureis a literal"worldview"connectedto materialexperience.The term is fromAlpers(1983). ApplyingAlpers'sanalysisof Dutchpaintingto visualizationandcognition, Latour(1986) has succinctly characterized visual cultureas "how a culturesees the world and makes it visible,"by definingboth "whatit is to see" and "whatthereis to see." 2. That engineeringdesigns, like scientific theories, are socially constructedproductsof interactionis not surprising.My use of the term constructedhenceforthis not in referenceto physical assemblybut social construction. 3. Polanyi (1958,1967) contributed the classic conceptsconcerningnonverbalknowledge in scientific practice.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Collins (1974)</xref> notes thattacit knowledgewas so crucialin buildingTEA lasers when they were a new technology that the only way the knowledge could be conveyed was by participation in a laboratory that had built one. See Cambrosio<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="166" class="deo:Reference">and Keating (1988)</xref> for an excellent overview of currentdefinitionsand discussionsof tacit knowledge. 4. I am drawinghere on Gardner's (1984) theoryof multipleintelligences.While I do not adhereto the biology-drivennatureof his model, I do agree with the evidence from Gardner's researchthatthe mind has ways of knowing otherthanthe verbaland mathematical knowledge measuredin intelligence testing and that these otherways of knowing requiresocial resources for development.Gardner posits seven intelligencesthatblend in normalcognitionbut aremore evident in child prodigies whose abilities exhibit the extreme end of possible combinations, allowing the definitionof the domainsof various intelligences in a mannersimilarto Weber's ideal types. Spatial intelligence and kinesthetic intelligence are two of the seven. Further evidence of kinestheticknowledge is documentedby <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Sudnow (1978)</xref>. Ferguson(1976, 1985) illustrates the importanceof visual knowledge in technology. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Hindle (1981)</xref> documents the necessity of both visual and"fingertip" or kinestheticknowledgein the transfer of technologies from Europeto colonial America. 5. Thereareno one-to-onecorrelations betweenthe mentalworldandtheworldof practice; the two areintertwined and interactive.Conceptsof mentalmodels, mechanicalrepresentations, and heuristicsas discussed by Gormanand Carlson(1990), while applicable,are too broadto serve the purposesintendedhere.Visualpractices,includingsketchesanddrawings,whichstand between mental models and mechanicalrepresentations, could be classified as heuristics,but that does not tell us much. Goodingemphasizesthe importance of situatedpracticebut misses its applicationto visual representations in his suggestion that "successful communicationof novel findings ... dependson findingthe rightpictorialor verbalimagery"(1990, 181). Rather, what takes place in practiceis the working out of imagery in simultaneousrelationshipto the workingout of the conceptsinvolved.Goodingpointsout thatthenarrative accountsof invention thathave come down to us leave out the uncertainties and contingenciesthatoccurredin context; so, too, the pictorialrepresentations that have come down to us leave out manyof the discarded earlierand interactivefirst approximations, thinkingdrawings,and roughdrafts. 6. Collins(1990) points out thatit is possible for people to makeuse of pocketcalculators, slide rules,logarithmtables,and the intelligentcomputers used in artificialintelligenceresearch only because "humanscompensatefor the deficiencies of artifactsin such a way thatthe social groupcontinuesto functionas before"(p. 215). 7. Subsequentstudies of representational practice in science mark the diversity of such visual and verbal formats, which range from graphs, diagrams,illustrations,and models to computerprograms,any combinationof which maybe employed to achieve succinct and per- suasive presentation of scientific phenomena.See the special issue of HumanStudies(Vol. 11,</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx170">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_023.image_24.png" thmb="62mk.page_023.image_24-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="171">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="172">470 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="181" confidence="possible">nos. 2-3, April/July1988, Lynchand Woolgar,eds.) on representation in scientific practice,for a variety of discussions about the use of representational devices and their relationto general issues in the sociology and philosophyof science, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="173" class="deo:Reference">and their relationto general issues in the sociology and philosophyof science, and Fyfe and Law (1988)</xref> for a collection of essays on the more general theme that power and knowledge as social processes can involve technologiesof depictionthatcontributeto the reproduction of the social order. 8. All companyand individualnames are pseudonyms. 9. Among numerousexamples, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="174" class="deo:Reference">Hindle (1981)</xref> for a discussion of the developmentof thesteamboatand telegraph,andConstant(1980) for a discussionof the developmentof turbine engines. 10. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="175" class="deo:Reference">Mukerji (1989)</xref> points out the low statusof techniciansand technologicalinnovatorsin oceanography despite theircrucialcontributions to the researchprocess. She further notes that scientistswith reputations as good buildersof research machinery have troubleobtainingfunding for more theoreticalwork. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="176" class="deo:Reference">Collins (1974)</xref> notes the intentionalwithholdingof tacit knowledge necessaryfor buildingTEA lasers when they were a new technology.Cambrosio<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="177" class="deo:Reference">and Keating (1988)</xref> have found that scientists using hybridoma technology in biotechnology research acknowledgetacit knowledgeas "art" or "magic,"thus mystifyingit. 11. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="178" class="deo:Reference">Lave (1988)</xref> tracesthe eclectic roots of practicetheoryto the work of Marx,Bourdieu, Sahlins,and Giddensamong others,potentiallydescribingit as "a clusterof theoriesaboutthe natureof practicewhich agree about the importanceof a broadrange of issues and levels of analysisembodiedin the focal concept." 12. This idea is in direct contrast with Giere's (1988) proposal that scientists develop schematain the mind, based on scientific textbooks. 13. Suchman (1988, 319-21) lists eight characteristics.I have included only those that appearespecially applicableand pertinenthere. 14. In this industry, drafters can still workup to the designationof seniordesignerandfrom there be promoted to the title of design "engineer"on the basis of experience ratherthan schooling. At least one well-knowncomputercompanyabandoned this practicewithin the past few years, creatinga cavernbetween draftingand engineeringthat can only be bridgedacross a college campus,a move similar to the change from shop-trained engineersto school-trained engineersin nineteenth-century America. 15. The importanceof play in learningto use the computeris exemplified in classroom studies,where thosewho use social networksandplay aremoresuccessful in learningcomputer skills thanthose who readmanuals(for example,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="179" class="deo:Reference">Mehan,Moll, and Riel 1984</xref>). 16. Braverman(1984), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="180" class="deo:Reference">Cooley (1980)</xref>, and Noble (1977, 1984) also see automationtech- nologies as intentionallydesigned to displaceand deskill workers.</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="182" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Alpers, S. 1983. The art of describing.Chicago:Universityof ChicagoPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Amann, K., and K. Knorr-Cetina.1988. The fixation of (visual) evidence. Human Studies 11:133-69.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Barnes,B. 1982. The science-technologyrelationship: A model and a query.Social Studiesof Science 12:166-72.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Barnes,B., and D. Edge, eds. 1982. Science in context.Cambridge: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Baynes, K., and F. Pugh. 1981. The art of the engineer.Guilford,Sussex: Lutherword Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Bijker,W.,Hughes,T., andT. Pinch,eds. 1987. Thesocial construction of technologicalsystems: New directionsin the sociology and historyof technology.Cambridge: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Bloor, D. 1976. Knowledgeand social imagery.London:Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Bly, S. 1988. A use of drawingsurfaces in differentcollaborativesettings. Paper presentedat Second Conferenceon Computer-Supported CooperativeWork,Portland,OR, September.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Booker,P. 1963. A historyof engineeringdrawing.London:Chatto&amp; Windus.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Bowker, G. 1987. A well-ordered reality: Aspects of the development of Schlulmberger, 1920-1939. Social Studiesof Science 17:611-55. . 1988. Picturesfrom the subsoil, 1939. In Picturingpower,visual depictionsand social relations,editedby G. Fyfe and J. Law, 221-54. London:Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Braverman, H. 1984. Laborand monopolycapital. New York:MonthlyReview Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Cambrosio,A., and P. Keating. 1988. "Going monoclonal":Art, science, and magic in the day-to-dayuse of hybridomatechnology.Social Problems35:244-60.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Callon, M., and B. Latour.1981. Unscrewingthe big Leviathan:How actors macro-structure realityand how sociologists help them to do so. In Advancesin social theoryand method- ology, edited by K. Knorr-Cetina &amp; A. V. Cicot~1, 277-303. Boston: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Callon, M., J. Law, and A. Rip, eds. 1986. Mappingthe dynamicsof science and technology: Sociology of science in the real world. Basingstoke:Macmillan.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Collins, H. M. 1974. The TEA set: Tacit knowledge and scientific networks.Science Studies 4:165-86. . 1985. Changingorder:Replicationand inductionin scientificpractice. London:Sage. . 1990. Artificialexperts.Cambridge: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Constant, E. W. 1980. Theoriginsof the turbojet revolution.Baltimore:JohnHopkinsUniversity Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Cooley, M. 1980. Architector bee? The human/technology relationship.Boston: South End Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Ferguson,E. 1976. The mind's eye: Nonverbalthoughtin technology.Science 197:827.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">----. 1985. La fondationdes machinesmodernes:Des dessins. CultureTechnique14:183- 207.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Fyfe, G., andJ. Law,eds. 1988. Picturingpower:Visualdepictionsandsocial relations. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Gardner, H. 1984. Framesof mind:Thetheoryof multipleintelligences.New York:Basic Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Garfinkel,H., M. Lynch,andE. Livingston.1981. The workof discoveringscience constructed with material from the optically discovered pulsar. Philosophy of the Social Sciences 11:131-58.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Giere,R. 1988. Explaining science:A cognitiveapproach.Chicago:Universityof ChicagoPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Gilbert,G., and M. Mulkay.1984. OpeningPandora'sbox:A sociological analysis of scientific discourse. Cambridge: Cambridge UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Gooding,D. 1990. Mappingexperimentas a learningprocess. Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values15:165-201.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Gorman,M., and W. Carlson. 1990. Interpretinginvention as a cognitive process. Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues15:131-64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Henderson,K. 1989. The "yellowbrickroad"to technologicalproduction: Conscription devices andboundary objects in designengineering.Paperpresentedatthe Society for Social Studies of Science Conference,Ccsta Mesa, CA, November.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Hindle, B. 1981. Emulationand invention.New York:Norton.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Hutchins,E. Forthcoming.The social organization of distributed cognition. In Perspectiveson socially sharedcognition,editedby L. Resnick andJ. Levine. Washington, DC: APAPress. Kidder,T. 1981. Soul of a new machine.Boston: Little, Brown.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Knorr-Cetina, K. 1981. The manufactureof knowledge:An essay on the constructivistand contextualnatureof science. Oxford:Pergamon.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Knorr-Cetina, K., and K. Amman. 1990. Image dissection in naturalscientific inquiry.Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues15:259-83.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Latour,B. 1986. Visualizationand cognition:Thinkingwith eyes and hands.Knowledgeand Society: Studiesin the Sociology of CulturePast and Present 6:1-40. . 1987. Science in action: How to follow scientists and engineers through society. Cambridge: Harvard UniversityPress. . 1988. Mixing humansandnonhumans together:The sociology of a door-closer. Social Problems35:298-310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Latour,B., and S. Woolgar.1986. Laboratorylife: The constructionof scientificfacts. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Laudan, R. 1984. The nature of technological knowledge:Are models of scientific change relevant?Dordrecht:Reidel.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Lave, J. 1988. Cognitionin practice. Cambridge: Cambridge UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Law,J., ed. 1986. Power,action,and belief:A new sociology of knowledge?London:Routledge. . 1987. On the social explanationof technical change: The case of the Portuguese maritimeexpansion.Technology and Culture28:227-52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Law,J., andM. Callon.1988. Engineeringandsociology in a militaryaircraft project: A network analysis of technologicalchange. Social Problems35:284-97</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Lynch,M. 1985a. Art and artifact in laboratoryscience: A studyof shop workand shop talkin a research laboratory.London:Sage. . 1985b. Discipline and the materialform of images: Analysis of scientific visibility. Social Studiesof Science 15:37-66. . 1988. The externalizedretina:Selection and mathematization in the visual documen- tationof objects in the life sciences. HumanStudies 11:201-34.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Lynch,M., E. Livingston,andH. Garfinkel.1983. Temporal order in laboratory work. In Science observed: Perspectives on the social study of science, edited by K. Knorr-Cetinaand M. Mulkay,205-38. London:Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Lynch, M., and S. Woolgar.1988. Introduction: Sociological orientationsto representational practicein science. HumanStudies 11:99-116.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">MacKenzie,D., andG. Spinardi.1988. The shapingof nuclearweaponsystem technology,parts I and II. Social Studiesof Science 18:419-63,581-624.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">MacKenzie, D., and J. Wajcman.1985. The social shaping of technology.Philadelphia: Open UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Mehan, H., L. Moll, and M. Riel. 1984. A quasi experimentin guided change. Final Report</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">G-83-0027, NationalInstituteof Education,Interactive TechnologyLaboratory, La Jolla.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Mukerji,C. 1989.A fragile power: Scientistsand the state. Princeton,NJ: PrincetonUniversity Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Noble, D. 1977. Americaby design. New York:OxfordUniversityPress. . 1984. Forces of production. New York:Knopf.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Pinch, T. 1985. Towardsan analysis of scientific observation:The externalityand evidential significanceof observationreportsin physics. Social Studiesof Science 15:1-36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Polanyi,M. 1958. Personalknowledge: Towards a post-criticalphilosophy. London:Routledge&amp; Kegan Paul. . 1967. The tac~tdimensionsLondon:Routledge&amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Rudwick, M. 1976. The emergence of a visual language for geological science, 1760-1840. Historyof Science 14:148-95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Shaiken,H. 1985. Worktransformed: Automationand labor in the computerage. New York: Holt, Rinehart&amp; Winston.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Shapin,S. 1984. Pumpand circumstance: Robert Boyle's literarytechnology.Social Studiesof Science 14:481-95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Star, S. L. 1989. The structureof ill-structuredsolutions: Heterogenous problem-solving, boundary objects anddistributed artificialintelligence.In Distributedartificial intelligence. Vol 2, editedby M. Huhnsand L. Gasser,37-54. San Mateo, CA: MorganKaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Star, S. L., and J. R. Griesmer. 1989. Institutionalecology, "translations," and coherence: Amateurs and professionalsin Berkeley'sMuseumof Vertebrate Zoology, 1907-1939.Social Studiesof Science 19:387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Suchman,L. A. 1988. Representing practicein cognitive science. HumanStudies 11:305-26.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Sudnow,D. 1978. Waysof the hand.Cambridge: Harvard UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Tang, J., and L. Leifer. 1988. A frameworkfor understanding the workspaceactivity of design teams.Proceedings of the Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work, September.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Ullman,D., L. Stauffer,andT. Dietterich.1987. TowardexpertCAD. Computers in Mechanical Engineering16:56-63.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Winner,L. 1985. Do artifacts have politics? In The social shaping of technology, edited by D. MacKenzieand J. Wajcman,26-38. Philadelphia: Open UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Woolgar, S. 1985. Why not a sociology of machines? The case of sociology and artificial intelligence.Sociology 19:557-72. . 1988. Time and documentsin researcher interaction: Some ways of makingout what is happeningin experimentalscience. HumanStudies 11:171-200.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Kathryn Henderson is Assistant Professor of Sociology at Texas A&amp;M University (College Station, TX 77843-4351). She holds an MFAin Art Criticismand a Ph.D. in Sociology from University of California, San Diego. Her dissertation concerned the impact of computergraphics on the visual cultureand visual communication of engi- neers.Her currentresearchinterestsincludetheplace of tacitknowledgeinprofessional workand the role of visual representation in science education.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx189">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_024.image_25.png" thmb="62mk.page_024.image_25-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="190" page="24" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="191" page="25" column="1">Henderson/ Design Engineering 471</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx215">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_025.image_26.png" thmb="62mk.page_025.image_26-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="216" page="25" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="217" page="26" column="1">472 Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx238">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_026.image_27.png" thmb="62mk.page_026.image_27-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="239" page="26" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="240" page="27" column="1">Henderson/ Design Engineering 473</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx252">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mk.page_027.image_28.png" thmb="62mk.page_027.image_28-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="253" page="27" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.156 on Mon, 18 Nov 2013 08:23:50 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
