<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>4dd1c1b3e61d4c259be88a982a484c0d617577a0db731478c5272d1e94698fdc</job>
    <base_name>62fu</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s0142-694x(97)00008-2</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">What do architects and students perceive in their design sketches? A protocol analysis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Masaki Suwa</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Barbara Tversky</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Advanced Research Laboratory</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Hitachi Ltd.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Hatoyama</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Saitama</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Japan Department of Psychology</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">Stanford University</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="10">Stanford</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="11">CA</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="12">USA</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="13" confidence="possible">The present research aims at examining what information architects think of and read off from their own freehand sketches, and at revealing how thev perceptually interact with and benefit from sketches. We explored this in a protocol analysis of retrospective reports; each participant worked on an architectural design task while drawing freehand sketches and later reported what shelhe had been thinking of during the design task. This research lies within the scope of examinations of why freehand sketches as external representation are essential for crystallizing design ideas in early design processes. © 1997 Elsevier Science Ltd. Keywords: architectural design, design cognition, drawings, perception, protocol analysis</abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">1 Gelernter, H 'Realization of a geometry-theorem proving machine' in E A Feigenbaum and J Feldman (eds) Computer and thought MacGraw-Hill (1963) 2 McDougal, T and Ham- mond, K 'A recognition model of geometry theorem-proving' in Proceedings of the 14th annual conference of the cognitive science society LEA, NJ (1992) pp 106-111 3 Koedinger, K R and Anderson, J R 'Abstract planning and perceptual chunks: elements of expertise in geometry' Cognitive Science Vol 14 (1990) pp 511- 550. 4 Suwa, M and Motoda, H 'peLEARN: a model for leaming perceptual-chunks' in Proceedings of the 16th annual conference of the cognitive science society LEA. NJ (1994) pp 830-835</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="1">xternal representations, e.g. diagrams, sketches, charts, graphs and E facilitate even hand-written and constrain memos inference, not only problem-solving serve as memory and aids, understand- but also ing. Geometry diagrams in theorem-proving tasks, e.g. guide solvers to explore only visually plausible inference paths I, facilitate retrieval of perceptual-chunks that are useful for constructing efficient proofs 2,3, and provide visual cues for extracting new chunks from the current problem and assimilating them for future use 4. Petre 5 showed that good use of graphical representations in programming environments, i.e. what she calls 'second- ary notation' of graphics, prevents programmers from miscueing and mis- understanding. Larkin and Simon 6 enumerated general features of diagrammatic representation by which human problem-solving is facilitated, providing a list of how facilitation tends to occur. Tversky discussed how people use space for conveying meanings and abstract concepts, drawing on examples from ancient depictions and children's early drawing 7, as well as from comtemporary charts, graphs and diagrams 8. <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Facilitation by external representation derives, not just from its external existence, but from the interaction between the representation and the cognitive processes of interpreting it 9. Architects' sketches are also a tool for this sort of interaction 10,11. Architects put ideas down on paper and inspect them. As they inspect their own sketches, they see unanticipated relations and features that suggest ways to refine and revise ideas. This cycle sketch, inspect, revise - is like having a conversation with one's self 12. Goldschmidt 13 conjectured that sketches give access to various mental images, figural or conceptual, that may potentially trigger ideas in the current design problem. Furthermore, she claimed that visual design thinking is a rational mode of reasoning as well, although it has been set aside behind the dominant paradigm of linguistic, logical reasoning in cognitive science 14. This claim perfectly coincides with a growing enthusiasm for diagrammatic reasoning in cognitive science, especially in the case of groups of researchers who claim that visual information is valid for reasoning and that visual reasoning has its own sound logic 15.16, just as conventional sentential reasoning does.<marker type="block"/> Why are sketches a good medium for reflective conversation with one's own ideas and imagery? This general question can be reduced to more precise issues to be addressed. One is the issue of what aspects or features of sketches themselves, as external representations, allow for reflective conversation, an issue addressed by Gael 17. He found that because freehand sketches in the early design process are 'dense' and 'ambiguous' in Goodman's 18 sense, they work well for exploring design ideas. Another is the issue of what kinds of interaction architects have with their own sketches. This issue can, in tum, be divided into three separate problems; 'how do they see sketches?', 'what do they see in sketches?' and 'how and what do they draw?' Goldschmidt's work 13 pertains to the first category. She observed that there are two ways of inspecting sketches, i.e. 'seeing as' and 'seeing that', and that the former is an especially powerful means for what she calls interactive imagery. Van Sommers's work 19 looked at graphic production from a developmental and cognitive perspective, and hence pertains to the third category. The present paper addresses the second problem, 'what architects see', by focusing more precisely than the past work on the contents of information categories that architects 'see' in their own sketches. The purpose of the present paper is to analyze how those different types of information intermingle with each other in their design thoughts and to reveal how practicing architects differ from students in it.<marker type="block"/> We brought these phenomena into the laboratory in a protocol analysis of retrospective reports of subjects' design thoughts. The most typical method<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> for analyzing subjects' cognitive processes IS and has been, concurrent thinking-aloud verbal reports 20.21. We did not employ it, because talking aloud may adversely interfere with participants' perceptions during their sketching activities 22. This issue is discussed in more detailed in Section 5.1.<marker type="block"/> Another purpose of this study is to explore implications for ways that future design tools, especially sketching tools, assist designers/architects. Many researchers 17.23,24 claim that the currently available computational tools do not support naive freehand sketching processes in the early design phases_ This is because they are intended for visualizing, comparing, testing and implementing the design ideas that have already been obtained in earlier design processes, not for supporting the very processes in which design ideas occur. Several projects 23-25 on pen-based sketch tools have recently addressed this problem. We believe that the present research will be able to provide important implications for more endeavors. This issue is discussed in Section 6.3.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="16" page="1" column="1">385</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17" page="1" column="1">ELSEVIER</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="18" page="1" column="1">0142-694XJ97 $17.00 Design Studies 18 (1997) 385-403 PlI: S0142-694X(97)OOOO8-2 © 1997 Elsevier Science Ltd All rights reserved Printed in Great Britain</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="21" page="2" column="1">5 Petre, M 'Why looking isn't always seeing: readership skills and graphical programming' Communications of the ACM, Vol 38 No 6 pp 33-44. 6 Lerkin, J and Simon, H A 'Why a diagram is (sometimes) worth ten thousand words' Cognitive Science Vol 11 (1987) pp 65-99. 7 Tversky, B 'Cognitive origins of graphic conventions' in F. T. Marchese (ed) Understanding images Springer, New York (1995a) pp 29-53 8 Tversky, B 'Perception and cognition of 2D and 3D graphics' in Human factors in computing systems: CHI95 conference companion ACM, New York (1995b) p 175 9 Miyake, Nand Hatano, G 'Socio-cultural constraints and beyond' ProgressesofCognmve Science (in Japanese) Vol 2 (1991) pp 105-131 10 Laseau, P Graphic thinking for architects and designers (2nd edn) Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York (1989) 11 Robbins, E Why architects draw MIT Press, Cambridge (1994) 12 SChon, D A and Wiggins, G 'Kinds of seeing and their functions in designing' Design Studies Vol 13 (1992) pp 135-156. 13 Goldschmidt, G 'The dia- lectics of sketching' Creativity Research Journal Vol 4 No 2 (1991) pp 123-143. 14 Goldschmidt, G ' On visual design thinking: the vis kids of architecture' Design Studies Vol 15 No 2 (1994) pp 158-174. 15 Barwise, J and Etch- emendy, J 'Visual infonmation and valid reasoning' in W. Zimm- erman (ed) Visualization in mathematics Mathematical Association of America, Wash- ington DC (1990) 16 Stenning, K and Ober- lander, J 'A cognitive theory of graphical and linguistic reasoning: logic and Implementation' Cognitive Science Vol 19 (1995) pp 97-140. 17 Goal, V Sketches of thought MIT Press, Cambridge (1995) 18 Goodman, N Languages of art Bobbs-Merrill, Indianapolis (1968) 19 Van Sommers, P Drawing and cognition Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (1984)</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="2" column="1">386</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="24" page="2" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx25">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62fu.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28" page="3" column="1">1</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="29" page="3" column="1">Experimental design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="3" column="1">The experiment consisted of two tasks, a design task and a report task. Two practicing architects and seven advanced students in an architectural department participated. In the design task, each participant worked on designing an art museum through successive sketches for 45 min. They were provided with a simple diagram representing an outline of the site, in which they were supposed to arrange not only a museum building, but also a sculpture garden, pond, green area and parking lot. The building was required to have an entrance(s), ticket office(s), display rooms for about 100 paintings. a cafeteria and gift shop. Participants were supposed to use freehand sketches as a tool for designing. They were not asked to report concurrently what was going on in their minds. nor were they interrupted by the experimenter during the design task. Their sketching activity was videotaped. <marker type="block"/> Following the design task was the report task. While watching their own videotape, participants were asked to remember and report what they were thinking as they drew each portion of each sketch. In case their reports lagged behind the videotape, they were allowed to stop the tape until reporting all that they remembered about the current topics. Therefore, the duration of the report task depended on the participant, varying from I hr to 1 hr 15 min. Participants were not interrupted with questions during the report, except for the following cases; when they obviously skipped reporting about certain portions of their sketching activity, then they were requested by the experimenter to rewind the videotape and report those<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> portions. We recorded the participants' voices, as well as videotaping the screen itself on which not only their sketching activity in the design task, but also their pointing gestures in the report task were visible.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="31" page="3" column="1">20 Ericsson, K A and Simon, H A Protocol analysis: verbal reports as data (revised edn) MIT Press, Cambridge (1993) 21 Dorst, K and Cross, N 'Protocol analysis as a research technique for analysing design activity' in Proceedings of 1995 design engineering technical conferences ASME, Vol 2 (1995) pp 563-570, 22 Lloyd, P 'Can concurrent verbalization reveal design cognition' DeSign Studies Vol 16 No 2 (1995) pp 237-259 23 Landay, J A and Myers, B A 'Interactive sketching for the early stages of user interlace design' in Human factors in com~ puting systems: proceedings of CHI'95 ACM, New York (1995) pp 43-50 24 Kramer, A 'Translucent patches - dissolving windows' in Proceedings of UIST'94 ACM, New York (1994) pp 121-130 25 Gross, M 0 'The electronic Cocktail Napkin - a computational environment for working with design diagrams' Design Studies Vol 17 No 1 (1996) pp 53-69,</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="33" page="3" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="34" page="3" column="1">387</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx35">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62fu.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="37" page="4" column="1">2</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="38" page="4" column="1">Information categories</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" page="4" column="1">In interpreting the data, the first step was to determine a set of information categories into which the contents of participants' protocols could be fit. Table 1 shows the four major categories and their subclasses. We derived the four categories from theoretical discussions and historical evidence on how external representations convey meanings and concepts, from past literature on design processes that suggest what architects generally think of in design process, and from intensive study of the protocols. Many theorists like Larkin and Simon 6 and Tversky 7 have suggested that the pictorial devices for expressing meanings and concepts consist of (a) depicted elements, whether objects, spaces or icons, and (b) spatial arrangement of them. They have also suggested that spatial arrangements have the ability to express not only literal spatial relations, but also abstract or conceptual relations. This analysis suggests three information categories: depicted elements, spatial relations and abstract relations. <marker type="block"/> Depicted elements are sometimes intentionally drawn, and thus possess explicit shapes and sizes, but sometimes they are embedded as partial elements or implicit objects, and emerge to the viewer's eyes only when he/she discovers a new way of restructuring the whole configuration that includes those elements 26. Larkin and Simon 6, and Koedinger and<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> Anderson' referred to this property of diagrams as 'emergent properties'. Therefore, we chose to name the first category as 'emergent properties', instead of just depicted elements. 'Spatial relations' hold among these depicted elements and are inherently visual features in the sense that architects/designers can see them in their own sketches, just as emergent properties are also visual. In the domain of architectural design, abstract relations typically correspond to 'functional relations'. Forms and functions are the two major concepts in the domain that are conceptually distinct, and yet intertwined 27. Functional relations in this domain denote interactions among spaces, things, people visiting or using them, and/or environments. Unlike emergent properties and spatial relations, functional relations are inherently non-visual aspects of architectural designs.<marker type="block"/> In addition to the previous three categories, we established a fourth one, i.e. 'background knowledge', because the past history of studies of cognitive science has indicated that every cognitive task performed by human beings is mediated by background knowledge about the domain to which the task belongs. Background knowledge in the domain of architectural design includes (a) domain knowledge about structures and materials for fulfilling certain functions, and spatial arrangements; (b) standards for doing the aesthetic and preferential evaluations for their own design decisions; and (c) knowledge about the relevance and influence of the architectural designs to/from the social contexts, and the environments in which the architecture is built.<marker type="block"/> After reviewing all the protocols, we distinguished subclasses of each category. For emergent properties, in cases where participants discovered or created certain areas for something or some functions, or referred to already depicted (e.g. encircled) areas, we encoded the evidence as spaces. In cases where subjects depicted things, referred to already depicted things, or even observed that things which were not actually there by the appearance of other surrounding depictions, we encoded the evidence as things. Shapes/angles denote the shapes of things or spaces, or the angle that two items form against each other. Sizes denotes the size of things or spaces. The latter two are visual attributes of the former two. These four subclasses constitute emergent properties.<marker type="block"/> Spatial relations were subdivided into two classes, local relations and global relations. Local relations includes (a) adjacency, (b) remoteness, (c) physical connectedness by mediation of other things and (d) alignment, which holds between two or more different spaces or things. Global relations includes (e) a configuration of spaces or things within the whole<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> site or a certain area in it, (D symmetry of spaces or things, and (g) axes, or a sense of direction which spaces or things inherently possess.<marker type="block"/> Functional relations were subdivided into five categories. Practical roles refers to semantic relevance, conflict, separateness among practical roles of spaces or things. This is a subclass concerning how people use them. Abstract features/reactions include interrelations among the abstract features of spaces or things, as well as interactions and feelings which people may have from experiencing spaces or things. This is a subclass concerning how people react to them. The other three subclasses are more specific types of interactions between people, spaces and/or things, which are typical in architectural design. Views includes the actual appearance of spaces or things imagined by participants, and the visibility of a space to and from another space within the site. Lights denotes interactions between depicted elements and sunlight. Circulation of people/cars is an encoding of participants' reports about people/cars moving around within or outside the site.<marker type="block"/> We did not divide background knowledge into subclasses, because the precise distinction of what types of knowledge participants refer to is not relevant to the present research.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="40" page="4" column="1">26 Liu, Y-T 'Some phenomena of seeing shapes in design' Design Studies Vol 16 No 3 (1995) pp 367-385.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="42" page="4" column="1">Table 1 Information</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="43" page="4" column="1">categories and their subclasses</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="44" page="4" column="1">Subclasses Examples of phrases in protocols as evidence</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="45" page="4" column="1">Major category Emergent properties</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="46" page="4" column="1">Spaces Things Shapes/angles</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="47" page="4" column="1">Spatial relations Functional relations</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="48" page="4" column="1">Sizes Local relation Global relation Practical roles Abstract features/reactions</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="49" page="4" column="1">Views Lights Circulation of people/cars</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="50" page="4" column="1">Background knowledge</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="51" page="4" column="1">"Areas", "places" Descriptions or names of something "Round", "prolonged", "wavy line", "too sharp a comer" ll "Big", "tinyll, "narrow "Adjacent", "far", "connected", "lined up" "Symmetrical", "configuration", "axis" "A ticket office should be close to an entrance.. " "Waves/forces (from this shape)", "good show to visitors" "View line", "the appearance (of this building)" "(This place is always) bright, having sunshine" "People meander through (this narrow space)" "Post/beam structures", "An important thing in an urban setting is... "</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="52" page="4" column="1">388</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="53" page="4" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx54">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62fu.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="58" page="5" column="1">27 Arnheim, R The dynamics of architectural form University of California Press, Berkeley (1977)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="60" page="5" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="61" page="5" column="1">389</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx62">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62fu.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="66" page="6" column="1">3 3.J</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="67" page="6" column="1">Protocol analysis Encoding into information categories</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" page="6" column="1">For each participant, we first encoded all the information In the verbal protocols into the subclasses of information categories. Basically, verbal protocols were the main target of our analysis; we analyzed words, phrases and sentences as evidence of each subclass of information categories. To supplement the verbal protocol, we employed the visual data of videotapes which had recorded participants' pointing gestures in reporting, in two ways. First, because verbal reports contained abbreviations and ambiguous pronouns, the participants' pointing gestures helped to clarify what was being referred to. Second, participants sometimes omitted reporting certain depictions that were used in their sketching activities. Visual data revealed these unreported depictions. In these cases, we encoded that some 'unknown' thoughts were actually there. <marker type="block"/> Table 2 displays a 3-min portion of a protocol of a practicing architect, beginning 9 min into the design task. When we encoded raw protocols, it was necessary to augment ambiguous phrases with interpretations. We did this by seeking justifications. One kind of justification was to know which areas or depictions the participant was talking about from his/her gestures<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> of pointing to the screen while reporting. Another kind was to interpret phrases or pronouns from contextual, pragmatic and semantic information. [p: .. ] corresponds to the former, and [s: ..] to the latter. In the right column, the encoded subclasses and phrases for which we encoded are listed.<marker type="block"/> We did not encode goals or intentions for future actions, as they typically referred to meta-level control over cognitive processes rather than interpretations of sketches. A typical example is seen in segment 43 in Table 2, i.e. 'yes, don't forget this'.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="70" page="6" column="1">390</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="71" page="6" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx72">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62fu.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" page="7" column="1">Segmentation</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="76" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">3.2</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" page="7" column="1">Then, we divided the entire encoded protocol into segments. A segment, whether consisting of one sentence or many, is defined as one coherent statement about a single item/space/topic. If a participant contributed more than one statement about an item/space/topic, the statements were regarded as different segments; e.g. see the portion of segments 42 and 43 in Table 2. This portion includes statements about a 'tension' between two areas, but should be divided into two segments as such. In segment 42, he devised a notion of 'tension', suggesting its importance in a surburban setting. Then, in segment 43, he explored the idea by placing water or sculpture elements in one of the two areas. Even if participants omitted reporting a depiction which was actually recognized in the videotape, the depiction should stand for a segment, because we are sure that some design thoughts had been actually there. <marker type="block"/> A segment usually included several information subclasses, and an entire protocol for a participant typically consisted of hundreds of segments.<marker type="block"/> Although we devised the notion of 'segments' independently, we learned afterwards that Goldschmidt 13 had already proposed a similar way of decomposing design processes into small units, 'design moves' and 'arguments'. According to her definition, a design move is 'an act of reasoning which presents a coherent proposition pertaining to an entity that is being designed', and arguments are 'the smallest sensible statements which go into the making of a move' (p 125). This definition and the examples shown suggest that a segment in our notion corresponds to a design move in its granularity.</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="80" page="7" column="1">3.3</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="81" page="7" column="1">Conceptual dependency among segments: two types of segments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="7" column="1">Next, we analyzed conceptual dependency among segments. We define a segment to have a conceptual dependency (CD) to a past segment, whether</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="83" page="7" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="84" page="7" column="1">391</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx85">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62fu.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="86" page="8" column="1">Table 2 An example of</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="87" page="8" column="1">encoding protocols into information categories</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="88" page="8" column="1">Segment no: protocols</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="89" page="8" column="1">(interpretations)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Encoded categories ("phrases" which are encoded as such)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="91" page="8" column="1">parking back behind that [s: build- this area [p: building area]. in the building] would go this bigger mass of this space</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="92" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">space ("parking", "this space") local spatial relation ("back behind that") practical roles ("shelter", "shield") size ("bigger mass")</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">things ("sculptures", "trees"), space ("water") views ("visual points", "what you see") background knowledge ("don't know what's out there") circulation ("where you are") abstract features/reactions ("magical project", "control all of our visual points", "control over where you are and what you see") abstract features/reactions ("something's going to happen") spaces ("here") local spatial relation ("between")</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="94" page="8" column="1">Sculptures, water, trees...It's points]. If I am going to of this area] ...since I don't the outside environments], we project here with the gallery. and lots of sculpture ... have our visual points. Where you have some control over that. between sculptures and the out- just a note to myself. Some- between. Maybe will look going to see this. This is going to stop my view]. notion that maybe parking the building] in this area [p: difficult because it's an awkward</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">spaces ("parking"), circulation ("access") local spatial relation ("backward") background knowledge ("awkward")</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">local spatial relation ("spatial relation") views ("see") space ("here", "entry point") things ("these elements")</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="97" page="8" column="1">you know I don't know... Oh what I'm doing [s: trying to thoughts]. I know exactly what I'm You have a spatial relation from here [p: the sculpture back to the entry point [p: nearest public road to the site]. elements [p, s: something located</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="98" page="8" column="1">37: I try to shelter my ing mass] Just a note behind Other things [s: some events on if I try to shield using [p: building areal .. 38: I've got features. become points [s: visual develop this [s: the design know what's out there [p: have kind of a magical with lots of outside water the building control all of are and what you see. We 39: This wavy line [p: side water] is just a rapid, thing's going to happen here at other things but I am to stop my view [s: a note 40: Just trying to fill in the is feeding backward [s: of parking area] .. , It's access ... 41: What did I do there" .. looking at the sequence of remember his past doing... That is from here ... ... carryon. You can see area drawn in segment 38] the entrance from the So you can see these near the entry point]. [s: .. ] - this interpretation is [p: .. ] - this interpretation is</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="99" page="8" column="1">obtained from pragmatic and semantic inference by the experimenter. grounded by the subject's act of pointing to areas or things in reporting.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">immediately preceding or anywhere in past, when (a) the item/space/topic in the current segment derives from its relationship with another item/space/topic which the past segment was concerned about, or (b) the current segment explores the same item/space/topic which the past segment was concerned about, or (c) a design idea or a constraint established in the past segment has been generalized and is applied to the current segment.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">As a result of this analysis, we found that the entire design process includes many blocks of contiguous segments. We call each block a 'dependency</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="102" page="8" column="1">392</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="103" page="8" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="104" page="8" column="1">1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx105">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62fu.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="106" page="9" column="1">Table 2 Continued</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="107" page="9" column="1">Segment no: protocols</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="108" page="9" column="1">(interpretations)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="109" page="9" column="1">Encoded categories ("phrases" which are encoded as such)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="110" page="9" column="1">42: There is a sense of from [s: entry point] and [s: the area in topic]. I important in a suburban attract people in here, to and use the light to focus</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="111" page="9" column="1">tension between where you came abstract featureslreactions ("tension") also where you are coming to space ("where you came from and where you are think that [s: this tension] is coming to") setting where you are trying to background knowledge ("it is important in a suburban make a good show out here setting ... to ... ") on what I hope. abstract featureslreactions (" attract people", "make a good show") lights ("use the light") assumption that the water and the things ("water", "sculptural pieces") be a nice draw in a surbur- abstract featureslreactions (" draw") water and sculptural pieces] abstract featureslreactions ("tension") things in my thought ... yes background knowledge ("important to me") important to me. whether or not this be a hard line shapes/angles ("hard line or soft formed ... ") If I follow that basic dia- spaces ("museum space", "around this zone") block of the museum space sizes ("large block of')</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="112" page="9" column="1">43: I am making an sculptural pieces are going to ban environment.. These [s: stand for a tension between don't forget this. This is 44: I am still not sure or a soft formed building ... gram before, this is a large around this zone ... 45: With an entry form museum space] and these the ticket booth, and the</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="113" page="9" column="1">46: And we have this building and the ancillary 47: And something's trolled outdoor area.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="114" page="9" column="1">48: Just a scribbled note to plaza texture [p, s: on the can be anything, but it's That can be out here.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="115" page="9" column="1">between common space [p: the spaces ("cafe", "ticket booth", "gift shop") ancillary functions. The cafe, local spatial relation ("between ... and ... ") gift shop. practical roles ("ancillary functions") circulation ("entry form") linkage [p: between the museum local spatial relation ("linkage") functions] practical roles ("linkage") gonna happen at this very con- abstract featureslreactions ("something's going to happen", "controlled") spaces ("outdoor area") just say ... some kind of a things ("plaza"), controlled area] can be glass, spaces ("surface", "out here") gonna be a controlled surface. abstract features/reactions ("controlled") background knowledge ("texture", "glass or anything")</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="116" page="9" column="1">[s: ..] - this interpretation is [p: ..] - this interpretation is</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="117" page="9" column="1">obtained from pragmatic and semantic inference by the experimenter. grounded by the subject's act of pointing to areas or things in reporting.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" page="9" column="1">chunk'. We call segments which stand alone, not forming a chunk with others, 'isolated segments'. The contiguous segments that should form a dependency chunk are determined such that, for each chunk, every consti- tuting segment, except for the first segment of the chunk has a CD from at least one of the preceding segments of the chunk, whether or not it is immediately preceding. The first segment does not have a CD from its immediately preceding segment ('segment P') nor from any segments in the dependency chunk, if any, to which 'segment P' belongs. <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> A dependency chunk stands for a sequence of conceptually interrelated design thoughts, each of which was evoked in relation to preceding thoughts in the chunk; e.g. suppose that a participant designed an entrance of the museum building, and then turned to design a ticket office and a gift shop. If the participant designed the ticket office and gift shop, con- sidering that a ticket office should be practically located near the entrance and a gift shop should be located near the entrance/exit for allowing visitors to browse around just before going home, then this sequence of design thoughts should form a dependency chunk. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FI" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Figure I</xref> is a schematic representation of a configuration of segments, conceptual-dependency links and dependency chunks, for the portion of the protocols of Table 2. Each rectangle node represents a segment and each link between two nodes a CD. The numbers written beside nodes correspond to the segment numbers. Segments are depicted from the left in the order of their occurrence. The segments forming a dependency chunk are depicted in the same vertical level.<marker type="block"/> The first segment of a dependency chunk and an isolated segment indicated that the participant's focus of attention departed from the preceding thoughts and moved to another item/space/topic. We classified such a segment as a 'focus-shift' segment. It corresponds to the gray nodes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FI" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Figure I</xref>. Each focus-shift segment is depicted such that it is displaced lower than its immediately previous segment. We call all the other segments, those belonging to a dependency chunk but not the first segment of the chunk, 'continuing segments'. In a continuing segment, the participant keeps exploring a topic which is conceptually related to the past segment(s) within the same chunk. It corresponds to the white nodes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FI" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Figure I</xref>.<marker type="block"/> A central tenet of this research is that architects' acts of shifting the focus of attention in an opportunistic way and their acts of exploring related</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="119" page="9" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="120" page="9" column="1">393</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx121">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62fu.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">37</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="129" page="10" column="1">o .-0 o</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">• focus-shift segments continuing segments dependency links dependency chunks</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="132" page="10" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FI" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Figure I</xref> A schematic representation of segments, conceptual dependency links and dependency chunks</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="133" page="10" column="1">394</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="134" page="10" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx135">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62fu.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" page="11" column="1">topics consecutively are the two important constituents of their design activity. This view was derived from our notion of dependency chunks. Shifts of focus allow for a lateral variety of design topics/ideas and a sequence of related thoughts allows for detailed, deep exploration of design ideas. The former corresponds to what Goel calls 'lateral transformation' and the latter to what he calls 'vertical transformation' 17</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="137" page="11" column="1">4 4.1</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="138" page="11" column="1">Results Observations about the design process</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="197" page="11" column="1">Table 3 shows the percentage of continuing segments and focus-shift segments for average students, and for the two architects. Architects have remarkably more continuing segments than students. Table 4 shows the total number of dependency chunks, the number of dependency chunks whose length is 2 and the number of dependency chunks whose length is more than 2. Architects have many more dependency chunks than students. Importantly, this difference comes mainly from the number of chunks whose length is more than 2, while the number of chunks whose length is 2 does not differ greatly between architects and students. These results, that architects have more and longer dependency chunks than students, indicate that once architects shift their focus of attention, they think more deeply about the topic. What causes this difference? We believe it occurs because architects are able to 'read-off' more different types of information from their sketches. In the following section, we will discuss what types <marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> of information are 'read' by architects and students in each of focus-shift segments and continuing segments.<marker type="block"/> Table 5 displays the percentages of each type of information for focus shift and continuing segments for architects and students. There were both strik- ing similarities and differences between architects and students in their interpretations of their sketches. For both, the predominant information in focus shift segments was spaces, whereas the predominant information in continuing segments was local spatial relations. This means that finding spaces was the major impetus for shifting focus to a new part of a sketch whereas examination of local spatial relations was the stimulus for continued consideration of related topics.<marker type="block"/> As for differences, the highlighted portions of the table indicate significant differences between architects and students. In focus-shift segments, both architects considered shapes/angles, sizes and views more than students. This means that architects, in contrast to students, began thinking about visual attributes of depictions and views, as soon as they shifted attention<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> to a new part of a sketch. In contrast, in continuing segments, architects differed from students only in the consideration of all the functional relations except practical roles. This means that architects continued to interpret functional relations, especially abstract features/reactions, more frequently than students as their thinking progressed within a dependency chunk. It should also be noted that only 'practical roles' were completely different in nature from all the other functional relations. Architects thought of practical roles of spaces/things and their relations equally or less frequently than students.<marker type="block"/> These results may be summarized by the following insights, which might be adopted as useful strategies to follow in designing. First, because architects are trained to, and thus able to, think of shapes/angles and sizes, which are inherently visual attributes of depicted elements (spaces and items/things), just after they shift focus to a new item, space, or topic, their focus shifts will not end in vain. Second, because architects are able to explore many more functional considerations, especially abstract features/reactions, in the continuing segments, they can pursue design thoughts more deeply within and across dependency chunks than students. This analysis has revealed that sketches stimulate thinking about not only perceptual relations, but also about inherently non-visual functional relations with both advanced design students and practicing architects. Practicing architects are even more adept at reading-off functional issues from perception of visual features than students of architecture.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="140" page="11" column="1">Table 3 The percentage</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="141" page="11" column="1">of both types of segments in the protocols of students and architects</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="142" page="11" column="1">Students (%) (aver. ± std.)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="143" page="11" column="1">Architect I (%) Architect 2 (%)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="144" page="11" column="1">Segment types Continuing Focus shift Total</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="145" page="11" column="1">35.2 ± 4.2 64.8 ± 4.2 100</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="146" page="11" column="1">49.2 50.8 100</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="147" page="11" column="1">46.8 53.2 100</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="148" page="11" column="1">Table 4 The number of</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="149" page="11" column="1">dependency chunks for students and architects</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="150" page="11" column="1">Students (aver. ± std.)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="151" page="11" column="1">Architect 1 Architect 2</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="152" page="11" column="1">Kinds of dependency chunks Two in length More than two Total number</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="153" page="11" column="1">13.7 ± 4.0 12.6 ± 2.7 26.3 ± 3.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="154" page="11" column="1">18 39 57</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="155" page="11" column="1">16 19 35</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="156" page="11" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="157" page="11" column="1">395</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx158">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62fu.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="160" page="12" column="1">4.2 Information categories in both types of segments</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="163" page="12" column="1">TableS Distribution of</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="164" page="12" column="1">information categories in protocols of students and architects by segment type</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="165" page="12" column="1">Focus-shift segments Continuing segments</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="166" page="12" column="1">aver. Architect I Architect 2 Students aver. Architect I Architect 2 ± std.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="167" page="12" column="1">0.7</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="168" page="12" column="1">28.1 2.3 8.7 5.0 6.0</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="169" page="12" column="1">24.6 4.6 10.9 5.7 4.0</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="170" page="12" column="1">19.8 ± 4.1 4.1 ± 2.5 8.4 ± 2.9 3.3 ± 2.0 6.3 ± 2.5</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="171" page="12" column="1">19.6 4.5 5.3 1.9 4.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="172" page="12" column="1">16.0 3.7 4.9 4.3 5.5</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="173" page="12" column="1">11.8 14.3</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="174" page="12" column="1">20.2 ± 3.2</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="175" page="12" column="1">19.1 19.0</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="176" page="12" column="1">1.9 3.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="177" page="12" column="1">4.6 6.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="178" page="12" column="1">8.6 ± 2.6 4.7 ± 1.5</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="179" page="12" column="1">4.5 7.9</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="180" page="12" column="1">8.6 6.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="181" page="12" column="1">8.3 4.4 9.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="182" page="12" column="1">8.0 1.7 5.7</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="183" page="12" column="1">5.4 ± 2.3 1.0 ± 1.1 8.1 ± 1.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="184" page="12" column="1">9.3 4.3 13.8</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="185" page="12" column="1">6.7 0.6 9.2</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="186" page="12" column="1">9.9 9.1</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="187" page="12" column="1">10.1 ± 2.2</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="188" page="12" column="1">5.0 14.7</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="189" page="12" column="1">Subclasses of students information ± std. category Spaces 30.8 ± Things 6.1 ± 3.8 Shapes/ang les 6.2 ± 2.4 Sizes 2.9 ± 1.3 Global spatial 7.5 ± 3.4 relations Local spatial 13.9 ± 2.1 relations Practical roles 5.1 ± 1.9 Abstract 2.9 ± 1.6 features/reactions Views 5.6 ± 2.1 Lights 1.5 ± 1.3 Circulation of 9.4 ± 2.9 cars/people Background 8.1 ± 2.0 knowledge Total 100</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="190" page="12" column="1">100 100 100 100 100</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="191" page="12" column="1">architects had a significantly higher percentage of responses than students are high-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="192" page="12" column="1">Note: categories in which lighted.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="193" page="12" column="1">396</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="194" page="12" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx195">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62fu.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="198" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">5</h2>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="199" page="13" column="1">Related work and discussion</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="200" page="13" column="1">5. I Think-Aloud protocols vs retrospective protocols</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="206" page="13" column="1">The analysis of think-aloud protocols has been a major method for seeking insights into human-thought processes in complex cognitive tasks 20. It has also been employed extensively in studies of design activities. We did not, however, employ the think-aloud protocol method because previous work suggested that talking aloud concurrently may interfere with participants' perception during their sketching activities 20.22. This effect would under- mine our research, because our purpose was to reveal the perceptual interactions between a designer and his own sketches. <marker type="block"/> Instead, we chose to employ the method of retrospective reporting. However, another undesirable effect, selective recall, is inevitable in this method 20. Participants may tend to selectively report what is relevant to the retrieval cues given in the reporting task and/or what is relevant to their purposes and intentions while reporting, neglecting other thoughts which might have occurred during the design session. The measure we took to reduce selec-<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> tive recall was to add memory cues to the retrospective reporting sessions by showing each participant the videotape of his/her own sketching behaviors. This provided the participant with visual cues about the exact sequence of sketching, including the timing, hesitations, returns and redrawings. Those visual cues were expected to help each participant remember what he/she thought, relevant or irrelevant.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="203" page="13" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="204" page="13" column="1">397</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx205">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62fu.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="207" page="14" column="1">5.2</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="208" page="14" column="1">Formal analysis informal analysis</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="209" page="14" column="1">vs</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="211" page="14" column="1">Past work on protocol analysis for design process has taken one of two approaches, formal analysis and informal analysis. In formal protocol analysis, design is seen as a rational problem-solving search process through a 'solution space' 28-32. Its main focus is to describe design in terms of a general taxonomy of problem-solving, i.e. problem states, oper- ators, plans, goals, strategies and so on, and thus to come up with generalizable findings on design methodology. In informal analysis, on the other hand, design is seen as a process in which each designer 'constructs his/her own reality' by his/her own actions that are reflective, responsive and opportunistic to the design situation, as Dorst and Dijkhuis 33 characterized it. Schon's work on 'designer as a reflective practitioner' 34 and Goldschmidt's work on the design cycle of 'seeing-as' and 'seeing-that' 13 are typical examples of this category. The present work belongs to the latter approach in the sense that we see the design process as composed of cycles of focus shifts and continuing thoughts, and that we aim at revealing how each small cycle is driven by designers' actions of seeing different information categories. <marker type="block"/> In comparison to Goldschmidt's work, the present research is an attempt to analyze the 'seeing-as' phenomena into distinct types by developing a precise set of information categories, e.g. architects often unintentionally discover certain 'spaces' and 'things', two basic visual elements in architectural sketches, from a configuration of unexpected line drawings. Some- times, functional issues, e.g. 'abstract features and reactions' emerge to them from the visual attributes of depictions such as 'shapes/angles' and 'sizes', and/or from the 'spatial arrangements' of depicted elements.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="212" page="14" column="1">5.3</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="213" page="14" column="1">The link between design process and the content of design problem</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="214" page="14" column="1">28 Eastman, C M 'On the analysis of intuitive design processes' in G. T. Moore (ed) Emerging methods in environ- mentai design and planning MIT Press, Cambridge (1970) pp 21-37 29 Krauss, R I and Myer, R M 'Design: a case history' in G T Moore (ed) Emerging methods in environmental design and planning MtT Press, Cambridge (1970) pp 11-20 30 Akin, 0 Psychology of architectural design Pion, lon- don (1986) 31 Akin, 0 'Architects' reasoning with structures and functions. Environment and Planning B: Planning and Design Vol 20 (1993) pp 273--294. 32 Chan, CoS 'Cognitive processes in architectural design problem solving' Design Studies Vol 11 No 2 (1990) pp 6O-S0. 33 Dorst, K and Oljkhuls, J 'Comparing paradigms for describing design activity' Design Studies Vol 16 No 2 (1995) pp 261-274. 34 Schon, 0 A The reflective practitioner Harper Collins, USA (1983)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" page="14" column="1">Dorst and Dijkhuis 33 argued that the analyses of design processes should focus on both 'design processes' and 'the contents of the design problem', in order to arrive at generalizable insights on what good and productive design activities are. What they mean by 'analyzing design processes' is to reveal general tendencies and features of how design processes are struc- tured. What they mean by 'analyzing contents' is to reveal what infor- <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> mation, resources and knowledge are involved there. Dorst and Dijkhuis pointed out that the formal 'rational problem-solving' approach focuses only on process components of design activities, and fails to analyze the contents of what designers see and think, and what knowledge they use. On the other hand, case studies pertaining to the informal approach, typically Schon's reflection-in-action theory, are content-oriented, and thus, difficult to compare and use in order to elicit generalizable insights on good ways of doing designs. Dorst and Dijkhuis finally concluded that the informal approach should be further developed, by 'building a taxonomy of design problems, and of frames' (p 274).<marker type="block"/> Our approach addresses precisely this issue. The set of information categories and their subclasses can be seen as a taxonomy of the content compo- nent of design problems. This categorization is general enough to be appli- cable to different design activities, because it was derived from the perspective of cognitive science, i.e. from general insights about how people see, think, and perform, perceptually and conceptually. On the other hand, the two types of segments, focus-shift and continuing segments, are the process components of design activities. The analysis we have developed explores the link between process components and content components, by revealing what information categories are dominant in and characteristic of both types of segments.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="216" page="14" column="1">398</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="217" page="14" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx218">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62fu.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="221" page="15" column="1">5.4</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="222" page="15" column="1">Chunks in design process</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="229" page="15" column="1">Recently there has been a growing belief in the field of architectural design that a fruitful way of analyzing a design process is to decompose the entire process into its smallest components and to focus on the interlinks among these components. Our notion of 'dependency chunks' falls into this category and, thus, it is not new in itself. The term 'chunk' was coined by Miller ,5 to describe subjective grouping of unrelated items. It was adopted by researchers studying problem solving and reasoning to characterize experts' knowledge 3,4,36. Experts are able to organize elements that seem unrelated to a novice into cohesive, meaningful units. <marker type="block"/> These ideas have been more recently adopted by researchers studying the design process. Out of several predecessors who have used this approach, Goldschmidt's work on 'linkograph' 37 is the most similar to ours. Her work is a forerunner of ours in the sense that we share her view that analyzing interconnectivity among segments will yield insights about what design process leads to good productivity. However, her notion of chunk differs from ours in granularity. A chunk in her notion takes the form of a pattern of links that circumscribes a large number of design moves in it, typically more than ten, so that there are few, or none at all, links across different chunks. In contrast, our chunk is configured from a relatively<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> smaller number of segments. This difference is brought about by the difference in purposes of what analyses of chunks are for. Goldschmidt aims at revealing a geometrically discernible pattern of interconnectivity of design moves, i.e. the relatively global structure of a design process. On the other hand, we aimed at revealing smaller cycles of design processes, which are characterized by focus-shift and continuing segments. The smaller granularity of our chunks is suitable for this purpose.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="224" page="15" column="1">35 Miller, G A 'The magical number seven, plus or minus two: some limits on your capacity for processing information' Psychological Review Vol 63 (1956) pp 81-97. 36 Chase, W G and Simon, H A 'Perception in chess' Cognitive psychology Vol 4 (1973) pp 55--81. 37 Goldschmidt, G 'Criteria for design evaluation: a process-ori- ented paradigm' in Y. E. Kalay (ad) Evaluating and predicting design performance John Wiley, New York (1992)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="226" page="15" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="227" page="15" column="1">399</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx228">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62fu.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="230" page="16" column="1">5.5</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="231" page="16" column="1">Design thoughts on form and function</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="234" page="16" column="1">Arnheim 27 insisted that the visual form and function of architecture is physically and psychologically intertwined, and that exploring psychologi- cal aspects of visual forms should help architects understand the interplay between form and function. Consider, e.g. an architect's depiction of several visual objects, e.g. the contours of buildings, in a plan drawing. Arnheim observed that not only their visual shapes emerge up in front ('figures') to architects, but also the interspaces among these figures ('ground') can be and often are, emergent objects in their own right. This is because, Amheim surmised, architects are able to sense invisible forces issuing from the visual forms of the depicted objects and from the interspaces, and to perceive the interplay of those counterbalancing forces from two sources (Chapter 3). <marker type="block"/> Here, note that invisible forces and their interplay are demystified and can be interpreted as functional thoughts which derive from visual shapes. In terms of our categorization, visual forms correspond to spaces, things, shapes/angles, sizes and their spatial relations, local or global. And invisible forces and their interplay correspond to abstract features and reactions.<marker type="block"/> Viewed this way, our findings corroborate his claim. Architects, more often than students, attend to shapes/angles and sizes, the visual attributes of depicted elements, just after they have shifted their focus to new thoughts. We may interpret this phenomenon as evidence that practicing architects know better that visual attributes are good sources from which to derive design thoughts on functions. In fact, our findings suggest that architects, when they are exploring related thoughts successively, are better than students at reading-off non-visual functional issues, especially abstract features and reactions, from visual features on sketches.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="235" page="16" column="1">6 6.1</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:FutureWork">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="236" page="16" column="1">Future work The causes offocus shift and exploration of related thoughts</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" page="16" column="1">The present research suggests that shift of focus and exploration of successive related thoughts are two important vehicles for pushing forward design <marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> processes. In this paper, we examined statistical relations between the segment types and the information categories characteristic of them. This is a rather rough examination, just the dominant information categories in each of the two segments. We have not yet analyzed in detail the reasons or causes of focus shift and exploration. Visual cues that can potentially be the causes are shapes/angles, sizes, textures, line attributes of depicted elements, and proximity, connectivity, continuity/alignment, comparison of more than one elements, etc. These cues are obtained by dividing the current information subclasses more precisely at a finer grain. Examining the visual cues that are involved with evidence of focus-shifts and explorations in protocols is one of our future plans.<marker type="block"/> The present research concluded that sketches allow architects to 'read-off' non-visual functional issues from visual features. So, what aspects of sketches as external representation enable and facilitate the act of 'reading- off'? Is it because sketches are visual and thus certain configurations of line drawings will visually cue the architect's background knowledge about functional issues? Or, is it because sketches are more or less specific in Stenning and Oberlander's sense 16 and thus a spatial relation between things that have been drawn on the sketch irrelevantly to each other becomes emergent all of a sudden, suggesting a certain functional issue? Or, is it because freehand sketches are ambiguous in Goel's sense 17 and thus afford re-interpretation of line drawings? A close look at each case of 'reading-off' in the protocols from a viewpoint of the nature of sketches involved is another future project. This line of study on architectural design sketches lies within the scope of a broader issue; why and how external representations function in people's problem-solving and concept-forming.<marker type="block"/> Due to the inflexibility of conventional design tools mentioned earlier, designers and architects still tum to freehand sketches for naive concept- forming. So, how should a design tool assist designers in early design processes? What implications have been brought to us by the present research?<marker type="block"/> This study implies that perception of visual attributes of sketched items, e.g. sizes and shapes/angles, plays an important role in exploring inherently non-visual functional thoughts, one important goal of a design process. In other words, sketches serve as a 'perceptual interface' through which one can discover non-visual functional relations underlying the visual features. This has motivated us to aim at a computational-sketching tool that pos- sesses the functionality of enriching perception 38. If a computational<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> sketching tool can encourage users to respond to visual features in sketches and to 'read-off' what they suggest, novice designers may improve their ability to use sketches as 'perceptual interfaces'. Even practicing architects may find it stimulating the discovery of new ways to look at their own sketches that they would otherwise not notice. It can provide users with enriched interactivity, motivate them to use the tool, and enable them to engage in their task productively.<marker type="block"/> Our vision is of a tool that will, when a user draws a new figure, present visual stimuli, e.g. 'animation' or 'highlighting' of sketched items (as 'figure'), as well as of interspaces among the items (as 'ground') 39. The basic concept is that if the look of visual features of items (e.g. shapes, angles, sizes, textures and line-features) and of patterns produced by their spatial arrangement fluctuates, then the fluctuation may encourage the user to 'read-off', beyond just their visual features, their potential appeal to perception in unanticipated ways. Which items and interspaces should be candidates for animation and highlighting? How should animation and highlighting be performed? Those are the immediate future issues to be addressed.<marker type="block"/> The functionality of 'enriching perception' is orthogonal to the criteria that past literature on computational sketching tools have proposed. Gross's Cocktail Napkin 25 has proposed a scheme of on-line access to peripheral information, e.g. past inventories of design sketches, either public or personal. This allows computational sketching to be 'useful' in early conceptual design phases. Kramer pointed out that, when architects make sketches on paper, they dynamically associate sketched marks with meanings, structures and operations only when the association is needed, not when the marks are put down. He proposed an infrastructure called translucent patches 24 to provide users with the freedom of dynamic and fluid associations. This allows computational sketching to be 'natural', free from unnatural constraints that conventional design tools would impose.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="238" page="16" column="1">400</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="239" page="16" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx240">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62fu.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="242" page="17" column="1">6.2 The roles of external representation</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="244" page="17" column="1">6.3 Implications for design tools</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="246" page="17" column="1">38 Suwa, M and Gross, M 0 'Enriching perception: a new paradigm for design sketching tools' (personal manuscript)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="248" page="17" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="249" page="17" column="1">401</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx250">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62fu.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="254" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">7</h2>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="255" page="18" column="1">Conclusions</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="256" page="18" column="1">39 Suwa, M and Tversky, B 'What architects see in their design sketches: implications for design tools' Human factors in computing systems: CHI'96 conference companion ACM, New York (1996) pp 191-192</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="262" page="18" column="1">We have examined participants' design thoughts in an architectural design task, by the method of retrospective protocol analysis. One of the main goals was the development of a set of information categories into which the contents of participants' protocols can be fitted. We devised this from the perspective of cognitive science, especially the research on diagrammatic reasoning. Another goal was the way of decomposing the entire protocol of a participant into segments and of analyzing the structure of dependency links among segments, i.e. dependency chunks. Our definitions of dependency links and chunks yielded an analysis of protocols with appro- <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> priate granularity which allowed us to conclude that the design process consists of smaller cycles of focus shift and continuing thoughts on related topics. Our finding, that architects had more and longer dependency chunks than students, indicates that once architects shifted their focus of attention, they thought more deeply about the topic.<marker type="block"/> Another contribution of the present research is the investigation of the information categories that are dominant in or characteristic focus-shift segments and continuing segments. We found that because architects are more able to think of shapes/angles and sizes, which are inherently visual attributes of depictions, just after they shift focus to a new item, space or topic, their focus shifts are more productive. Moreover, we found that because architects are able to 'read-off' many more functional relations in continuing segments, especially abstract features and reactions, from perceptions of depicted elements, they can pursue design thoughts more deeply within and across dependency chunks.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="258" page="18" column="1">402</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="259" page="18" column="1">Design Studies Vol 18 No 4 October 1997</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx260">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62fu.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="263" page="19" column="1">Acknowledgments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="264" page="19" column="1">We would like to express our thanks to Y. E. Kalay at the University of California, Berkeley, his former student, Jinwon Choi and P. Teicholz at CIFE, Stanford University, for putting us in contact with students of architecture and practising architects, to the staff at the Department of Architecture of U. C. Berkeley for lending space and equipment to us, and to all the participants of the experiment for their goodwill to participate. We are grateful to G. Goldschmidt at Technion - Israel Institute of Technology, Y. E. Kalay, O. Akin at the Department of Architecture at Carnegie Melon University, M. D. Gross at the University of Colorado, Boulder and J. P. Protzen at U. C. Berkeley for insightful discussion of design processes, for suggestions on our research and for references to previous work. Weare grateful to D. M. Cannon at CDR, Stanford University, for discussions from which the idea of using videotapes came out. This research was done when the first author was visiting CSLI of Stanford University, and he is grateful to the staff of CSLI and Department of Psychology for arranging his visit.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="265" page="19" column="1">A protocol analysis</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="266" page="19" column="1">403</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx267">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fu.page_019.image_19.png" thmb="62fu.page_019.image_19-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
