<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>ff2e149ff1181e3bd3bcfada34924fb50c8b9facb6768a6a215b5bc495a9da6c</job>
    <base_name>62gm</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08468.x</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62gm.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">T H E O R E T I C A L P E R S P E C T I V E Metadesign as an Emergent Design Culture E very time the word metadesign is used, it causes even more confusion than the word design. The term seems vague, elusive. Semantically, the principal meaning of the Greek word meta- when used as a prefix is “change of place, order, or nature” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="2" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. Historically, since the 1960s, the term metadesign has been used to focus on the possibilities of “de- signing the design”—possibilities that later, in the 1980s, were realized by using information technologies. In the last two decades, the idea of metadesign has appeared as both a theoretical issue and an operational methodology; however, it has always been an isolated concept, producing neither an estab- lished approach nor a coherent theory. The development of the notion of metadesign can be categorized as critical and reflexive thinking about the boundaries and scope of design, aimed at coping with the complexity of natural human interaction made tangible by technology. Metadesign seeks to trans- form this complexity into an opportunity for new forms of creativity and sociability. This text aims at tracing the development of the notion of metadesign and the multiplicity of its definitions by offering a map of correlated concepts and es- tablishing the foundations of metadesign as a distinct and emergent design culture. M ETADESIGN IN A RTISTIC AND C ULTURAL D EBATE Within the artistic and cultural debate, the idea of metadesign has primarily addressed the emergence of digital networks and biotechnologies. Both represent alternatives to “juridical” models of communication, interaction and life—as embodied by mass media and moral law. In 1986, at the time of the emergence of advanced telecommunications and the first virtual communities, Gene Youngblood wrote “Metadesign: Toward a Postmodernism of Reconstruction” for Ars Electronica [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="3" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. Inspired by the pio- neering work of Kit Galloway and Sherrie Rabinowitz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="4" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>], Youngblood defined metadesign as a strategy for instigating a revolution in the communication world and overcoming the broadcasting style of mass culture. As such, metadesign deals with the creation of context rather than content; it is a mode Elisa Giaccardi (theorist, researcher, designer), Center for LifeLong Learning and Design (L3D), University of Colorado, ECOT 717, 430 UCB, Boulder, CO 80309-0430, U.S.A. E-mail: <email id="5">&lt;giaccard@cs.colorado.edu&gt;</email>. Web: &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://x2.i-dat.org/" id="6">http://x2.i-dat.org/</ext-link>~eg/&gt;. Article Frontispiece. NOX, V2_Lab, 1998. (© NOX Architects) By means of their metadesign technique, NOX Architects adapt architecture to evolution. Their architecture is an interface for a dynamic organization of space in which visitors act upon architectural struc-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx8">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62gm.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="9">Elisa Giaccardi</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15">T he concept of metadesign was adopted in the 1980s of integrating systems and setting regarding the use of information actions in order to create environ- technologies in relation to art, cultural theories and design ments in which people may culti- practices (from interactive vate “creative conversations” and to biotechnological design). take control of the context of their article introduces theories and cultural and aesthetic production practices of metadesign and contributes to the unfolding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="10" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>). metadesign as an emergent Some years later, in his 1995 essay design culture, calling for an “Networked Art and Virtual Com- expansion of the creative munities” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="11" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>], Derrick De Kerck- process in the new design hove defined metadesign as a space engendered by information technologies. quality of the new art forms that were emerging over the Web in its early years. According to De Kerckhove, metadesign is the kind of design that puts the tools rather than the object of design in the users’ hands, and defines the conditions for the process of interaction rather than the process itself. However, in subsequent writings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="12" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>], De Kerckhove has addressed metadesign as a model of design actually mediated by digital networks rather than an emerging quality of design promoted by art experimentation. As such, metadesign can be described as the design of tools, parameters and operating conditions that allow an infinite flexibility in tailoring the industrial product and enable the end-user to take charge of the final design by choos- ing among many different options. In the same period, Paul Virilio expressed shock at Stelarc’s techno-performances. In his book The Art of the Motor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="13" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>], published in 1995, Virilio wrote that he feared the advent of a neu- rological form of design directed at shaping our perceptual and cognitive systems via information processing and further directed at reorganizing the organic according to a machinic model. He called the aftermath of this “technomorphization” of society “metadesign.” Biologist Humberto Maturana refuted the idea that such a process of adaptation to electronic media can ever take place in his emblematic 1997 paper “Metadesign” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="14" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>]. In this paper, Maturana argued that if a process of metadesign as design of living systems does exist, this enlarges the issue of design to include the nature of our very existence, and it implies an epistemological and ethical rethinking of the relations between human beings and technology. He strongly disputed any deterministic understanding of biological evolution, and there- fore of “human design.” From Maturana’s perspective, metadesign is a dynamic work of art: It produces an aesthetic experience of the world that is intertwined with our social and technological present. Like art, metadesign has the potential to open up new relational dimensions and create a grounding reality in the course of human history.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="16">ABSTRACT</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="17">art This</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="18">of</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="19">tures that respond in real time to their needs.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="20">The social construction of reality is for Maturana—from a</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21">©2005 ISAST</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22">LEONARDO, Vol. 38, No. 4, pp. 342–349, 2005</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="23">343</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86">design perspective—an ethical impera- tive, as it is for Youngblood [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="24" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] and Galloway and Rabinowitz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="25" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. On this point, Eugene Thacker, in a workshop paper, “Bioethics and Bio-ethics,” for the 2002 conference “Towards Human Technolo- gies” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="26" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>], explicitly tackled the question of biotechnological design and bioethics. In this paper, Thacker tried to clarify that even though metadesign is a kind of design that is not instrumental, but ethical, it is nevertheless not based on a moral law. Metadesign must allow a social mode of existence that is flexible and based on mutual processes of affecting and being affected rather than on a juridical model. According to Thacker, metadesign represents a critical and creative investigation into the possibilities of transformation of human beings and culture. The ideas expressed around the last decades of the 20th century by these few<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> but crucial theoretical writings on meta- design—reflecting on the scope, boundaries and qualities of the expanded design space that is engendered by information technologies—have found some conceptual frameworks and opera- tive methodologies in several application domains. These ideas combine here with design theory and methodology with promising results.<marker type="block"/> C ONCEPTUAL F RAMEWORKS AND P RACTICES OF M ETADESIGN The notion of metadesign has been applied in many fields, including graphic design, industrial design, information architecture and system design. These applications have focused differently on the concepts associated with metadesign, ranging from processes of high-order de-<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> sign to participation and co-evolution. However, these concepts are often tied together. The idea of reflexive thinking about design has been commonly translated in the application field as the “design of a design process.” In graphic design and industrial design, in particular, metadesign has primarily been connected to the idea of working with computational structures on a higher level of design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="31" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. Because a computational object has a discrete structure, parts of the object can be easily accessed, modified and sub- stituted by other parts; it is not fixed and it can be generated and manipulated without actually drawing it. In this context, metadesign can be associated with the passage from traditional typography to interface design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="32" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. John Maeda [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="33" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>], in a series of short essays published in Japan for MdN Magazine in 1995, men-<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tioned the concept of metadesign in relation to his idea of graphic design not as printed image but as “reactive” computer programs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>). In architecture, similarly, Lars Spuybroek promotes metadesign techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="40" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>] as tools for constructing dynamic spaces where people can unpredictably and creatively interact with their environment (Article Frontispiece, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 3</xref> and Color Plate F No. 2). Considering the capability of code to define “transformation rules,” Celestino<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Soddu has addressed metadesign as the design of an “artificial DNA” since 1989 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="44" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. In his work, the objective is the design of “species of design”: the designer is the producer of an “executable idea” (the generative code), and the consumer is the one who chooses one of its possible realizations. The creative process defines a “seed” able to generate endless variations recognizable as belonging to the same idea but open to change by the client. Thus, the final consumer will choose from this endless sequence of<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> variations the result that better fits his or her needs and subjectivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 4</xref>). Like De Kerckhove [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="47" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>], Soddu empowers the user as consumer, making him or her proactive, but does not question the user’s passive role as designer. Evolution here is the result of the execution of a notation and its exploration, rather than the aftermath of the user’s full participation in the creative process. In this generative process model, the “seed” can be defined and modified only by the designer. In the last few years, two organizations have been working on frameworks and applications of metadesign: the Labo- ratory for Architecture and Urbanism (Lab[au]), a collective of artists, archi- tects and computer scientists based in Brussels; and the Center for LifeLong Learning and Design (L3D) of the University of Colorado at Boulder. These two organizations have developed research agendas that incorporate most of the aforementioned theoretical statements and operational methodologies. Lab[au] has adopted the term metadesign with the objective of enacting a new discipline of information architecture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="48" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. For Lab[au], metadesign is a matter of the setting of codes that allow data to be organized in spatial and temporal forms—that is, a design process of a higher order. Participation and evolution, however, are important. The integration of user interaction over time is a key element in the collective’s work, and it represents an active component in the structuring of information itself. Sim-<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ilar to Galloway and Rabinowitz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="54" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>], Lab[au] focuses on the construction of electronic spaces, viewing information not as content but as an environment in which users’ perceptual and cognitive ca- pabilities can be expanded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 5</xref>). At the Center for LifeLong Learning and Design, however, metadesign seems to have undergone a conceptual and operational development that places it in the context of current debate in design theory and methodology. Gerhard Fischer and his colleagues, particularly in the last few years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="56" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>], have consis- tently focused on metadesign. Concep- tually, metadesign represents to them the question of how to create new media and environments that allow users, when needed and desired, to act as designers and be creative. By providing users with social and technical support, the environments designed at L3D are intended to sustain users as the actual “owners of problems” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="57" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. Operationally, metadesign is viewed at L3D as a design methodology characterized by activities,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> processes and techniques focused on cre- ating socio-technical environments that empower users actively and collabora- tively to engage with the original designer(s) in the continuous development of a system and to design solutions that range from the creation of content to the modification of code (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 6</xref>). The conceptual framework developed at L3D re- flects some important objectives shared with user-centered and participatory design, but it transcends these objectives by changing the processes by which systems and content are designed. To Fischer and his colleagues, it is clear that existing design frameworks and methodologies are insufficient to cope with the emergent as- pects of reality and to support creative practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="60" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>].<marker type="block"/> U NFOLDING M ETADESIGN AS AN E MERGENT D ESIGN C ULTURE By tracing a conceptual map of metadesign theories and applications, we can see<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> that some elements emerge as crucial: a focus on the design of general structures and processes, rather than on fixed objects and contents; the need for methods and techniques that are fluid, rather than prescriptive (such as diagramming or seeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="63" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]); the call for environments that can evolve; and the necessity of relational settings that allow systems to be based on a mutual and open process of affecting and being affected. Considering the current debate in design theory and methodology, we see that the contours of this map reveal a thoughtful reflection on controversial design issues, such as the problems of anticipation, participation and emergence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="64" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>]. Users’ needs and tasks, as well as sit- uations and behaviors, cannot be fully an- ticipated at design time because they are ill-defined and change over time. There- fore, users need to be engaged in the problem-framing/problem-solving process, both when the system is designed and when the system is used. Keeping the system open to participation and evolu-<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tion at use time is meant to join social and technical systems, not only to make them optimized and efficient, but also to let new conditions, interactions and relationships emerge. In this way—by sustaining emergence and evolution—new forms of sociability and creativity can develop and innovation can be fostered. The focus of metadesign on the success- ful integration of methodologies of design by anticipation, participation and emergence translates into the identifica- tion of a multidimensional design space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="70" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>]. Whereas operational similarities show metadesign to be a consistent development in design theory and methodology, the cultural path that metadesign theories and applications reveal is not unidi- rectional. On one side, metadesign has been considered as a networked model of design aimed at product refinement, personalization and mass customization. According to this approach, metadesign is conceived as a new praxis of design that does not question the role of the user in the process of production as consumer but rather empowers the user in this role. This development relies on operational assumptions about metadesign, but it does not fully achieve its potential as a new design culture. On the other side, and more interestingly, metadesign has been conceived as co-creation: a shared design endeavor aimed at sustaining emergence, evolution and adaptation. According to this development, the operational terms and potential of designing at a higher-order level must be joined to a more reflexive and collaborative practice of design.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Art practice and cultural debate have been extremely active in promoting metadesign as a reflexive method of thinking about and beyond design, rather than as a new praxis of design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="73" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>]. The idea of metadesign developed by Yevgeny N. Lazarev and colleagues as a result of a reflection on the emerging relationships among art, technology and science is another case. Concerned with an expansion of human creativity, Lazarev writes:<marker type="block"/> The connections between metadesign, telematic culture and interactive art are<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> significant and based on a similar call for the expansion of human creativity. Some overlaps, in particular, are interesting and can be pointed out as further indi- cations of how metadesign actually ex- presses the emergence of a new culture, somehow at the convergence of art and design. The idea of the interactive artist as a “systems designer,” for instance, elab- orated by Margot Lovejoy in her book Postmodern Currents: Art and Artists in the Age of Electronic Media [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="79" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>], recalls Galloway and Rabinowitz’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="80" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>] idea of the metadesigner as a “systems integra- tor.” Even more interestingly, some ideas expressed by Roy Ascott in his article “The A-Z of Interactive Arts” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="81" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>] recall the operational methodology typical of metadesign: the idea of “seeding,” defined as a way of designing that should re- place top-down designing; the idea of a “non-trivial interactivity,” conceived as an<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> open-ended and infinite interactivity capable of accommodating always-new variables; and the idea of “open-ended systems” (OES), in which interaction takes place within networked and evolving systems that put the user or the environment in control of the interaction itself.<marker type="block"/> I S M ETADESIGN A W ORK OF A RT OR A W ORK OF S CIENCE ? This paper introduces and promotes metadesign not simply as a new design methodology, but as a cultural development exploring the new design space engendered by information technologies and ultimately concerned with expand- ing the creative process of emergence and invention of the world. Metadesign represents a cultural shift from design as “planning” to design as “seeding.” By promoting collaborative and transformational practices of design that can support new modes of human interaction and sustain an expansion of the creative process, metadesign is de- veloping toward new ways of understanding and planning with the goal of producing more open and evolving systems of interaction. Metadesign can be seen not only as a design approach informing a specific design methodology for the development of interactive media and environments but also as a form of cultural strategy informing and integrating different domains. Rather than a new model of design, metadesign represents a constructive mode of design: an en- hancement of the creative process at the convergence of “art” and “science.”</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="28">Fig. 1. Mobile Image, Electronic Cafe International, 1984. (© Kit Galloway and Sherrie Rabinowitz) An early example of a metadesign environment, ECI was a telecommunications system characterized as an accessible, flexible and end-user-modifiable system that allowed users the greatest possible freedom to design and control their own information environments.</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62gm.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="35">344</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="36">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62gm.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="38">Fig. 2. John Maeda, reactive graphics, 1995. (© John Maeda) Maeda’s metadesign technique allows generation of visual experiences that involve the viewers in the creation of the form by responding to their inputs in real time.</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="43">Fig. 3. NOX, V2_Lab, 1998. (© NOX Architects) Lars Spuybroek and colleagues progress seamlessly from a computer-generated process of forces, vectors and springs to the flowing transition—for instance, between floor and tables—allowing people to interact with their environment in a more open and creative manner.</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62gm.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="50">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="51">345</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62gm.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="53">Fig. 4. Celestino Soddu, Generated architectures to increase the Hong Kong identity, 2002. (© Celestino Soddu) In this metaproject, a mayor can customize the “morphogenetic code” of evolution for his or her town and use it to control the future identity of the local environment.</caption>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="66">346</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="67">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62gm.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="69">Fig. 5. Lab[au], i-Tube, 1999. (© Lab[au]) A metadesign environment, this project proposes a graphical user interface and a navigation system for on-line databanks based on cartographies that display information as a process-oriented and generative space. Information is transformed into membranes that are then folded into space according to user-defined parameters and behaviors.</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx72">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_006.image_08.png" thmb="62gm.page_006.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="76">The specific perspectives of metadesign are hard to define since it is quite a new phenomenon. But one can already see an exceptional vitality in this trend, whether it remains within the domain of design or transforms into a phenomenon of human creativity that has never ex- isted or been possible before [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="75" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>].</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="78">Fig. 6. L3D, The Seeding, Evolutionary Growth, and Reseeding (SER) Process Model. (© L3D, University of Colorado) This process model is applied to the metadesign environments developed at L3D in order to integrate “design time” and “use time,” and to allow users to act as designers at different stages of the continuous development of a system.</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gm.page_006.image_09.png" thmb="62gm.page_006.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="83">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84">347</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="87" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Acknowledgments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">The author wishes to thank (in alphabetical order): Manuel Abendroth, Ernesto Arias, Marco Brizzi, Hal Eden, Gerhard Fischer, Kit Galloway, John Maeda, Anders Mörch, NOX, Jonathan Ostwald, Sherrie Rabinowitz, Celestino Soddu, Yunwen Ye and the re- viewers.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="89" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">References and Notes</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" page="7" column="1">1. See terms such as metalinguistics and metadata, but also metamorphosis.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="7" column="1">2. Gene Youngblood, “Metadesign: Toward a Postmodernism of Reconstruction,” in Ars Electronica Cat- alog (Linz, Austria: Linzer Veranstaltungsgesellschaft, 1986), &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.aec.at/en/archives/festival_" id="91">http://www.aec.at/en/archives/festival_</ext-link> einstieg.asp&gt;. 3. See &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ecafe.com/" id="92">http://www.ecafe.com/</ext-link>&gt;.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" page="7" column="1">4. Derrick De Kerckhove, “Networked Art and Virtual Communities,” in Claude Faure et al., eds., Ars- lab: I Sensi del Virtuale (Milan, Italy: Fabbri Editore, 1995) pp. 103–110.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" page="7" column="1">5. See in particular Derrick De Kerckhove, Connected Intelligence: The Arrival of the Web Society (Toronto, On- tario: Somerville House, 1997).</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" page="7" column="2">6. Paul Virilio, The Art of the Motor, Julie Rose, trans. (Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1995).</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="98" page="7" column="2">7. Available at &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.hum.auc.dk/" id="97">http://www.hum.auc.dk/</ext-link>~rasand/ Artikler/metadesign.htm&gt;.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="7" column="2">8. Youngblood [2].</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="100" page="7" column="2">9. See [3].</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="101" page="7" column="2">10. Eugene Thacker, “Bioethics and Bio-ethics,” in Towards Human Technologies Conference (Brisbane, Aus- tralia: University of Queensland, 2002) &lt;http:// www.uq.edu.au/gsm/Confpapers/thacker1.doc&gt;;</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">see also Eugene Thacker, Biomedia (Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 2004).</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="103" page="7" column="2">11. In industrial design, for instance, metadesign is primarily used to mean the construction of a tem- plate that makes a product “that thing” without actually designing it.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="105" page="7" column="2">12. I owe this consideration to Lev Manovich, with whom I had a short e-mail correspondence on the relationships between metadesign and interface design. 13. See &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.maedastudio.com/" id="104">http://www.maedastudio.com/</ext-link>&gt;.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" page="7" column="2">14. See in particular Lars Spuybroek and Cho Im Sik, “Diagramming: Lars Spuybroek Interviewed by Cho Im Sik,” in R.S. Vasudevan et al., eds., Sarai Reader 02: The Cities of Everyday Life (Delhi, India: Sarai— The New Media Initiative; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Society for Old and New Media, 2002) pp. 243–248.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" page="7" column="2">15. Soddu first adopted the term metadesign in his book Città Aleatorie (Milan, Italy: Masson Editore, 1989). Later, he started to substitute the term argenic</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">design for metadesign. The Generative Art conference, which he has organized annually since 1998, gathers artists and designers who adopt and question metadesign from a generative perspective; see &lt;http:// www.generativeart.com&gt;. 16. See De Kerckhove [4] and [5].</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="7" column="2">17. See in particular Lab[au], “MetaDeSign: The Set- ting of a Discipline,” in l’ARCA, No. 178 (February 2003) pp. 2–5. See also &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.lab-au.com" id="109">http://www.lab-au.com</ext-link>&gt;. 18. See [3].</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" page="7" column="2">19. See in particular Gerhard Fischer and Elisa Giaccardi, “Meta-Design: A Framework for the Future of End User Development,” in H. Lieberman et al., eds., End User Development: Empowering People to Flex- ibly Employ Advanced Information and Communication Technology (Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer Aca- demic Publishers, in press).</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" page="7" column="2">20. For an understanding of the set of concerns sur- rounding the development of a metadesign framework at L3D, see in particular Gerhard Fischer, “Social Creativity, Symmetry of Ignorance and Meta- Design,” in Linda Candy and Ernest Edmonds, eds., Proceedings of the Third Conference on Creativity &amp; Cog- nition (New York, NY: ACM Press, 1999) pp. 116–123; see also Ernesto Arias et al., “Transcending the In-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">dividual Human Mind: Creating Shared Under- standing through Collaborative Design,” in J. Carroll, ed., Human Computer Interaction in the New Millennium (New York, NY: ACM Press; Boston, MA: Addison- Wesley, 2001) pp. 347–372.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" page="7" column="2">21. See Elisa Giaccardi and Gerhard Fischer, “Cre- ativity and Evolution: A Metadesign Perspective,” in the Sixth International Conference of the European Academy of Design (EAD06) on Design, System, Evolution (Bremen, Germany: University of the Arts, 29–31 March 2005).</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="116" page="7" column="2">22. From a metadesign perspective, seeding is a participatory and evolutionary technique that allows the modification of a system and its adaptation to users’ emerging needs. The SER Process Model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 6</xref>) ar- ticulates this technique in three different stages (Seeding, Evolutionary Growth, Reseeding).</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" page="7" column="3">23. For a more detailed description of the design issues raised by metadesign, see Elisa Giaccardi, Prin- ciples of Metadesign: Processes and Levels of Co-Creation in the New Design Space, Ph.D. diss. (Plymouth, U.K.: CAiiA-STAR, University of Plymouth, 2004).</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="118" page="7" column="3">24. For a more detailed description of the design space entailed by metadesign, see Giaccardi [23].</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="119" page="7" column="3">25. Here, “reflexive” is used to indicate not only the critical attitude of reflecting upon oneself, but also the process of transformation that such a behavior involves.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" page="7" column="3">26. Yevgeny N. Lazarev, “The Art of Metadesign,” Leonardo 27, No. 5, 423–425 (1994) p. 425.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" page="7" column="3">27. Margot Lovejoy, Postmodern Currents: Art and Artists in the Age of Electronic Media, 2nd Ed. (Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1997). 28. See [3].</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="123" page="7" column="3">29. Roy Ascott, “The A-Z of Interactive Arts,” Leonardo Electronic Almanac 3, No. 9 (September 1995), &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mitpress2.mit.edu/e-journals/LEA/TEXT/" id="122">http://mitpress2.mit.edu/e-journals/LEA/TEXT/</ext-link> Vol_3/lea_v3_n09.txt&gt;.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="124" page="7" column="3">30. Herbert A. Simon, The Sciences and the Artificial (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1969).</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" page="7" column="3">31. Here I mean “making” in general—that is, any human activity where some kind of production is im- plied.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="126" page="7" column="3">32. Richard Buchanan and Victor Margolin, eds., Dis- covering Design: Explorations in Design Studies (Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press, 1995).</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="127" page="7" column="3">33. Herbert A. Simon, The Sciences and the Artificial, 3rd Rev. Version (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1996).</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="128" confidence="possible" page="7" column="3">Glossary</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="7" column="3">co-creation—the emergent process of constructing and sharing intelligent and meaningful activities, expressed by a socio-technical environment conceptu- alized as a complex system. co-evolution—the evolution of a socio-technical environment conceived as a living entity, by which changes of each participant in the interaction process (either the software or the human subjects, variously organized) influence the evolution of the other participants. In metadesign, co-evolution can occur by either gradual or disruptive adaptation. design—generally conceived as the conception and planning of the artificial (or the invented) as a nor- mative form of science (“how things ought to be”) in contrast to natural sciences (“how things are”) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="129" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>]. Design is better defined today as an inquiry and experimentation in the activity of “making” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="130" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>]. That is, design is a humanistic enterprise in which the subject matter is not fixed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="131" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>] and is meant to allow us to envision possibilities and elaborate them (“how things might be”) in order to enable people to experience the world in more and richer ways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="132" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]. emergence—the stage of metadesign in which planning is superseded by participation and the open processes of co-evolution and co-creation. The pro- motion of tacit knowledge and situated action—and consequently new forms of creativity and sociabil- ity—is crucial at this stage. evolutionary design—evolutionary design can be either generative or interactive—that is, it can rely on either the absolute autonomy of the software or the human guidance of the process; the further development of an initial “seed” (or a structure created by the seed) to adapt it to needs that were not accounted for in the original design. It aims at the best possible solutions through cycles of either parameterization or exploration. generative design—the design of a piece of software (“seed”) capable of autonomously generating design proposals by notation and execution. It allows the</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="134" page="7" column="3">348</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="135" page="7" column="3">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">generation of endless variations recognizable as belonging to the same designer. metadesign—conceived as the design of a “metapro- ject,” metadesign shares with generative and evolutionary design the focus on the design of initial conditions or “seeds.” In this sense, it methodolog- ically comprises both generative and evolutionary design. However, metadesign transcends them by in- corporating the principles of participation and emergence and by changing the way in which systems and content are designed (see co-evolution and co-creation).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="137" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Leonardo Codex Sforza Monument ($5,000 and above) (The Bronze Horse) The California Tamarack Foundation ($1,000 to $4,999) College of Extended Learning, Martin Anderson San Francisco State University Art Science Research Lab CRSS Architects Lisa Bornstein The Ford Foundation Donna Cox Interval Research Corporation Creative Disturbance Roger Malina Char Davies The Malina Trust The Daniel Langlois Foundation Rockefeller Foundation Penny Finnie The San Francisco Art Institute Steve Forestieri Al Smith Intel Corporation U.S. National Endowment for the Arts Marjorie Malina Christine Malina-Maxwell Sonya Rapoport Itsuo Sakane School of the Art Institute of Chicago Martin Segal Makepeace Tsao Rhode Island School of Design University of Plymouth, U.K. University of Texas at Dallas Angel ($249 and under) Steve Dietz Aaron Alpar Augus Dorbie Charles Ames Hubert Duprat Art Science Collaborations Inc. Elmer Duncan (ASCI) Michele Emmer Roy Ascott Lawrence Fane Yasuhiro Asoo William Fawley Bret Battey Theodosia Ferguson Marc Battier John Fobes Mark and Lauren Beam Alan &amp; Mickey Friedman Patricia Bentson Ryozo Fujii Timothy Binkley David Gamper Anna Campbell Bliss Jonathan &amp; Donna R. Gennick Deborah Branton Ken Goldberg Bettina Brendel Pamela Grant-Ryan Robert A. Brown Michael Joaquin Grey Ronald Brown Karen Guzak Willi Bruns Isabel Hayden Leif Brush Craig Harris Annick Bureaud Linda Dalrymple Henderson David Carrier Margaret Hermann Rosa Casarez-Levison Doris Herrick Katherine Casida Lynn Hershman Joel Chadabe Estate of Dick Higgins Richard Clar Anthony Hill Computer Art Studio/Gunter Schulz Toshiyuki Hiruma Holly Crawford Gerald Holton Ivo Cristante Hungarian University Elizabeth Crumley of Crafts &amp; Design Mary &amp; Michael Cunningam Amy Ione Danish Film Festival Raymond Jurgens Bob Davis Eduardo Kac Goery Delacote Robert Kadesch Lily Diaz Melinda Klayman Emma Lou Diemer Ken Knowlton</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Manuscript received 7 June 2004. Elisa Giaccardi has a background that brings together humanities, media and design. An abstract of her doctoral dissertation is avail- able on LABS at: &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://leonardolabs" id="138">http://leonardolabs</ext-link>. pomona.edu/&gt;. She is currently a Research As- sociate at the Center for LifeLong Learning and Design (L3D), University of Colorado at Boulder. In her work, Giaccardi combines in- A WORD OF THANKS Thanks to Our Supporters La Gioconda (Mona Lisa) ($500 to $999) Lars Ole Belhage James D. Burke Una Dora Copley Arana Greenberg Rosemary Jackson Alan Malina Michael Punt Isabel Maxwell Merrill Lynch Foundation Emanuel Nadler Sam Okoshken Joel Silverman Zdenek Kocib Kenji Kohiyama Thomas Kostusiak Kathleen Laziza Levi Family Foundation Guy Levrier Carl Machover William Marchant Delle Maxwell Elliot Mazer Kevin Meehan Minneapolis College of Art &amp; Design Mit Mitropoulos Moët Hennessy-Louis Vuitton Jacques Mandelbrojt Jason Monberg Roger Mulkey Frieder Nake Barbara Nessim Alex Nicoloff Greg Niemeyer Hiroshi Ninomiya Jack Ox Elaine Petschek Anne Brooks Pfister Victor A. Pickett Sheila Pinkel Ann Pizzorusso Frank Popper Herbert &amp; Joan Webster Price Patric Prince Wolf Rainer Harry Rand Trudy Reagan</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140" confidence="possible" page="8" column="3">teraction design, media arts and cultural management. She has lectured and published on several occasions and she is a member of editorial boards and committees for MIT Press, ACM and The European Journal of Higher Arts Education. Her interdisciplinary research in the convergence of communication technologies and the humanities was awarded the European grant “Ideas for the Future” by Fon- dazione Eni Enrico Mattei in 2001.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" confidence="possible" page="8" column="3">Flying Machine ($250 to $499) Ray Bradbury George Gessert Oliver Grau Curtis Karnow Ed Payne and Liss Fain Mark Resch Eric Roll Sonia Sheridan Christian Simm Darlene Tong Jonathan Willard Barbara Lee Williams Beverly Reiser Ron Rocco David Rosenboom Peter Rudolfi Mr. and Mrs. Robert Russett Colin Sanderson Piero Scaruffi Patricia Search Edward Shanken Allan Shields Gregory C. Shubin Leonard Shlain Joel Slayton John Slorp Kirill Sokolov Rejane Spitz Anait Stephens Robert Strizich The Sun Microsystems Foundation, Inc. Tamiko Thiel Rodrigo B. Toledo Heinz Trauboth Mark Tribe Joan Truckenbrod Roman Verostko Alexandre Vitkine Natalie &amp; Mark Whitson Alan Thompson &amp; Sharon A. Widmayer Richard A. Wilson Stephen Wilson Gary Zellerbach Robert Zimmerman</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="142" page="8" column="3">Giaccardi, Metadesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="143" page="8" column="3">349</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
