<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>f7962b2e06b7d9c8bc5c3e21a65997ecf4c0483eaa8948bf5ef2fe65eabc9026</job>
    <base_name>62cy</base_name>
    <doi>10.1207/s15327884mca0501_3</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library] On: 02 October 2013, At: 06:52 Publisher: Routledge Informa Ltd Registered in England and Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered office: Mortimer House, 37-41 Mortimer Street, London W1T 3JH, UK</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">Mind, Culture, and Activity Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/hmca20" id="2">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/hmca20</ext-link></region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx4">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62cy.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">The Concept of Breakdown in Heidegger, Leont'ev, and Dewey and Its Implications for Education</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Timothy Koschmann</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Kari Kuutti</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Larry Hickman Published online: 10 Jun 2010.</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="9">To</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">cite this article:</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="12" confidence="possible">Timothy Koschmann , Kari Kuutti &amp; Larry Hickman (1998) The Concept of Breakdown in Heidegger, Leont'ev, and Dewey and Its Implications for Education, Mind, Culture, and Activity, 5:1, 25-41, DOI: 10.1207/s15327884mca0501_3 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1207/s15327884mca0501_3" id="11">http://dx.doi.org/10.1207/s15327884mca0501_3</ext-link></abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="13">To</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="14">link to this article:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible">PLEASE SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">views the relied and</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="17">or</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="19">Taylor &amp; Francis makes every effort to ensure the accuracy of all the information (the “Content”) contained in the publications on our platform. However, Taylor &amp; Francis, our agents, and our licensors make no representations or warranties whatsoever as to the accuracy, completeness, or suitability for any purpose of the Content. Any opinions and expressed in this publication are the opinions and views of the authors, and are not views of or endorsed by Taylor &amp; Francis. The accuracy of the Content should not be upon and should be independently verified with primary sources of information. Taylor Francis shall not be liable for any losses, actions, claims, proceedings, demands, costs, expenses, damages, and other liabilities whatsoever or howsoever caused arising directly indirectly in connection with, in relation to or arising out of the use of the Content. article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, distribution in any form to anyone is expressly forbidden. Terms &amp; Conditions of access use can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-conditions" id="18">http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-conditions</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="20">This or or and</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="21">MIND, CULTURE, AND ACTIVITY, 5(1), 25-41 Copyright O 1998, Regents of the University of California on behalf of the Laboratory of Comparative Human Cognition</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">The Concept of Breakdown in Heidegger, Leont'ev, and Dewey and Its Implications for Education</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible">Timothy</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="24">Koschmann Institute of Cognitive Science University of Colorado at Boulder</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible">Kuutti</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="26">Kari Department of Information Processing Science University of Oulu, Finland</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" confidence="possible">Hickman</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28">Larry Centerfor Dewey Studies Southern Illinois University</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible">Heidegger, Leont'ev, and Dewey held surprisingly similar views on the role of breakdown or failure as a means of revealing the nature of the world around us. For Heidegger, the resources by which we conduct our day-to-day activities do not usually require our conscious awareness. If our ongoing activity is blocked, however, this "transparency of equipment" is dispelled, forcing a more deliberate mode of action. Leont'ev's development of breakdown hinges on the analytic distinction he made amongdctivities,Actions, and Operations. When the necessary conditions for an Operation are absent, the chain of Operations becomes transformed ("unfolded") back into a sequence of independent Actions. Dewey's notion of breakdown is related to his views on sensory excitation, stimulus and response, and the habit-formation function in the lives of complex organisms. Implications of these three models for learning and instruction are developed.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="30">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44">Heidegger, the German phenomenologist; Leont'ev, the Russian psychologist; and Dewey, the American philosopher-psychologist-educator, seemed to hold surprisingly convergent views on the role of breakdown or failure as a means of revealing the nature of the world around us. Although they were contemporaries, their work arose from quite different intellectual traditions and they operated within different professional worlds. Heidegger was a continental philosopher working within the phenomenological tradition of his mentor, Edmund Husserl. Leont'ev, a founding member of the "Kharkov school" ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Valsiner, 1988</xref>), devoted his career to the development of a new approach to psychological research based on Marxist principles, and in the process, he helped to establish what has come to be known as the Theory of Activity. Dewey was a prominent member of the American Pragmatist school of philosophy and wrote prolifically on issues related to education and psychology.<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> We are not, of course, the first to attempt to link the contributions of these three authors (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus, 1991</xref> ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Haugeland, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Rorty, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Tolman &amp; Piekkola, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Toulmin, 1988</xref>).' We are interested here, however, in a particular connection-namely, the development of the concept of breakdown within their respective bodies of work. The term breakdown is used in a variety of ways in day-to-day parlance (e.g., the breakdown of a mechanical device, the breakdown of social order, suffering a nervous breakdown). In this article, however, we use it in a special sense to refer to a disruption in the normal functioning of things forcing the individual to adopt a more reflective or deliberative stance toward ongoing activity. We begin by describing the treatment of breakdown in the works of the three authors, comparing and contrasting their descriptions. We then discuss some implications of these three conceptualizations of breakdown for learning and instruction.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="33">Requests for reprints should be addressed to Timothy Koschmann, Department of Computer Science, University of</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="35">Colorado at Boulder, Campus Box 430, Boulder, CO 80309. E-mail: <email id="34">tdk@cs.colorado.edu</email></outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx36">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62cy.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="37">26</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="38">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="3" column="1">HEIDEGGER: BREAKDOWN AND</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="46" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">DASElN</h2>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="47" page="3" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="3" column="1">This analysis draws on the early writings of Heidegger and, in particular, on Division I of Being and Time (195311962). The nature of Heidegger's project in writing Being and Time was to explicate the structure of the commonsensical background shared by all knowing beings. His goal was to provide a phenomenological account of being-in-the-world, what he termed Dasein. Heidegger himself did not use the term breakdown in his writing, although the term is often associated with his work (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Guignon, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Suchman, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Winograd &amp; Flores, 1986</xref>). He tended instead toward more prolix neologisms, such as "a deficiency in our having-to-do with the world concernfully" (einer Defzienz des besorgenden Zu-tun-habens mit der Welt; p. 61/88).' Breakdown is critically important in Heidegger's account because of what it reveals of the world. In ordinary use, the resources3 (e.g., tools, implements, appliances) with which we conduct our day-to-day activities do not usually require (or attract) our conscious awareness. Heidegger indicated, however, that when ongoing, nonreflective practice is interrupted, these equipmental aspects of the world become "lit up" (p. 721102) or brought "into view" (p. 741104). Resources for Heidegger can present themselves in different modes of being-that is to say, they can assume different states with respect to our ongoing activity. The status of an entity can, in turn, affect the nature of our activity and our understanding of the object in use. These different modes are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>, adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus (1991)</xref>. Two important observations can be made with respect to this table: First, breakdown for Heidegger is a graded rather than an all-or-nothing phenomenon, and second, it is the degree of breakdown that determines the status of an entity with respect to our purposes. Heidegger designated resources as "ready-to-hand" (Zuhandenheit; p. 69/98) when we are fully engaged in an activity and the equipment and materials needed for sustaining that activity are</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">'indeed, in some cases the authors themselves recognized such links. Leont'ev (1981), for example, made reference to the writings of both Heidegger and Dewey. Dewey also apparently perceived some parallels between his own work and that of Heidegger. When first heruing a description of Sein und Zeit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Heidegger, 1953</xref>), Dewey was quoted as observing that "it sounded as if a German peasant were trying to render p&amp;s of Experience and Nature into his daily idiom" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Hook, 1962</xref>, p. 6). he he convention is followed here of specifying the page number for quotations in Sein und Zeit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Heidegger, 1953</xref>), followed by the corresponding page number in the Macquarrie and Robinson translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Heidegger, 1962</xref>).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="60" page="3" column="1">' ~ e i d e ~ used ~e r the term das Zeug, usually translated as "equipment."</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx61">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62cy.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="62" page="4" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="4" column="1">27</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="64" page="4" column="1">TABLE 1</caption>
            <content>
              <h1 class="table"> Heidegger's Modes of Being and Understanding</h1>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="4">
                <thead class="table">
                  <tr class="table">
                    <th class="table"> Status of Entity</th>
                    <th class="table"> Nature of Activity or Stance</th>
                    <th class="table"> Mode of Understanding</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> ready-to-hand</td>
                    <td class="table"> absorbed, coping</td>
                    <td class="table"> primary</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> (Zuhandenheit)</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> un-ready-to-hand</td>
                    <td class="table"> deliberating</td>
                    <td class="table"> interpretive</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> (Unzuhandenheit)</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> present-at-hand</td>
                    <td class="table"> reflection</td>
                    <td class="table"> theoretical</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> (Vorhandenheit)</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> purely present-at-hand</td>
                    <td class="table"> pure contemplation</td>
                    <td class="table"> abstract</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> (pure Vorhandenheit)</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> - -</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Note. From Being-in-the-world:</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> A Commentary on Heidegger's Being</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> and Time (p. 210), by H.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> 1991, Cambridge, MA: MIT</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> Press. Copyright 1991 by MIT Press. Adapted</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> with permission.</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="65" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Heidegger's Modes of Being and Understanding</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="66" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Status of Entity Nature of Activity or Stance Mode of Understanding</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="68" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">ready-to-hand absorbed, coping primary (Zuhandenheit) un-ready-to-hand deliberating interpretive (Unzuhandenheit) present-at-hand reflection theoretical (Vorhandenheit) purely present-at-hand pure contemplation abstract (pure Vorhandenheit) - Note. From Being-in-the-world: A Commentary on Heidegger's Being and Time (p. 210), by H. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus, 1991</xref>, Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. Copyright 1991 by MIT Press. Adapted with permission.</region>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="69" page="4" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="4" column="1">readily available. Our stance with respect to the activity (what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus, 1991</xref>, p. 51, termed "comportment") can be described as absorbed coping. In this situation, we observe the object not as a thing in itself, but rather as a means to some end. Heidegger used the example of a skilled carpenter using a hammer. The carpenter does not recite in her or his mind, "Strike the nail with the hammer," and the carpenter does not necessarily reflect on the properties of the object that make it a hammer. Instead, the hammer is applied directly to the task at hand in what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus (1991)</xref> referred to as "the transparency of equipment7'(p. 64). As Heidegger (195311962) said, "The peculiarity of what is proximally ready-to-hand is that, in its readiness-to-hand, it must, as it were, withdraw in order to be ready-to-hand quite authentically" (p. 69/99). For Heidegger, this is the primary way in which things are known-namely, nonreflectively-while we are engaged in concernful activity. When equipment fails, when ongoing activity is disrupted, our stance may change. Consider, for example, when a carpenter reaches for a particular hammer, but the hammer is not there. Heidegger referred to this condition as "conspicuousness" (Auffalligkeit; p. 74/104), in that the hammer now becomes conspicuous in its absence. It is clear, however, that Heidegger did not consider this to be a true form of breakdown. If the carpenter is able to proceed with the task at hand, perhaps by using a different hammer, the problem is so quickly redressed that no change occurs in the nature of the activity itself or in the carpenter's understanding of the activity. On the other hand, the worker's hammer could be availablebut still be found to be unusable if, for example, the head worked its way loose or the handle were broken. Under these circumstances, the unusability of the tool may be experienced as "obstinacy" (Aufsassigkeit; p. 741104). Finally, if the hammer cannot be located at all, other equipment that is ready-to-hand but inappropriate or otherwiseunusable may now be experienced as obstructive or, as Heidegger described it, it acquires the property of "obstrusiveness" (Aufdringlichkeit; p. 741104). To resume working, the carpenter must attend to the missing hammer and develop a plan for resolving its absence. The activity, therefore, becomes deliberate and the carpenter's understanding interpretive. Heidegger said the environment is brought "closer in circumspective deliberation" (p. 3591410). In this situation, Heidegger would describe the missing hammer as "present-at-hand" (Vorhandenheit, p. 73/103).~ Equipment that is present-at-hand can be considered in an entirely theoretical<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> way. Predicates can be attached to the object, as in "this hammer is heavy" or "this hammer is broken." The meaning of these statements is still bound to the current context-that is, to the referent of the this-but we relate to the hammer (and the situation) in a different way. Heidegger (195311962) wrote</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="74" page="4" column="1">4~ranslated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus (1991)</xref> as "occurent" (p. xi).</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx75">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62cy.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="76" page="5" column="1">28</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="77" page="5" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">In one's current using and manipulating, the concernful circumscription that does this surveying, brings the ready-to-hand closer to Dasein, and does so by interpreting what has been sighted. This specific way of bringing the object of concern close by interpreting it circumspectively, we call "deliberating" (Uberlegung). The scheme peculiar to this is the 'if-then'; if this or that, for instance, is to be produced, put to use, or averted, then some ways and means, circumstances,or opportunities will be needed. (p. 3591410)</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="5" column="1">In this way, aspects of the situation that were previously tacit, such as the causal connections among actions and goals, now become explicit. Thus, the disruption of the "habitual, standard, [and] comfortable" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Winograd &amp; Flores, 1986</xref>) may make visible aspects of the situation that might otherwise elude awareness, features that "often are not articulated, but are discovered only in the breach" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Suchman, 1987</xref>, p. 163). Heidegger (195311962) presented yet another mode of being even further detached from the ongoing activity that he referred to as "pure presence-at-hand" or "pure occurentness" (pure Vorhandenheit; p. 731103). In this mode, it is possible to contemplate concepts in an entirely abstract way, independent of any context. As he described it, however, it is only a transient state of affairs: "Pure presence-at-hand announces itself in such equipment, but only to withdraw to the readiness-to-hand of something we find when we put it back into repair" (p. 731103). Concepts understood in this abstract and decontextualized way are, for Heidegger, the stuff of formal logics and calculi. It is important to note, in marked contrast to the traditions of Western philosophy, that Heidegger considered this a derivative mode of understanding relative to the ontologically more primitive "prepredicative" (Guignon, 1983,p. 131)form of knowing found in unreflective practice.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="83" page="5" column="1">LEONT'EV: ACTIVITY THEORY AND BREAKDOWN</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="84" page="5" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" page="5" column="1">Like Heidegger, Leont'ev did not actually use the term breakdown, and there is no independent corresponding concept in Activity Theory. There is, however, a corresponding mechanism discussable and explainable within a broader system of concepts, related to the hierarchical levels of activities and movements between these levels. Leont'ev (197511978) was the first to use the analytical distinction of three qualitatively different hierarchical levels: Activities (dejatel'nosti), Actions (dejstvja), and Operations (operatsii). As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>, an Activity is composed of Actions or chains of Actions, which in turn consist of Operations. The Action level (or, actually, set of levels) is where the focus of psychology has typically been-in conscious, goal-directed Actions. Often the goal of an Action is subordinated to some larger goal, and so on. When we move upward in the sequence, we finally meet a goal that is self-sufficient, not subordinated to anything else. This uppermost level is called an Activity, and the corresponding "goal" is called either the object or motive of the Activity, depending on its purpose. An Activity, therefore, is the minimal meaningful context to understand individual Actions belonging to it. This approach to understanding human activity stands in stark contrast to the less molar units of analysis traditionally applied in psychological studies and represents one<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> of the major contributionsof this tradition. Leont'ev (197511978) provided an example of primitive hunters who divide into two groups: catchers and bush-beaters who frighten the game toward them. When compared with the motive of hunting-to catch the game to get food and clothing material-the Actions of the bush-beaters may seem irrational; they can be understood only as a part of the larger system of the hunting Activity. One Activity may be realized using different Actions, depending on the situation. On the other hand, one and the same Action can belong to different Activities, in which case the different objects and motives of Activities will cause the Action to have a different personal sense for the individual in the context of each Activity. The Action of beating bushes during the hunting will have adifferent meaning if it belongs to the Activity of hunting, as in the previous example, than if it belongs to the Activity of animal preservationists seeking to frighten the prey away from the hunters-even if their actions are exactly the same. The expression "motive of an Activity" should not be confused or directly related to the motives of individuals participating in the Activity. The motive of an Activity refers to both the potentiality to transform the object of the Activity and the ability of the outcome to fulfill some need of at least some members of the community participating in the Activity. How this translates into individual motives depends very much on the way in which the Activity is organized. If we go downward in subordinated Actions, the goals must become smaller and smaller. Eventually we reach a level in which the Actions are no longer performed consciously; that level, and levels below that, are called Operations. Operations, therefore, lack conscious goals but are instead triggered by conditions faced during an Action. They are employed in adapting an Action to actual conditions. Finally, Operations are the lowest hierarchical level of activity. They are specific ways to carry out Actions under actual conditions. There are two kinds of Operations: adaptive and conscious. Adaptive Operations are formed in unconscious adaptation to objective conditions of a given situation;they are involuntary, initially unconscious, and rigid (e.g., bodily movements needed for balancing on a bicycle). Conscious Operations originate as Actions that have been transformed in the course of learning. Using a term borrowed from Gal'perin, Leont'ev (197211974) referred to conscious Actions possessing an "orienting basis" (p. 106127).~ Before it is performed, conscious Action is typically planned according to a model of the situational circumstances. The better the model, the more successful the Action. Thus, models and plans are not rigid and accurate descriptions of the execution steps, but always incomplete and tentative, resources in the sense of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Suchman (1987)</xref>. When a model for a conscious Action is good enough, the Action has been</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx87">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62cy.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="88" page="6" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="89" page="6" column="1">29</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="90" page="6" column="1">FIGURE 1</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="91" page="6" column="1">Activity - ObjecVMotive 4 v 4 f Action - Goal 4 v 4t Hienrchical levels of an activity after Leont'ev (197211974). Operation - Conditions</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="92" page="6" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">5 ~ continue e the convention of specifying the page number in the original text (either Leont'ev, 1972, or Leont'ev, 1975) followed by the page number in the English translation (i.e., Leont'ev, 1974, or Leont'ev, 1978, respectively).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx96">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62cy.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="97" page="7" column="1">30</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="98" page="7" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" page="7" column="1">practiced long enough, and the situation is sufficiently stable, the Action loses its "orienting basis" and becomes "routini~ed"~ into an Operation (Leont'ev, 197211974). Thus, to become skilled at something entails developing a set of articulated Operations. The process of "routinization" of independent Operations and the subsequent broadening scope of associated Actions are fundamental features of human development. Leont'ev (197511978) discussed learning to drive using a manual gearbox as an example of ActionIOperation dynamics. At the beginning, every step in the process (i.e., ease the gas pedal, push the clutch pedal, move the gear lever to a new position, release the clutch, depress gas pedal) is aconscious Action that requires planning, sequencing, and decisions. As these conscious Actions become routinized, however, the planning and decision making eventually fade away, resulting in a smoothly integrated Action. Ultimately, this gear-changing Action becomes an embedded Operation in more complex driving Actions such as cornering, changing lanes, and ascending hills. This account provides a background to our discussion of the concept of breakdown within Activity Theory. In skilled practice, there are chains of Operations to every Action, each Operation establishing the conditions for the one that follows. However, it is possible to reverse this process of routinization. Leont'ev (197211974) stated, "in the course of attaining a discerned common goal, intermediate goals can also be discerned [italics added] that in effect divide unitary Action into a series of separate, sequential Actions" (p. 107128). He observed that this typically occurs, "when conditions impede an Action's execution through previously formed ~ ~ e r a t i o n s Under ."~ such circumstances, previously formed Operations revert to individual Actions and recover their orienting basis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Kaptelinin, 1996</xref>). For instance, in the gear-changing example, the operator may be forced to resort to conscious Action in the event that the engine suddenly begins to noticeably labor. Leont'ev's mechanism for the decomposition of fluidly articulated Operations into individual Actions with consciously discerned goals in some ways resembles Heidegger's description of a disruption of ongoing activity precipitating reflective action. Leont'ev's model of breakdown can be easily extended to the domain of tool use by the recognition that to be skilled in using a tool, in his view, simply means that one has established an appropriate set of tool-using Operations. With such a set of well-learned Operations, a tool becomes transparent in the work and all attention can be focused on the object of Actions. But, from the perspective of Activity Theory, this transparency is not the basic and fundamental mode, because all Operations were initially conscious Actions that had been routinized through a process (sometimes slow and painful) of practice and learning. Ontogenetically, therefore, the level of conscious action is primary for Leont'ev. On the</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="101" page="7" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="102" page="7" column="1">'This process is referred to as "technization" (p. 66) in Activity, Consciousness and Personality (Leont'ev, 1978). 7 ~ h complete e passage, which appeared both in Leont'ev (1972) and in chapter 3 of Leont'ev (1975), was as follows:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">v</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="104" page="7" column="1">Tak, v hode dostizeniya vydelyavshseisya obshei tseli mozet proishodit' vydelenie promezutocnyh tselei, v rezultate cego tselostnoe deistvie drobitsya na ryad otdelnyh posledovatelnyh dejstvij; eto osobenno harakterno dlya slucayev, kogda dejstvie protekaet usioviyah, zatrudnyayushih ego vypolnenie s pomoshs'yu uze sfomi- rovavshsihsya operacij. (pp. 107 &amp; 110, respectively).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">In this passage, there are two words-the adjective vydelyuvshseisyu and the noun vydelenie-that share the Russian stem vy-del. The verb vydeljat can carry different meanings, depending on context. Possible translations include "discern," "distinguish," "select," or "separate." The noun vydelenie, as a consequence, can in some circumstances refer to the product of extracting a chemical material from a mixture. Here, it seems to be used more in the sense of "the thing discerned" or "the thing isolated." Word constructions based on the vy-del stem appear frequently in the writings of Leont'ev.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx106">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62cy.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="8" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="8" column="1">31</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="109" page="8" column="1">other hand, in practice our Actions build on the foundation of existing Operations and cannot take place without them. Thus, Actions and Operations are tightly interwoven.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="110" page="8" column="1">JOHN DEWEY ON BREAKDOWN</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="111" page="8" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" page="8" column="1">Dewey thought that one of the most important implications of the work of Darwin was the overthrow of the Cartesian assumption of a radical split between an experiencing individual and an objectively experienced world. After Darwin, organisms were understood as parts of living environments and as evolving together with their environments. What the Cartesian modernists had sharply separated into "internal" and "external" with respect to an organism, Dewey regarded as aspects or factors of a total experienced situation as experienced by an organism. He conse- quently rejected the notion that a stimulus is something "outside" of an organism. He argued instead that a stimulus is "total state of the organism" ( ~ ~ 1 2 : 3 6 during )' some particular moment. He also thought it important to distinguish a stimulus from what he termed a sensory excitation. A sensory excitation occurs, for example, when a sleeping animal exhibits a sniffing response to some ambient scent. In such cases, the animal's response is strictly localized; olfactory sensors and facial muscles are involved, but the energy relations within the organism as a whole remain in a state of equilibrium. Because there is no disequilibration, there is no need for readjustment of the organic and environmental factors of the total experienced situation. In cases where an animal experiences global disequilibration, however, such as those in which hunger moves it to search for food, "stimulus-and-response" enters the picture. Disequilibration is expressed in terms of certain tensions among the organism's energy relations. Fatigue conflicts with pangs of hunger. Other organic tensions may also be present, and they may further complicate the state of disequilibration; fear of exposure, for example, may conflict with excitement of the hunt. In other words, the stimulus is not something external to the organism, but it is instead a function of the breakdown of a previously achieved balance among various organic energy relations, such as those that involve neuromuscular, autonomic, and digestive activities. In Dewey's view, behavioral processes that are undertaken as a part of efforts to return to a state of equilibrium are integrated in ways that are sequential; they involve, as he put it, more than just "a succession of isolated and independent units of excitation-reaction" (LW12:37). But within such sequential behavioral processes there also tend to be other, less extensive breakdowns that alter subordinate organic relations. A hunting animal, for example, may experience a rush of adrenaline as it narrows the distance to its prey. This, in turn, increases the hunter's heart rate and supplies the energy needed to allow it to strike. In all this, however, there is a more primary, global organic need to move toward the closure, or "consummation" of the process of reequilibration. Among nonhuman hunting animals, adjustive behavior is nonreflective, oriented toward short-term goals, and noninstrumental. Among humans, especially among those whose modes of life involve pastoral, agricultural, and industrial instrumentalities, goals tend to be longer term, adjustive activities tend to involve the use of symbols, and consummations tend to be experienced as richer and more secure. Dewey thought that consummations, regardless of whether they are proximate</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">'~tandxd references to John Dewey's work are to the critical edition, The Collected Works of John Dewey, edited by Boydston (1969-1991) and published as The Early Works (EW), The Middle Works (MW), and The Later Works (LW). These designations are followed by volume and page numbers.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx114">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62cy.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="115" page="9" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="116" page="9" column="1">32</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" page="9" column="1">or have to do with longer term ends-in-view, are felt as an aesthetic event in the life of the organism. Dewey's choice of the term consummation, which has explicit sensual and sexual connotations, was deliberate. As has already been indicated, Dewey thought that organic reequilibrat~on is sequential and not merely serial. It therefore plays an essential role in the formation of new habits. Even though an organism may experience repeated occurrences of excitation-response behavior, such behavior does not contribute to readjustment within a total experienced situation. For there to be readjustment, there must first have been a breakdown of organic energy relations. The consequent struggle for reequilibration is then the basis for reformation of habits. In such cases, closure or consummation involves a consolidation of past experiences with a view to their potential use in future breakdowns of relevant types. In the case of nonhuman animals, habit formation is "pushed from behind," unreflectively. Among humans, however, habit formation is "pulled from beyond" by reflectively constructed ends-in-view. For Dewey, life, especially life that involves complex organizational factors, is a continuing process of breakdown and reconstruction of habits. Dewey observed that humans often attempt to recover equilibrium in ways that do not promote growth. Faced with a breakdown, they often retreat to more primitive levels of behavioral response rather than moving forward onto behavioral plateaus that are more richly meaningful. Sometimes, he wrote, a problem</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">may be dealt with by retrogression to a lower level; life may continue because accommodation or integration of organism and environment is established on a plane which from the standpoint of prior habits involves deterioration: parasitism, chronic fixations, abandonment of "higher habits," accommodation to a less heterogeneous environment. (MW15:249)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" page="9" column="1">But when it occurs, growth is most often achieved by "inquiry," which Dewey defined as "the controlled or directed transformation of an indeterminate situation into one that is so determinate in its constituent distinctions and relations as to convert the elements of the original situation into a unifed whole" (LW12:108). He contrasted inquiry to other methods that have proven less successful in the recovery of equilibrium, such as chance, tenacity, authority, and appeal to a priori principles. For Dewey, then, breakdown or disequilibration is an observable fact of life. Like walking or chewing, its existence requires no explanation. But for humans, it is also the occasion for the formation of new habits, including enriched technologies of all sorts, with a view toward the promotion of growth and enriched experience.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="120" page="9" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="121" page="9" column="1">ARE THESE THREE CONCEPTIONS THE SAME?</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" page="9" column="1">All three authors provided descriptions of breakdown that offer models in which the disruption of ongoing, nonreflective activity results in a shift to a more deliberate form of practice, although their terminology varies (i.e., absorbed coping vs. circumspective deliberation for Heidegger, routinized operations and discernment of intermediate goals for Leont'ev, habitual responding vs. engagement in inquiry for Dewey). These differences, in part, reflect differences in the philosophical and historical traditions within which the authors wrote. Heidegger, writing as an existential phenomenologist, provided an account of breakdown as experienced by the individual (as opposed, e.g., to the institutional forms of breakdown that interested Dewey as a social psychologist). His treatment, therefore, is personal and emotive, <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> referring to inappropriate equipment as obstinate and obtrusive. Heidegger's account is also the most elaborate of the three presented here, describing breakdown not as a dichotomous state, but rather as a continuous and graded phenomenon. Leont'ev, working in a Marxist tradition of dialectical materialism, produced an account that focused instead on the organization of labor and practical activity. No less practical is Dewey's analysis, but instead of focusing on the activity per se, he focused on the effects of breakdown on the acting organism and, in the case of complex organisms, on the effects of the breakdown of social relations and institutions. His account is thus more "naturalistic" than Heidegger's. Beyond these contrasts were more fundamental differences in the methods they advocated and used within their work. Heidegger's phenomenological approach was introspective, relying on a particular form of reflection. Dewey, on the other hand, has been labeled a "social behaviorist" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Garrison, 1995</xref>, p. 721). Not to be confused with the methodological behaviorism of Watson and Skinner, social behaviorism constructs a "theory of meaning . .. in terms of a culture's language, tools, and forms of labor" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Garrison, 1995</xref>, p. 721). Used in this sense, this label might apply to Leont'ev as well, because a central theme of his later writings concerned the means by which consciousness and personality are shaped by engagement in productive activity. The authors also differed in regard to what they considered to be the primary or fundamental mode by which things are known. For Heidegger, the nonreflective and prelinguistic sort of knowing that occurs when engaged in concernful activity is the primary mode of understanding. He considered other, more abstract modes of understanding to be at best derivative. Leont'ev and Dewey, on the other hand, considered reflective knowledge to be ontogentically prior to the sort of prepredicative form of knowing described by Heidegger. For Leont'ev, conscious Operations come into being only when Actions become routinized through extensive practice; whereas Dewey considered reflective inquiry to be the primary mechanism by which new habits are acquired and learning occurs. Despite these differences, however, there are at least two common themes that emerge from these three accounts of breakdown. First, all three reflect an implicit rejection of dualistic ontologies based on distinctions of mind and body, of subjective and objective worlds. Both Heidegger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Guignon, 1983</xref>) and Dewey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Hickman, 1990</xref>) viewed Cartesian dualism as an aberration of modern philosophy. Heidegger (195311962) argued as follows:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx123">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62cy.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="124" page="10" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="125" page="10" column="1">33</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="131" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">When Dasein directs itself toward something and grasps it, it does not somehow first get out of an inner sphere in which it has been proximally encapsulated, but its primary kind of Being is such that it is always "outside" alongside entities which it encounters and which belong to a world already discovered. (p. 62/89)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="132" page="10" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140" page="10" column="1">Dewey was also careful to distance his own position from Cartesian and other "modernist" views that involve subject-object dualism (LW12:42-43; MW10:64-66). His example of breakdown (i.e., breakdown among the organic activities of the organism) was designed to demonstrate that analyses based on inner versus outer worlds do not adequately capture the means by which organisms adapt to environing conditions. Both Heidegger and Dewey viewed breakdown as a feature of the "situation" rather than an attribute of the organism or its environment. Consequently, although both allowed that the organism and environing conditions can be separated in reflective inquiry, they should be considered only logically distinct, and not ontologically so. At the level of consciousness of a situation, the situation is just what is experienced, whatever that experience may be. <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> Similarly, Leont'ev (197211974) sought to provide a foundation for psychology that eliminated "classical Cartesian-Lockean" (p. 103121) subject-object distinctions. Leont'ev (197511978) asserted that "Activity is a process in which mutual transfers between the poles 'subject-object' are accomplished" (p. 81/50). Leont'ev's dialectical materialism has its roots in Marx's philosophy and theory of production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Livergood, 1967</xref>). Leont'ev (197511978) quoted Marx as saying, "In production the personality is objectivized; in need the thing is subjectivized" (p. 81/50). In place of Cartesian dualism, Leont'ev proposed that psychology adopt a tripartite formula consisting of conditions, goals, and the means by which one is transformed into the other. He argued further that the distinction among internal-subjective worlds and external-objective worlds is an arbitrary one. He cited Vygotsky's studies on the internalization of interpsychological processes to demonstrate that the structure of Activity is the same, regardless of whether it is enacted on an intra- or interpsychological plane. As a result, the form of breakdown described by Leont'ev (i.e., the unraveling of an integrated chain of Operations) can also occur on either intra- or interpsychological planes. A second unifying theme among the three models is one of intentionality; that is to say, breakdown always occurs in the context of directed activity. Heidegger (195311962), in describing Dasein, said the following:<marker type="block"/> Concernful activity, for Heidegger, is action projected toward some goal or purpose.y he status of equipment within this context, therefore, is always relative to some goal. As Heidegger asserted, "Anything ready-to-hand is, at the worst, appropriate for some purposes [italics added] and inappropriate for others, and its 'properties' are, as it were, still bound up in these ways in which it is appropriate and inappropriate" (p. 831115). By the same token, Leont'ev (197211974) stressed the "object-directed" nature of an Activity (predrnetnuju dejatel'nost', p. 9611 I)."' He specified (197511978)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx134">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62cy.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="135" page="11" column="1">34</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="136" page="11" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="139" page="11" column="1">Its Being-in-the World has always dispersed itself or even split itself up in definite ways of Being-in. The multiplicity of these is indicated by the following examples: having to do with something, producing something, attending to something and looking after it, making use of something, giving something up and letting it go, undertaking, accomplishing, evincing, interrogating, considering, discussing, determining. . . . All these ways of Being-in have concern (Besorgen) as their kind of Being. (pp. 56-57/83)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="141" page="11" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="142" page="11" column="1">Only that content is actually recognized which appears before the subject as an object to which one action or another of his is directly aimed. In other words, in order that the perceived content be recognized, it is necessary that it occupy the structural place of a direct goal ofaction [italics added] in the subject's activity. This position is valid with respect to internal and external, practical and theoretical activity. (p. 248f153)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">'we might note here that Heidegger took pains to differentiate his notion of intentional comportment from Husserl's more mentalistic notions of intention (see "Heidegger's Critique of Intentionality" in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="143" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus, 1991</xref>). 10 This expression is a Russian rendering of the German gegenstiindliche Tatigkeit, which Leont'ev appropriated from Marx's first thesis on Feuerbach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Marx &amp; Engels, 1959</xref>, p. 533). It has been described as the key tounderstandingLeont'ev's psychological theory of Activity (Davydov, Zinchenko, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Talyzina, 1983</xref>).The expression is translated as "object-type activity" in Leont'ev's 1974 work (p. lo), "objective activity" in Leont'ev's 1978work (p. 50), and "object-related activity" in Davydov et al. (1983, p. 34), although "object-directed activity" may come closer to capturing the original meaning.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx147">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62cy.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="148" page="12" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="149" page="12" column="1">35</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="150" page="12" column="1">The process of inquiry, so central to Dewey's theories, is also always directed toward some goal. He wrote</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Organic interactionbecomes inquiry when existential consequences are anticipated; when environing conditions are examined with reference to their potentialities; [italics added] and when responsive activities are selected and ordered with reference to actualization of some of the potentialities, rather than others, in a final existential situation. (LWIO: 1 11)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" page="12" column="1">There are, however, also some fundamental differences among the three accounts of breakdown that should not be obscured. These differences can be most easily seen by considering the range of circumstances under which each of the models might be applied. The example of breakdown described by Dewey resulting from a physiological state of disequilibrium brought on by hunger could be considered a type of organismic breakdown. On the other hand, the examples of breakdown described by Heidegger and Leont'ev could be considered forms of equipmental breakdown. These two categories are clearly not exhaustive, however, and additional possibilities might include social breakdown (i.e., breakdown in relations with others), communicative breakdown (i.e., failure to achieve a shared understanding), and conceptual forms of breakdown involving violations of theories and hypotheses. Heidegger's model of breakdown could easily accommodate breakdown of an organismic variety-one might envision, for example, how certain bodily states (e.g., hunger, fatigue, injury) might interfere with absorbed performance and cause us to circumspectly consider aspects of our own body. Heidegger (195311962) also allowed for some forms of social breakdown. Although he observed, "Being towards Others [Sein zu Anderen] is ontologically different from Being towards Things which are present-at-hand [Sein zu vorhandenen Dingen]" (p. 1241162), a similar mechanism could be conceived in which properties of our relationship to those around us become visible as a result of a disruption of ongoing interaction. Heidegger also discussed a form of breakdown involving language:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Language is a totality of words-a totality in which discourse has a "worldly" Being of its own; and as an entity within-the-world, this totality thus becomes something which we may come across as ready-to-hand.Language can be broken up into word-Things which are present-at-hand. (p. 161f204)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="154" page="12" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" page="12" column="1">He described language here in an "instrumental" sense ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="155" class="deo:Reference">Guignon, 1983</xref>), that is as a tool for interpersonal intelligibility. It is experienced, for the most part, as ready-to-hand-that is, as a tool that is used unreflectively. When intelligibility breaks down, however, "word-Things" (Worterdinge) become objects of contemplation, resources that are present-at-hand. Heidegger's model, therefore, also accommodates communicative forms of breakdown. Problems arise, however, when we try to apply his model to what we have termed conceptual breakdown. Because the form of understanding that Heidegger sought to bring to light is of the prelinguistic, prepredicative sort found in absorbed coping, breakdown involving theories and ideas would seem to fall outside the scope of his analysis. The model of breakdown developed here for Leont'ev is a technical one and rather narrowly defined. It would be a mistake, however, to conclude by his choice of example that his analysis extended only to equipmental forms of breakdown. He saw Action-Operation transformations as fundamental to all human activity, from automatic and low-level functions such as walking to higher level functions such as conversing and thinking. A child (or a patient recovering from an<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> injury to the central nervous system), for example, must focus on and plan each individual step before walking becomes routinized. Leont'ev (1981) introduced the notion offunctional organs to describe the process by which advanced skills are developed. As he described them, functional organs consist of assemblies of internal and external resources integrated to perform a specific function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="160" class="deo:Reference">Kaptelinin, 1996</xref>). These resources might include sensory systems, specific motor units, tools and other technological artifacts, and conceptual entities. Because the process by which these special functional systems are developed is assumed to involve Action-Operation dynamics, the possibility exists for breakdown to occur when they are applied to practical tasks. Inasmuch as functional organs incorporate organismic, equipmental, and conceptual elements, Leont'ev's analysis can be seen as readily extending to each of these categories of breakdown. However, Leont'ev would likely view these not as isolated forms of breakdown, but rather as aspects of the breakdown of more molar, integrated functional units. Leont'ev's treatment of language provides a basis for also extending his analysis to communicative forms of breakdown. His focus on mediated action as a unit of analysis represented a point of departure from the earlier work of Vygotsky, who was more centrally concerned with word meaning and semiotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="161" class="deo:Reference">Wertsch, 1985</xref>). Language use for Leont'ev was just another form of Action, and as a result, his model by which linguistic skills are acquired resembles that by which one acquires a physical skill or learns to use a tool. Anyone who has tried to acquire a second language later in life is familiar with the way in which the production of a single utterance, even a single word, initially requires conscious attention and only becomes routine with extensive practice. Although in his research Leont'ev tended to focus on individual action, his theory was meant to extend to social and institutional action. Indeed, the very concept of action in Leont'ev's writing can be seen to develop from social activity. He (197511978) wrote</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx157">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62cy.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="158" page="13" column="1">36</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159" page="13" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">The development .. . of even the simplest technical division of work necessarily leads to isolation of, as it were, intermediate partial results, which in themselves cannot satisfy the worker's needs. Their needs are satisfied not by these "intermediate" results but by a share of the product of their collective activity, obtained by each of them through forms of the relationships binding them to one another, which develop in the process of work, that is, social relationships. (p. 103163)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="164" page="13" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" page="13" column="1">Individual actions, therefore, may be directed toward achieving some intermediate goal, but they can only be understood in the context of a broader and collectively pursued motive. Models of Activity in these more institutionalized settings were developed by later theorists (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Engestrom, 1987</xref>). Dewey viewed the acquisition of skills broadly and, as a consequence, developed a model of breakdown that is comparably broad. Because he, like Leont'ev, considered tools and media to be extensions of the organism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Hickman, 1990</xref>), his analysis applies not only to organismic forms of breakdown, but also to the equipmental forms discussed by the other two authors. Dewey's project in Logic: The Theory of Inquiry was to provide a "naturalistic theory of logic," one that could account for "the ways in which it is possible for the traits that differentiate deliberate inquiry to develop out of biological activities not marked by those traits" (LW12:31). Although, in its most general form, inquiry is shared with lower organisms, Dewey made it quite clear that he did not consider it lowly or rudimentary. This requirement for continuity means not only that his model can be applied to all of the categories of breakdown considered earlier (i.e., organismic, equip-<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> mental, social, communicative, conceptual), but also that he viewed the underlying process as being essentially the same in all cases. Inquiry is central to Dewey's epistemological perspective. In The Questfor Certainty, he argued that what we term thinking and knowledge are both inextricably tied to this ubiquitous process. With respect to the first point he asserted the following:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx168">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62cy.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="169" page="14" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="170" page="14" column="1">37</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="172" page="14" column="1">Thinking is the actual transition from the problematic to the secure, as far as that is intentionally guided. . .. Thinking is objectively discoverable as that mode of serial responsive behavior to a problematic situation in which transition to the relatively settled and clear is effected. (LW4:181)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">He went on to argue</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="174" page="14" column="1">Anything that may be called knowledge, or a known object, marks a question answered, a difficulty disposed of, a confusion cleared up, an inconsistency reduced to coherence, a perplexity mastered. .. . The concrete pathologies of belief, its failures and perversions, whether of defect or excess, spring from failure to observe and adhere to the principle that knowledge is the completed resolution of the inherently indeterminate or doubtful. (LW4: 181)</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="175" page="14" column="1">IMPLICATIONS FOR EDUCATION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="176" page="14" column="1">Just as Heidegger's model of breakdown is more elaboratethan the other two in recognizing various degrees of breakdown, Dewey's model is more developed in describing the process of recovery following breakdown. First, Dewey observed that resolution of complex problems typically occurs in stages. He wrote</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">a</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="178" page="14" column="1">When the problematic situation is such as to require extensive inquiries to effect its resolution, a series of interactions intervenes. Some observed facts point to an idea that stands for a possible solution. This idea evokes more observations. Some of the newly observed facts link up with those previously observed and are such to rule out other observed things with respect to their evidential function. The new order of facts suggests modified idea (or hypothesis) which occasions new observations whose result again determines a new order of facts, and so on until the existing order is both unified and complete. In the course of this serial process, the ideas that represent possible solutions are tested or "proved." (LW 12:117)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="179" page="14" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="187" page="14" column="1">Inquiry, therefore, consists of "a progressive determination of a problem" (LW 12:113). Second, Dewey emphasized that organism and environment are both altered through this interaction. He noted <marker type="block"/> Dewey elaborated this view of learning on several levels, including his publications for teachers such as How We Think (LWS), which presented a general method of problem solving; in more complex formulations,such as his discussions in Logic: The Theory of Inquiry (LW12) of the ways<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> in which generic and universal terms function in highly abstract reasoning; and in his later descript~ons of "transactional" inquiry." Dewey's treatment of these matters both grew out of and fed back into his philosophy of education. He thought that teaching could only be provocative and supportive, but never fully determinative of a learning outcome-that is, of a newly unified whole that consolidates the experience of the learner (a new habit). In effective teaching, such consummatory experiences on the part of a learner are often sources of surprise (breakdown) for a teacher. This, in Dewey's view, was one of the aspects of teaching that makes it also a learning experience. It is one of the tasks of a teacher to question and criticize the work of the learner in ways that create appropriate breakdowns of the learner's situation and lead the learner to initiate a sequence of inquiry. Such breakdowns must be appropriate in three senses: They must be relevant to the material at hand, they should not be so great as to create total frustration, and they should not be so minor as to merely support the status quo. Beyond simply inducing breakdown, however, Dewey argued that teachers must support learners in the inquiry process. He provided several examples in The School and Society (MW 1) that demonstrate the teacher's role in questioning, critiquing, and providing suggestions. These interventions are made all the more relevant to the learner by the preceding doubt and conflict. Dewey argued that lifelong learners of all sorts-in the arts, in the sciences, and in other areas as well-often purposely place themselves in situations where breakdown of existing habits is actively sought as a stimulus to further inquiry. In one of its aspects, this is what he called "the scientific temperament" (LW4:182). Although Dewey's rejection of rote learning as a method of education is well known, he also repudiated educators who identified themselves with his "progressive education," but who saw their role as little more than facilitators of the flowering of the child. He consistently argued that education requires active direction of children's instincts and capacities: The extremes of rote memorization and laissez-faire were in his view the twin evils of educational practice (LW5:3 19). Leont'ev's account, by which isolated Actions become assimilated (routinized)into more molar units, represents, in a simple sense, a model of habit formation. Conversely, the mechanism by which previously assimilated Actions recover their "orienting basis" can be seen as a form of habit disruption or unlearning. Beyond this, however, Leont'ev was clearly interested in what situations of breakdown could reveal about the process of learning. In a supplement to Activity, Consciousness, and Personality (197511978) entitled "Psychological Questions on the Consciousness of Learning," he proposed that understanding the object of the learner's conscious awareness is a central problem of pedagogical research. He observed that learning requires that which is being learned to occupy consciousness "in an appropriate place and at an appropriate time" (p. 2731168). By his analysis, the object of consciousness is that which occupies "the structural place of a direct goal of action in the subject's activity" (p. 2481153). He demonstrated how the motive of an individual's activity can be revealed by placing the individual in what Dewey would refer to as an "indeterminate7' situation and observing the means by which the individual endeavors to resolve</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="181" page="14" column="1">Inquiry, in settling the disturbed relation of organism-environment (which defines doubt) does not merely remove doubt by recurrence to a prior adaptive integration. It institutes new environing conditions that occasion new problems. What the organism learns during this process produces new powers that make new demands upon the environment. (LW12:41-42)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx183">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62cy.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="184" page="15" column="1">38</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="185" page="15" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="186" page="15" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="188" page="15" column="1">...</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="189" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">I 1 ~ e w e y writing , with Arthur F. Bentley in Knowing and the Known (LW16), distinguished between different levels of inquiry such as "inter-action," in which "thing is balanced against thing in causal interconnection" and the more sophisticated "trans-action," in which "systems are employed to deal with aspects and phases of action, without final attribution to 'elements' or other presumptively detachable or independent 'entities', or 'essences', or 'realities', and without isolation of presumptively detachable 'relations' from such detachable 'elements"' (LW16:lOl-102). They held the shift in physics from Newtonian mechanics to relativity to exemplify this distinction.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx190">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62cy.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="191" page="16" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="192" page="16" column="1">39</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="193" page="16" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="194" page="16" column="1">problem</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="199" page="16" column="1">the situation. Problematic situations, therefore, served Leont'ev and other Soviet developmental psychologists as an important tool for investigatingthe object of consciousness in learning and the process of learning generally.12 The mechanism of breakdown also has clear implications for pedagogical models subsequently developed within the conceptual framework of the Theory of Activity. Gal'perin (1969), for example, postulated three stages in the process by which external actions are internalized into mental operations, progressing from gross physical manipulation to audible verbalization and, finally, to "internal speech." In certain circumstances, however, this transformation may be disrupted, forcing the learner to return to an earlier stage. In Gal'perin's model of learning, therefore, breakdown serves to obstruct the process of internalization.In other models of learning, however, breakdown might also serve as a stimulus for learning. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Davydov (1982)</xref>, for example, developed a model of educational problem solving consisting of a number of "learning actions" (p. 42), one of which involved transforming a problematic situation into an example of a more general model. Opportunities for learning arise when the problem solver is unable to match the current problem to an existing model. In such circumstances, the application of previously learned abstract principles breaks down, suggesting the need to modify or augment the learner's available set of abstractions. Instances of breakdown appear, therefore, both in the inductive process of internalizing and integrating rudimentary skills and in the more deductive process of applying abstract principles. Heidegger himself discussed neither learning nor instruction in his explication of the process of breakdown, although his model had implications for both. His discussion of various modes of understanding, for example, is important for our understanding of how expertise is acquired and is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="196" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="197" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus and Dreyfus (1986)</xref> developed an account of advanced skill acquisition that is closely tied to these modes of understanding developed within Heidegger's model of breakdown. By their account, novices learn skills first by acquiring a set of decontextualized rules. The novices' mode of understanding is "theoretical." As they become more experienced, they become more attuned to situationalspecifics and their reasoning becomes more holistic. Previously solved problems are retained as resources for future problem solving. Eventually, a level of expertise is achieved in which problems are approached "intuitively" instead of "analyti- cally." Expert problem solving, therefore, involves a more "primary" mode of understanding. However, when the expert encounters a novel problem, one for which a previously solved case is not available (or not recognizable), the expert may be required to adopt an "interpretive" approach to solving the problem, appealing to previously learned rules and reasoning from basic principles. With respect to the teaching of new skills, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="198" class="deo:Reference">Suchman (1987)</xref> described what she termed the ofthe instructionfollower, that is the problem "of turning essentially partial descriptions of objects and actions into concrete practical activities with predictable outcomes" (p. 101). She discussed this problem in the context of learning to use a complex piece of equipment (i.e., a photocopy machine), but her discussion can be considered more broadly to include the application of knowledge in practical circumstances in general. The problem of the instruction follower arises from the "irremediable incompleteness of instructions" (p. 101)-that is, from our inability to specify all the conditions that must be assumed for any particular fact or rule to hold true. For example, even the simple instruction, "Place the sheet to be copied on the glass, close the cover, and press the 'copy' button," makes extensive assumptions (e.g., that the copying machine is</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="200" page="16" column="1">12 See, in this regard, Valsiner's (1988) description of Vygotsky's method of "double stimulation."</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx201">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62cy.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="202" page="17" column="1">40</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="203" page="17" column="1">KOSCHMANN, KUUTTI, HICKMAN</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="204" page="17" column="1">' ~</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="208" page="17" column="1">plugged in, that it is not malfunctioning, that the user knows how to open the cover and where the copy button is located). But in attempting to articulate these assumptions, we engage in a form of infinite regress because every assumption supplied rests on additional, unarticulated a ~ s u m ~ t i o n s . If instruction is ever and unavoidably incomplete, one might ask, how is it that we can learn anything? The answer is that the "implicit work of anchoring descriptions to concrete objects and actions" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="205" class="deo:Reference">Suchman, 1987</xref>, p. 101) undertaken by the recipient of the instruction is made possible by virtue of the shared, commonsensical background knowledge of the world that we all possess. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="206" class="deo:Reference">Dreyfus (1991)</xref> made a distinction between knowing-that and knowing-how-that is, between decontextualized factual knowledge and knowledge of how to actually do things (e.g., ride a bicycle, conduct a conversation, use a subway).14 It is the gulf between knowing-that and knowing-how that stands as the basis for Suchman's problem of the instruction follower. It arises in the discrepancy between what can be neatly described in the language of instruction and what one needs to know to apply the instruction in practical settings. Know-how is acquired through successive experiences of trying, failing, and eventually acquiring the skills (and knowledge) we need to function competently in the world. Or, stated more succinctly, "distinctions arise from recurrent patterns of breakdown in concernful activity" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="207" class="deo:Reference">Winograd Flores, 1986</xref>, &amp; p. 69). Breakdown, therefore, is more than a simple disruption of ongoing activity-it is a vital precursor to productive inquiry and subsequent learning.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="209" page="17" column="1">CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="211" page="17" column="1">As described here, breakdown results from the confrontation of subjective plans and goals with practical circumstances. It occurs when concernful, ongoing activity is interrupted by a "collapse of everyday intelligibility" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="210" class="deo:Reference">Guignon, 1983</xref>, p. 102), precipitating a denouement in which the problematic aspects of the current situation are brought to some resolution. Although the phenomenon itself is disarmingly commonplace, the key role afforded to it in the works of Heidegger, Leont'ev, and Dewey speaks to its theoretical importance. By focusing on this universally experienced phenomenon, a new appreciation is acquired of the contributions of these three writers. Given their importance to contemporary thought, the points of entry that this analysis provides into their respective bodies of work might be taken as the most useful contribution of this article. To do so, however, would serve to devalue the potential enrichment of our conceptual understanding of breakdown itself, made possible through diligent study of their varying accounts of this ubiquitous phenomenon.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="212" page="17" column="1">2013 October 02 06:52 at Library] University [Lancaster by Downloaded</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="213" page="17" column="1">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214" page="17" column="1">An abbreviated version of this article was presented as a poster at the 18th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society. We thank Hubert Dreyfus, Pentti Hakkarainen, Viktor Kaptelinin, Arnie Raeithel, and two anonymous reviewers for their helpful suggestions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="215" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">" ~ r e ~ f u (1991) s referred to these unspoken assumptions as ceterisparibus conditions. 14 Interestingly, Dreyfus credited Dewey with having first developed this distinction in Human Nature and Conduct (MW14).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx216">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62cy.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="217" page="18" column="1">BREAKDOWN IN HEIDEGGER, LEONT'EV, AND DEWEY</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="218" page="18" column="1">41</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="219" page="18" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="18" column="1">Boydston, J. A. (Ed.). (1969-1991). The collected works ofJohn Dewey. Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" page="18" column="1">Davydov, 'V. V. (1982). The psychological structure and contents of the learning activity. In R. Glaser &amp; J. Lompscher</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="18" column="1">(Eds.), Cognitive and motivational aspects of' instruction (pp. 37-44). Berlin, Germany: Deutsche Verlag der Wissenschaften.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="18" column="1">Davydov, V., Zinchenko, V., &amp; Talyzina, N. (1983). The problem of activity in the works of A. N. Leont'ev. Soviet Psychology, 21(4), 31-42.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="18" column="1">Dreyfus, H. (1991). Being-in-the-world: A commentary on Heidegger's Being and Time. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" page="18" column="1">Dreyfus, H., &amp; Dreyfus, S. (1986). Mind over machine: The power uf human intuition and expertise in the era qf the computer. New York: Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" page="18" column="1">Engestrom, Y. (1987). Learning by expanding: An activity-theoretical approach to developmental research. Helsinki, Finland: Orienta-Konsultit.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Gal'perin, P. Ya. (1969). Stages in the development of mental acts. In M. Cole &amp; I. Maltzman (Eds.), A handbook of contemporary Sovietpsychology (pp. 249-273). New York: Basic Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Garrison, J. (1995). Deweyan pragmatism and the epistemology of contemporary social constructivism. American Educational Research Journal, 32, 7 16-740.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="18" column="1">Guignon, C. (1983). Heidegger and the problem qfknowledge. Indianapolis, IN: Hackett.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" page="18" column="1">Haugeland, J. (1982). Heidegger on being a person. Noas, 16, 15-26.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" page="18" column="1">Heidegger, M. (1953). Sein undZeit [Being and time] (8th ed.). Tiibigen, Germany: M. Niemeyer.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" page="18" column="1">Heidegger, M. (1962). Being and time (J. Macquarrie &amp; E. Robinson, Trans.). New York: Harper &amp; Row. (Original work published 1953)</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" page="18" column="1">Hickman, L. (1990). John Dewey'spragmatic technology. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Hook, S. (1962, November 11). The map was redrawn to make man's agony a part of the geography. New York Times Book Review, Part I, pp. 6,42.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" page="18" column="1">Kaptelinin, V. (1996). Activity theory: Implications for human-computer interface. In B. Nardi (Ed.), Context and consciousness (pp. 103-1 16). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Leont'ev, A. N. (1972). Problem dejatel'nosti v psihologii [The problem of activity in psychology]. Voprosy Filosofii, No. 9,95-108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Leont'ev, A. N. (1974). The problem of activity in psychology (E. Berg, Trans.). Soviet Psychology, 13, 4-33. (Original work published 1972)</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Leont'ev, A. N. (1975). Dejatel'nost, Soznanie, Lichnosf' [Activity, consciousness, and personality]. Moscow: Politnzdat.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Leont'ev, A. N. (1978). Activity, consciousness, andpersonality (M. J. Hall, Trans.). Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall. (Original work published 1975)</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Leont'ev, A. N. (1981). Problems of'the development of'fhe mind. Moscow: Progress Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" page="18" column="1">Livergood, N. (1967). Activity in Marx's philosophy. Hague, The Netherlands: Martinus Nijhoff.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" page="18" column="1">Marx, K., &amp; Engels, F. (1959). Werke (Vol. 3). Berlin, Germany: Dietz Verlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Rorty, R. (1979). Philosophy and the mirror ofnature. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" page="18" column="1">Suchman, L. (1987). Plans and situated actions: The problem of human-machine communication. Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" page="18" column="1">Tolman, C. W., &amp; Piekkola, B. (1989). Anticipations of activity theory in the critique of the reflex arc concept. Multidisciplinary Newsletter,fi)rActivity Theory, 3/4, 43-46.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" page="18" column="1">Toulmin, S. (1988). Introduction. In J. A. Boydston (Ed.), John Dewey: The laterworks, 1925-1953 (Vol. 4 , pp. vii-xxii). Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Valsiner, J. (1988). Developmental psychology in the Soviet Union. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Wertsch, J. (1985). Vygotsky and the !ocial,fbrmation of' mind. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" page="18" column="1">Winograd, T., &amp; Flores, F. (1986). Understandingcomputers and cognition: A new foundationfir design. Nonvood, NJ: Ablex.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx250">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62cy.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62cy.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
