<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>b78c0a692065ad1a31e29e9bb70c0094bfb2632385ef57371e089ceabe5d45e6</job>
    <base_name>62qm</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2955477</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">BEING AND TIME  </article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">MARTIN HEIDEGGER Translated by</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">John Macquarrie</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Edward Robinson</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">HARPER &amp; ROW. PUBLISHERS   New York. Hagerstown, San Francisco, London  </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">BEING AND TIME</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">Copyright © 1962 by Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, Incorporated.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" confidence="possible">Printed in the United States of America. All rights reserved. No part of this book may be used or repro duced in any manner whatsoever without written pennission except in the case of brief quotations em bodied in critical articles and reviews. For infonna tion address Harper &amp;: Row. Publishers, Incorporated. 10 East 53rd Street, New York, N. Y. 1002~</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">Translated from the Gennan</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">Sein und Zeit</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11" confidence="possible">(Seventh edition, Neomarius Verlag, Tiibingen)</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="12">LIBRARY OF CONGRESS CATALOG CARD NUMBER: 62-7289</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx13">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62qm.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="14">INT. II Being and Time , 6. The Task oj Destroying the History of Ontology</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15">20</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19">All research-and not least that which operates within the range of the central question of Being-is an ontical possibility of Dasein. Dasein's Being finds its meaning in temporality. But temporality is also the con --which makes historicality possible as a temporal kind of Being . which Dasein itself possesses, regardless of whether or how Dasein is an entity 'in time'. Historicality, as a determinate character, is prior to what is called "history" (world-historical historizing).l "Historicality" stands for the state of Being that is constitutive for Dasein's 'historizing' as such; only on the basis of such 'historizing' is anything like 'world-history' possible or can anything belong historically to world-history. In its factical Being, any Dasein is as it already was, and it is 'what' it already was. It is its past, whether explicitly or not. And this is so not only in that its past is, as it were, pushing itself along 'behind' it, . and that Dasein possesses what is past as a property which is still present at-hand and which sometimes has after-effects upon it: Dasein 'is' its past in the way of its own Being, which, to put it roughly, 'historizes' out of its future on each occasion. 2 Whatever the way of being it may have at the time, and thus with whatever understanding of Being it may possess, Dasein has grown up both into and in a traditional way of interpreting itself: in terms of this it understands itself proximally and, within a certain range, constantly. By this understanding, the possibilities of its Being are disclosed and regulated. Its own past-and this always means the past of its 'generation'-is not something which follows along after Dasein, but something which already goes ahead of it. This elemental historicality of Dasein may remain hidden from Dasein itself. But there is a way by which it can be discovered and given proper attention. Dasein can discover tradition, preserve it, and study it explicitly. The discovery of tradition and the disclosure of what it 'transmits' and how this is transmitted, can be taken hold of as a task in its own right. In this way Dasein brings itself into the kind of Being which consists in historiological inquiry and research. But historiology-or more precisely historicity 3-is possible as a kind of Being which the inquiring Dasein may 1 'weltgeschichtliches Geschehen'. While the verb 'geschehen' ordinarily means to   'happen', and will often be so translated, Heidegger stresses its etymological kinship to   'Geschichte' or 'history'. To bring out this connection, we have coined the verb 'historize',   which might be paraphrased as to 'happen in a historical way'; we shall usually translate   'geschehen' this way in contexts where history is being discussed. We trnst that the reader   will keep in mind that such 'historizing' is characteristic of all historical entities, and is not   the sort of thing that is done primarily by historians (as 'philosophizing', for instance,   is done by philosophers). (On 'world-historical' see H. 381 ff.)   2 'Das Dasein "ist" seine Vergangenheit in der Weise seines Seins, das, roh gesagt.   jeweils aus seiner Zukunft her "geschieht".' '  3 'Historizitiit'. Cf. note 2, p. 31. H. 10 above. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> 42 Being and Time INT. II possess, only because historicality is a detennining characteristic for Dasein in the very basis of its Being. If this historicality remains hidden from Dasein, and as long as it so remains, Dasein is also denied the possibility of historiological inquiry or the discovery of history. If his toriology is wanting, this is not evidence against Dasein's historicality; on the contrary, as a deficient model of this state of Being, it is evidence for it. Only because it is 'historical' can an era be unhistoriological. On the other hand, if Dasein has seized upon its latent possibility not only of making its own existence transparent to itse1fbut also of inquiring into the meaning of existentiality itself (that is to say, of previously inquiring into the meaning of Being in general), and if by such inquiry its eyes have been opened to its own essential historicality, then one cannot fail to see that the inquiry into Being (the ontico-ontological necessity of which we have already indicated) is itself characterized by historicality. The ownmost meaning of Being which belongs to the inquiry into Being as an historical inquiry, gives us the assignment [Anweisung] of inquiring into the history of that inquiry itself, that is, of becoming historiological. In working out the question of Being, we must heed this assignment, so that by positively making the past our own, we may bring ourselves into full possession of the ownmost possibilities of such inquiry. The question of the meaning of Being must be carried through by explicating Dasein beforehand in its temporality and historicality; the question thus brings itself to the point where it understands itself as historiological. Our preparatory Interpretation of the fundamental structures of Dasein with regard to the average kind of Being which is closest to it (a kind of Being in which it is therefore proximally historical as well), will make manifest, however, not only that Dasein is inclined to fall back upon its world (the world in which it is) and to interpret itself in terms of that world by its reflected light, but also that Dasein simultaneously falls prey to the tradition of which it has more or less explicitly taken hold. 2 This tradition keeps it from providing its own guidance, whether in</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx17">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62qm.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">2I</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible">1 'defizienter Modus'. Heidegger likes to think of certain characteristics as occurring in various ways or 'modes', among which may be included certain ways of ' not occurring' or 'occurring only to an inadequate extent' or, in general, occurring 'deficiently'. It is as if zero and the negative integers were to be thought of as representing 'deficient modes of being a positive integer'. I! ' ••• das Dasein hat nicht nur die Geneigtheit, an seine Welt, in der es ist, zu verfallen and reluzent aus ihr her sich auszulegen, Dasein verfallt in eins damit auch seiner mehr oder minder ausdrucklich crgriffenen Tradition.' The verb 'verfallen' is one which Heidegger will use many times. Though we shall usually translate it simply as 'fall', it has the connotation of deteriorating, collapsing, or falling down. Neither our 'fall back upon' nor our 'falls prey to' is quite right: but 'fall upon' and 'fall on to', which are more literal, would be misleading for 'an ... zu and though 'falls to the lot of' and 'devolves , would do well for 'verfiillt' with the in other contexts, they will not do so here.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx21">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62qm.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">22</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">physicae</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24">INT. II Being and Time 43 inquiring or in choosing. This holds true-and by no means least-for that understanding which is rooted in Dasein's ownmost Being, and for the possibility of developing it-namely, for ontological understanding. When tradition thus becomes master, it does so in such a way that what it 'transmits' is made so inaccessible, proximally and for the most part, that it rather becomes concealed. Tradition takes what has come down to us and delivers it over to self-evidence; it blocks our access to those primordial 'sources' from which the categories and concepts handed down to us have been in part quite genuinely drawn'! Indeed it makes us forget that they have had such an origin, and makes us suppose that the neces sity of going back to these sources is something which we need not even understand. Dasein has had its historicality so thoroughly uprooted by tradition that it confines its interest to the multiformity of possible types, directions, and standpoints of philosophical activity in the most exotic and alien of cultures; and by this very interest it seeks to veil the fact that it has no ground of its Own to stand on. Consequently, despite all its iological interests and all its zeal for an Interpretation which is philologically 'objective' ["sachliche"], Dasein no longer understands the most elcmentary conditions which would alone enable it to go back to the past in a positive manner and make it productively its own. We have shown at the outset (Section I) not only that the question of the meaning of Being is one that has not been attended to and one that has been inadequately formulated, but that it has become quite forgotten in spite of all our interest in 'metaphysics'. Greek ontology and its history -which, in their numerous filiations and distortions, determine the con ceptual character of philosophy even today-prove that when Dasein understands either itself or Being in general, it does so in terms of the 'world', and that the ontology which has thus arisen has deteriorated to a tradition in which it gets reduced to something self-evident -merely material for reworking, as it was for In the Middle Ages this uprooted Greek ontology became a fixed body of doctrine. Its syste matics, however, is by no means a mere joining together of traditional pieces into a single edifice. Though its basic conceptions of Being have been taken over dogmatically from the Greeks, a great deal of unpre tentious work has been carried on further within these limits. With the peculiar character which the Scholastics gave it, Greek ontology has, in its essentials, travelled the path that leads through the Disputationes meta of Suarez to the 'metaphysics' and transcendental philosophy of modern times, determining even the foundations and the aims of Hegel's</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="25">the prefix</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="26">1 In this passage Heidegger juxtaposes a number of words beginning 'Uber-': 'ilbergibt' ('transmits'); 'Uberantwo; ('what has come down to us'); 'ilberlieferten'</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">Being and Time   II</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28">23  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible">P t:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35">44 INT. 'logic'. In the course of this history certain distinctive domains of Being have come into view and have served as the primary guides for subsequent problematics : the ego cogito of Descartes, the subject, the "I", reason, spirit, person. But these all remain uninterrogated as to their Being and its structure, in accordance with the thoroughgoing way in which the question of Being has been neglected. It is rather the case that the cate gorial content of the traditional ontology has been carried over to these entities with corresponding formalizations and purely negative restric tions, or else dialectic has been called in for the purpose of Interpreting the substantiality of the subject ontologically. If the question of Being is to have its own history made transparent, then this hardened tradition must be loosened up, and the concealments which it has brought about 1 must be dissolved. We understand this task as one in which by taking the question of Being as our clue, we are to destroy the traditional content of ancient ontology until we arrive at those prim ordial experiences in which we achieved our first ways of determining the nature of Being-the ways which have guided us ever since. In thus demonstrating the origin of our basic ontological concepts an investigation in which their 'birth certificate' is displayed, we have nothing to do with a vicious relativizing of ontological standpoints. But this destruction is just as far from having the negative sense of shaking off the ontological tradition. We must, on the contrary, stake out the positive possibilities of that tradition, and this always means keeping it within its limits; these in turn are given factically in the way the question is for mulated at the time, and in the way the possible field for investigation is thus bounded off. On its negative side, this destruction does not relate itself towards the past; its criticism is aimed at 'today' and at the prevalent way of treating the history of ontology, whether it is headed towards doxography, towards intellectual history, or towards a history of problems. But to bury the past in nullity [Nichtigkeit] is not the purpose of this destruction; its aim is positive; its negative function remains unexpressed and indirect. The destruction of the history of ontology is essentially bound up with the way the question of Being is formulated, and it is possible only within such a formulation. In the framework ofour treatise, which aims at working out that question in principle, we can carry out this destruction only with regard to stages of that history which are in principle decisive. In line with the positive tendencies of this destruction, we must in the first instance raise the question whether and to what extent the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 45 Interpretation of Being and the phenomenon of time have been brought together thematically in the course of the history of ontology, and whether the problematic of Temporality required for this has ever been worked out in principle or ever could have been. The first and only person who has gone any stretch of the way towards investigating the dimension of Temporality or has even let himself be drawn hither by the coercion of the phenomena themselves is Kant. Only when we have established the problematic of Temporality, can we succeed in casting light on the obscurity of his doctrine of the schematism. But this will also show us why this area is one which had to remain closed off to him in its real dimensions and its central ontological function. Kant himself was aware that he was venturing into an area of obscurity: 'This schematism of our understanding as regards appearances and their mere form is an art hidden in the depths of the human soul, the true devices of which are hardly ever to be divined from Nature and laid uncovered before our eyes.'! Here Kant shrinks back, as it were, in the face of something which must be brought to light as a theme and a principle if the expression "Being" is to have any demonstrable meaning. In the end, those very phenomena which will be exhibited under the heading of 'Temporality' in our analysis, are precisely those most covert judgments of the 'common reason' for which Kant says it is the 'business of philosophers' to provide an analytic. In pursuing this task of destruction with the problematic of Temporality as our clue, we shall try to Interpret the chapter on the schematism and the Kantian doctrine of time, taking that chapter as our point of depar ture. At the same time we shall show why Kant could never achieve an insight into the problematic of Temporality. There were two things that stood in his way: in the first place, he altogether neglected the problem of Being; and, in connection with this, he failed to provide an ontology with Dasein as its theme or (to put this in Kantian language) to give a preliminary ontological analytic of the subjectivity of the subject. Instead of this, Kant took over Descartes' position quite dogmatically, notwith standing all the essential respects in which he had gone beyond him. Furthermore, in spite of the fact that he was bringing the phenomenon of time back into the subject again, his analysis of it remained oriented towards the traditional way in which time had been ordinarily under stood; in the long run this kept him from working out the phenomenon of a 'transcendental determination of time' in its own structure and func tion. Because of this double effect of tradition the decisive connection between time and the '1 think' was shrouded in utter darkness; it did not even become a problem.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="31">1 ' • • • der durch sie gezeitigten Verdeckungen.' The verb 'zeitigen' will appear fre quently in later chapters. See H. 304 and our note ad loco</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx32">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62qm.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="33">INT. II   Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="34">24</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="36">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="37">II</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible">25</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39">46 INT. In taking over Descartes' ontological position Kant made an essential omission: he failed to provide an ontology of Dasein. This omission was a decisive one in the spirit Lim Sinne] of Descartes' ownmost tendencies. With the 'cogito sum' Descartes had claimed that he was putting philo sophy on a new and firm footing. But what he left undetermined when he began in this 'radical' way, was the kind of Being which belongs to the res cogitans, or-more precisely-the meaning of the Being of the 'sum'.l By working out the unexpressed ontological foundations of the 'cogito sum', we shall complete our sojourn at the second station along the path of our destructive retrospect of the history of ontology. Our Interpretation will not only prove that Descartes had to neglect the question of Being alto gether; it will also show why he came to suppose that the absolute 'Being certain' ["Gewisssein"] of the cogito exempted him from raising the ques tion of the meaning of the Being which this entity possesses. Yet Descartes not only continued to neglect this and thus to accept a indefinite ontological status for the res cogitans sive mens sive animus ['the thing which whether it be a mind or spirit']: he regarded this entity as afundamentum inconcussum, and applied the medieval ontology to it in carrying through the fundamental considerations of his Meditationes. He defined the res cogitans ontologically as an ens; and in the medieval ontology the meaning of Being for such an ens had been fixed by understanding it as an ens creatum. God, as ens infinitum, was the ens inc rea tum. But createdness [Geschaffenheit] in the widest sense of something's having been produced [HergestelltheitJ, was an essential item in the structure of the ancient conception of Being. The seemingly new beginning which Descartes proposed for philosophizing has revealed itself as the implantation of a baleful prejudice, which has kept later generations from making any thematic ontological analytic of the 'mind' ["Gemutes"J such as would take the question of Being as a clue and would at the same time come to grips criticallv with the traditional ancient ontology. who is acquainted with the middle ages sees that Descartes is 'dependent' upon medieval scholasticism and employs its terminology. But with this 'discovery' nothing is achieved philosophically as long as it remains obscure to what a profound extent the medieval ontology has influenced the way in which posterity has determined or failed to deter mine the ontological character of the res cogitans. The full extent of this cannot be estimated until both the meaning and the limitations of the ancient ontology have been exhibited in terms of an orientation directed</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" confidence="possible">1 We follow the later editions in reading 'der Seinssirm des "sum" '. The earlier editions have an anacoluthic 'den' for 'der'.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx41">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62qm.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="42">INT. II Being and Time</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43">47 towards the question of Being. In other words, in our process of destruc tion we find ourselves faced with the task of Interpreting the basis of the ancient ontology in the light of the problematic of Temporality. When this is done, it will be manifest that the ancient way of interpreting the Being of entities is oriented towards the 'world' or 'Nature' in the widest sense, and that it is indeed in terms of 'time' that its understanding of Being is obtained. The outward evidence for this (though of course it is merely outward evidence) is the treatment of the meaning of Being as 1To.pOVU{o. or ovuto., which signifies, in ontologico-Temporal terms, 'presence' ["Anwesenheit"].l Entities are grasped in their Being as 'pre sence'; this means that they are understood with regard to a definite mode of time-the 'PresenC2 The problematic of Greek ontology, like that of any other, must take its clues from Dasein itself. In both ordinary and philosophical usage, Dasein, man's Being, is 'defined' as the whose Being is essentially determined course. 3 MYELJI is the clue for arriving at those structures of Being which belong to the entities we encounter in addressing ourselves to anything or speaking about it Lim Ansprechen und BesprechenJ. (Cf. Section 7 B.) This is why the ancient ontology as developed by Plato turns into 'dialec tic'. As the ontological clue gets progressively worked out-namely, in the 'hermeneutic' of the .\6yoS' -it becomes increasingly possible to grasp the problem of Being in a more radical fashion. The 'dialectic', which has been a genuine philosophical embarrassment, becomes superfluous. That</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" confidence="possible">1 The noun ouaia is derived from one of the stems used in conjugating the irregular verb Elva" ('to be'); in the Aristotelian tradition it is usually translated as 'substance', though translators of Plato are more likely to write 'essence', 'existence', or 'being'. Heidegger suggests that ouaia is to be thought of as synonymous with the derivative noun 7Tapoua{a ('being-at', 'presence'). As he points out, 1Tapou(}ia has a close etymological correspondence with the Gennan 'Anwesenheit' which is similarly derived from the stem of a verb meaning 'to be' (ef. O.H.G. and a of the or time at which ('an-'). We shall in general translate as 'presence' the participle 'anwesend' as some form of the expression 'have presence'. 2. 'die "Gegenwart"'. While this noun may, like 7Tapoua{a or 'Anwesenheit', mean the of someone (1/ some place or on some occasion, it more often means the present, as Ulsnnguished from the past and the future. In its etymological root-structure, however, it means a While Heidegger seems to think of all these meanirgs as somehow fused, we translate this noun as 'the Present', reserving 'in the present' for the 'gegenwartig'. a The phrase 'ril0Y A6yov ,xov is traditionally translated as 'rational animal', on the assumption that AOyo, refers to the faculty of reason. Heidegger, however, points out that AoyoS' is derived from the same root as the verb A.!YEtV ('to talk', 'to hold discourse'); he identifies this in turn with VOELV ('to cognize', 'to be aware of', 'to know'), and calls attention to the fact that the same stem is found in the adjective 8".J.£K"'I(O, ('dialectical'). (See also H. 165 below.) He thus interprets A6yos as 'Rede', which we shall usually translate as 'discourse' or 'talk', depending on the context. See Section 7 B below (H. 32 IT.) and Sections 34 and 35, where 'Rede' will he defined and distinguished both from 'Sprache' ('language') and from 'Geredc' (,idle talk') (H. 160 ff.).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" confidence="possible">26</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61">48 Being and Time INT. II is why Aristotle 'no longer has any understanding' of it, for he has put it on a more radical footing and raised it to a new level [aufhob]. My",I' itself--or rather 1'01,'1', that simple awareness of something present-at hand in its sheer presence-at-hand, l which Parmenides·had already taken to guide him in his own interpretation of Being-has the Temporal structure of a pure 'making-present' of something. I! Those entities which show themselves in this and for it, and which are understood as entities in the most authentic sense, thus get interpreted with regard to the Present; that is, they are conceived as presence (ovaia). 3 Yet the Greeks have managed to interpret Being in this way without any explicit knowledge of the clues which function here, without any acquaintance with the fundamental ontological function of time or even any understanding of it, and without any insight into the reason why this function is possible. On the contrary, they take time itself as one entity among other entities, and try to grasp it in the structure of its Being, though that way of understanding Being which they have taken as their horizon is one which is itself naIvely and inexplicitly oriented towards time. Within the framework in which we are about to work out the principles of the question of Being, we cannot present a detailed Temporal Inter pretation of the foundations of ancient ontology, particularly not of its loftiest and purest scientific stage, which is reached in Aristotle. Instead we shall give an interpretation of Aristotle's essay on time, ii which may be chosen as providing a way of discriminating the basis and the limitations of the ancient science of Being. Aristotle's essay on time is the first detailed Interpretation of this 1 ' . . • von etwas Vorhandenem in seiner puren Vorhandenheit .. .' The adjective 'vorhanden' means literally 'before the hand', but this signification has long since given way to others. In ordinary German usage it may, for instance, be applied to the stock of goods which a dealer has 'on hand', or to the 'extant' works of an author; and in earlier philosophical writing it could be used, like the word 'Dasein' itself, as a synonym for the Latin 'existentia', Heidegger, however, distinguishes quite sharply between 'Dascin' and 'Vorhandenheit', using the latter to designate a kind of Being which belongs to things other than Dasein. We shall translate 'vorhanden' as 'present.at·hand', and 'Vorhanden. heit' as ·presence·at·hand'. The reader must be careful not to confuse these expressions with our 'presence' {'Anwesenheit'} and 'the Present' ('die Gegenwart'), etc., or with a few other verbs and adjectives which we may find it convenient to translate by 'present'. 2'. .. des rein en "Gegenwiirtigens" von etwas', The verb 'gegenwartigen', which is derived from the adjective 'gegenwartig', is not a normal German verb, but was used by HusserI and is used extensively by Heidegger. While we shall translate it by various forms of 'make present', it does not necessarily mean 'making physieally present', but often means something like 'bringing vividly to mind'. 3 'Uas Seiende, das sich in ihm ftir es zeigt und das als das eigentliche Seiende verstanden wird, erhalt demnach seine Auslegung in Rucksicht auf--Gegen.wart, d.h. es ist als Anwescnhcit (ow/a) begriffen.' The hyphenation of 'Gegen·wart' calls attention to the structure of this word in a way which cannot be reproduced in English. See note 2, p. 47, H. 25 above. 'The pronouns 'ihm' and 'es' presumably both refer back to M"nv, though their reference is ambiguous, as our version suggests. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> INT. 49 phenomenon which has come down to us. Every subsequent account of time, including.Bergson's, has been essentially determined by it. When we analyse the Aristotelian conception, it will likewise become clear, as we go back, that the Kantian account of time operates within the structures which Aristotle has set forth; this means that Kant's basic ontological orientation remains that of the Greeks, in spite of all the distinctions which arise in a new inquiry. The question of Being does not achieve its true concreteness until we have carried through the process of destroying the ontological tradition. In this way we can fully prove that the question of the meaning of Being is one that we cannot avoid, and we can demonstrate what it means to talk about 'restating' this question. In any investigation in this field, where 'the thing itself is deeply veiled'iii one must take pains not to overestimate the results.• For in such an inquiry one is constantly compelled to face the possibility of disclosing an even more primordial and more universal horizon from which we may draw the answer to the question, "What is 'Being'?" We can discuss such possibilities seriously and with positive results only if the question of Being has been reawakened and we have arrived at a field where we can come to terms with it in a way that can be controlled.<marker type="block"/> , 7. The Phenomenological Method of Investigation In provisionally characterizing the object which serves as the theme of our investigation (the Being of entities, or the meaning ofBeing in general), it seems that we have also delineated the method to be employed. The task of ontology is to explain Being itself and to make the Being of entities stand out in full relief. And the method of ontology remains questionable in the highest degree as long as we merely consult those ontologies which have come down to us historically, or other essays of that character. Since the term "ontology" is used in this investigation in a sense which is formally broad, any attempt to clarify the method of ontology by tracing its history is automatically ruled out. When, moreover, we use the term "ontology", we are not talking about some definite philosophical discipline standing in interconnection with the others. Here one does not have to measure up to the tasks of some discipline that has been presented beforehand; on the contrary, only in terms of the objective necessities of definite questions and the kind of treatment which the 'things themselves' require, can one develop such a discipline. With the question of the meaning of Being, our investigation comes up<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 244 1.6 something. The 'generalization' is rather one that is ontological and a priori. What it has in view is not a set of ontical properties which con stantly keep emerging, but a state of Being which is already underlying in every case, and which first makes it ontologically possible for this entity to be addressed ontically as "cum". The existential condition for the possibility of 'the cares of life' and 'devotedness', must be conceived as care, in a sense which is primordial-that is ontological. The transcendental 'generality' of the phenomenon of care and of all fundamental existentialia is, on the other hand, broad enough to present a basis on which every interpretation of Dasein which is ontical and belongs to a world-view must move, whether Dasein is understood as affliction [Not] and the 'cares of life' or in an opposite manner. The very 'emptiness' and 'generality' which obtrude themselves in existential structures, have an ontological definiteness and fulness of their own. Thus Dasein's whole constitution itselfis not simple in its unity, but shows a structural articulation; in the existential conception of care, this articulation becomes expressed. Thus, by our ontological Interpretation of Dasein, we have been brought to the existential conception of care from Dasein's pre-ontological interpretation of itself as 'care'. Yet the analytic of Dasein is not aimed at laying an ontological basis for anthropology; its purpose is one of funda mental ontology. This is the purpose that has tacitly determined the course of our considerations hitherto, our selection of phenomena, and the limits to which our analysis may proceed. Now, however, with regard to our leading question of the meaning of Being and our way of working this out, our investigation must us explicit assurance as to what we have so far achieved. But this sort of thing is not to be reached by super ficially taking together what we have discussed. Rather, with the help of what wc have achieved, that which could be indicated only crudely at the beginning of the existential analytic, must now be concentrated into a more penetrating understanding of the problem.<marker type="block"/> The question of the meaning of Being becomes possible at all only if there is something like an understanding of Being. Understanding of Being belongs to the kind of Being which the entity called "Dasein" possesses. The more appropriately and primordially we have succeeded in explicating this entity, the surer we are to attain our goal in the further course ofworking out the problem offundamental ontology. In our pursuit of the tasks of a preparatory existential analytic ofDasein,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 1.6 Being and Time 245 there emerged an Interpretation of understanding, meaning, and inter pretation. Our analysis ofDasein's disclosedness showed further that, with this disclosedness, Dasein, in its basic state of Being-in-the-world, has been revealed equiprimordially with to the world, Being-in, and the Self. Furthermore, in the factical disclosed ness of the world, entities within-the-world are discovered too. This implies that the Being of these entities is always understood in a certain manner, even ifit is not conceived in a way which is appropriately ontological. To be sure, the pre-ontological understanding of Being embraces all entities which are essentially disclosed in Dasein; but the understanding of Being has not yet Arti culated itself in a way which corresponds to the various modes of Being. At the same time our interpretation of understanding has shown thClt, in accordance with its falling kind of Being, it has, proximally and for the most part, diverted itself [sich ... verlegt] into an understanding of the 'world'. Even where the issue is not only one of ontical experience but also one of ontological understanding, the interpretation of Being takes its orientation in the first instance from the Being of entities within-the world. Thereby the Being of what is proximally ready-to-hand gets passed over, and entities are first conceived as a context of Things (res) which are present-at-hand. "Being" acquires the meaning of "Reality".vlii Sub stantiality becomes the basic characteristic of Being. Corresponding to this way in which the understanding of Being has been diverted, even the ontological understanding of Dasein moves into the horizon of this con ception of Being. Like any other entity, Dasein too is present-at-hand as Real. In this way "Being in general" acquires the meaning of "Reality". Accord ingly the concept of Reality has a peculiar priority in the ontological problematic. By this priority the route to a genuine existential analytic ofDasein gets diverted, and so too does our very view of the Being ofwhat is proximally ready-to-hand within-the-world. It finally forces the general problematic of Being into a direction that lies off the course. The other modes of Being become defined negatively and privatively with regard to Reality. Thus not only the analytic ofDasein but the working-out ofthe question of the meaning of Being in general must be turned away from a one-sided orientation with regard to Being in the sense of Reality. We must demon strate that Realityis not only one kind of Being among others, but that onto logically it has a definite connection in its foundations with Dasein, the world, and readiness-to-hand. To demonstrate this we must discuss in principle the problem qf Reality, its conditions and its limits. Under the heading 'problem of Reality' various questions are clustered: (I) whether any entities which supposedly 'transcend our consciousness'<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 24 6 Being and Time 1.6 are at all; (2) whether this Reality of the 'external world' can be adequately proved; (3) how far this entity, ifit is Real, is to be known in its Being-in itself; (4) what the meaning of this entity, Reality, signifies in general. The following discussion of the problem of Reality will treat three topics with regard to the question of fundamental ontology: (a) Reality as a problem of Being, and whether the 'external world' can be proved; (b) Reality as an ontological problem; (c) Reality and care.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx47">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62qm.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="48">II Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="49">27</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="52">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="53">200</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="55">43. Dasein, Worldhood, and Reality</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx57">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62qm.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="58">201</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="60">202</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" confidence="possible">Proved (a) Reality as a problem of Being, and whether the 'External World' can be</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="63">Proved</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70">Of these questions about Reality, the one which comes first in order is the ontological question of what "Reality" signifies in general. But as long as a pure ontological problematic and methodology was lacking, this question (if it was explicitly formulated at all) was necessarily con founded with a discussion of the 'problem of the external world'; for the analysis of Reality is possible only on the basis of our having appropriate access to the Real. But it has long been held that the way to grasp the Real is by that kind of knowing which is characterized by beholding [das anschauende Erkennen]. Such knowing 'is' as a way in which the soul or consciousness-behaves. In so far as Reality has the character of something independent and "in ,itself", the question of the meaning of "Reality" becomes linked with that of whether the Real can be inde pendent 'of consciousness' or whether there can be a transcendence of consciousness into the 'sphere' of the Real. The possibility of an adequate ontological analysis of Reality depends upon how far that ofwhich the Real is to be thus independent-how far that which is to be transcendedI-has itself been clarified with regard to its Being. Only thus can even the kind of Being which belongs to transcendence be ontologically grasped. And finally we must make sure what kind of primary access we have to the Real, by deciding the question of whether knowing can take over this function at all. These investigations, which take precedence ouer any possible ontological question about Reality, have been carried out in the foregoing existential analytic. According to this analytic, knowing is a founded mode of access to the ReaL The Real is essentially accessible only as entities within-the world. All access to such entities is founded ontologically upon the basic state of Dasein, Being-in-the-world; and this in turn has care as its even more primordial state of Being (ahead of itself-Being already in a world -as Being alo~side entities within-the-world). The question of whether there is a world at all and whether its Being <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 1.6 Being and Time 247 can be proved, makes no sense if it is raised by Dasein as Being-in-the world; and who else would raise it? Furthermore, it is encumbered with a double signification. The world as the "wherein" [das Worin] of Being- in, and the 'world' as entities within-the-world (that in which [das Wobei] one is concernfully absorbed) either have been confused or are not distinguished at all. But the world is disclosed essentially along with the Being of Dasein; with the disclosedness of the world, the 'world' has in each case been discovered too. Of course entities within-the-world in the sense of the Real as merely present-at-hand, are the very things that can remain concealed. But even the Real can be discovered only on the basis of a world which has already been disclosed. And only on this basis can anything Real still remain hidden. The question of the 'Reality' of the 'external world' gets raised without any previous clarification of the of the world as such. Factically, the 'problem of the external world' is constantly oriented with regard to entities within-the-world (Things and Objects). So these discussions drift along into a problematic which it is almost impossible to disentangle ontologically. Kant's 'Refutation of Idealism'ix shows how intricate these questions are and how what one wants to prove gets muddled with what one does prove and with the means whereby the proof is carried out. Kant calls it 'a scandal of philosophy and of human reason in general'X that there is still no cogent prooffor the 'Dasein of Things outside of us' which will do away with any scepticism. He proposes such a proof himself, and indeed he does so to provide grounds for his 'theorem' that 'The mere conscious ness of my own Dasein-a consciousness which, however, is empirical in character-proves the Dasein of objects in the space outside of me.'xi We must in the first instance note explicitly that Kant uses the term 'Dasein' to designate that kind of Being which in the present investigation we have called 'presence-at-hand'. 'Consciousness of my Dasein' means for Kant a consciousness of my Being-present-at-hand in the sense of Descartes. When Kant uses the term 'Dasein' he has in mind the Being present-at-hand of consciousness just as much as the Being-present-at hand of Things. The proof for the 'Dasein of Things outside of me' is supported by the fact that both change and performance belong, with equal primordiality, to the essence of time. My own Being-present-at-hand-that is, the Being-present-at-hand of a multiplicity of representations, which has been given in the inner sense-is a process of change which is present-at-hand. To have a determinate temporal character [Zeitbestimmtheit], however, presupposes something present-at-hand which is permanent. But this cannot be 'in us', 'for only through what is thus permanent can my</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="65">1 ' ••• du, wollOn Unabhangigkeit bestehen solI, was transzendiert werden soli .. .'</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx66">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62qm.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="67">20</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="68">3</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="69">phenomenon</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="71">1.6</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="72">248</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="73">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="74">20 4</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" confidence="possible">Dasein in time be determined'.xlI Thus if changes which are present-at hand have been posited empirically 'in me', it is necessary that along with these something permanent which is present-at-hand should be posited empirically 'outside of me'. What is thus permanent is the condition which makes it possible for the changes 'in me' to be present-at-hand. The experience of the Being-in-time of representations posits something changing 'in me' and something permanent 'outside of me', and it posits both with equal primordiality. Of course this proof is not a causal inference and is therefore not encumbered with the disadvantages which that would imply. Kant gives, as it were, an 'ontological proof' in terms of the idea of a temporal entity. It seems at first as if Kant has given up the Cartesian approach of positing a subject one can come across in isolation. But only in semblance. That Kant demands any proof at all for the 'Dasein of Things outside of me' shows already that he takes the subject-the 'in me'-as the starting point for this problematic. Moreover, his proof itself is then carried through by starting with the empirically given changes 'in me'. For only 'in me' is 'time' experienced, and time carries the burden of the proof. Time provides the basis for leaping off into what is 'outside of me' in the course of the proof. Furthermore, Kant emphasizes that "The problem atical kind [of idealism], which merely alleges our inability to prove by immediate experience that there is a Dasein outside of our own, is reason able and accords with a sound kind of philosophical thinking: namely, to permit no decisive judgment until an adequate proof has been found. "xIII But even if the ontical priority of the isolated subject and inner exper ience should be given up, Descartes' position would still be retained ontologically. What Kant proves-if we may suppose that his proof is correct and correctly based-is that entities which are changing and entities which are permanent are necessarily present-at-hand toget!ler. But when two things which are present-at-hand are thus put on the same level, this does not as yet mean that subject and Object are present-at hand together. And even if this were proved, what is ontologically decisive would still be covered up-namely, the basic state of the 'subject', Dasein, as Being-in-the-world. The Being-present-at-hand-together of the physical</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="76">and the psychical is completely different ontically and ontologically from the phenomenon ofBeing-in-the-world.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" confidence="possible">Kant presupposes both the distinction between the 'in me' and the 'outside of me', and also the connection between these; factically he is correct in doing so, but he is incorrect from the standpoint of the tendency of his proof. It has not been demonstrated that the sort of thing which gets established about the Being-present-at-hand-together of the changing and</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx78">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62qm.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="79">1.6 Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="80">249</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="81">20 5</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="82">faith',xiv</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="83">206</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible">the permanent when one takes time as one's clue, will also apply to the connection between the 'in me' and the 'outside of me'. But if one were to see the whole distinction between the 'inside' and the 'outside' and the whole connection between them which Kant's proof presupposes, and if one were to have an ontological conception of what has been presupposed in this presupposition, then the possibility of holding that a proof of the 'Dasein of Things outside of me' is a necessary one which has yet to be given [noch ausstehend], would collapse. The 'scandal of philosophy' is not that this proof has yet to be given, but that such proofs are expected and attempted again and again. Such expectations, aims, and demands arise from an ontologically inadequate way of starting with something of such a character that independently of it and 'outside' of it a 'world' is to be proved as present-at-hand. It is not that the proofs are inadequate, but that the kind of Being of the entity which does the proving and makes requests for proofs has not been made definite enough. This is why a demonstration that two things which are present-at-hand are necessarily present-at-hand together, can give rise to the illusion that something has been proved, or even can be proved, about Dasein as Being-in-the-world. If Dasein is understood correctly, it defies such proofs, because, in its Being, it already is what subsequent proofs deem necessary to demonstrate for it. If one were to conclude that since the Being-present-at-hand of Things outside of us is impossible to prove, it must therefore 'be taken merely on one would still fail to surmount this perversion of the problem. The assumption would remain that at bottom and ideally it must still be possible to carry out such a proof. This inappropriate way of approaching the problem is still endorsed when one restricts oneself to a 'faith in the Reality of the external world', even if such a faith is explicitly 'acknow ledged' as such. Although one is not offering a stringent proof, one is still in principle demanding a proof and trying to satisfy that demand. Even if one should invoke the doctrine that the subject must presuppose and indeed always does unconsciously presuppose the presence-at-hand of the 'external world', one would still be starting with the construct of an isolated subject. The phenomenon of Being-in-the-world is something that one would no more meet in this way than one would by demon strating that the physical and the psychical are present-at-hand together. With such presuppositions, Dasein always comes 'too late'; for in so far as it does this presupposing as an entity (and otherwise this would be impossible), it is, as an entity, already in a world. 'Earlier' than any pre supposition which Dasein makes, or any of its ways of behaving, is the 'a priori' character of its state of Being as one whose kind of Being is care.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible">25° Being and Time   1.6 To have faith in the Reality of the 'external world', whether rightly or wrongly; to "prove" this Reality for it, whether adequately or inade quately; to presuppose it, whether explicitly or not-attempts such as these which have not mastered their own basis with full transparency, presuppose a subject which is proximally worldless or unsure of its world, and which must, at bottom, first assure itselfofa world. Thus from the very beginning, Being-in-a-world is disposed to "take things" in some way [Auffassen], to suppose, to be certain, to have faith-a way of behaving which itself is always a founded mode of Being-in-the-world. The 'problem ofReality' in the sense of the question whether an external world is present-at-hand and whether such a world can be proved, turns out to be an impossible one, not because its consequences lead to inextric able impasses, but because the very entity which serves as its theme, is one which, as it were, repudiates any such formulation of the question. Our task is not to prove that an 'external world' is present-at-hand or to show how it is present-at-hand, but to point out why Dasein, as Being-in the-world, has the tendency to bury the 'external world' in nullity 'epistemologically' before going on to prove it.l The reason for this lies in Dasein's falling and in the way in which the primary understanding of Being has been diverted to Being as presence-at-hand-a diversion which is motivated by that falling itself. If one formulates the question 'critically' with such an ontological orientation, then what one finds present-at hand as proximally and solely certain, is something merely 'inner'. After the primordial phenomenon of Being-in-the-world has been shattered, the isolated subject is all that remains, and this becomes the basis on which it gets joined together with a 'world'. In this investigation we cannot discuss at length the many attempts to solve the 'problem of Reality' which have been developed in various kinds of realism and idealism and in positions which mediate between 207   them. Certainly a grain of genuine inquiry is to be found in each of these; but certain as this is, it would be just as perverse if one should want to achieve a tenable solution of the problem by reckoning up how much has been correct in each case. What is needed rather is the basic insight that while the different epistemological directions which have been pur sued have not gone so very far off epistemologically, their neglect of any existential analytic of Dasein has kept them from obtaining any basis for a well secured phenomenal problematic. Nor is such a basis to be obtained by subsequently making phenomenological corrections on the concepts of subject and consciousness. Such a procedure would give no guarantee 1 ' • • • warum das Dasein als In-der-Welt-sein die Tendenz hat, die "Aussenwelt" zunachst "erkenntnistheoretisch" in Nichtigkeit zu begraben urn sie dann erst zu be weisen.'</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx86">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62qm.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible">208</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91">1.6 Being and Time 25 1 that the inappropriate formulation oj the question would not continue to stand. Along with Dasein as Being-in-the-world, entities within-the-world have in each case already been disclosed. This existential-ontological assertion seems to accord with the thesis of realism that the external world is Really present-at-hand. In so far as this existential assertion does not deny that entities within-the-world are present-at-hand, it agrees doxographically, as it were-with the thesis of realism in its results. But it differs in principle from every kind of realism; for realism holds that the Reality of the 'world' not only needs to be proved but also is capable of proof. In the existential assertion both of these positions are directly negated. But what distinguishes this assertion from realism altogether, is the fact that in realism there is a lack of ontological understanding. Indeed realism tries to explain Reality ontically by Real connections of interaction between things that are Real. As compared with realism, idealism, no matter how contrary and unten able it may be in its results, has an advantage in principle, provided that it does not misunderstand itself as 'psychological' idealism. If idealism emphasizes that Being and Reality are only 'in the consciousness', this expresses an understanding of the fact that Being cannot be explained through entities. But as long as idealism fails to clarify what this very understanding of Being means ontologically, or how this understanding is possible, or that it belongs to Dasein's state of Being, the Interpretation of Reality which idealism constructs is an empty one. Yet the fact that Being cannot be explained through entities and that Reality is possible only in the understanding of Being, does not absolve us from inquiring into the Being of consciousness, of the res cogitans itself. If the idealist thesis is to be followed consistently, the ontological analysis of conscious~ ness itself is prescribed as an inevitable prior task. Only because Being is 'in the consciousness'-that is to say, only because it is understandable in Dasein-can Dasein also understand and conceptualize such character istics of Being as independence, the 'in-itself', and Reality in general. Only because of this are 'independent' entities, as encountered within-the- world, accessible to circumspection. If what the term "idealism" says, amounts to the understanding that Being can never be explained by entities but is already that which is 'transcendental' for every entity, then idealism affords the only correct possibility for a philosophical problematic. If so, Aristotle was no less an idealist than Kant. But if "idealism" signifies tracing back every entity to a subject or consciousness whose sole distinguishing features are that it remains indefinite in its Being and is best characterized negatively as <marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Being and Time 1.6 'un-Thing-like', then this idealism is no less naIve in its method than the most grossly militant realism. It is still possible that one may give the problematic of Reality priority over any orientation in terms of 'standpoints' by maintaining the thesis that every subject is what it is only for an Object, and vice versa. But in this formal approach the terms thus correlated-like the correlation itself -remain ontologically indefinite. At the bottom, however, the whole correlation necessarily thought of as 'somehow' being, and must therefore be thought of with regard to some definite idea of Being, Of course, if the existential-ontological basis has been made secure beforehand by exhibiting Being-in-the-world, then this correlation is one that we can know later as a formalized relation, ontologically undifferentiated. Our discussion of the unexpressed presuppositions of attempts to solve the problem of Reality in ways which are just 'epistemological', shows that this problem must be taken back, as an ontological one, into the existential analytic of Dasein. xvt<marker type="block"/> If the term "Reality" is meant to stand for the Being of entities present at-hand within-the-world (res) (and nothing else is understood thereby), then when it comes to analysing this mode of Being, this signifies that entities within-ike-world are ontologically conceivable only if the pheno menon of within-the-world-ness has been clarified. But within-the-world ness is based upon the phenomenon of the world, which, for its part, as an essential item in the structure of Being-in-the-world, belongs to the basic constitution of Dasein. Being-in-the-world, in turn, is bound up onto logically in the structural totality of Dasein's Being, and we have charac terized care as such a totality. But in this way we have marked out the foundations and the horizons which must be clarified if an analysis of Reality is to be possible. Only in this connection, moreover, does the character of the "in-itself" become ontologically intelligible. By taking our orientation from this context of problems, we have in our earlier analyses Interpreted the Being of entities within-the-world. xvtt . To be sure, the Reality of the Real can be characterized phenomen ologically within certain limits without any explicit existential-ontological basis. This is what Dilthey has attempted in the article mentioned above, He holds that the Real gets experienced in impulse and will, and that Reality is resistance, or, more exactly, the character ofresisting.1 He then works out the phenomenon of resistance analytically. This is the positive contribution of his article, and provides the best concrete substantiation</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="90">(b) Reality as an Ontological Problem</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="92">1 'Realitat ist Widerstand, genauer Widerstandigkeit.'</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx93">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62qm.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="94">II. I Being and Time 293</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" confidence="possible">249</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99">which has been devised accidentally and at random. We can restrain this arbitrariness only by giving beforehand an ontological characterization of the kind of Being in which the 'end' enters into Dasein's average every dayness. To do so, we must fully envisage those structures of everydayness which we have earlier set forth. The fact that in an existential analysis of death, existentiell possibilities of Being-towards-death are consonant with it, is implied by the essence of all ontological investigation. All the more explicitly must the existential definition of concepts be unaccompanied by any existentiell commitments, 1 especially with relation to death, in which Dasein's character as possibility lets itself be revealed most precisely. The existential problematic aims only at setting forth the ontological structure of Dasein's Being-towards--the-end. v1 <marker type="block"/> From our considerations of totality, end, and that which is still out standing, there has emerged the necessity of Interpreting the phenomenon of death as Being-towards-the-end, and of doing so in terms of Dasein's basic state. Only so can it be made plain to what extent Being-a-whole, as constituted by Being towards-the-end, is possible in Dasein itself in conformity with the structure of its Being. We have seen that care is the basic state of Dasein. The ontological signification of the expression "care" has been expressed in the 'definition': "ahead-of-itself-Being already-in (the world) as Being-alongside entities which we encounter (within-the-world)".vl1 In this are expressed the fundamental character istics of Dasein's Being: existence, in the "ahead-of-itself"; facticity, in the "Being-already-in"; falling, in the "Being-alongside". If indeed death belongs in a distinctive sense to the Being of Dasein, then death (or Being towards-the-end) must be defined in terms of these characteristics. We must, in the first instance, make plain in a preliminary sketch how Dasein's existence, facticity, and falling reveal themselves in the pheno menon of death. The Interpretation in which the "not-yet-and with it even the utter most "not-yet", the end of Dasein-was taken in the sense of something still outstanding, has been rejected as inappropriate in that it included the ontological perversion of making Dasein something present-at-hand. Being-at-an-end implies existentially Being-towards-the-end. The utter most "not-yet" has the character of something towards which Dasein comports itself. The end is impending [steht ... bevor] for Dasein. Death is not something not yet present-at-hand, nor is it that which is ultimately</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="97">, 50. Preliminary Sketch oj the Existential-ontological Structure oj Death</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="98">250</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="100">1 tUm so ausdrticklicher muss mit der existenzialen Begriffsbestimmung die existen  zielle Unverbindlichkeit zusammengehen •.•'  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx101">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62qm.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="102">lZ94 Being and Time</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" confidence="possible">still outstanding but which has been reduced to a minimum.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="104">l something that stands before us-something impending.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="105">25 1</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="129">However, there is much that can impend for Dasein as Being-in-the world. The character of impendence is not distinctive of death. On the contrary, this Interpretation could even lead us to suppose that death must be understood in the sense of some impending event encountered environmentally. For instance, a storm, the remodelling of the house, or the arrival of a friend, may be impending; and these are entities which are respectively present-at-hand, ready-to-hand, and there-with-us. The death which impends does not have this kind of Being. But there may also be impending for Dasein a journey, for instance, or a disputation with Others, or the forgoing of something of a kind which Dasein itself can be-its own possibilities of Being, which are based on its Being with Others. Death is a possibility-of-Being which Dasein itself has to take over in every case. With death, Dasein stands before itself in its ownmost poten tiality-for-Being. This is a possibility in which the issue is nothing less than Dasein's Being-in-the-world. Its death is the possibility of no-longer being-able-to-be-there. 1I If Dasein stands before itself as this possibility, it has been folly assigned to its ownmost potentiality-for-Being. When it stands before itself in this way, all its relations to any other Dasein have been undone. 3 This ownmost non-relational 4 possibility is at the same time the uttermost one. As potentiality-for-Being, Dasein cannot outstrip the possibility of death. Death is the possibility of the absolute impossibility of Dasein. Thus death reveals itself as that possibility which is one's ownmost, which is non-relational, and which is not to be outstripped [uniiberholbare]. As such, death is something distinctively impending. Its existential possibility is based on the fact that Dasein is essentially disclosed to itself, and disclosed, indeed, as ahead-of-itself. This item in the structure of care has its most primordial con cretion in Being-towards-death. As a phenomonon, Being-towards-the-end 1 '. • • sondem eher ein Belxmtand.' While we shall ordinarily use various forms of 'impend' to translate 'Bevorstand', 'bevorslehen', etc., one must bear in mind that the literal meaning of these expressions is one of 'standing before', so that they may be quite plausibly contrasted with 'Ausstehen', etc. ('standing out'). Thus we shall occasionally use forms of 'stand before' when this connotation seems to be dominant. ' II 'Nicht-mehr-dasein-konnens.' Notice that the expressions 'Seinkonnen' (our 'poten tiality-for-Being') and 'Nichtmehrdasein' (our 'no-Ionger-Dasein') are here fused. Cf. H.237- 24 2 • 3 'So sich bevorstehend sind in ihm aile Beziige zu anderem Dasein gelOst.' 4 'unbeziigliche'. This term appears frequently throughout the chapter, and, as the present passage makes clear, indicates that in death Dasein is cut off from relations with others. The term has accordingly been translated as 'non-relational', in the sense of 'devoid of relationships' • <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> I 295 becomes plainer as Being towards that distinctive possibility of Dasein which we have characterized. This ownmost possibility, however, non-relational and not to be out stripped, is not one which Dasein procures for itself subsequently and occasionally in the course of its Being. On the contrary, if Dasein exists, it has already been thrown into this possibility. Dasein does not, proximally and for the most part, have any explicit or even any theoretical knowledge of the fact that it has been delivered over to its death, and that death thus belongs to Being-in-the-world. Thrownness into death reveals itself to Dasein in a more primordial and impressive manner in that state-of-mind which we have called "anxiety". viii Anxiety in the face of death is anxiety 'in the face of' that potentiality-for-Being which is one's ownmost, non relational, and not to be outstripped. That in the face of which one has anxiety is Being-in-the-world itself. That about which one has this anxiety is simply Dasein's potentiality-for-Being. Anxiety in the face Qf death must not be confused with fear in the face of one's demise. This anxiety is not an accidental or random mood of 'weakness' in some individual; but, as a basic state-of-mind of Dascin, it amounts to the disclosedness of the fact that Dasein exists as thrown Being towards its end. Thus the existential conception of "dying" is made clear as thrown Being towards its ownmost potentiality-for-Being, which is non-relational and not to be outstripped. Precision is gained by distinguishing this from pure dis appearance, and also from merely perishing, and finally from the 'Experi encing' of a demise. l Being-towards-the-end docs not first arise through some attitude which occasionally emerges, nor does it arise as such an attitude; it belongs essentially to Dasein's thrownness, which reveals itself in a state-of-mind (mood) in one way or another. The factical 'knowledge' or 'ignorance' which prevails in any Dasein as to its ownmost Being-towards-the-end, is only the expression of the existentiell possibility that there are different ways of maintaining oneself in this Being. Factically, there are many who, proximally and for the most part, do not know about death; but this must not be passed off as a ground for proving that Being-towards-death does not belong to Dasein 'universally'. It only proves that proximally and for the most part Dasein covers up its ownmost Bcing-towards-death, fleeing in the Jace of it. Factically, Dasein is dying as long as it exists, but proximally and for the most part, it does so by way ofJailing. For factical existing is not only generally and without further differentiation a thrown poten tiality-for-Being-in-the-world, but it has always likewise been absorbed in the 'world' of its concern. In this falling Being-alongside, fleeing from<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> uncanniness announces itself; and this means now, a fleeing in the face of one's ownmost Being-towards-death. Existence, facticity, and falling characterize Being-towards-the-end, and are therefore constitutive for the existential conception of death. As regards its ontological possibility, dying is<marker type="block"/> But if Being-towards-death belongs primordially and essentially to Dasein's Being, then it must also be exhibitable in everydayness, even if proximally in a way which is inauthentic. 1 And if Being-towards-the-end should afford the existential possibility of an existentiell Being-a-whole for Dasein, then this would give phenomenal confirmation for the thesis that "care" is the ontological term for the totality of Dasein's structural whole. If, however, we are to provide a full phenomenal justification for this principle, a preliminary sketch of the connection between Being-towards death and care is not sufficient. We must be able to see this connection above all in that concretion which lies closest to Dasein-its everydayness.<marker type="block"/> , 51. Being-towards-death and the Everydayness of Dasein In setting forth average everyday Being-towards-death, we must take our orientation from those structures of everydayness at which we have earlier arrived. In Being-towards-death, Dasein comports itself towards itself as a distinctive potentiality-for-Being. But the Self of everydayness is the "they".1x The "they" is constituted by the way things have been publicly interpreted, which expresses itself in idle talk. 2 Idle talk must accordingly make manifest the way in which everyday Dasein interprets for itself its Being-towards-death. The foundation of any interpretation is an act of understanding, which is always accompanied by a state-of mind, or, in other words, which has a mood. So we must ask how Being towards-death is disclosed by the kind of understanding which, with its state-of-mind, lurks in the idle talk of the "they". How does the "they" comport itself understandingly towards that ownmost possibility ofDasein, which is non-relational and is not to be outstripped? What state-of-mind discloses to the "they" that it has been delivered over to death, and in what way? In the publicness with which we are with one another in our everyday manner, death is 'known' as a mishap which is constantly occurring-as a 'case of death'. 3 Someone or other 'dies', be he neighbour or stranger 1 ' ••• dann muss es auch-wenngleich zunachst uneigentlich-in der Alltaglichkei t aufweisbar sein.' The earlier editions have another 'auch' just before 'in der Alltaglichkeit'. II ' ••• das sich in der offentlichen Ausgelegtheit konstituiert, die sich im Gerede auss pricht.' The earlier editions have ' .•. konstituiert. Sie spricht sich aus im Gerede.' :I 'Die Offentlichkeit des alltaglichen Miteinander "kennt" den Tod als standigivor kommendes Begegnis, als "Todesfall".'<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> [Nachste oder Fernerstehende]. People who are no acquaintances of ours are 'dying' daily and hourly. 'Death' is encountered as a well-known event . occurring within-the-world. As such it remains in the inconspicuousnessx characteristic of what is encountered in an everyday fashion. The "they" has already stowed away [gesichert] an interpretation for this event. It talks of it in a 'fugitive' manner, either expressly or else in a way which is mostly inhibited, as if to say, "One of these days one will die too, in the end; but right now it has nothing to do with US."l The analysis of the phrase 'one dies' reveals unambiguously the kind of Being which belongs to everyday Being-towards-death. In such a way of talking, death is understood as an indefinite something which, above all, must duly arrive from somewhere or other, but which is proximally not yet present-at-hand for oneself, and is therefore no threat. The expression 'one dies' spreads abroad the opinion that what gets reached, as it were, by death, is the "they". In Dasein's public way of interpreting, it is said that 'one dies', because everyone else and oneself can talk himself into saying that "in no case is it I myself", for this "one" is the "nobody".z 'Dying' is levelled off to an occurrence which reaches Dasein, to be sure, but belongs to nobody in particular. If idle talk is always ambiguous, so is this manner of talking about death. Dying, which is essentially mine in such a way that no one can be my representative, is perverted into an event of public occurrence which the "they" encounters. In the way of talking which we have characterized, death is spoken of as a 'case' which is constantly occurring. Death gets passed off as always something 'actual' ; its character as a possibility gets concealed, and so are the other two items that belong to it-the fact that it is non-relational and that it is not to be outstripped. By such ambiguity, Dasein puts itself in the position oflosing itselfin the "they" as regards a distinctive potentiality-for-Being which belongs to Dasein's ownmost Self. The "they" gives its approval, and aggravates the temptation to cover up from oneself one's ownmost This evasive concealment in the face of death U1UlUi;ues everydayness so stubbornly that, in Being with one another, the often still keep talking the 'dying person' into the belief that will escape death and soon return to the tranquillized everydayness of world of his concern. Such 'solicitude' is meant to 'console' him. It upon bringing him back into Dasein, while in addition it helps him<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> to keep his owrunost non-relational possibility-of-Being completely con cealed. In this manner the "they" provides [besorgt] a constant tion about death. At bottom, however, this is a tranquillization not only for him who is 'dying' but just as much for those who 'console' him. And even in the case of a demise, the public is still not to have its own tranquillity upset by such an event, or be disturbed in the carefreeness with which it concerns itself.l Indeed the dying of Others is seen often enough as a social inconvenience, if not even a downright tactlessness, against which the public is to be guarded. xU But along with this tranquillization, which forces Dasein away from its death, the "they" at the same time puts itself in the right and makes itself respectable by tacitly regulating the way inwhich one has to comport oneself towards death. It is already a matter of public acceptance that 'thinking about death' is a cowardly fear, a sign of insecurity on the part of Dasein, and a somhre way of fleeing from the world. The "they" does not permit us the courage for anxiery in the face of death. The dominance of the manner in which things have been publicly interpreted by the "they", has already decided what state-of-mind is to determine our attitude towards death. In anxiety in the face of death, Dasein is brought face to face with itself as delivered over to that possibility which is not to be outstripped. The "they" concerns itself with transforming this anxiety into fear in the face of an oncoming event. In addition, the anxiety which has been made ambiguous as fear, is passed off as a weakness with which no self-assured Dasein may have any acquaintance. What is 'fitting' [Was sich ... "gehort"] according to the unuttered decree of the "they", is indifferent tranquillity as to the 'fact' that one dies. The cultivation of such a 'superior' indifference alienates Dasein from its owrunost non relational potentiality-for-Being. But temptation, tranquillization, and alienation are distinguishing marks of the kind of Being called ''falling''. As falling, everyday Being towards-death is a constant fleeing in the face oj death. Being-towardr-the-end has the mode of evasion in the face oj it--giving new explanations for understanding it inauthentically, and concealing it. Factically one's own Dasein is always dying already; that is to say, it is in a Being-towards its-end. And it hides this Fact from itself by r~coining "death" as just a "case of death" in Others-an everyday occurrence which, if need be, gives us the assurance still more plainly that 'oneself' is still 'living'. But in thus falling and fleeing in the face oj death, Dasein's everydayness attests that the very "they" itself already has the definite character of</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx107">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62qm.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="108">II. Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="109">25</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="110">2</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="112">1 ' .•• gegen eill "Erlcbell" des Ablebens.' (Cf. Section 49 above.)</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="113">Being and Time II. I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="115">grounded in care.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="117">253</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx119">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62qm.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="120">II. I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="121">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="122">297</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="123">!.....</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="125">1 ' ••. man stirbt am Ende auch einmal, aber zunachst bleibt man selbst unbetroffen.' a 'Die offentliche Daseinsauslegung sagt: "man stirbt", wei! damit jeder andere und selbst sich einreden kann: je nicht gerade ich; denn dieses Man ist das Niemand.' we have usually followed the convention of translating the indefinite pronoun 'one' and the expression 'das Man' as 'the "they" " to do so here would obscure pomt.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="126">298 Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="127">254</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="128">II. I II. I Being and Time 299 Being-towardr-death, tranquilliza Even in average everydayness, this ownmost potentiality-jor-Being, which is non-relational and not to be outstripped, is constantly an issue for Dasein. This is the case when its concern is merely in the mode ofan untroubled indifference towards   the uttermost possibility of existence. 1  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible">1 'Und selbst im Falle des Ablebens noch soli die Offentlichkeit durch das Ereignis nicht in ihrer besorgten Sorglosigkeit gestart und beunruhigt werden.'</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx131">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62qm.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="132" confidence="possible">even when it is not explicitly engaged in 'thinking about</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="133">255</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" confidence="possible">death'.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="135">face</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136">In setting forth everyday Being-towards-death, however, we are at the same time enjoined to try to secure a full existential conception of Being towards-the-end, by a more penetrating Interpretation in which fulling Being-towards-death is taken as an evasion in the face of death. That in the oj which oneflees has been made visible in a way which is phenomenally adequate. Against this it must be possible to project phenomenologically the way in which evasive Dasein itself understands its death.xm</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="137" confidence="possible">52.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="138">Everyday Being-towardr-the-end, and the Full Existential Conception of   Death  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142">In our preliminary existential sketch, Being-towards-the-end has been defined as Being towards one's owrunost potentiality-for-Being, which is non-relational and is not to be outstripped. Being towards this possibility, as a Being which exists, is brought face to face with the absolute impos sibility of existence. Beyond this seemingly empty characterization of Being-towards-death, there has been revealed the concretion of this Being in the mode of everydayness. In accordance with the tendency to falling, which is essential to everydayness, Being-towards-death has turned out to be an evasion in the face of death-an evasion which conceals. While our investigation has hitherto passed from a formal sketch of the ontological structure of death to the concrete analysis of everyday Being-towards-the end, the direction is now to be reversed, and we shall arrive at the full existential conception of death by rounding out our Interpretation of everyday Being-towards-the-end. In explicating everyday Being-towards-death we have clung to the idle talk of the "they" to the effect that "one dies too, sometime, but not right away.'" All that we have Interpreted thus far is the 'one dies' as such. In the 'sometime, but not right away', everydayness concedes something like a certainry of death. Nobody doubts that one dies. On the other hand, this 'not doubting' need not imply that kind of Being-certain which corre sponds to the way death-in the sense of the distinctive possibility char acterized above--enters into Dasein. Everydayness confines itself to 1 ' ••• wenn auch nUT im Modus des Besorgens einer unbehelligten Gleichgiiltigkeit gegea dill Iiluserste M oglichkeit seiner Existenz.' Ordinarily the expression 'Gleichgiiltigkeit gegen' means simply 'indifference towards'. But Heidcgger's use of boldface type suggests that here he also has in mind that 'gegen' may mean 'against' or 'in opposition to'. l! ' ••• man stirbt auch einmal, aber vorlaufig noch nicht.' <marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> conceding the 'certainty' of death in this ambiguous manner just in order to weaken that certainty by covering up dying still more and to alleviate its own thrownness into death. By its very meaning, this evasive concealment in the face of death can not be authentically 'certain' of death, and yet it is certain of it. What are we to say about the 'certainty of death'? To be certain of an entity means to hold it for true as something true.! But "truth" signifies the uncoveredness of some entity, and all uncovered ness is grounded ontologically in the most primordial truth, the disclosed ness of Dasein.xlv As an entity which is both disclosed and disclosing, and one which uncovers, Dasein is essentially 'in the truth'. But certainty is grounded in the truth, or belongs to it equiprimordially. The expression 'certainty', like the term 'truth', has a double signification. Primordially "truth" means the same as "Being-disclosive", as a way in which Dasein behaves. From this comes the derivative signification: "the uncovered ness of entities". Correspondingly, "certainty", in its primordial signification, is tantamount to "Being-certain", as a kind of Being which belongs to Dasein. However, in a derivative signification, any entity of which Dasein can be certain will also get called something 'certain'. One mode of certainty is conviction. In conviction, Dasein lets the testi mony of the thing itself which has been uncovered (the true thing itself) 2 be the sole determinant for its Being towards that thing understandingly. Holding something for true is adequate as a way of maintaining oneself in the truth, if it is grounded in the uncovered entity itself, and if, as Being towards the entity so uncovered, it has become transparent to itself as regards its appropriateness to that entity. In any arbitrary fiction or in merely having some 'view' ["Ansicht"] about an entity, this sort of is lacking. The adequacy of holding-for-true is measured according to the truth claim to which it belongs. Such a claim gets its justification from the kind of Being of the entity to be disclosed, and from the direction of the dis closure. The kind of truth, and along with it, the certainty, varies with the way entities differ, and accords with the guiding tendency and extent of the disclosure. Our present considerations will be restricted to an</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="140">Being and Time II. I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="141">3 00</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" confidence="possible">1 'Eines Seienden gewiss-sein besagt: es als wahres fur wahr halten.' The earlier editions have 'Gewisssein' instead of 'gewiss-sein'. Our literal but rather unidiomatic translation of the phrase 'fUr wahr halten' seems desirable in view of Heidegger's extensive use of the verb 'halten' ('hold') in subsequent where this phrase occurs, though this is obscured by our translating 'halten in .. .' as 'maintain itself in .• .' and 'halten sich an .. .' as 'cling to .. .' or 'stick to .. .'. l1. 'In ihr lasst sich das Dasein durch das Zeugnis der entdeckten (wahre) Sache selbst sein verstehendcs Sein zu dieser bestimmen.' The connection between 'Vberzeu gung' (,conviction') and 'Zeugnis' (testimony) is obscured in our translation.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx144">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62qm.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="145">II. Being and Time</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="146">257</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163">I 3 0 ! analysis of Being-certain with regard to death; and this Being-certain will in the end present us with a distinctive certainty ofDasein. For the most part, everyday Dasein covers up the ownmost possibility of its Being-that possibility which is non-relational and not to be out stripped. This factical tendency to cover up confirms our thesis that Dasein, as factical, is in the 'untruth'.xv Therefore the certainty which belongs to such a covering-up of Being-towards-death must be an inappropriate way of holding-for-true, and not, for instance, an uncertainty in the sense of a doubting. In inappropriate certainty, that of which one is certain is held covered up. If 'one' understands death as an event which one encounters in one's environment, then the certainty which is related to such events does not pertain to Being-towards-the-end. They say, "It is certain that 'Death' is coIning.'! They say it, and the "they" overlooks the fact that in order to be able to be certain of death, Dasein itself must in every case be certain of its ownmost non relational potentiality-for-Being. They say, "Death is certain"; and in saying so, they implant in Dasein the illusion that it is itself certain of its death. And what is the ground of everyday Being-certain? Manifestly, it is not just mutual persuasion. Yet the 'dying' of Others is something that one experiences daily. Death is an undeniable 'fuct of experience' . The way in which everyday Being-towards-death understands the certainty which is thus grounded, betrays itself when it tries to 'think' about death, even when it does so with critical foresight-that is to say, in an appropriate manner. So far as one knows, all men 'die'. Death is probable in the highest degree for everyman, yet it is not 'unconditionally' certain. Taken strictly, a certainty which is 'only' empirical may be attri buted to death. Such certainty necessarily falls short of the highest certainty, the apodictic, which we reach in certain domains of theoretical 'knowledge. In this 'critical' determination of the certainty of death, and of its impendence, what is manifested in the first instance is, once again, a failure to recognize Dasein's kind of Being and the Being-towards-death which belongs to Dasein-a failure that is characteristic of everydayness. <marker type="block"/> way decisive as to the certainty of death. Cases of death may be the factical occasion for Dasein's first paying attention to death at all. So long, however, as Dasein remains in the empirical certainty which we have mentioned, death, in the way that it 'is', is something ofwhich Dasein can by no means become certain. Even though, in the publicness of the "they", Dasein<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 3°2 seems to 'talk' only of this 'empirical' certainty of death, neverthele.fs bottom Dasein does not exclusively or primarily stick to those cases of death which merely occur. In evading its death, even everyday Being. towards-the-end is indeed certain of its death in another way than it might itself like to have true on purely theoretical considerations. This 'other way' is what everydayness for the most part veils from itself. Every dayness does not dare to let itself become transparent in such a manner. We have already characterized the every-day state-of-mind which consists in an air of superiority with regard to the certain 'fact' ofdeath-a super iority which is 'anxiously' concerned while seemingly free from anxiety. In this state-of-mind, everydayness acknowledges a 'higher' certainty than one which is only empirical. One knows about the certainty of death, and yet 'is' not authentically certain of one's own. The falling everydayness of Dasein is acquainted with death's certainty, and yet evades Being-certain. But in the light of what it evades, this very evasion attests phenomenally that death must be conceived as one's ownmost possibility, non-relational, not to be outstripped, and-above all--certain. One says, "Death certainly comes, but not right away". With this 'but .• .', the "they" denies that death is certain. 'Not right away' is not a purely negative assertion, but a way in which the "they" interprets itself. With this interpretation, the "they" refers itself to that which is proximally accessible to Dasein and amenable to its concern. Everyday ness forces its way into the urgency of concern, and divests itself of the fetters of a weary 'inactive thinking about death'. Death is deferred to 'sometime later', and this is done by invoking the so-called 'general opinion' ["allgemeine Ermessen"]. Thus the "they" covers up what is peculiar in death's certainty-that it is possible at any moment. Along with the certainty of death goes the indefiniteness of its' 'when". Everyday Being towards-death evades this indefiniteness by conferring definiteness upon it. But such a procedure cannot signify calculating when the demise is due to arrive. In the face of definiteness such as this, Dasein would sooner flee. Everyday concern makes definite for itself the indefiniteness ofcertain death by interposing before it those urgencies and possibilities which can be taken in at a glance, and which belong to the everyday matters that are closest to us. But when this indefiniteness has been covered up, the certainty has been covered up too. Thus death's ownmost character as a possibility gets veiled-a possibility which is certain and at the same time indefinite that is to say, possible at any moment. Now that we have completed our Interpretation of the everyday manner in which the "they" talks about death and the way death enters<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 3 0 3 into Dasein, we have been led to the characters ofcertainty and indefinite ness. The full existential-ontological conception of death may now be defined as follows: death, as the eTid of Dasein, is Dasein's Ownmost possibilifJ 7,lon-relational, certain and as such indefinite, not to be outstripped. Death is, as Dasein's end, in the Being of this entity towards its end. Defining the existential structure of Being-towards-the-end helps us to work out a kind of Being of Dasein in which Dasein, as Dasein, can be a whole. The fact that even everyday Dasein already is towards its end-that is to say, is constantly coming to grips with its death, though in a 'fugitive' manner-shows that this end, conclusive [abschliessende] and determina tive for Being-a-whole, is not something to which Dasein ultimately comes only in its demise. In Dasein, as being towards its death, its own utter most "not-yet" has already been included-that "not-yet" which all others lie ahead of. 1 So if one has given an ontologically inappropriate Interpretation of Dasein's "not-yet" as something still outstanding, any formal inference from this to Dasein's lack of totality will not be correct. The phenomenon of the "not-yet" has been taken over from the "ahead-of-itself"; no more than the care-structure in general, can it serve as a higher court which would rule against the possibilifJ of an existent Being-a-whole,. indeed this "ahead-of itself" is what first of all makes such a Being-towards-the-end possible. The problem of the possible Being-a-whole of that entity which each of us is, is a correct one if care, as Dasein's basic state, is 'connected' with death -the uttermost possibility for that entity. Meanwhile, it remains questionable whether this problem has been as yet adequately worked out. Being-towards-death is grounded in care. Dasein, as thrown Being-in-the-world, has in every case already been delivered over to its death. In being towards its death, Dasein is dying factically and indeed constantly, as long as it has not yet come to its demise. When we say that Dasein is factically dying, we are saying at the same time that in its Being-towards-death Dasein has always decided itself in one way or another. Our everyday falling evasion in the face of death is an inauthentic Being-towards-death. But inauthenticity is based on the pos· sibiIity of authenticity.xvi Inauthenticity characterizes a kind of Being into which Dasein can divert itself and has for the most part always diverted itself; but Dasein does not necessarily and constantly have to divert itself into this kind of Being. Because Dasein exists, it determines its 1 ' • • • dem aUe anderen vorgelagert sind .. .' This clause is ambiguous, both in the German and in our translation, though the point is fairly clear. The ultimate 'noJt-yet' is !lot one which all others 'lie ahead of' in the sense that they lie beyond it or come after It; for nothing can 'lie ahead of it' in this sense. But they can 'lie ahead of it' in the sense that they might be actualized before the ultimate 'not-yet' has beer. actualized. (Contrast passage with H. 302, where the same participle 'vorgc1agert' is apparently applied In the former sense to &lt;l,eath itself.)<marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 3 0 4 own character as the kind of entity it is, and it does so in every case in terms of a possibility which it itself is and which it understands. 1 Can Dasein also understand authentically its ownmost possibility, which is non-relational and not to be outstripped, which is certain and, as such, indefinite? That is, can Dasein maintain itself in an authentic Being towards-its-end? As long as this authentic Being-towards-death has not been set forth and ontologically defined, there is something essentially lacking in our existential Interpretation of Being-towards-the-end. Authentic Being-towards-death signifies an existentiell possibility of Dasein. This on tical potentiality-for-Being must, in turn, be ontologically possible. What are the existential conditions of this possibility? How are they themselves to become accessible?<marker type="block"/> , 53. Existential Projection of an Authentic Being-towards-death Factically, Dasein maintains itself proximally and for the most part in an inauthentic Being-towards-death. How is the ontological possibility of an authentic Being-towards-death to be characterized 'Objectively', if, in the end, Dasein never comports itself authentically towards its end, or if, in accordance with its very meaning, this authentic Being must remain hidden from the Others? Is it not a fanciful undertaking, to project the existential possibility of so questionable an existentiell potentiality-for Being? What is needed, if such a projection is to go beyond a merely fictitious arbitrary construction? Does Dasein itself give us any instruc tions for carrying it out? And can any grounds for its phenomenal legitimacy be taken from Dasein itself? Can our analysis of Dasein up to this point us any prescriptions for the ontological task we have now set ourselves, so that what we have before us may be kept on a road of which we can be sure? The existential conception of death has been established; and therewith we have also established what it is that an authentic Being-towards-the end should be able to comport itself towards. We have also characterized inauthentic Being-towards-death, and thus we have prescribed in a negative way [prohibitiv] how it is possible for authentic Being-towards death not to be. It is with these positive and prohibitive instructions that the existential edifice of an authentic Being-towards-death must let itself be projected. Dasein is constituted by disclosedness-that is, by an understanding with a state-of-mind. Authentic Being-towards-death can not evade its own most non-relational possibility, or cover up this possibility by thus fleeing 1 'Weil das Dasein eXlStJert, bestimmt es sich aIs Seiendes, wie es ist, je aus einer Moglichkeit, die es selbst is! und versteht.'</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="148">The fact that demise, as an event which occurs, is 'only' empirically certain, is in no</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="150">1 'Man sagt: es ist gewiss, class "der" Too kommt.'</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="151">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="152">II. I at.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="153">25 8</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx155">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62qm.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="156">II. I Being and Time</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="157">259</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="159">Being and Time</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="160">II. I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="161">260</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx164">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_019.image_19.png" thmb="62qm.page_019.image_19-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="165">II. I Being and Time</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="166">261</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="167" confidence="possible">3 0 5   from it, or give a new explanatioll for it to accord with the common sense of   the "they". In our existential projection of an authentic Being-towards  death, therefore, we must set forth those items in such a Being which are   constitutive for it as an understanding of death-and as such an under  standing in the sense of Being towards this possibility without either   fleeing it or covering it up.   In the first instance, we must characterize Being-towards-death as a Being towards a possibility-indeed, towards a distinctive possibility of Dasein itself. "Being towards" a possibility-that is to say, towards some thing possible--may signify "Being out for" something possible, as in concerning ourselves with its actualization. Such possibilities are con stantly encountered in the field of what is ready-to-hand and present-at hand-what is attainable, controllable, practicable, and the like. In concernfully Being out for something possible, there is a tendency to annihilate the possibility of the possible by making it available to us. But the concernful actualization of equipment which is ready-to-hand (as in producing it, getting it ready, readjusting it, and so on) is always merely relative, since even that which has been actualized is still characterized in terms of some involvements- indeed this is precisely what characterizes its Being. Even though actualized, it remains, as actual, something pos sible for doing something; it is characterized by an "in-order-to". What our analysis is to make plain is simply how Being out for something con cernfully, comports itself towards the possible: it does so not by the theoretico-thematical consideration of the possible as possible, and by lnlving regard for its possibility as such, but rather by looking circum spectively away from the possible and looking at that for which it is possible [das Wofur-moglich]. Manifestly Being-towards-death, which is now in question, cannot have   the character of concernfully Being out to get itself actualized. For one   thing, death as possible is not something possible which is ready-to-hand   or present-at-hand, but a possibility of Dasein's Being. So to concern   . oneself with actualizing what is thus possible would have to signify, . "bringing about one's demise". But if this were done, Dasein would deprive itself of the very gro-und for an existing Being-towards-death. Thus, ifby "Being towards death" we do not have in view an 'actuali  zing' of death, neither can we mean "dwelling upon the end in its pos  sibility". This is the way one comports oneself when one 'thinks about   death', pondering over when and how this possibility may perhaps be   actualized. Of course such brooding over death does not fully take away   from it its character as a possibility. Indeed, it always gets brooded over as   something that is coming; but in such brooding we weaken it by calculating  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" confidence="possible">g06   Being and Time II. I how we are to have it at our disposal. As something possible, it is to show as little as possible of its possibility. On the other hand, if Being towards-death has to disclose understandingly the possibility which we have characterized, and if it is to disclose it as a possibility, then in such Being-towards-death this possibility must not be weakened: it must be understood as a possibility, it must be cultivated as a possibility, and we must put up with it as a possibility, in the way we comport ourselves towards it. However, Dasein comports itself towards something possible in its possibility by expecting it [im ErwartenJ. Anyone who is intent on something 262   possible, may encounter it unimpeded and undiminished in its 'whether it comes or does not, or whether it comes after all'. 1 But with this pheno menon of expecting, has not our analysis reached the same kind of Being towards the possible to which we have already called attention in our description of "Being out for something" concernfully? To expect some thing possible is always to understand it and to 'have' it with regard to whether and when and how it will be actually present-at-hand. Expecting is not just an occasional looking-away from the possible to its possible actualization, but is essentially a waiting for that actualization [ein Warten auf diesel. Even in expecting, one leaps away from the possible and gets a foothold in the actual. It is for its actuality that what is expected is expected. By the very nature of expecting, the possible is drawn into the 2 actual, arising out of the actual and returning to it. But Being towards this possibility, as Being-towards-death, is so to comport ourselves towards death that in this Being, and for it, death reveals itself as a possibility. Our terminology for such Being towards this possibility is "anticipation" of this possibility. 3 But in this way of behaving does there not lurk a coming-close to the possible, and when one is close to the possible, does not its actualization emerge? In this kind of coming close, however, one does not tend towards concernfully making available something actual; but as one comes closer understandingly, the pos sibility of the possible just becomes 'greater'. The closest closeness which one may have in Being towards death as a possibility, is asfar as possible from anything</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible">1 'Fur ein Gespanntsein auf es vermag ein Mogliches in seinem "ob oder nicht oder schliesslich doch" ungehindert und ungeschmalert zu begegnen.' II 'Auch im Erwarten liegt ein Abspringen vom Moglichen und Fussfassen im Wirk lichen, dafur das Erwartete erwartet ist. Vom Wirklichen aus und auf es zu wird das Mogliche in das Wirkliche erwartungsmii.ssig hereingezogen.' 3 ' ••• Vorlatifen in die Moglichkeit.' While we have used 'anticipate' to translate 'vor greifen', which occurs rather seldom, we shall also use literally-to translate 'vorlaufen', which appears very often in the following pages, which has the special connotation of 'running ahead'. But as Heidegger's remarks have indicated, the kind of 'anticipation' which is involved in Being-towards-death, does not consist in 'waiting for' death or 'dwelling upon it' or 'actualizing' it before it normally comes; nor does 'running ahead into it' in this sense mean that we 'rush headlong into it'.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx170">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_020.image_20.png" thmb="62qm.page_020.image_20-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="171">II. I Being and Time  </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="172">g07</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible">263</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="193">actual. The more unveiledly this possibility gets understood, the more purely does the understanding penetrate into it as the possibility of the impossibility ofany existence at all. Death, as possibility, gives Dasein nothing to be 'actualized', nothing which Dasein, as actual, could itself be. It is the possibility of the impossibility of every way of comporting oneself towards anything, of every way of existing. In the anticipation of this possibility it becomes 'greater and greater'; that is to say, the possibility reveals itself to be such that it knows no measure at all, no more or less, but signifies the possibility of the measureless impossibility of existence. In accordance with its essence, this possibility offers no support for becoming intent on something, 'picturing' to oneself the actuality which is possible, and so forgetting its possibility. Being-towards-death, as anti cipation of possibility, is what first makes this possibility possible, and sets it free as possibility. Being-towards-death is the anticipation of a potentiality-for-Being of that entity whose kind of Being is anticipation itself.l In the anticipatory revealing of this potentiality-for-Being, Dasein discloses itself to itself as regards its uttermost possibility. But to project itself on its ownmost potentiality-for-Being means to be able to understand itself in the Being of the entity so revealed-namely, to exist. Anticipation turns out to be the possibility of understanding one's ownmost and uttermost potentiality far-Being-that is to say, the possibility of authentic existence. The ontological constitution of such existence must be made visible by setting forth the concrete structure of anticipation of death. How are we to delimit this structure phenomenally? Manifestly, we must do so by determining those characteristics which must belong to an anticipatory disclosure so that it can become the pure understanding of that ownmost possibility which is non-relational and not to be outstripped-which is certain and, as such, indefinite. It must be noted that understanding does not primarily mean just gazing at a meaning, but rather understanding oneself in that poten tiality-for-Being which reveals itself in projection. XVIi Death is Dasein's ownmost possibility. Being towards this possibility dis closes to Dasein its ownmost potentiality-for-Being,in which its very Being is the issue. Here it can become manifest to Dasein that in this distinctive possibility of its own self, it has been wrenched away from the "they". This means that in anticipation any Dasein can have wrenched itself away from the "they" already. But when one understands that this is something Dasein 'can' have done, this only reveals its facticallostness in the everydayness of the they-self. 1 ' ••• dessen Seinsart das Vorlaufen selbst i5t.' The earlier editions have 'hat' instead of'ist'. <marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 308 Being and Time II. I The vyvIlmost possibility is non-relational. Anticipation allows Dasein to understand that that potentiality-for-being in which its ownmost Being is an issue, must be taken over by Dasein alone. Death does not just 'belong' to one's own Dasein in an undifferentiated way; death lays claim to it as an individual Dasein. The non-relational character of death, as understood in anticipation, individualizes Dasein down to itself. This individualizing is a way in which the 'there' is disclosed for existence. It makes manifest that all Being-alongside the things with which we concern ourselves, and all Being-with Others, will fail us when our ownmost potentiality-for Being is the issue. Dasein can be authentically itself only if it makes this possible for itself of its own accord. But if concern and solicitude fail us, this does not signify at all that these ways of Dasein have been cut off from its authentically Being-its-Self. As structures essential to Dasein's constitution, these have a share in conditioning the possibility of any existence whatsoever. Dasein is authentically itself only to the extent that, as concernful Being-alongside and solicitous Being-with, it projects itself upon its ownmost potentiality-for-Being rather than upon the possibility of the they-self. The entity which anticipates its non-relational possibility, is thus forced by that very anticipation into the possibility of taking over .from itself its ownmost Being, and doing so of its own accord. The ownmost, non-relational possibility is not to be outstripped. Being towards this possibility enables Dasein to understand that giving itself up impends for it as the uttermost possibility of its existence. Anticipation, however, unlike inauthentic Being-towards-death, does not evade the fact that death is not to be outstripped; instead, anticipation frees itself for accepting this. When, by anticipation, one becomes free for one's own death, one is liberated from one's lostness in those possibilities which may accidentally thrust themselves upon one; and one is liberated in such a way that for the first time one can authentically understand and choose among the factical possibilities lying ahead of that possibility which is not to be outstripped. l Anticipation discloses to existence that its utter most possibility lies in giving itself up, and thus it shatters all one's tena ciousness to whatever existence one has reached. In anticipation, Dasein guards itself against falling back behind itself, or behind the potentiality for-Being which it has understood. It guards itself against 'becoming too old for its victories' (Nietzsche). Free for its ownmost possibilities, which are determined by the end and so are understood asfinite [endliche], Dasein dispels the danger that it may, by its own finite understanding ofexistence, fail to recognize that it is getting outstripped by the existence-possibilities of Others, or rather that it may explain these possibilities wrongly and<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> II. I Being and Time 3 0 9 force them back upon its own, so that it may divest itself of its ownmost factical existence. As the non-relational possibility, death individualizes -but only in such a manner that,as the possibility which is not tobe out stripped, it makes Dasein, as Being-with, have some understanding of the potentiality-for-Being ofOthers. Since anticipation ofthe possibility which is not to be outstripped discloses also all the possibilities which lie ahead of that possibility, this anticipation includes the possibility of taking the whole of Dasein in advance [Vorwegnehmens] in an existentiell manner; that is to say, it includes the possibility of existing as a whole potentiality<marker type="block"/> The ownmost, non-relational possibility, which is not to be outstripped, is certain. The way to be certain of it is determined by the kind of truth which corresponds to it (disclosedness). The certain possibility of death, however, discloses Dasein as a possibility, but does so only in such a way that, in anticipating this possibility, Dasein makes this possibility possible for itself as its ownmost potentiality-for-Being. l The possibility is disclosed because it is made possible in anticipation. To maintain oneself in this truth-that is, to be certain of what has been disclosed-demands all the more that one should anticipate. We cannot compute the certainty of death by ascertaining how many cases of death we encounter. ThIS certainty is by no means of the kind which maintains itself in the truth of the present-at-hand. When something present-at-hand has been un covered, it is encountered most purely if we just look at the entity and let it be encountered in itself. Dasein must first have lost itself in the factual circumstances [Sachverhalte] (this can be one of care's own tasks and possibilities) if it is to obtain the pure objectivity-that is to say, the indifference-of apodictic evidence. If Being-certain in relation to death does not have this character, this does not mean that it is ofa lower grade, but that it does not belong at all to the graded order of the kinds ofevidence we can<marker type="block"/> Holding death for true (death is just one's pwn) shows another kind of certainty, and is more primordial than any certainty which relates to entities encountered within-the-world, or to formal objects; for it is certain of Being-in-the-world. As such, holding death for true does not deInand just one definite kind of behaviour in Dasein, but deInands Dasein 1 'Die gewisse Moglichkeit des Todes erschliesst das Dasein aber als Moglichkeit nur so, dass es vorlaufend zu ihr diese Mtiglichkeit als eigenstes Seinkonnen fUr sich ermiig lieht.' While we have taken 'Die gewisse Mtiglichkcit des Todes' as the subject of this puzzling sentence, 'das Dasein' may be the subject instead. The use of the preposition 'zu' lllstead of the usual 'in' after 'vorlaufend' suggests that in 'anticipating' the possibility of death, Dasdn is here thought of as 'running ahead' towards it or up to it rather than into it. this construction occurs in later passages, we shall indicate it by subjoining 'zu' 1ll brackets.<marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> itself in the full authenticity of its existence. In anticipation Dasein can first make certain of its ownmost Being in its totality-a totality which is not to be outstripped. Therefore the evidential character which belongs to the immediate givenness of Experiences, of the "I", or of consciousness, must necessarily lag behind the certainty which anticipa tion includes. Yet this is not because the way in which these are grasped would not be a rigorous one, but because in principle such a way of grasping them cannot holdfor true (disclosed) something which at bottom it insists upon 'having there' as true: namely, Dasein itself, which I myself am, and which, as a potentiality-for-Being, I can be authentically only by anticipation. The ownmost possibility, which is non-relational, not to be outstripped, and certain, is indefinite as regards its certainty. How does anticipation disclose this characteristic of Dasein's distinctive possibility? How does the anticipatory understanding project itself upon a potentiality-for-Being which is certain and which is constantly possible in such a way that the "when" in which the utter impossibility of existence becomes possible remains constantly indefinite? In anticipating [zum] the indefinite certainty of death, Dasein opens itself to a constant threat arising out of its own "there". In this very threat Being-towards-the-end must maintain itself. So little can it tone this down that it must rather cultivate the indefiniteness of the certainty. How is it existentially possible for this constant threat to be genuinely disclosed? All understanding is accom panied by a state-of-mind. Dasein's mood brings it face to face with the thrownness of its 'that it is there' .xix But the state-oj-mind which can hold open the utter and constant threat to itself arisingfrom Dasein's ownmost individual ized Being, is anxiety.xx 1 In this state-of-mind, Dasein finds itselfface to face with the "nothing" of the possible impossibility of its existence. Anxiety is anxious about the potentiality-for-Being of the entity so destined [des so bestimmten Seienden], and in this way it discloses the uttermost pos sibility. Anticipation utterly individualizes Dasein, and allows it, in this individualization of itself, to become certain of the totality of its potenti ality-for-Being. For this reason, anxiety as a basic state-of-mind belongs 2 to such a self-understanding of Dasein on the basis of Dasein itself. Being-towards-death is essentially anxiety. This is attested unmistakably, though 'only' indirectly, by Being-towards-death as we have described it, 1 'Die Befouilichkeit abet', welclze die stiindige und schlechthinnige, GUS dem eigensten vereinzelten Sein des Dasiens auftteigende Bedrohung seiner selbst offen zu halten vermag, ist die Angst.' Notice that 'weicht' may be construed either as the subject or as the direct object of the relative clause. ' 2 '. • • gehort zu diesem Sichverstehen des Daseins am seinem Grunde die Grund-. befindlichkeit der Angst.' It is not grammatically clear whether 'seinem' refers to 'Sich verstehen' or to 'Daseins'.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 3 II when it perverts anxiety into cowardly fear and, in surmounting this fear, only makes known its own cowardliness in the face of anxiety. We may now summarize our characterization of authentic Being towards-death as we have projected it existentially: anticipation reveals to Dasein its lostness in the they-self, and brings it face to face with the possibility oj being itself, primarily unsupported by concernful solicitude, but oj being itself, rather, in an impassioned freedolD towards death-afreedom which has been released from the Illusions oj the "they", and which is factical, certain oj itself, and anxious. All the relationships which belong to Being-towards-death, up to the full content of Dasein's uttermost possibility, as we have characterized it, constitute an anticipation which they combine in revealing, unfolding, and holding fast, as that which makes this possibility possible. The existen tial projection in which anticipation has been delimited, has made visible the ontological possibility of an existentiell Being-towards-death which is authentic. Therewith, however, the possibility of Dasein's having an authentic potentiality-for-Being-a-whole emerges, but only as an ontological possibility. In our existential projection of anticipation, we have of course clung to those structures of Dasein which we have arrived at earlier, and we have, as it were, let Dasein itself project itself upon this possibility, without holding up to Dasein an ideal of existence with any special 'con tent', or forcing any such ideal upon it 'from outside'. Nevertheless, this existentially 'possible' Being-towards-death remains, from the existentiell point of view, a fantastical exaction. Thefact that an authentic potentiality for-Being-a-whole is ontologically possible for Dasein, signifies nothing, so long as a correspondingontical potentiality-for-Being has not been demon strated in Dasein itself. Does Dasein ever factically throw itself into such a Being-towards-death? Does Dasein demand, even by reason of its own most Being, an authentic potentiality-for-Being determined by anticipation? Before answering these questions, we must investigate whether to any extent and in anyway Dasein gives testimony, from its ownmost potentiality for-Being, as to a possible authenticity of its existence, so that it not only makes known that in an existentiell manner such authenticity is possible, but demands this of itself. The question of Dasein's authentic Being-a-whole and of its existential constitution still hangs in mid-air. It can be put on a phenomenal basis which will stand the test only if it can cling to a possible authenticity of its Being which is attested by Dasein itself. If we succeed in uncovering that attestation phenomenologically, together with what it attests, then the problem will arise anew as to whether the anticipation oj [zum] death,</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="175">264</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="177">1 ' ••. die der unuberholbaren vorgelagert sind.' See note I, p. 3 0 3, H. 259 above.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx178">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_021.image_21.png" thmb="62qm.page_021.image_21-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="180">for-Being.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="181">26 5</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="183">have about the present-at-hand.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="185">II. I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="186">3 10</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="187">Being and Time xvlii</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="188">266</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx190">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qm.page_022.image_22.png" thmb="62qm.page_022.image_22-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="191">II. I Being and Time</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="192">26 7</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="194">which we have hitherto projected only in its ontological possibility, has an essential connection with that authentic potentiality-for-Being which has been attested.</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter"/>
  </article>
</pdfx>
