<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>25b86bde7e832741c6fafd5fc65df9140f1aa1c8c36f08a67cb01055110d902e</job>
    <base_name>62h5</base_name>
    <doi>10.2752/175470710X12735884220853</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">The Design Journal VOLUME 13, ISSUE 2 REPRINTS AVAILABLE PHOTOCOPYING © BERG 2010 PP 157–180 DIRECTLY FROM THE PERMITTED BY PRINTED IN THE UK PUBLISHERS LICENSE ONLY</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2" confidence="possible">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Katharina Bredies</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Rosan Chow</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Gesche Joost</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">Deutsche Telekom Laboratories, Berlin, Germany</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7">Although there is often no straightforward relationship between theory and practice in design, it is necessary to articulate their mutual impact more clearly. Drawing on Wolfgang Jonas’ generic model of design, a complete design process involves three domains of knowledge; namely analysis, projection and synthesis. For analysis, designers have adopted many methods from other disciplines, but it is not always obvious how they affect projection and synthesis. This is also the case when adopting a constructivist approach to design. Considering the ‘applicability gap’</abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="8">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">between design analysis and projection, we are interested in how design practitioners deal with the increased uncertainty inherent in constructivism. To investigate the underlying assumptions about meaning construction, we compare four different design approaches, namely Participatory Design, Critical Design, Non-Intentional Design and Human- Centred Design. From the basic assumptions of each approach, we draw conclusions about how it addresses participation in design and anticipation of use. Our main proposition is that a constructivist perspective in designing requires designers to address ‘use as design’ more explicitly. KEYWORDS: human-centred design, methods, use, anticipation</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="2" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="11" page="2" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" page="2" column="1">+ Design methods has from been related influenced disciplines. by many In the theories 1960s, and the Design Methods Movement borrowed approaches from engineering. During the 1980s, social science, cognitive science and anthropology became an important source for User-Centred Design, for instance, to inform designers about the social context they were designing for (Bayazıt, 2004). At the same time, to emancipate itself as an independent academic discipline, it is often not sufficient for Design simply to adopt theories and approaches from other fields. Instead, design researchers need to investigate particular ‘designerly ways of knowing’ (Cross, 2001) and generate independent theoretical and methodological positions. 1 By merely taking up theories from other disciplines, Design risks neglecting the development of proprietary theoretical positions (Jonas, 1996). In order to adopt methods and theories for Design it is necessary to investigate their implications for developing and implementing design proposals. It is part of Design’s distinctive qualities (in contrast to the analytical sciences, for example) that it is concerned about the ‘true’ as well as the ‘ideal’ and the ‘real’ (Nelson and Stolterman, 2003). The ‘true’ deals with what is, the ‘ideal’ with what should be and the ‘real’ with how it can be achieved. Design knowledge should support the projection of possible future world states, and/or help to implement them. Analytical scientific data describes existing situations, but often does not carry implications for actions – there is an ‘applicability gap’ between analytical scientific data and design projection (Chow, 2005). She states that analysing a situation tells us what exists, but it does not per se imply what is needed to change this situation for the better. ‘Designerly’ methods have been developed to face this problem, but were then in turn criticized by <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> researchers from the analytic sciences for their lack of rigour and their inherent uncertainty. 2 As Design is dealing with changes in social systems, it is necessarily risky and uncertain. 3 Herbert Simon argues the impossib- ility of gaining complete information about real situations and thus the ‘bounded rationality’ of design decisions (see Simon, 1996). Reactions to a design intervention are usually unpredictable in a fairly complex environment. There is, however, an ongoing debate about if and how far scientific results can help to decrease this uncertainty, and accordingly the relationship of science to design. Early approaches like Simon’s suggest that it is possible to determine the impact of design – if not in reality, at least in principle. This determinism is not necessarily a mainstream position in the contemporary design research discourse. But in transdisciplinary fields such as Human–Computer Interaction (HCI), a common position about such differences between Design and Science cannot always be taken for granted. We suspect the weak linking of theory and practice in Design to be the source of these misunderstandings between designers and scientists. Designerly methods might be developed without making the underlying theoretical assumptions explicit. Theories might be adopted for explanation but not made actionable for design practice. We thus suggest that the transfer from theory to designerly methods has not been fully realized yet. On the one hand, designers might have been rigorous in the use of analytical methods, in striving to be accepted as a ‘proper’ research discipline, whilst not questioning their appropriateness for Design. On the other hand, researchers from other fields are critical about the opportunistic adoption of their methods by designers. 4 We should thus be careful in general not only about the applicability, but also the relevance of theories for design practice. While theories from psychology or linguistics for instance, are frequently used, it is difficult to trace how they have actually affected work practice. Particularly because there is no straightforward one-on-one relationship of theory to practice, a single theoretical position supports diverse interesting practical interpretations. In turn, it is necessary to be explicit about the theoretical assumptions for practice, if Design wants to be taken seriously as a research discipline. A better linking of theory and practice thus enriches both sides. We find this linking particularly necessary if adopting a constructivist perspective in Design. Taking a constructivist viewpoint is already a more uncertain position for analysis. It requires the researcher to communicate their interpretation, because they cannot assume it to be commonly shared. Analytical constructivist methods might have been simply adopted by Design from the social sciences, but the impact of a constructivist perspective on the ‘applicability gap’ of scientific results is often not made clear. So while constructivism has been appropriated by design practice already, we need to explore<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> this appropriation more explicitly. Therefore, it is necessary to take a closer look at how constructivist design practitioners actually deal with the applicability gap and the increased uncertainty it brings.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="13" page="3" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="14" page="3" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="16" page="4" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="18" page="4" column="1">Constructing and Coordinating Meanings in Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="4" column="1">We will present and compare four different constructivist approaches, based on design practice from Human-Centred Design, Participatory Design, Critical Design and Non-Intentional Design. Klaus Krippendorff’s constructivist account will be the basis to classify them as constructivist practices. 5 Our comparison will be guided by two implications drawn from constructivism that we find crucial: first, understanding perception as a constructive act, and second, coordinating meanings through interaction and communication. For our comparison, we will use a model based on a generic design process model developed by Wolfgang Jonas. According to the model, we will be able to spot how each approach organizes the coordination of meanings between design and use. In the discussion, we will then identify the differences in attitude and draw further implications for design practice, education and research. <marker type="block"/> In The Semantic Turn (2006), Krippendorff presents a compre- hensive interpretation of constructivism for design. He grounds his understanding in ecological cognitive theory, radical biological constructivism and Wittgenstein’s notion of language games. Additionally, he proposes a set of methods for design analysis and projection. Krippendorff’s basic assumption is that people, in perceiving artefacts, construct and coordinate meanings, by assuming a mutual understanding. To Krippendorff, designers should employ this ‘second-order understanding’ in designing if the artefacts are to be useful, usable and understandable. It also implies that designers need to anticipate the meanings that their artefacts will evoke. If they can do so successfully, they are properly representing the users in the design process. 6 Following Krippendorff, we suggest that the less familiar a new artefact is, the more its meaning has to be coordinated anew, the more uncertain second-order understanding becomes. 7 For us, it means that the more a design artefact deviates from the norm, understanding it (in terms of use) becomes increasingly similar to designing. Also, the success of a new artefact cannot necessarily be deduced from existing meanings, as the artefact requires a re- coordination of those meanings. In comparing different approaches, we will look at how they address ‘use as design’, and how they manage the coordination of meanings between design and use. We see ‘use as design’ as cases when users create and enact meanings<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> that are so original that they become similar to designing. Therefore, our analysis of the design processes will include the assessment of artefacts already in use.<marker type="block"/> The Method: Jonas’ Generic Process Model For our comparison, we will propose a model that is closely related to the evolutionary-systemic account of Design developed by Wolfgang Jonas. For this purpose, we will refer to a simplified version of his generic design process model (Jonas, 2006) and the theoretical background it is based upon. 8 However, being concerned about establishing Design as a research discipline, Jonas identifies two major logical gaps, drawing on radical constructivism and systems theory: one is the gap between autopoietic systems (consciousness, communication and the body); the other is the gap between the evolutionary mechanisms of variation, selection and re-stabilization (Jonas, 2003). We will elaborate on these concepts while describing our model. Referring to evolutionary epistemology, Jonas frames designing itself as a feedback learning cycle, ‘grounded in the need of org- anisms to survive in an environment’ (Jonas, 2003). Designing can be regarded as such a cycle of action/designing and reflection/using (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). However, with industrialization, acting and reflecting was separated in time and space and is now enacted by different people. Furthermore, Jonas proposes the three major phases of analysis, projection and synthesis to be part of a design (research) process. Those phases are similar to the different ‘domains of knowing’ described by Nelson and Stolterman (2003). They are, however, independent from each other. Thus all combinations of phases and orders of the phases are theoretically possible (Boland Jr, 2004), although only a few make actual sense. For our analysis, we are proposing to divide use into similar phases, and name them adoption, appropriation and reuse. Those terms do not derive from a comparable ready-made framework; they<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> are frequently used within the literature about how technology is used and modified in use. In our case, we use ‘adoption’ to describe that an artefact is being used. ‘Appropriation’ happens when the artefact has to be modified to match the situation at hand, for example, when a software interface is adjusted to be used for a particular purpose. With ‘reuse’, this adjustment extends considerably the intentions of the designer, for instance, when the artefact is used to support another activity or in a different situation. Adopting the three major evolutionary mechanisms in socio- artefactual systems from Jonas, we can divide the cycle into variation, selection and re-stabilization. Following Luhmann, Jonas describes the three phases as separate evolutionary steps. 9 As designers, we can only propose more (and more extreme?) ‘variations’ of artefacts. These artefacts might – or might not be – selected (that is, bought, built, imitated), and the systems re-stabilize (that is, people get used to their new kitchen appliance, computer operating system version or application form). We are thus mapping this macro-process with the six phases in use and design that we already have (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>). ‘Variation’ then spans across projection and synthesis, ‘selection’ embraces adoption and appropriation, and ‘re-stabilization’ includes reuse and analysis in design.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> Comparison of ‘Anticipation of Use’ and ‘Participation in Design’ From a constructivist perspective, the coordination of meanings across the two divides between design and use is fundamental. In practice, this is done by two complementary movements: by ‘anticipation of use’ and ‘participation in design’. Anticipating use during design is meant to make the transition of the new artefact into its prospective environment more successful. Participation of ‘users’ during the designing stage should ensure a good transition of habits and meanings into the design process. Both are closely intertwined. Putting these aspects into a matrix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3a" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3a</xref> and 3b), we will compare Human-Centred Design (HCD), Participatory Design (PD), Critical Design (CD) and Non-Intentional Design (NID) as four approaches that differ significantly between them. Each of them can be related to Krippendorff’s account of constructivism: most explicitly, he is a strong proponent of HCD; he also describes PD as a subset of it, as ‘dialogical ways of designing’ (Krippendorff, 2006). NID is covered by ‘delegating design to the users’ (Krippendorff, 2006), allowing them to create their own meanings; and CD would be included in ‘designing the design discourse’ (Krippendorff, 2006). In the following, the introduced cyclic process model will serve to identify the sequence of design phases and the overlapping of practices in design and use, to see how the coordination of meanings is organized.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="20" page="4" column="1">The Starting Point: Krippendorff’s Appropriation of Constructivism</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="21" page="4" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23" page="5" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="27" page="5" column="1">Figure 1 The action–reflection cycle in design</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="28" page="5" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx29">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_005.image_01.png" thmb="62h5.page_005.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="30" page="6" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="33" page="6" column="1">Figure 2 A design process model with evolutionary phases mapped across Design and Use</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="34" page="6" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx35">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_006.image_02.png" thmb="62h5.page_006.image_02-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="7" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="7" column="1">Comparing Constructivist Design Practice</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="7" column="1">According to Jonas’ model, we have identified ‘anticipation of use’ and ‘participation in design’ as the two major moves in transcending the spatial, temporal and personal separation of design and use. We have proposed Human-Centred Design, Participatory Design, Critical Design and Non-Intentional Design as four approaches that vary significantly according to these two criteria. A model of design and use, based on Jonas’ social-systemic theory, will be used to compare them. We will give a short description of each of the approaches, and how they convey meanings in design and in use. <marker type="block"/> HCD is the most applied, convenient and pragmatic form of constructivist practice. Due to limited resources and the need to produce a successful outcome, design practitioners often investigate users’ understandings during analysis, either directly (for example, with focus groups or interviews) or indirectly (in aggregated, often narrat- ive forms, such as personas and use scenarios). Indirect user data does not have to be explicitly produced, but can be collected for the design question at hand. In iterative design processes, sketches and prototypes are often evaluated prior to the final implementation. The aim is to produce a design artefact that evokes desirable meanings for all stakeholders and that is successful during its whole life cycle.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="41" page="7" column="1">Human-Centred Design (HCD)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="42" page="7" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="44" page="8" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3a">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="45" page="8" column="1">Figure 3a Matrix with constructivist design approaches</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_008.image_03.png" thmb="62h5.page_008.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3b">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="46" page="8" column="1">Figure 3b Matrix with constructivist design approaches, shown as process diagrams</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx48">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_008.image_04.png" thmb="62h5.page_008.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49" page="9" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" page="9" column="1">Examples of Human-Centred Design can often be found in everyday consumer products, such as shavers, kitchen appliances, groceries or cars. Those artefacts are meant to address a particular group of users or customers and their needs and requirements. The requirement can be rather symbolic, for instance, how to design the packaging of a cleaning product to be associated with hygiene. Or it is more instrumental, as in software or machine interface design, where Human-Centred Design should help developers to come up with an appropriate ‘mental model’ to handle a device. The ‘desktop metaphor’ of computer operating systems can be regarded as an early example of Human-Centred Design in addressing the needs of office workers. <marker type="block"/> Participatory Design (PD) PD is often treated as a subset of HCD. It requires, however, a direct involvement of actors concerned with the design situation. 10 This involvement includes self-observation with verbal and visual material provided for expression. Prospective users attend workshops to produce sketches, models or mock-ups of their envisioned design artefacts. 11 In turn, designers ideally participate in the situated (work) practice of the design situation. Intermediary prototypes are tested and evaluated in the prospective use context, and over longer periods of time, if possible. Appropriation and reuse should feed back immediately into the design process. Problem and process construction is as much part of the PD process as the construction of an artefact. Participatory Design has been applied where automation has significantly changed work, for example, in designing electronic patient records for hospitals, or computer applications for document layout pre-printing. A participatory design process has also been executed in architecture, to design semi-public shared spaces, such as youth centres, park furniture and playgrounds, or public housing. Community services are another domain where participatory design is used to ensure acceptability, for instance, of public healthcare services. But participatory methods are also often part of Human- Centred Design projects on a smaller scale, such as designing car interiors or products for children, to increase acceptability.<marker type="block"/> NID happens whenever we use a designed artefact in an unin- tended way, or when the use deliberately ignores or dismisses the use inscribed during design. 12 This happens often spontaneously, is driven by situated needs, and without conscious planning or projection. Non-Intentional Design examples can be found in many everyday life situations. When people use a chair as a shelf or a ladder, or crown bottle tops as ashtrays, or wine bottles as candleholders, stairs as seats, and knives as screwdrivers; this can all be regarded as NID.<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> Critical Design (CD) In CD, the result of the design process is central, and the process itself is often not well articulated in the literature. We assume it to be similar to HCD with regard to an initial inquiry of the design situation, but it is not generally formalized or made explicit. Participation of users during design is not a necessary feature. However, CD artefacts are meant to provoke discussions about controversial issues. In some academically oriented projects, functioning prototypes have been built and evaluated in real-life situations over long periods of time, mainly to observe their adoption and appropriation. 13 In those projects, diverse and controversial interpretations of a concept or artefact are also a desirable outcome. Critical Design proposals tackle issues such as energy production and consumption, scientific innovations in medicine or food production, or domestication of communication media. Prototypes from those projects include, for example, an awkwardly behaving piece of interactive furniture, or illustrated narratives of how pets become a potential energy source for the TV set.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="52" page="9" column="1">Non-Intentional Design (NID)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="53" page="9" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="10" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="57" page="10" column="1">Discussions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="10" column="1">After having described the four distinct approaches, we will analyse how they rely on ‘anticipation of use’ and ‘participation in design’. By ‘anticipation of use’, we refer to the implicit or explicit use scenario that the designer has in mind; by ‘participation in design’, we address how non-professional designers are involved in the design process. Our basic focus is on analysing how each approach deals with and refers to ‘use as design’. We will also look at the solutions the approaches propose to coordinate meanings and the ways they use to communicate them. We will use Jonas’ model to describe the sequence of phases in each approach and how the coordination of meanings spans across different phases of design and use. The sequence in the design process also indicates if the design process is consolidating (for a determined problem situation) or diversifying (open-ended).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Human-Centred Design: Throwing Stuff over the Fence</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="60" page="10" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" page="10" column="1">In HCD, the design process sequence typically starts with an extensive initial analysis, followed by design projection and synthesis. Design and use practice overlap during the design analysis phase, when the situated meanings are subject to investigation ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>). However, users are often not the most influential stakeholders for the design to be realized. 14 Where a direct involvement is too time-consuming, they are represented by (scientific) data in the design process. HCD was developed to fit into industrial environments with an efficient separation of professional roles. It acknowledges ‘use as design’ by taking meanings in use as the basis for redesign, for example, when doing a quick ethnographic observation of mobile<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> phone use or evaluating problems with existing dishwashers. This does not overcome the professional separation, but it should increase the possibility that the designed artefact might evoke desirable meanings in use. When the reliability of the interface is at stake, such a consolidating design process makes complete sense. However, we should be aware of its peculiarities. The first one is that the creation of meanings in use actually has to be more original than the one during designing. Algorithms to make SMS writing easier were developed after people started using it for texting; initi- ally, SMS was not introduced as a texting service. If only desirable meanings are to be evoked, then the designer needs to anticipate them reliably. The second one is the reference to scientific inquiry results. Highly abstracted scientific data might further omit individual differences in the construction of meaning. 15 Designers are more likely to discard the original meanings developed in use for the popular ones if they rely on scientific data based on the status quo. 16 Stable meanings might be further stabilized instead of being varied. Variations are discarded for their lack of reliability, because the designer cannot guarantee that it fits the design situation. In designing a new chair, designers will look at how the majority of people use chairs (probably for sitting). Therefore, single original instances of chair use might get lost in the statistics. Intermediary testing of design proposals might enforce this tendency to discard unconventional variations, because it cannot<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> cover long-term learning effects (Greenberg and Buxton, 2008). While HCD relies on individual meaning construction, it threatens to mainstream it at the same time by favouring conventional understandings. 17<marker type="block"/> Participatory Design: Trapped in the Cycle In an ideal PD process, practices in use and design overlap seam- lessly. 18 For an initial analysis, designers and non-designers mutually experience the other’s (work) practice. During projection, designers act as facilitators to allow others to express their ideas. Results from synthesis, such as working prototypes, are evaluated by how they are adopted and appropriated in use (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>). PD arose to overcome the shortcomings of HCD in sharing the decision power with other concerned parties. Instead of accepting the professional divide of design and use, PD practitioners frame their projects as a mutual learning process and a co-construction of problem and solution. Therefore, direct communication and shared practice is required, and a mere indirect representation of users is not acceptable. 19 The collective problem formulation can be part of the analysis. The resulting artefacts are often intentionally implemented to allow further modification in use. Design decisions are delegated to users, accepting the higher risk of errors and inconsistencies within a shared working environment. 20 Ideally, ongoing ‘design in use’ (Henderson and Kyng, 1991) is continuously changing artefactual systems and social practice in parallel.<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> In principle, designers do not have exclusive rights to creativity in PD, but the responsibility to use their professional skills for mediation (Sanders and William, 2001). However, the final implementation is again a matter of professional design practice, and needs to be evaluated afterwards with prospective users. During projection, designers often impose their methods for expression on people who have often no practice in using them. 21 Nurses, lorry drivers or businessmen need to translate their wishes not only into written and spoken language, but also into sketches, paper models or collages. PD researchers have also been interested in self-initiated acts of design such as appropriation, bricolage and do-it-yourself practice, and are still searching for effective ways to include them. It remains an issue for designers how to interpret other people’s professional practice when they do not work in the area of those they are designing for.<marker type="block"/> Non-Intentional Design: Not Much Reflection in Action In NID, design and use are not separated, but overlap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>). It is the ideal case of participation (as user and designer are identical) without any anticipation (things are just put to use).<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> To professional designers, even those with a constructivist mind- set, it is often not acceptable as a serious form of design. 22 Regarding the overlapping of phases, professional designing and NID can be described using the same diagram: both are aiming at reconfiguring situations with available material for other purposes; both do so by interacting with the given situation. Bricolage, improvisation and reuse are accepted forms of designing (Büscher et al, 2001; Gerber, 2007, 2009) – but on their lowest level, they are still often dismissed as insignificant. In the meantime, the divide of design and use is getting more blurry. While designers cannot ignore or suppress those practices anymore, they can often only face them as a problem or a threat to their professional status. There is no way that thoughtlessly using plastic bags as bicycle saddle covers or water buckets can count as ‘design’! In the narrow definition of the term given by Brandes (2008), 23 it is indeed difficult to draw implications from NID for professional designers. 24 For our comparison, we will indeed regard it as a design process. Differing from Brandes’ definition, we will handle the term more loosely and include the categories that she excludes, such as DIY, and reuse to replace a lacking artefact, as well. 25 We then find it appropriate to investigate its circumstances and prerequisites in design terms. Although the originality of NID is not always exciting, the identity of designer and user is beneficial, because it bypasses communication. The meanings of artefacts in NID might not even enter language properly, because they do not have to. 26 Also, the interventions are often reversible, so that the design is only present as a process, not as a product. As a design practice, NID does not require extensive production, but can easily be communicated and imitated, modified and adjusted.<marker type="block"/> In academic projects, CD and related design practices show a slightly different process to that of HCD and PD: the initial analysis of the design situation is less important than the evaluation at the end; 27 projection and synthesis are followed by analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>), which reaches far into the adoption and appropriation of the artefact. CD thus embodies an anti-HCD process: taking existing meanings as a benchmark only to choose the most idiosyncratic ones as an inspiration for design, and exposing consensus by confusing it. This seems logical, as the intended outcome of CD is to provoke public debate. Functional prototypes are implemented and put to use with the explicit aim to evoke individually deviating interpretations (Sengers and Gaver, 2006). In Dunne and Raby’s ‘placebo project’, for example, pieces of furniture are given a ‘para-functionality’ to detect and react to electromagnetic radiation. The furniture was thus also inspired with the supposed needs of a very small and specific user group in mind.<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> Designers thus try to address use as a complement to design. However, it is unclear if this move is meant as an explicit delegation of design to the users. The actual use of CD artefacts often reaches only a small number of individuals. A broader public can participate in the public debate through the proliferation of the projects via media and exhibitions, but then provide themselves a rather speculative anticipation of how the artefact would be used. The original sceptical attitude of CD towards industrial mass-production almost requires that it stays within the realms of academics, discourse and art. Therefore, its attitude can afford much more deviating meanings than HCD. Their controversial proposals address issues that, in some cases, contradict ethical standards or political laws. The private understandings of an artefact have to remain virtual and cannot – or must not – be enacted. Despite the value that CD has to the fuelling of public debate about controversial issues, it still resists a simple adaptation to everyday design practice. 28</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="63" page="11" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="64" page="11" column="1">Figure 4 A Human-Centred Design process</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_011.image_05.png" thmb="62h5.page_011.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="65" page="11" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="67" page="12" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="71" page="12" column="1">Figure 5 A Participatory Design process</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="72" page="12" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx73">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_012.image_06.png" thmb="62h5.page_012.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="74" page="13" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="78" page="13" column="1">Figure 6 A Non-Intentional Design process</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="79" page="13" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx80">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_013.image_07.png" thmb="62h5.page_013.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="14" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="83" page="14" column="1">Critical Design: Provoking the People</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="84" page="14" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="87" page="15" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="88" page="15" column="1">Figure 7 A Critical Design process</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62h5.page_015.image_08.png" thmb="62h5.page_015.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="90" page="15" column="1">Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="91" page="15" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" page="15" column="1">Following the ideas of design theorist Wolfgang Jonas, we are proposing to regard creation of meaning in use as an integral part of the design process, and to understand design as variation. We conclude that design can only be regarded as such if it accepts or addresses creation of meaning in use. It is then possible to describe ‘use as <marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> design’ more precisely not as routine use, but as original variations in use. Our comparison shows how the four approaches can be regarded as four attempts to address meaning construction, each with a slightly different (professional) attitude. HCD needs to consolidate (rather than diversify) meanings to guarantee reliable interfaces. PD tries to reconcile the functional differentiation with democratic values through extensive communication. While in PD, design is meant to cause changes in practice (and society), it needs to do so in accord with the concerned parties. Design becomes the design of participatory processes and tools. Both approaches thus rely, though differently, on consensus of some sort. CD and NID, in contrast, do not rely on consensus. CD is deliberately seeking and provoking debate about controversial issues. Aiming at discourse, it does not require a material implementation, if demonstrating its purpose works well without doing so. NID, in turn, can completely bypass communication and industrial (re-)production because it simply reuses existing artefacts. Both approaches rely on diversification, but their processes are not well explored from a professional design point of view. From a constructivist perspective, we suggest that CD and NID still have the potential to address ‘use as design’ that has not been explored yet in HCD and PD. Especially where designers cannot hope for the friendly circumstances required to set up a PD project, CD and NID can provide useful hints. CD preserves a professional position for the designer – emphasizing their skills to develop far- reaching variations – while finding different means of embracing ‘use as design’. NID as a phenomenon might be investigated further and feed into the ‘infrastructuring’ process as proposed in PD. We would also like to suggest that the issues CD brings to the table deserve a more thorough reflection on design as a profession. It encourages designers to look for ways that idiosyncratic behaviour may be supported. Which production infrastructure, design proposals, communication platforms and interaction with users-as- designers may be ways to make this possible? How can we finally affect the structures CD is exposing so powerfully? CD practitioners give us some answers, but still owe us some more.<marker type="block"/> From our comparison, we learned that it is not an easy thing to be a practising constructivist designer. Designers refer to existing meanings, but they also constantly disturb and question them. If we frame design as the reference to meanings, we are considering just one aspect of design. But if we understand design as variation, we can include ‘use as design’ and compare the originality of the variations, not their origin. Expertise in how artefacts evoke meanings is still an important prerequisite. But Design dilettantism should not be treated<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> as a thread, but as a new opportunity to embrace different activities with design. Design proposals that should be implemented on a large scale are a high financial risk for the producing industries. Highly uncertain ideas that would invite design-in-use are thus difficult to argue for. To realize more risky artefacts in design practice, and yet act from a constructivist perspective, it is not always possible to share practices as proposed in PD. Designers need different strategies that work across the divide of use and design. It means that designers need either support from the risk-loving managers of big companies, or more workarounds for bypassing large-scale industrial production. 29 The former increases if non-consensual design approaches are accepted. The latter evolves with computer-aided production methods or production services that allow more customization and production of prototypes for a reasonable price. DIY products and practices are another related field. When artefacts are individually rebuilt and reproduced, they can be locally appropriated and modified in every instance. Ideally, experiences with the artefact would be fed back into the community by the users. 30 After the success of HCD approaches not only in practice, but also in design education institutes, we need to remember design’s roots in art once again: not to obscure design as a creative, black-boxed process, but to be more aware of the contingency in how design artefacts are received and interpreted. The designers’ gut feeling that meanings evolve both in the production and the reception of an artefact has been neglected in methodological design education. Also, when we think of design as variation of artefacts to evoke different meanings, we need designers trained in producing variations beyond what appears immediately reasonable. Study of the design context should serve as a benchmark, not as a limiting frame. Design practices such as improvisation with and reinterpretation of artefacts is often already part of the curriculum and should be further related to ‘use as design’. For design research, a constructivist perspective obliges us to think about the organization of the design process differently: that the risk and contingency is in the nature of the cause, not in the lack of carefulness during designing. Depending on the risk we can account for, designers can better argue when to apply a convergent process – and compromise on the originality; or a divergent process – and compromise on the immediate reliability and general applicability of the artefact. We might never be able to understand the construction of meaning fully, but we can investigate and benefit from its side effects more systematically. The practices of adoption and appropriation should not be dismissed as insignificant, but rather amplified with design interventions. The artefacts people choose to adopt and appropriate are a valuable resource for design transfer. Therefore we need to describe ‘use as design’ and creation of meaning from<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> an actionable design perspective, not only how we can investigate, but how we can encourage it. To do so, design researchers should feel inspired by the way CD practitioners provoke and evaluate reactions to controversial design proposals. However, we need to be more explicit about what those projects can contribute to design theory and practice, for example, in terms of transferable design knowledge, methods, or communication strategies.<marker type="block"/> Delimitation Our comparison represents just one possible point of view of how to relate design practices to a constructivist perspective. It derived from our reading of constructivist theory and emphasizes the two criteria we found most meaningful. It is, therefore, not meant to be an exhaustive map of constructivist design practice as such. In presenting the approaches, we have drawn a somewhat purified and exaggerated image, to make their differences and commonalities clear. We are aware that in reality, those practices are usually more diverse and less clearly distinguishable in their objectives. Also, the descriptions of the approaches are necessarily quite short and do not go into great detail. We hope that our analysis outweighs these necessary simplifications. As our analysis relies on secondary literature and not on original empirical data, it remains reflective and speculative. We are also aware of the rather casual use of theoretical frameworks from different design theorists. In this case, looking at Krippendorff’s constructivist account by using Jonas’ model was useful and practical. Although they share some similar positions, their theoretical bases are reasonably different, to the point where they might be even incommensurate. However, a detailed comparison of both positions would deserve an article of its own.<marker type="block"/> Outlook As next steps, we propose to explore further if and how artefact- driven design can encourage ‘use as design’. We have already described existing practices and phenomena related to ‘use as design’. For further research, we need to connect some of those loose ends, such as, operationalize further some of the practices around CD that until now often remain in an academic environment. In doing so, we need to be aware of its origins, and try to find productive niches where it is possible to preserve its basic intuitions. Finally, we need to empirically evaluate whether CD practices are really capable of provoking ‘use as design’, as we expect it to be, or not.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93" page="16" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="95" page="16" column="1">Implications for Practice, Education and Research</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="96" page="16" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="98" page="17" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="99" page="17" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="101" page="18" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="105" page="18" column="1">Notes</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="106" page="18" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" page="18" column="1">1. This claim often goes back to Herbert Simon’s distinction of analytical sciences and productive sciences or ‘Sciences of the Artificial’ (see Simon, 1996). <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> 2. As an example, this is visible in the case of ‘Cultural Probes’, a method to collect situated personal data to inspire designers. Cultural probes often consist of diverse materials such as disposable cameras, diaries and postcards (see Gaver et al, 1999). The data it produces are evidently useful for designers, but loses much of its value when analysed scientifically. Boehner et al locate the problem in merely adopting the method, but neglecting its underlying methodology (see Boehner et al, 2007). 3. Clive Dilnot consequently named Design the ‘Science of Uncertainty’, claiming that it comprises the knowledge not of what is, but what could be (see Dilnot, 1998). 4. For example, Paul Dourish argues that the ‘implications for design’ from ethnographic field research are not an appropriate criterion for their evaluation, in this case within HCI (see Dourish, 2006). 5. We will mainly refer to Krippendorff’s book The Semantic Turn (2006). 6. Actually, Krippendorff introduces the term ‘stakeholders’ to include other concerned actors as well. To him, users are not always the most important and most influential stakeholders. For our comparison, however, we would like to narrow the focus down to use again, because we are interested in the interpretation that is necessary to use an artefact. 7. Although this might sound like a truism, this basic intuition about design seems to get lost occasionally. 8. We have to acknowledge that Krippendorff’s and Jonas’ theoretical accounts are reasonably different, although they seem to share some basic assumptions. At least the concept of auto- poiesis that is also central in Luhmann’s theory seems to be based on the work of biologist Humberto Maturana (see Jonas, 1993). 9. There might be a causal or logical connection between them that we might never be able to access from within the system, as they reside in the difference of a system and its environment (see Jonas, 2003). 10. PD has been developed as a democratic approach to design in Scandinavia since the 1970s. The initial motivation was to include workers in the design process of the workplace, as they would be most affected by the design changes. See Ehn (1988). 11. Liz Sanders developed a PD process that should address user meanings about the past, present and future by using different media and methods for sensitization and expression (see, for example, Sanders and William, 2001). 12. Following the definition of NID given by Brandes (2008). 13. For examples, see Dunne and Raby (2001), Gaver et al (2007) and Höök (2006). 14. Krippendorff makes this point not only because ‘users’ as stakeholders is too narrow a perspective. Even if a design<marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> might be perfectly suitable for users, other stakeholders such as producers, sellers and sometimes political organizations need to be equally convinced before a design artefact gets implemented. 15. This is due to the different objectives of Science and Design mentioned above. At least some forms of scientific data have to be generalizable to be valid, while Design is always concerned with particular situations (see Chow, 2005). 16. Greenberg and Buxton (2008) state that if user evaluation is undertaken in the early stages, there is a danger of discarding creative ideas too early. 17. However, Krippendorff claims that it is possible to design original artefacts and preserve the stakeholder’s understandings by using narratives and metaphors. At the same time, he seems to be aware that his readers might suspect a contradiction here. 18. Pelle Ehn states that the design phase can be covered with participatory design, while the use phase should be addressed with ongoing ‘infrastructuring’ or ‘design for design after design’, as he puts it (see Ehn, 2008). 19. Both should not only ensure a democratic design process, but increase democratic structures in society as a whole, more explicitly in the Scandinavian approach (see, for example, Gregory, 2003). 20. Gregory (2003) mentions the case of the District Health Inform- ation System (DHIS) to illustrate this fact. 21. The results from participatory design workshops might be very suitable for design interpretation – hence as a source of inspiration. However, these workshops are part of the ‘design game’, contrived settings in which people are asked to do things they would not normally do. It is still the subject of study how well such workshop results (for example, prototypes) are suitable as an ‘expression’ of latent needs and wants, or if they are largely shaped by the frame that designers set: the task at hand, the material provided, and workshop group dynamics. Finally, the results need to be judged from a design perspective, as the design professional is still in charge of refining and implementing a design proposal. 22. Seeking academic emancipation, designers need to distinguish their competences from others rather than claiming everything to be design. Krippendorff describes that creating meaning in use is not entirely different from designing itself; however, he also claims that designers are constructing their professional identity through their discourse, which clearly excludes other professions. One can of course argue whether or not NID deserves a special category. Rooting design in action and reflection, we propose it does. 23. p. 270 ff. Brandes explicitly excludes similar practices such as Do-It-Yourself (DIY), reuse out of a shortage of original products,<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="block"/> or the replication of artefacts with a high symbolic value and states that ‘Non-Intentional Design is not a design process; nothing is designed, as such’ (Brandes, 2008, p. 271). 24. Brandes provides an analysis with general properties that non-intentional designs fulfil, such as being cheap, multi- functional, simple, that the intervention is reversible, and so forth (see Brandes et al, 2009). While such generalizable principles are already helpful, we also expect to learn much from Brandes’ extensive empirical collection of actual NID examples. 25. Following Jonas’ notion, we frame design as variation, or variation as design, and thus regard reconfigurations on different levels as designing as well. Our interest thus lies more in the degree of variation, and less in the intention, which might have been the basis for Brandes’ definition. 26. The downside is of course that things without a name virtually do not exist. 27. At least it is not as much formalized and made explicit as it is in HCD and PD. 28. There are, however, attempts to integrate disruptive design proposals in more established user-centred processes, see, for example, Bowen (2007). 29. One could object that ‘crowdsourcing’, delegating design ideation to the public, has become tremendously popular for large industries. The production, however, can only be crowd- sourced to a certain limit, for instance, as self-build furniture. 30. There are already many websites for sharing DIY projects and instructions, such as www.hackaday.com, www.makezine. com, www.i-hacked.com, and so forth.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="108" page="19" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="109" page="19" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="111" page="20" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="112" page="20" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="114" page="21" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="116" page="21" column="1">References</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="117" page="21" column="1">EAD07: Dancing with Disorder: Design, Discourse &amp; Disaster,</region>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="118" page="21" column="1">Journal Design The</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" page="22" column="1">Journal Design The</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" page="21" column="1">Bayazıt, EAD07: N. Dancing (2004). ‘Investigating with Disorder: design: Design, A review Discourse of forty &amp; Disaster, years of design research’. Design Issues, 20(1), 16–29. Boehner, K., Vertesi, J., Sengers, P. and Dourish, P. (2007). ‘How HCI interprets the probes’. Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 1077–1086. Boland Jr, R. J. (2004). ‘Design in the punctuation of management action’. In Boland Jr, R. J. and Collopy, F. (eds), Managing as Designing. Stanford, CA: Stanford Business Books, pp. 106–112. Bowen, S. (2007). ‘Crazy ideas or creative probes? Presenting critical artefacts to stakeholders to develop innovative product ideas’. Izmir, Turkey, 11–13 April 2007. Brandes, U. (2008). ‘Non-Intentional Design’. In Erlhoff, M. and Marshall, T. (eds), Design Dictionary: Perspectives on Design Terminology. Basel, Switzerland: Birkhäuser. Brandes, U., Stich, S. and Wender, M. (2009). Design durch Gebrauch: Die alltägliche Metamorphose der Dinge. Basel: Birkhäuser.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="120" page="22" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 541–550. Dunne, A. and Raby, F. (2001). Design Noir: The Secret Life of Electronic Objects. Basel: Birkhäuser. Ehn, P. (1988). Work-oriented Design of Computer Artifacts. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates. Ehn, P. (2008). ‘Participation in design things’. 10th Participatory Design Conference. New York: ACM, pp. 92–101. Gaver, B., Dunne, T. and Pacenti, E. (1999). ‘Design: Cultural probes’. Interactions, 6(1), 21–29. Gaver, W., Sengers, P., Kerridge, T., Kaye, J. and Bowers, J. (2007). ‘Enhancing ubiquitous computing with user interpretation: Field testing the home health horoscope’. CHI ’07: Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 537–546. Gerber, E. (2007). ‘Improvisation principles and techniques for design’. CHI ’07: Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 1069–1072. Gerber, E. (2009). ‘Using improvisation to enhance the effectiveness of brainstorming’. CHI ’09: Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 97–104. Greenberg, S. and Buxton, B. (2008). ‘Usability evaluation consid- ered harmful (some of the time)’. Proceeding of the Twenty- sixth Annual SIGCHI conference on Human factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 11–120. Gregory, J. (2003). ‘Scandinavian approaches to Participatory Design’. International Journal of Engineering Education, 19(1), 62–74. Henderson, A. and Kyng, M. (1991). ‘There’s no place like home: Continuing Design in use’. In Greenbaum, J. and Kyng, M. (eds),</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" page="22" column="1">Büscher, SIGCHI M., Conference Gill, S., Mogensen, on Human P. Factors and Shapiro, in Computing D. (2001). Systems. ‘Land- New scapes York: of practice: ACM, pp. Bricolage 541–550. as a method for situated design’. Dunne, Computer A. and Supported Raby, F. Cooperative (2001). Design Work Noir: (CSCW), The 10(1), Secret 1–28. Life of Chow, Electronic R. (2005). Objects. ‘For Basel: user study: Birkhäuser. The implications of design’. PhD Ehn, Braunschweig: P. (1988). Work-oriented Hochschule Design für Bildende of Computer Künste Artifacts. (HBK). Hillsdale, Cross, NJ: Lawrence N. (2001). Erlbaum ‘Designerly Associates. ways of knowing: Design discipline Ehn, versus P. (2008). design ‘Participation science’. Design in design Issues, things’. 17(3), 49–55. 10th Participatory Dilnot, Design C. Conference. (1998). ‘The New science York: ACM, of uncertainty pp. 92–101. – The potential Gaver, contribution B., Dunne, of T. design and Pacenti, to knowledge’. E. (1999). ‘Design: Doctoral Cultural Education probes’. in Design Interactions, Conference, 6(1), 21–29. Ohio State University, Columbus, 9–11 Gaver, October W., Sengers, 1998, pp. P., 65–98. Kerridge, T., Kaye, J. and Bowers, J. (2007). Dourish, ‘Enhancing P. (2006). ubiquitous ‘Implications computing for with design’. user Proceedings interpretation: of Field the testing the home health horoscope’. CHI ’07: Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 537–546. Gerber, E. (2007). ‘Improvisation principles and techniques for design’. CHI ’07: Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 1069–1072. Gerber, E. (2009). ‘Using improvisation to enhance the effectiveness of brainstorming’. CHI ’09: Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 97–104. Greenberg, S. and Buxton, B. (2008). ‘Usability evaluation consid- ered harmful (some of the time)’. Proceeding of the Twenty- sixth Annual SIGCHI conference on Human factors in Computing Systems. New York: ACM, pp. 11–120. Gregory, J. (2003). ‘Scandinavian approaches to Participatory Design’. International Journal of Engineering Education, 19(1), 62–74. Henderson, A. and Kyng, M. (1991). ‘There’s no place like home: Continuing Design in use’. In Greenbaum, J. and Kyng, M. (eds), Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, pp. 219–240. Höök, K. (2006). ‘Designing familiar open surfaces’. Proceedings of the 4th Nordic Conference on Human–Computer Interaction: Changing Roles. New York: ACM, pp. 242–251. <marker type="page" number="23"/><marker type="block"/> Jonas, W. (1993). ‘Design as problem-solving? Or: here is the solution – what was the problem?’ Design Studies, 14(2), 157–170. Jonas, W. (1996). ‘Design als systemische Intervention – für ein neues (altes) “postheroisches” Designverständnis’. 17. designwiss. Kolloquium ‘Objekt und Prozeß’. Halle, Germany, 28–30 November 1996. Jonas, W. (2003). ‘Mind the gap! – on knowing and not-knowing in design. Or: there is nothing more theoretical than a good practice’. The Fifth International Conference of the European Academy of Design. Barcelona, Spain, 28–30 April 2003 [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://home.snafu.de/jonasw/JONAS4-62.html" id="125">http://home.snafu.de/jonasw/JONAS4-62.html</ext-link> [accessed 22 February 2010]. Jonas, W. (2006). ‘Research through DESIGN through research – a problem statement and a conceptual sketch’. DRS Wonderground Conference, Lisbon, Portugal, 1–4 November 2006 [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.iade.pt/drs2006/wonderground/" id="126">http://www.iade.pt/drs2006/wonderground/</ext-link> proceedings/fullpapers/DRS2006_0230.pdf [accessed 22 February 2010]. Krippendorff, K. (2006). The Semantic Turn: A New Foundation for Design. Boca Raton, FL: Taylor and Francis. Nelson, H. and Stolterman, E. (2003). The Design Way: Intentional Change in an Unpredictable World: Foundations and Fund- amentals of Design Competence. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Educational Technology Publications. Sanders, E. B.-N. and William, C. T. (2001). ‘Harnessing people’s creativity: Ideation and expression through visual communica- tion’. In Langford, J. and McDonagh-Philp (eds), Focus Groups: Supporting Effective Product Development. London: Taylor and Francis, pp. 145–156. Sengers, P. and Gaver, B. (2006). ‘Staying open to interpretation: engaging multiple meanings in design and evaluation’. Proceedings of the 6th Conference on Designing Interactive Systems. University Park, PA: ACM, pp. 99–108. Simon, H. A. (1996). The Sciences of the Artificial. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="124" page="23" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Rosan Chow and Gesche Joost</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="128" page="23" column="1">Biographies</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" page="23" column="1">Katharina Bredies is a research scientist and PhD candidate at Deutsche Telekom Laboratories. She holds a diploma in product and interface design from the University of Arts Bremen. In her dissertation, she explores the impact of irritating interfaces on the ‘interpretative flexibility’ of an artefact. She also assists in research projects on design methodology and theory. <marker type="block"/> Dr Rosan Chow is a research scientist at the Deutsche Telekom Laboratories. She holds a Bachelor and a Masters Degree in Communication Design and a PhD in Designwissenschaft. She has studied, practised and sessionally taught design in Canada, the USA<marker type="page" number="24"/><marker type="block"/> and Germany. She is the project manager of the newly established Design Research Network. Her research focuses on design theory and design research methodology.<marker type="block"/> Prof. Dr Gesche Joost is the head of the Design Research Lab at Deutsche Telekom Laboratories in Berlin, Germany. She is in charge of all design-driven innovation activities in R&amp;D of Deutsche Telekom AG. At the Technical University of Berlin, she is affiliated as Junior Professor and teaches Interaction Design &amp; Media. Her current research topics are interface and interaction design, gender and design in Human–Computer Interaction, as well as user-centric design methods. In these fields, she runs several interdisciplinary research projects with international partners, for example, on tactile interaction with mobile devices and on gender and diversity aspects in communication technology. She holds a PhD in Rhetoric and a Masters in Design. Recently, she completed two books on the ‘Image-Language’ of audio-visual media as well as on ‘Design as Rhetoric’. In 2008, she was honoured with the Berlin Young Scientist award. Gesche Joost is the chairwoman of the German Society for Design Theory and Research DGTF e.V., and co-initiator of the Design Research Network (www.design-research-network.org).</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="130" page="23" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="132" page="24" column="1">Addressing Use as Design: A Comparison of Constructivist Design Approaches</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="135" page="24" column="1">Addresses for Correspondence</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" page="24" column="1">Katharina Bredies, Deutsche Telekom Laboratories, Ernst-Reuter- Platz 7, 18. Etage, 10587 Berlin, Germany. Tel: +40 30 8353 58572 Email: <email id="136">katharina.bredies@telekom.de</email> Website: www.design-research-lab.org<marker type="block"/> Dr Rosan Chow, Deutsche Telekom Laboratories, Ernst-Reuter- Platz 7, 18. Etage, 10587 Berlin, Germany. Tel: +40 30 8353 58357 Email: <email id="138">rosan.chow@telekom.de</email> Website: www.design-research-lab.org<marker type="block"/> Prof. Dr Gesche Joost, Head of Design Research Lab, Deutsche Telekom Laboratories, Ernst-Reuter-Platz 7, 18. Etage, 10587 Berlin, Germany. Tel: +40 30 8353 58443 Email: <email id="140">gesche.joost@telekom.de</email> Websites: www.geschejoost.org, www.design-research-lab.org</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="142" page="24" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
