<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e9ac397487e1e52951df2d20e7831dfa86d870aba3fdf88e214ac962e99b65e4</job>
    <base_name>62mp</base_name>
    <doi>10.1177/1350507608101225</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">Management Learning <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com/" id="1">http://mlq.sagepub.com/</ext-link></outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Introduction: The Critical Power of the `Practice Lens'</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6" confidence="possible">Silvia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="4" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi Management Learning 2009</xref> 40: 115 DOI: 10.1177/1350507608101225 The online version of this article can be found at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com/content/40/2/115" id="5">http://mlq.sagepub.com/content/40/2/115</ext-link></abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">Published by:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx8">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mp.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62mp.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepublications.com" id="9">http://www.sagepublications.com</ext-link> Additional services and information for Management Learning can be found at: Email Alerts: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com/cgi/alerts" id="10">http://mlq.sagepub.com/cgi/alerts</ext-link> Subscriptions: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com/subscriptions" id="11">http://mlq.sagepub.com/subscriptions</ext-link> Reprints: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.com/journalsReprints.nav" id="12">http://www.sagepub.com/journalsReprints.nav</ext-link> Permissions: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav" id="13">http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav</ext-link> Citations: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com/content/40/2/115.refs.html" id="14">http://mlq.sagepub.com/content/40/2/115.refs.html</ext-link> &gt;&gt; Version of Record - Mar 17, 2009 What is This?</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="16">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="17">Management Learning Copyright © The Author(s), 2009.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="20">Reprints and permissions: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav" id="18">http://www.sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mlq.sagepub.com" id="19">http://mlq.sagepub.com</ext-link> Vol. 40(2): 115–128 1350–5076</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="2" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="22" page="2" column="1">Silvia Gherardi University of Trento, Italy Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="2" column="1">Managerial and organizational studies have rediscovered the concept of practice in recent years. The term has spread in such a rapid and unnoticed way that it has generated a body of research bearing the acronym PBS (Practice-Based Studies) almost from nothing. In this introduction I shall treat the rapid diffusion of the practice concept as evidence of the power intrinsic to the central concept of practice. In fact, the greater diffusion and acceptance of Practice-Based Studies (PBS) has been accompanied by concerns about the loss of critical power of the practice concept to more orthodox accounts shaped by assumptions of rationalism and cognitivism in organization studies. We often find the term ‘practice’ being assumed to be synonymous with ‘routine’, or taken to be a generic equivalent of ‘what people really do’, without addressing the link between practice and knowledge, its original and distinctive critique of the modernist conceptions of knowledge (i.e. practice as the generative source of knowledge), and the methodological problems that its use implies. It was with these concerns in mind that the call for papers was made for this special issue. How the conception of practice as epistemology constitutes a critical approach to the modernist conceptions of knowledge dominant in organization studies can be better understood if we recall the distinction drawn by Ira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Cohen (1996)</xref> between theories of action and theories of practice. We may say that while the former theories privilege the intentionality of actors, from which derives meaningful action (in the tradition of Weber and Parsons), the latter locate the source of significant patterns in how conduct is enacted, performed or produced (in the tradition of Schutz, Dewey, Mead, Garfinkel and Giddens). Hence theories of practice assume an ecological model in which agency is distributed between humans and non-humans and in which the relationality between the social world and materiality can be subjected to inquiry. While theories of action start from individuals and from their intentionality in pursuing courses of action, theories of practice view actions as ‘taking place’ or ‘happening’, as being performed through a network of connections-in-action, as life-world and dwelling.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="25" page="2" column="1">DOI: 10.1177/1350507608101225</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="26" page="2" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="27" page="3" column="1">116</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28" page="3" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="29" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Practice: A Polysemic Concept</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="3" column="1">It appears that practice has become a buzz-word in organization studies, and the aggregate of voices under the label ‘practice-based studies’ is rather polyphonic. When we leave aside the commonplace use of the word ‘practice’ and assume that reference is being made to practice as epistemology, we can see how practice- based studies converge on a common interest in understanding the production/ consumption of knowledge and its circuit of reproduction. ‘Practice’, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Schatzki (1996, 2001)</xref> argues, is a term that seems to be descriptive of fundamental phenomena of society, as encountered, for example, in the writings of philosophers and sociologists such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu (1972)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Lyotard (1979)</xref>, Foucault (1980), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Taylor (1995)</xref>, as well as in ethnomethodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Garfinkel, 1967</xref>). In Bourdieu’s case the deeper-lying structures that organize general social practices are self-reproducing dispositions; in Lyotard discursive moves or language games; in Foucault geneal- ogies of practice; in Taylor the vocabulary embedded within the practice marks its range of possible actions and meanings, while in Garfinkel the reflexive tendency of social interaction provides for its own constitution through practices of accountability and scenic display. In organization studies, the influence of practice theorists has been seen as more important as an epistemology for the study of working practices and the kind of practical and ‘hidden’ knowledge that supports them. Paradoxically, the term ‘practice’ has the connotation of being something transferable, teachable, trans- mittable, or reproducible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Turner, 1994</xref>), but at the same time, practices are dif- ficult to access, observe, measure or represent because they are hidden, tacit, and often linguistically inexpressible in propositional terms. The problem of repre- senting practices is well illustrated in the contributions in this special issue by Blacker and Regan, Geiger and Nicolini. In both scientific and ordinary language, the term ‘practice’ relates to a plurality of semantic fields. Although this may be a limitation, it also has the advantage that ‘practice’ is a malleable term which can be put to numerous uses and employed to denominate many aspects of the phenomenal reality under study. The numerous phenomenal aspects comprised in a practice can be studied in relation to their recursiveness, socially sustained habits, the knowledge implicit in a dominion of action, the values that give social accountability to action, and the shared ways of accomplishing any practice. The challenge raised by the current recovery of the concept of practice within organization studies is to conjecture whether it is possible to consider the set of all these aspects in their phenomenal occurrence and in their temporality. If this challenge is taken up, the ‘growing calls to get close to work/organizational practices happening’ (Samra-Fredericks and Bargiela-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Chiappini, 2008</xref>: 654) would constitute an objective attainable with rigorous theorization and methodology.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="38" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Practice from Outside and Practice from Inside</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="3" column="1">The difficulty of defining what is meant by ‘practice’ is due not only to the polysemy of the term but also to the various epistemic positioning of different <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> researchers. Applying the fundamental distinction in sociology between object- ivism and subjectivism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1990</xref>), or in Evered and Louis’s terms (1981) between ‘inquiry from outside’ and ‘inquiry from inside’, yields different conceptions of practices and different methodologies for studying them. When practices are read ‘from outside’, the inquiry concentrates on their regularity, on the pattern which organizes activities, and on the more or less shared understanding that allows their repetition. The recursiveness of practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Giddens, 1984</xref>) is the element which enables both practitioners and researchers to rec- ognize a practice as practice, that is, a way of doing sustained by canons of good practice (a normative accountability) and beautiful practice (an aesthetic accountability). Therefore a practice becomes such when it is socially recognized as an institutionalized doing. When a practitioner tells a colleague that from 10 to 12 o’clock she or he will be doing ‘X’, the expression is intersubjectively meaningful as indexing a specific work practice that is different from others, not only because of the use of specific technologies and tasks but also because of the set of relations activated to produce that practice and to sustain its legitimacy and value. In this case knowledge about the practice is anterior to the practitioner who will put it into practice, that is, perform it as situated activity complying with the logic of the situation. When researchers read practice ‘from outside’ their knowledge interest will be driven by questions such as: How does the object of the ‘X’ practice emerge from the recursiveness of the activity? Reading practices from outside enables them to be analysed as an ‘array of activities’. It is this epistemological position that links the analysis of practices with the analysis of routines—as conducted, for instance, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Feldman and Pentland (2003)</xref> and by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Feldman (2000)</xref>, who propose a reading of routines as practices in order to move from the analysis of routines as programmes of action to that of routines as performances. In these studies, the tradition of inquiry into routines initiated by March overlaps with a new research programme concerned with the dynamic aspect of the recursiveness of organizational actions, although it maintains the function of routines and practices as uncertainty reduction devices. This reflects an increasingly common interpretation of organizing in terms of ‘recurrent action patterns’ (M. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Cohen, 2007</xref>) and a resumption of interest among organization scholars in Dewey and pragmatism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Elkjaer, 2003</xref>) and in Heidegger and pheno- menology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Chia and Holt, 2006</xref>). Let us go ‘inside’ practices. A second reading can be conducted ‘from within’, that is, from the point of view of the practitioners and the activity that is being performed, with its temporality and processuality, as well as the emergent and negotiated order of the action being done. This perspective is discussed and illustrated in the articles by Geiger and Nicolini in this issue. Seen from the inside, practice is a knowledgeable collective action that forges relations and connections among all the resources available and all the constraints present. Performing a practice therefore requires knowing how to align humans and artefacts within a sociotechnical ensemble and therefore knowing how to construct and maintain an action-net (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Czarniawska, 2004</xref>), which is interwoven and deployed so that every element has a place and a sense in the interaction. From this definition it follows that knowing is a situated activity and that knowing-in-practice is always a practical accomplishment.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> Knowing is something that people do together, and it is done in every mundane activity, in organizations when people work together, and also in academic fields. To know is to be able to participate with the requisite competence in the complex web of relationships among people, material artefacts and activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi, 2001</xref>). Acting as a competent practitioner is synonymous with knowing how to connect successfully with the field of practices thus activated. Empirical studies, which analyse practice from inside, consist in the study of the practical organization of knowledge, taking the form of methods of seeing, listening, reasoning and acting in association with human and non-human elements. In fact, objects and their material world can be construed as material- ized knowledge and matter, which interrogate humans and interact with them. And practical reasoning can be considered as a mode of ordering and deploying the interweaving between knowledge and power (Foucault, 1980). In this sense, practice from inside constitutes an epistemology that can be called ‘post-humanist’ in that it seeks to decentre the human subject (as in the object-centred sociality of Knorr-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Cetina, 1997</xref>) or to reconfigure agency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Latour, 2005</xref>) as a capacity real- ized through the associations of humans and materiality. The article by Bjørkeng, Clegg and Pitsis in this special issue proposes an apt neologism to convey the duality of the researcher’s practice and positioning. ‘Becoming (a) practice’ comprises both the message that the object of empirical study of practices is a practice, that is, identification by the researcher of the empirical object of study, and the sense that the emergence of a shared way of doing becomes a shared practice (i.e. a habit) through a series of social processes which the authors identify in authoring boundaries, negotiating competences and adapting materiality. Their empirical study responds to the question: How are practices born?</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40" page="3" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="4" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="42" page="4" column="1">117</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="52" page="4" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="53" page="5" column="1">118</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54" page="5" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Practice and its Effects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="5" column="1">Within an ecological model, practice can be described and analysed as a texture of connections in action ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi, 2006</xref>), delineating a third analytical level in ad- dition to those of practices ‘from outside’ and ‘from inside’, a level that involves analysis of practices in terms of their deliberate and non-deliberate consequences as and when they are being practised. Hence, practice is viewed as the effect of a weaving-together of interconnections in action, or as a ‘doing’ of society. Such a third reading of practice considers the social effects of a single practice in relation to its being practised within society. This is the level of the reflexivity of practices and the reproduction of society. Ethnomethodologists talk of the inevitable reflexivity of practices to show that every practice creates its context: ‘Reflexivity refers to the dynamic self-organizational tendency of social interaction to provide for its own constitution through practices of accountability and scenic display’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Flynn, 1991</xref>: 28). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu (1972)</xref> speaks of ‘circuits of reproduction’, that is, the reciprocal, cyclical relationships through which practice creates and re- creates the objectified social structures and the conditions in which it occurs. At this analytical level the researcher asks: What is it that doing the practice does? And it is the level at which ethical questions can be asked and at which<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> the emancipatory or exploitative effects of a social practice may be questioned. Mathieu’s contribution in this issue illustrates this third level of analysis. In his article Mathieu illustrates how gender is a social practice that cuts across other practices (of work and organization) and produces inequality effects rooted in the unintentional doing of actors. The theme of the effects of practices, of the morality associated with their accomplishment, and of the applications of theories of practice in action research, is introduced in this special issue by Blackler and Regan, who present an example of intervention interpreted from within activity theory: that is, from a theoretical point of view originating in cultural psychology which uses the concept of system of activity rather than practice. This preference has historical and disciplinary origins, which the article clearly describes and which, interestingly, represent the other extreme of the concept of practice. In fact, we may say that the term ‘practice’ is an in-between concept which relates on the one hand to the semantic domain of habit and of habitual action (and therefore, as we have seen, to routine as an uncertainty reduction device), and on the other, to the domain of deliberate action. Practice contains elements of both domains, but it coincides with neither of them. Blackler and Regan’s article is particularly efficacious in its discussion of intentionality and agency in theories of practice, and it also addresses the question of the usability of PBS in relation to organizational change. The essays by Bjørkeng, Clegg and Pitsis and by Blackler and Regan respond to the following questions: Why study practices? What relationships do they entertain with change and organizational stability? What should the researcher’s relationship be with the moral accountability of the practices that he or she studies? These are questions which have been variously addressed in the main fields of study that have employed practice as a lens, and which I now outline in order to show how PBS are mainly concerned to develop a politics of knowledge while criticizing the representationalist conception of knowledge.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="64" page="5" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="6" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="66" page="6" column="1">119</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="68" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">When Practice is Used as a Lens</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" page="6" column="1">The complex map of PBS can be presented in many different ways; delineating a map is always an arbitrary operation. I have done so previously in relation to the intellectual traditions converging in the study of knowing-in-practice ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi, 2001</xref>) and in relation to the so-called paradigm of situated action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi, 2008</xref>). My approach here is to point up its most salient themes, when practice has been used as a lens, to employ the apt metaphor coined by Wanda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski (2000)</xref>. I shall therefore describe the ways in which the concept of social practice has been critically appropriated as a critique of representationalist conceptions of knowledge:<marker type="block"/> 1. within studies on science to show how scientific knowledge is the situated product of laboratory practices; 2. within organizational learning to problematize what is meant by knowing in its everyday use; 3. within studies on technology (computer supported cooperative work, information systems, workplace studies) to direct attention to ‘real’ work practices,<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> to the knowledge performed within them, and to participatory design of work and technologies; 4. within gender studies in order to ‘read’ gender as a social practice and a politics of knowledge.<marker type="block"/> These are complex debates in terms of both the topic and the number of authors involved. I am therefore aware that my treatment will be limited 1 and will not do justice to the richness of the contributions. What do all these strands of inquiry have in common? Intuitively, we can see that abstract and universal concepts, in the case of both science and gender, are inscribed in a distinct temporality and spatiality. ‘Science’ is what scientists ‘do’ in their laboratories and which institutional practices transform into ‘science’; ‘gender’ is what people in interaction ‘do’, ‘say’, ‘think’ so that ‘gender’ is produced as a social effect. The same holds for the appropriation of technology and of practical knowledge. This is therefore an intentional ‘doing’ (as in the work practices of scientists), but also an unintentional one (as in the gendering of scientific occupations). It is a ‘doing’ which is productive, but simultaneously reproductive because it is a ‘doing of society’. I shall now briefly describe each of the foregoing strands.<marker type="block"/> Science as Practice The roots of ‘science as practice’ can be traced back to the 1970s and the advent of a new approach to science within the sociology of scientific knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Pickering, 1992</xref>). It was argued that scientific knowledge—much as technology— is intrinsically social. It must therefore be understood as such and studied as a set of historically situated social practices. The 1970s and 1980s saw flourishing ethnographic studies of scientific laboratories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Latour and Woolgar, 1979</xref>; Knorr- <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Cetina, 1981</xref>). In the USA, ethnomethodologists applied themselves to laboratory life and to mathematics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Lynch et al., 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Lynch, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Livingstone, 1986</xref>), whilst the ‘Tremont group’ in California continued the tradition of symbolic interactionism in the study of science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Fujimura, 1992</xref>, 1995), and in England there arose the discourse analysis developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Gilbert and Mulkay (1984)</xref> and by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Ashmore (1989)</xref> on reflexivity. Scientific knowledge was thus removed from the pedestal erected for it by positivism, and science could be seen as a culture much as every other form of knowledge and, as such, subject to implications of social control and social interests. The connection between the micro-social (laboratory practices) and the macro-social (science in society) was thematized together with issues concerning ethics and social change. The metaphor of ‘ecologies of knowledge’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Star, 1995</xref>) was proposed to locate the production of knowledge within an ecosystem that rejects the dichotomies of functionalist thought between nature and society and between the social and technical. It is argued that science and technology become ‘monsters’ when they lose their connections with the social conditions of their production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Law, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Haraway, 1992</xref>). We may say therefore that this field of studies conducted a critique against positivism and focused on the circuit of knowledge reproduction and its societal effects.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> Organizational Learning and Knowing in Practice The concept of practice gained ground in studies of organizational learning through a critical approach to learning as cognition, on the one side, and to change on the other. The strong criticisms provoked by the concept of ‘com- munity of practice’ (CoP), especially in its managerialist version (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Wenger et al., 2002</xref>), have changed the setting in which the conception of knowledge is delineated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Fox, 2000</xref>, 2006). Authors who have criticized the concept of community of practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Contu et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Cohendet et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Elkjaer, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Lindkvist, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Handley et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Roberts, 2006</xref>) have done so mainly to move from the absence of conflict to the absence of power in the concept of CoP. Now that the fashion has passed, and with it the persuasive power of the rhetoric associated with the label CoP, several authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Swan et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Roberts, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="108" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi, 2009</xref>) have proposed reversing the emphasis between the two terms—from community of practice to practices of a community. Stressed in the former case is that community constitutes the container of knowledge and the community pre-exists its activities. In the latter, it is the activities themselves that generate a community, in that they form the ‘glue’ which holds together a configuration of people, artefacts and social relations. In this case the attention is directed at the practical knowledge contextually enacted during performance of a practice and at the knowing coming from the senses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Strati, 2007</xref>). Knowledge, therefore, is not an ‘asset’ of the community, but rather an activity (a ‘knowing’), and an activity that itself constitutes the practice (‘knowing-in-practice’). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Fox (1997, 2000)</xref> and other authors, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Contu and Willmott (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Gherardi (2001)</xref>, have pointed out the ambiguity between realist and constructionist assumptions, with respect to consideration of the context as sometimes pregiven and sometimes emergent. The criticism of the conception of ‘context’ consists in showing how practices are tightly interwoven to constitute a field of practices or a network of more or less closely connected practices enduring over time, variously sustained by power, and anchored in materiality. The community is one of those effects, as well as being a device for the reproduction of the field of practices. It is therefore through the conceptions of power and materiality in actor-network theory, that the epistemology of knowledge as an object or an asset is displaced in favour of an epistemology of knowing in practice. It is in this field of studies where PBS have most contributed to a critique of the power effects of organizational learning (and knowledge management) as a man- agerial ideology.<marker type="block"/> Critical Studies of Technology and Technology as a Social Practice Technology, knowledge-sharing and coordination as an emergent phenomenon can be considered the themes which unite strands of inquiry—such as computer- supported cooperative work, critical information systems, and workplace studies— which, although highly diversified, are jointly considered here for the sake of brevity.<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> Particularly influential in this area has been Lucy Suchman’s book (1987 first edition, 2007 second) based on a symbolic interactionist framework and which criticized the concept of ex ante rationality in the form of plans assumed to regulate action, indicated by the notion of ‘situated rationality’ in contrast to the rationality of plans and programs. Before action takes place, plans serve only a predictive or organizational purpose; after that action, plans serve to justify the actions undertaken. Central to the paradigm of situated action are interactions with others, situated communication, the construction of situations, the relationship with the physical environment and the objects in it, but above all the idea that these elements are ‘held together’ by and express a situational rationality. The theme of situated rationality is taken forward by workplace studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Heath and Luff, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Luff et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Heath and Button, 2002</xref>) that are anchored in an ethnographic and ethnomethodological framework, which seek to determine how the verbal, the visual, and the material take shape through practice (and discursive practices) during the production and coordination of interaction. The terms ‘technology-in-use’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski, 1992</xref>) and ‘technology as social practice’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Suchman et al., 1999</xref>) have been coined to distinguish this approach to technology. The studies by Wanda Orlikoswki (2000, 2002, 2007) on technological practices are exemplary for their adoption of the theoretical framework of ‘structuration’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Giddens, 1984</xref>) to connect agency and structure. There arose ethnographic methods of investigation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Blomberg et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Barley, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Østerlund and Carlile, 2005</xref>) which set the study of situated working practices in opposition against the positivist methods then current in order to emphasize user requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Richardson et al., 2006</xref>). There ensued reflection on the methods adopted by researchers to represent work practices and on the need for reflexivity by researchers, who should conduct ethnographic research upon themselves, given that they are ‘knowledge workers’ who study other knowledge workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Schultze, 2000</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Gender as a Social Practice Since the publication of West and Zimmerman’s (1987) article on ‘doing gender’, drawing on Garfinkel’s (1967) classic account of Agnes, many articles and books about gender as actions that people do, not only who/what they are, or the positions they occupy, have fostered insights about how gender is accomplished through interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Bruni and Gherardi, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Martin, 2001</xref>; 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Ashcraft and Mumby, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Poggio, 2006</xref>). ‘Gender practices’, ‘gendered practices’ and ‘gendering practices’ stand for a class of activities that are available—culturally, socially, narratively, discursively, physically—to be done, asserted, performed in social contexts. How we do gender (and how we can do it differently) is still a question central to micro-politics between the sexes, in the social construction of the everyday reality of our society and culture, an assertion that presupposes that gender is a social practice that anchors other practices, in other words, it is a methodical and recurrent accomplishment. Following the line of ‘gender as social practice’, Mathieu’s contribution in this issue illustrates this stream of research in PBS, and I therefore refer the reader to his presentation.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74" page="6" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="7" column="1">120</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="76" page="7" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93" page="7" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94" page="8" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="95" page="8" column="1">121</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="115" page="8" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="116" page="9" column="1">122</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="117" page="9" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="137" page="9" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="138" page="10" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="139" page="10" column="1">123</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="140" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">The Limits of the Visual Metaphor and the Limits of Language</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" page="10" column="1">The metaphor of using practice as a lens through which to examine social phenomena is highly efficacious because it evokes a mental image of the researcher as a Sherlock Holmes intent upon the close scrutiny of a reality. However, it is also misleading because it simultaneously activates an image in which the researcher is disconnected from the field of study, which exists independently from him/her, ‘out there’. The role of language in the construction of social phenomena is too well known to require treatment here. I shall therefore merely point out that the ‘practice turn’ was preceded by a ‘linguistic turn’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Deetz, 2003</xref>) in organization studies as well, so that the concept of practice can be used as much within a positivist epistemology and a realist empiricism, as within a social constructionist epistemology. In this context, the notion of the critical power of PBS makes implicit reference to a constructionist epistemology, which conceives practices only in relation to their practitioners, and the accountability practices that have constituted them as socially sustained modes of practising. The definition of something as ‘ a practice’ is therefore itself the result of a discursive practice that has intersubjectively created a feeling and a doing around a socially recognized and recognizable modality of collective doing. All the contributions to this special issue are committed, in various ways, to describing the discursive construct which drives the emergence and unfolding of a practice over time and its ruptures and disconnections. The limitation of the metaphor of the lens is that it obscures the fact that researchers—as well as practitioners who talk about their knowing—discursively construct the phenomenon which they study and describe. Consequently, the representation of practices is the crucial issue for PBS and for the methodologies available to talk and write about knowing in practice. This theme is developed in this special issue by the article by Nicolini. The theme is crucial for several reasons, and Nicolini’s article comes last in this special issue because it links with the first article, in which Geiger poses the problem of whether practices should be defined as patterns of activity, or vice versa; whether they should be defined in their being socially sustained by a normative accountability. If the former definition is favoured, the methodologies for the analysis of practices seek to describe the tasks making up practice in analytical and routine-like manner. If the latter definition is preferred, the activities making up practice are viewed as the tip of an iceberg: they emerge and become visible because lying beneath them is a mass of practical knowledge and discursive (material-semiotic) practices that justify practices as morally and aesthetically acceptable. In this sense, practice discloses its aspect as an institution, the product of a negotiated order which has momentarily crystallized a shared mode of doing and sustains it while the premises for its change are being set. These two authors suggest two topical moments in which to study practices. Geiger suggests looking at breakdowns and the discursive forms of practice repair in order to direct attention to the moments in which practices constitute an uninterrupted flow (a life-world) and the moments in which practitioners reflect upon and negotiate practices. Nicolini instead proposes accessing practices through the discursive practices of the practitioners that make practices accountable for the researcher through a projective technique.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> Methodological questions in the empirical study of practices raise crucial theoretical issues because, on the one hand, theories of practice start from the assumption that practical knowledge is observable and describable without the need for categories such as intentionality, values or knowledge (one therefore understands why ethnomethodology is one of the most influential theories of practice within PBS), and on the other, because they fully endorse the contention of both Bourdieu and Polanyi that practical knowledge is personal knowledge: it is ineffable, and hence our re-presentations of practices are always ‘poor’ because, as Polanyi puts it, we know more than we can tell. Language thus reveals its limitations, showing that human knowledge is also pre-discursive, sensorial and embodied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Strati, 2007</xref>). We know through the body and sensorial experience that knowledge is not only individual but is also collectively elaborated in the form of taste-making. The question of what socially sustains practices and how practices are reproduced and in being reproduced change over time—intentionally and unintentionally—is more challenging for opening a critical stance on society and the social effects of consolidated practices than the study of practice as a recurrent pattern of action. The shifts from organization to organizing and from work to working entail consideration not only of temporality and becoming, but also of (temporary) permanence, and therefore of practices as order-generating mechanisms.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="143" page="10" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144" page="11" column="1">124</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="145" page="11" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="148" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Where is the Critical Power?</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="149" page="11" column="1">The ‘practice turn’ in organizational studies is at odds with cognitivism and rationalism because it defines knowledge as a practical and situated activity. It propounds a vision of organizing as knowledgeable collective action within an ecology of humans and non-humans. PBS therefore constitutes both a sociology and a politics of knowledge in its everyday use. In summary, practice as epistemology articulates knowledge in and about organizing as practical accomplishment, rather than as a transcendental account of a decontextualized reality done by a genderless and disembodied researcher. The knowledge interest of critical PBS in regard to work and organizations is determining how practitioners do what they do and what doing does; how working and organizing practices become institutionalized because they are sustained by a ‘working consensus’ (an institutional work) and a moral and aesthetic order; and on how practising is interactionally sustained by a pre-verbal understanding, a mutual orientation and a production of mutually intelligible artefacts. Theories of practice furnish the theoretical and methodological bases for the construction of middle-range theories which flank the vision of organization as planning and design (rationality from outside) with the vision of organization as an unstable accomplishment in becoming, but based on widespread social intelligibility (contingent and plural rationalities).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="150" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Note</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">1. I shall not refer to the large stream of ‘strategy as practice’ since in this case practice is used to refer to processes (i.e. strategizing) rather than to practices of knowledge</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="152" page="11" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="153" page="12" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="154" page="12" column="1">125</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">production. While the debate is critical of the prescriptive ethos in strategy studies, seldom has it a critical stance toward cognitivism and positivism.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="156" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="12" column="1">Ashcraft, K. and Mumby, D. (2004) Reworking Gender. London: SAGE.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Ashmore, M. (1989) The Reflexive Thesis: Writing Sociology of Knowledge. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Barley, S. R. (1996) ‘Technicians in the Workplace: Ethnographic Evidence for Bringing Work into Organizational Studies’, Administrative Science Quarterly 41(3): 404–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="12" column="1">Blomberg, J., Giacomi, J., Mosher, A. and Swenton-Wall, P. (1993) ‘Ethnographic Field Methods and Their Relation to Design’, in D. Schuler and A. Namioka (eds) Participatory Design: Principles and Practices, pp. 123–55. Hillsdale, NY: Lawrence Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="12" column="1">Bourdieu, P. (1972) Outline of a Theory of Practice. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="12" column="1">Bourdieu, P. (1990) The Logic of Practice. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="12" column="1">Brown, J. S. and Duguid, P. (1991) ‘Organizational Learning and Communities of Practice: Toward a Unified View of Working, Learning and Bureaucratization’, Organization Science 2(1): 40–57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="12" column="1">Brown, J. S. and Duguid, P. (2001) ‘Knowledge and Organization: A Social-Practice Perspective’, Organization Science 12(2): 198–213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="12" column="1">Bruni, A. and Gherardi, S. (2001) ‘Omega’s Story: The Heterogeneous Engineering of a Gendered Professional Self’, in M. Dent and S. Whitehead (eds) Managing Professional Identities. Knowledge, Performativity and the New Professional, pp. 174–98. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="12" column="1">Carlile, P. R. (2002) ‘A Pragmatic View of Knowledge and Boundaries: Boundary Objects in New Product Development’, Organization Science 13(4): 442–55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Chia, R. and Holt, R. (2006) ‘Strategy as Practical Copying: an Heideggerian Perspective’, Organization Studies 27(5): 635–55</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="12" column="1">Cohen, I. J. (1996) ‘Theories of Action and Praxis’, in B. S. Turner (ed.) The Blackwell Companion to Social Theory, pp. 111–42. Cambridge, MA: Blackwell.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="12" column="1">Cohen, M. (2007) ‘Reading Dewey: Reflections on the Study of Routines’, Organization Studies 28(5): 773–86.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="12" column="1">Cohendet P., Creplet, P., Diani, M., Dupouet, O. and Schenk, E. (2004) ‘Matching Communities and Hierarchies Within the Firm’, Journal of Management and Governance 8(1): 27–48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="12" column="1">Contu, A. and Willmott, H. (2003) ‘Re-embedding Situatedness: The Importance of Power Relations in Learning Theory’, Organization Science 14(3): 283–96.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="12" column="1">Contu, A., Grey, C. and Ortenblad, A. (2003) ‘Against Learning’, Human Relations 56(8): 931–52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Czarniawska, B. (2004) ‘On Time, Space and Action Nets’, Organization 11(6): 773–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="12" column="1">Deetz, S. (2003) ‘Reclaiming the Legacy of the Linguistic Turn’, Organization 10(3): 421–9.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="12" column="1">Elkjaer, B. (2003) ‘Organizational Learning with a Pragmatic Slant’, International Journal of Lifelong Education 22(5): 481–94.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="12" column="1">Elkjaer, B. (2004) ‘Organizational Learning: The “Third Way”’, Management Learning 35(4): 419–34.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="12" column="1">Evered, R. and Louis, M. R. (1981) ‘Alternative Perspectives in the Organizational Sciences. “Inquiry from the Inside” and “Inquiry from the Outside”’, Academy of Management Review 6: 385–95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="13" column="1">Feldman, M. (2000) ‘Organizational Routines as a Source of Continuous Change’, Organization Science 11(6): 611–29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="13" column="1">Feldman, M. S. and Pentland, B. T. (2003) ‘Re-conceptualizing Organizational Routines as a Source of Flexibility and Change’, Administrative Science Quarterly 48(1): 94–118.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="13" column="1">Flynn, P. (1991) The Ethnomethodological Movement. New York: Mouton de Gruyter. Foucault, M. (1980) Power/Knowledge. New York: Pantheon Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Fox, S. (1997) ‘Situated Learning Theory Versus Traditional Cognitive Theory: Why Management Education Should not Ignore Management Learning’, Systems Practice 10(6): 749–71.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="13" column="1">Fox, S. (2000) ‘Communities of Practice, Foucault and Actor-Network Theory’, Journal of Management Studies 37(6): 853–67.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Fox, S. (2006) ‘Inquiries of Every Imaginable Kind: Ethnomethodology, Practical Action and the New Socially Situated Learning Theory’, The Sociological Review 54(3): 426–45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="13" column="1">Fujimura, J. (1992) ‘Crafting Science: Standardized Packages, Boundary Objects, and “Translation”’, in A. Pickering (ed.) Science as Practice and Culture, pp. 168–214. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="13" column="1">Fujimura, J. (1995) ‘Ecologies of Action: Recombining Genes, Molecularizing Cancer, and Transforming Biology’, in S. L. Star (ed.) Ecologies of Knowledge, pp. 302–46. Albany: State University of New York Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="13" column="1">Garfinkel, H. (1967) Studies in Ethnomethodology. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" page="13" column="1">Gherardi, S. (2001) ‘Practice-based Theorizing on Learning and Knowing in Organizations: An Introduction’, Organization 7(2): 211–23.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="13" column="1">Gherardi, S. (2006) Organizational Knowledge: The Texture of Workplace Learning. Oxford: Blackwell.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="13" column="1">Gherardi, S. (2008) ‘Situated Knowledge and Situated Action: What Do Practice-Based Studies Promise?’ in D. Barry and H. Hansen (eds) SAGE Handbook of the New &amp; Emerging in Management and Organization, pp. 516–25. London: SAGE.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="13" column="1">Gherardi, S. (2009) ‘Communities of Practice or Practices of a Community?’ in S. Armstrong and C. Fukami (eds) Handbook of Management Learning, Education and Development, pp. 514–30. London: SAGE.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="13" column="1">Gherardi, S., Nicolini, D. and Odella, F. (1998) ‘Towards a Social Understanding of how People Learn in Organizations’, Management Learning 29(3): 273–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="13" column="1">Giddens, A. (1984) The Constitution of Society. Cambridge: Polity.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="13" column="1">Gilbert, G. and Mulkay, M. (1984) Opening Pandora’s Box: a Sociological Analysis of Scientists’ Discourse. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="13" column="1">Handley, K., Sturdy, A., Fincham, R. and Clark, T. (2006) ‘Within and Beyond Communities of Practice: Making Sense of Learning Through Participation, Identity and Practice’, Journal of Management Studies 43(3): 641–53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="13" column="1">Haraway, D. (1992) ‘The Promises of Monsters: A Regenerative Politics for Inappropiate/ d Others’, in P. Treichler, C. Nelson and L. Grossberg (eds) Cultural Studies Now and in the Future, pp.295–337. New York: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Heath, C. and Button, G. (2002) ‘Special Issue on Workplace Studies: Editorial Introduction’, The British Journal of Sociology 53(2): 157–61.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Heath, C. and Luff, P. (2000) Technology in Action. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="13" column="1">Knorr-Cetina, K. (1981) The Manufacture of Knowledge. Oxford: Pergamon Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="13" column="1">Knorr-Cetina, K. (1997) ‘Sociality with Objects: Social Relations in Post-Social Knowledge Societies’, Theory, Culture and Society 14(4): 1–30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="13" column="1">Latour, B. (2005) Reassembling the Social. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="13" column="1">Latour, B. and Woolgar, S. (1979) Laboratory Life: The Social Construction of Scientific Facts. Beverly Hills, CA: SAGE.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Law, J., ed. (1991) ‘Sociology of Monsters? Power, Technology and the Modern World’, The Sociological Review Monograph 38. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="14" column="1">Lindkvist, L. (2005) ‘Knowledge Communities and Knowledge Collectivities: A Typology of Knowledge Work in Groups’, Journal of Management Studies 42(6): 1189–210.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="14" column="1">Livingstone, E. (1986) The Ethnomethodological Foundations of Mathematics. Boston, MA: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="14" column="1">Luff, P., Hindmarsh, J. and Heath, C., (eds) (2000) Workplace Studies. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Lynch, M. (1985) Art and Artifact in Laboratory Life. A Study of Shop Work and Shop Talk in a Research Laboratory. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" page="14" column="1">Lynch, M., Livingstone, E. and Garfinkel, H. (1983) ‘Temporal Order’, in K. Knorr- Cetina and M. Mulkay (eds) Science Observed, pp. 205–80. London: SAGE.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Lyotard, J. (1979) The Postmodern Condition. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="14" column="1">Martin, P. Y. (2001) ‘“Mobilizing Masculinities”: Women’s Experience of Men at Work’, Organization 8(4): 587–618.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Martin, P. Y. (2003) ‘“Said and Done” Versus “Saying and Doing”. Gendered Practices/ Practicing Gender at Work’, Gender &amp; Society, 17(3): 342–66.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="14" column="1">Orlikowski, W. J. (1992) ‘The Duality of Technology: Rethinking the Concept of Technology in Organizations’, Organization Science 3(3): 398–427.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" page="14" column="1">Orlikowski, W. J. (2000) ‘Using Technology and Constructing Structures: A Practice Lens for Studying Technology in Organizations’, Organization Science 11(4): 404–28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="14" column="1">Orlikowski, W. J. (2002) ‘Knowing in Practice: Enacting a Collective Capability in Distributed Organizing’, Organization Science 13: 249–73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="14" column="1">Orlikowski, W. J. (2007) ‘Sociomaterial Practices: Exploring Technology at Work’, Organization Studies 28(9): 1435–48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" page="14" column="1">Østerlund, C. and Carlile, P. (2005) ‘Relations in Practice: Sorting Through Practice Theories on Knowledge Sharing in Complex Organizations’, The Information Society 21(2): 91–107.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="14" column="1">Pickering, A. (1992) Science as Practice and Culture. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="14" column="1">Poggio, B. (2006) ‘Editorial: Outline of a Theory of Gender Practices’, Gender, Work and Organization 13(3): 225–33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="14" column="1">Richardson, H., Tapia, A. and Kvasny, L. (2006) ‘Introduction: Applying Critical Theory to the Study of ICT’, Social Science Computer Review 24(3): 267–73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" page="14" column="1">Roberts, J. (2006) ‘Limits to Communities of Practice’, Journal of Management Studies 43(3): 623–39.</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" page="14" column="1">Samra-Fredericks, D., Bargiela-Chiappini, F. (2008) ‘Introduction to the Symposium on the Foundations of Organizing: the Contribution from Garfinkel, Goffman and Sacks’, Organization Studies 29(5): 653–75.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" page="14" column="1">Schatzki, T. R. (1996) Social Practices: A Wittgensteinian Approach to Human Activity and the Social. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" page="14" column="1">Schatzki, T. R. (2001) ‘Introduction. Practice Theory’, in T. R. Schatzki, K. Knorr-Cetina and E. von Savigny (eds) The Practice Turn in Contemporary Theory, pp. 1–14. London and New York: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="14" column="1">Schultze, U. (2000) ‘A Confessional Account of an Ethnography about Knowledge Work’, MIS Quarterly 24(1): 3–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" page="14" column="1">Star, S. L. (1995) Ecologies of Knowledge. Albany: State University of New York Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" page="14" column="1">Star, S. L. and Griesemer, J. (1989) ‘Institutional Ecology, “Translations”, and Coherence: Amateurs and Professionals in Berkeley’s Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, 1907–1939’, Social Studies of Science 19: 387–420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Strati, A. (2007) ‘Sensible Knowledge and Practice-Based Learning’, Management Learning 38(1): 61–77.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" page="14" column="1">Suchman, L. (1987) Plans and Situated Action: The Problem of Human–Machine Com- munication. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" page="15" column="1">Suchman, L. (2007) Human–Machine Reconfigurations: Plans and Situated Actions. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" page="15" column="1">Suchman, L., Blomberg, J., Orr, J. E. and Trigg, R. (1999) ‘Reconstructing Technologies as Social Practice’, American Behavioural Scientist 43(3): 392–408.</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" page="15" column="1">Swan, J., Scarbrough, H. and Robertson, M. (2002). ‘The Construction of “Communities of Practice” in the Management of Innovation’, Management Learning 33(4): 477–96.</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" page="15" column="1">Taylor, C. (1995) Philosophical Arguments. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R76" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Turner, S. (1994) The Social Theory of Practices. Chicago, IL: The University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R77" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" page="15" column="1">Wenger, E., Mc.Dermott, R. and Snyder, W. M. (2002) Cultivating Communities Of Practice. Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R78" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" page="15" column="1">West, C. and Zimmerman, D. (1987) ‘Doing Gender’, Gender and Society 1(2): 125–51.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="178" page="12" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="179" page="13" column="1">126</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="13" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="206" page="13" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="207" page="14" column="1">Gherardi: Introduction: The Critical Power of the ‘Practice Lens’</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="208" page="14" column="1">127</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="234" page="14" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="235" page="15" column="1">128</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="236" page="15" column="1">Management Learning 40(2)</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="244" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Contact Address</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="246" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Silvia Gherardi is professor in the Department of Sociology, Universita Degli Studi Di Trento, Piazza Venezia 41, Trento, I 38100, Italy. [email: <email id="245">silvia.gherardi@soc.unitn.it</email>]</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="247" page="15" column="1">Downloaded from mlq.sagepub.com at Lancaster University Library on November 18, 2013</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
