<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>07dea36a6cd5e08244b5405e759d830840e7be61a5d226577f5b725b5f32d979</job>
    <base_name>62it</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s0164-1212(98)10080-8</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Joint application design (JAD) in practice</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">E.J. Davidson</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Department of Decisions Sciences, College of Business Administration, University of Hawai'i, Manoa, 2404 Maile Way, Honolulu, HI 96822, USA</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6">Joint application design (JAD) is an intuitively appealing systems development method that encompasses approaches for en- hancing user participation, expediting development, and improving the quality of speci®cations. Although the JAD method has been widely acclaimed, little is actually known about its eectiveness in practice. This paper reports ®ndings of a ®eld study at three organizations in which JAD practices were examined to assess how practice in ̄uenced outcomes of JAD use. Findings suggest that the organizations realized modest improvements in systems development outcomes by using the JAD method. JAD use was most eective in small, clearly focused projects and less eective in large, complex projects. Findings also suggest that practices for using JAD at the research sites reduced its potential eectiveness by limiting user participation, focusing workshop exercises on devel- opers' analytical models and terminology, and applying the JAD method prematurely in large projects. Adaptations of the JAD method in practice stemmed from unresolved con ̄icts between assumptions underlying the espoused JAD method and the status quo IS development approach at each organization. Implications for the eectiveness of the JAD method as a software process improvement are considered. Ó 1999 Elsevier Science Inc. All rights reserved.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="1" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="5" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Received 1 April 1998; accepted 22 October 1998</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" page="1" column="1">Joint application design (JAD) is a generic term which describes a variety of proprietary and custom- developed methods for conducting workshops in which users and technical developers work together on infor- mation system (IS) project planning, requirements de®- nition, user interface design, or other activities. A key feature of JAD is the use of a session leader trained in group dynamic techniques to facilitate the workshop sessions. Steps for setting workshop objectives, identi- fying participants, and selecting analytical tasks and documentation are also speci®ed. (See Carmel et al. (1993) for an overview of the JAD method and Wood and Silver (1995) for a practitioner guide.) Well-known systems development methodologies such as Informa- tion Engineering (Martin, 1990) and Rapid Application Design (Andrews, 1991) prescribe the use of JAD workshops in conjunction with other analytical methods to improve and expedite system speci®cation activities. JAD methods have been heralded by consultants (An- drews, 1991; Rush, 1985) and enthusiastically endorsed by organizations reporting improvements in system</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">* Corresponding author. Tel.: +1-808-956-6657; fax: +1-808-956- 9889; e-mail: <email id="9">davidson@busadm.cba.hawaii.edu</email></h1>
      </section>
      <region class="unknown" id="11" page="1" column="2">*</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="2">quality, IS productivity, development time, or user commitment resulting from JAD use (Aiosa, 1989; Bradley, 1989; Duncan, 1990; Kettelkut, 1997; Keyes, 1989). Despite these testimonials, we know little about the ecacy of a joint user/developer workshop approach in systems speci®cation activities or the potential of the JAD method to improve systems development out- comes. One industry study indicated that JAD, when used in combination with other software process im- provement techniques, may contribute to software error prevention (Jones, 1991), but the speci®c contributions of the JAD method to this type of improvement are unclear. Academic researchers have examined the eects of using groupware technology in JAD workshops (Carmel et al., 1995; Liou and Chen, 1993), but thus far research has not addressed fundamental questions about the ecacy of the JAD method as a software process improvement. In particular, research has not examined the role that practice may play in realizing bene®ts from JAD use, yet the JAD method has been applied to a variety of system speci®cation activities from simple meeting facilitation to highly structured workshops (Kettelkut, 1997; Wood and Silver, 1995). Such a variation in practice clearly may have impli- cations for the eectiveness of the JAD method. There is <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> often a gap between the way a systems development method is portrayed in scienti®c and technical literature and its application in an organizational context (Bansler and Bùdker, 1993). Gaps between espoused methods and practice result not only from misunderstanding or lack of training but also from organizational constraints on how a method may feasibly be applied. Thus, when evaluating a method's eectiveness, it is important to consider how the method is actually applied in practice and whether organizational constraints on practice limit its bene®ts. In the case of the JAD method, such sys- tematic ®eld research on JAD practices is lacking. Thus, the goals of this exploratory research project were to investigate how the JAD method has been applied in practice, to examine organizational constraints on practice that may aect outcomes of JAD use, and to consider the eectiveness of JAD as a software process improvement given organizational constraints on prac- tice. This paper reports the ®ndings of a ®eld study of JAD practices in three business organizations and dis- cusses the relationship between JAD-as-practiced and reported bene®ts of JAD use. Implications of these ®ndings for the eectiveness of the JAD method as a software process improvement are also considered.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="13" page="1" column="2">0164-1212/99/$ ± see front matter Ó 1999 Elsevier Science Inc. All rights reserved. PII: S 0 1 6 4 - 1 2 1 2 ( 9 8 ) 1 0 0 8 0 - 8</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="14" page="2" column="1">216</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="15" page="2" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="17" page="2" column="1">2. Field study methodology</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="2" column="1">The research study was conducted at three business organizations, each having more than three years expe- rience using a JAD method. The research sites were se- lected as a convenience sample drawn from a group of about 15 companies participating in a regional JAD facilitators user group. Each research site was a medi- um- to large-sized ®nancial services company in the northeast United States, with four to eight thousand employees in the headquarters oce. The three organi- zations had adopted a variety of systems development process changes in the three to ®ve years prior to the research study, such as the information engineering (IE) methodology, computer assisted software engineering (CASE) tools, and data  ̄ow and data entity modeling methods. The ®ndings presented in this paper are drawn from interviews with 34 organization members who had par- ticipated in JAD workshops in these organization (see Table 1). Open-ended questions were used to elicit in- formants' experiences in one or more JAD workshops, their descriptions of workshop activities, participants, and project outcomes, and their perceptions of the ef- fects of using the JAD method in the development process. In one project, the researcher observed a two- day JAD workshop session before interviewing the facilitator, IS project manager, and business manger involved in the project, and in this way compared ®rst- hand observations with informants' accounts.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="19" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">Table 1 Interviews conducted Research site IS project Business Facilitators Total managers managers Alpha 4 2 4 10 Beta 7 5 4 16 Gamma 2 3 3 8 Total 13 10 11 34</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="2" column="2">In the 34 interviews conducted, a total of 20 projects in which the JAD method had been used were described by one to four informants. Descriptive data about these projects and the associated JAD workshops were ex- tracted from informants' accounts. Table 2 summarizes project characteristics; Table 3 summarizes JAD prac- tices used in the project workshops. Descriptions of the ocial policies for JAD use at each research site, de- scribed in Table 4, were derived from reviewing JAD procedural manuals and from interviews with JAD fa- cilitators at the research sites. Except for user satisfaction surveys, these organiza- tions had not formally evaluated the eectiveness of the JAD method. Quantitative evaluations of reductions in development time, costs, design errors, etc., were not feasible because the sites lacked sucient statistical data on systems development outcomes. Thus, to obtain data on JAD eectiveness, study informants were asked open-ended questions about their perceptions of how use of the JAD workshop method had aected systems development outcomes on projects in which they had participated. Their responses were later analyzed and coded. Table 5 summarizes the frequency of responses by category for the 20 projects examined in the study. To provide a basis for comparison of ®ndings from the small convenience sample used in the ®eld study to a broader group of organizations using the JAD method, the researcher participated in and observed six-day-long meetings of two JAD facilitators user groups. Each meeting was attended by JAD facilitators representing 12±15 organizations. As an observer in these meetings, the researcher noted discussion of issues, problems, and examples related to JAD practice and organizational constraints on JAD use. As a participant, the researcher had the opportunity to pose questions about aspects of JAD practice which were emerging from the analysis of data from the research sites. To further explore practice- related themes, in-depth interviews were conducted with ®ve JAD facilitators who had extensive experience with JAD in a variety of organizations. Comparison of the ®ndings from the three research sites with information reported by this broader group of organizations sug- gested that JAD practices identi®ed in the study were common among this group. Major themes concerning the relationship between the practice of JAD, perceived outcomes of JAD use,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="21" page="3" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="22" page="3" column="1">217</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Table 2 Characteristics of the 20 projects examined Projects studied at Alpha: 6 Project size/complexity AIC: MIS/medium (4 informants) Small (one functional area, less than 1 year to implement) CFG: TPS/large (2 informants) Medium (more than one functional area or more than 1 year) EIS: MIS/medium (1 informant) Large (multiple functions, multiyear project) HMO: TPS/small (1 informant) LH: TPS/large (2 informants) SIS: TPS/large (1 informant)</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="24" page="3" column="1">Projects studied at Beta: 9 Type of application system</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="25" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">ACCT: TPS/small (4 informants) Management information or reporting system (MIS) LTC: TPS/small (1 informant) Transaction processing system (TPS) LTDB: MIS/small (1 informant) MIRA: MIS/small (2 informants) (TPS) PI(1): TPS/medium (1 informant) PI(2): TPS/small (1 informant) PVAL: TPS/medium (3 informants) SWH: MIS/large (1 informant) MORT: TPS/medium (2 informants)</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="26" page="3" column="1">Projects studied at Gamma: 5 Project status at time of ®eld study</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">CIS: MIS/medium (1 informant) Application system implemented; project completed DCBS: TPS/large (4 informants) Development tasks ongoing or ®rst stage implemented EIS: MIS/medium (1 informant) Project suspended MAJ: TPS/medium (1 informant) PL: TPS/medium (1 informant)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="3" column="1">and its ecacy as a software process improvement were identi®ed through a qualitative data analysis process (Miles and Huberman, 1994), in which thematic cate- gories were identi®ed from the interview data, the cat- egories were applied in the content analysis of the data, and categories were iteratively re®ned and reapplied.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="29" page="3" column="1">3. Findings and analysis</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" page="3" column="1">Three areas of JAD practice at the research sites were identi®ed that re ̄ected organizational constraints on use of the JAD method or that aected outcomes of JAD use. These ®ndings are discussed in the following sections and relationships between JAD-as-practiced and reported bene®ts of JAD use are considered.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="31" page="3" column="1">3.1. Limiting user participation in the JAD workshop</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="3" column="1">JAD is typically portrayed as a vehicle for enhancing user participation in systems development activities (Carmel et al., 1993; Wood and Silver, 1995). The es- poused JAD method speci®es an intensive workshop lasting several days or more in which users participate on a full-time basis with developers to complete system speci®cation activities (Wood and Silver, 1995). How- ever, the extent and breath of user participation in JAD workshops at the three research sites was limited in practice due to the ways in which personnel were allo- cated to systems development activities. IS personnel typically were assigned full-time to projects and systems</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="33" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">6 9 5</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="34" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">7 13</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">8 10 2</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="3" column="2">development activities, whereas business area personnel usually were given little or no relief from their day-to- day responsibilities to attend JAD sessions. Comment- ing on his experiences facilitating a number of JAD workshops, the senior facilitator at one research site observed:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Organizationally, Alpha hasn't dealt with the time commitment of clients [business users].</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="3" column="2">As a result, user personnel were unable or unwilling to commit to full-time participation in JAD workshop, and the JAD method was adapted in practice to ac- commodate users' limited availability. As indicated in Table 3, in 35% of the projects studied, IS personnel familiar with existing information systems attended sessions in place of business users. In one project, the ratio of IS personnel attending the workshops to users was 3-to-1. In 25% of the projects studied, IS per- sonnel performed key analytical activities outside of the workshop setting to minimize the time users would be asked to spend in the JAD sessions. In four of the 20 projects described by informants, headquarters personnel substituted for actual systems users from ®eld operations, who did not attend the JAD sessions at all. The comments of a headquarters business manager illustrated the consequences of these JAD practices:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">We didn't use the [®eld managers] in the actual JADs. It was too much time. We met too often.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="40" page="4" column="1">218</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="4" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="42" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Table 3 JAD practices in 20 projects studied</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="43" page="4" column="1">Project/Workshop characteristic Type of workshop schedule used</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Traditional, intensive workshop (3±5 consecutive days) Modi®ed workshop (1/2 day/whole days spread over weeks) Series of meetings (2±3 hrs 1±3/week)</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="45" page="4" column="1">Objectives of the JAD workshop a</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="46" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">High-level systems planning Requirements/business rules de®nition IS analytic models (DFDs, E-R/Ds,etc.) System design tasks (reports, interface) Implementation planning</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="47" page="4" column="1">Accommodations for limited user time availability</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="48" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">IS sta attend workshop to represent business requirements Headquarters sta or management attend JAD sessions in place of actual system users such as ®eld oce personnel IS personnel perform analyst tasks outside the workshop in order to reduce users' time in the JAD sessions Designated users attended workshops full-time a More than one answer may apply to each project.</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">We couldn't bring them out of the ®eld that often. We knew that we [three headquarters managers] knew 80±90% of the requirements. We felt that was good enough.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="4" column="1">Constraints on the time business area participants had to dedicate to system development activities also aected how the JAD workshop sessions were sched- uled. In practice, the espoused workshop approach was less than feasible, as this business manager commented:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">We met two to three times a week for two to three hours a session. That's not ideal, but with time con- straints, that's all we could do.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="4" column="1">While there were instances at each research site in which the JAD workshop approach was implemented as espoused, in 60% of the projects studied the workshop</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Table 4 JAD-related policies and practices at the three research sites Alpha Beta Gamma JAD method Custom in-house method Proprietary method Custom in-house method Typical uses of JAD New development or systems replacement, New development or systems replacement, New development or systems re- With information engineering life cycle To develop systems analytical models placement For specifying business (ISP, BAA) rules and policies Facilitator sta IS development personnel in decentralized Corporate IS sta in productivity depart- Corporate IS sta and IS person- groups, Part-time ment, Full-time nel in distributed development groups, Part-time Facilitator tasks Project screening, Consulting with project Project screening, Agenda planning, Project screening, Consulting with leader to develop agenda, Workshop logis- Preliminary analysis, Workshop logistics, project leader to develop agenda, tics, Workshop meeting facilitation Workshop meeting facilitation, Session Workshop logistics, Workshop documentation meeting facilitation Session docu- mentation Charge back policy No chargeback for facilitators' time Facilitator time charged per-hour of Facilitator time charged per-day activity of workshop</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="54" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2"># % 8 40 9 45 3 15</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="55" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">10 50 6 30 12 60 8 40 1 5</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">7 35 4 20 5 25 4 20</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" page="4" column="2">schedule was spread over weeks or months as a series of whole-day or half-day sessions or to a series of meetings (see Table 3). As evident in Table 5, practicing JAD in this way had implications for the bene®ts of using the JAD method. Stretching out the JAD workshop schedule to accom- modate part-time participation by users limited the ex- tent to which system speci®cation time could be reduced through JAD use. In only two of 20 projects did infor- mants report that JAD use had helped the project team to de®ne requirements faster. None of the informants suggested that the JAD method had reduced the overall systems development timeframe. Other bene®ts such as improved quality of requirements de®ned, learning about business applications and systems, improved re- lationships between users and developers, and so on, are largely the result of interactions among business users and between users and developers in the workshop set-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="58" page="5" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="59" page="5" column="1">219</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="60" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Table 5 Perceived bene®ts and contributions to project outcomes of JAD use in 20 projects studied</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="61" page="5" column="1">Bene®cial outcomes of JAD use for the project a</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Completion/documentation of analytical tasks or steps Better quality of requirements de®ned Relationship building (IS/users; users/users) Business personnel learn about systems, business Vehicle for completing methodological steps Requirements de®ned more eciently (IS developers' time) User satisfaction and buy-in to system as speci®ed IS personnel learn about business, system Consensus achieved on requirements Requirements de®ned faster</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="63" page="5" column="1">Use of system speci®cations from the JAD workshop in subsequent project activities</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">System implemented as speci®ed (5 small pjcts.; 6 medium pjcts.) JAD speci®cation partially implemented (1 small pjct.; 2 large pjcts.) JAD speci®cation not implemented (2 large pjcts.) Project development on hold (1 medium pjct.; 1 large pjct.) JAD approach abandoned during project (1 medium pjct.) JAD used to develop a plan only (1 medium project pjct.) a More than one answer may apply to each project.</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="5" column="1">ting. It is not surprising, given the ways the JAD method was modi®ed in practice to accommodate constraints on users' participation in the workshops, that informants cited these outcomes for only 15±30% of the projects studied. <marker type="block"/> The JAD method has been described as a forum for business users to articulate requirements for information systems in terms they can understand (Duncan, 1990; Keyes, 1989; Wood and Silver, 1995). JAD practice at the three research sites, however, was heavily weighted towards use of IS developers' language and modeling methods. A key objective of the JAD workshop in 60% of the projects studied was to produce analytical models such as data ̄ow diagrams, data entity diagrams, func- tional decomposition diagrams, or logical record designs (see Table 3). Completing and documenting such mod- els was the most frequently cited systems development outcome (75% of the projects) of using the JAD method (see Table 5). At Alpha, where JAD sessions were used to conduct phases of the Information Engineering life cycle, a CASE tool was sometimes used during the workshop to collect and document information for IS models, which further structured workshop activities and dialogue along these lines. In the workshop sessions, facilitators used a combi- nation of open-ended and structured exercises to elicit the information from JAD participants for IS analytical models. Most of the IS personnel interviewed saw no diculties with this approach. As one IS manager maintained,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="66" page="5" column="1">3.2. Focusing on IS analytical models in workshop sessions</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="68" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Projects reporting % 15 75 6 30 5 25 5 25 4 20 3 15 3 15 3 15 3 5 2 10</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="69" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">11 55 3 15 2 10 2 10 1 5 1 5</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">The data model was a form everyone could use.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="5" column="2">However, several IS and business managers interviewed for this study questioned how eectively users could articulate business requirements in the terms of these models in the workshop setting. One IS manager, de- scribing the use of a JAD workshop to arrive at a data model, commented:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">We used a group process, a large group process, to try to put together a data model. That was I'd say at best 25% successful.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="5" column="2">Business area participants in such analytical exercises typically received only written descriptions of these modeling techniques or a brief introduction in a pre- workshop presentation. A business manager, while commenting positively about his experience with the JAD workshop and the system which resulted, expressed his frustration with the data modeling exercise:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Doing the data model. We'd go crazy. The world changes, the law changes, the business changesF F F We had to say, stop. We can't get the model perfect. Things got really bogged down.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="5" column="2">In a project at Gamma, the business area manager lost interest and stopped attending sessions as the modeling exercises got more detailed. A facilitator at Alpha de- scribed a series of workshop meetings dedicated to producing a data entity model, in which hostility that arose between the business area participants and the data modeling experts persisted for several years after the JAD workshops. <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The frequency of outcomes of JAD use cited by study informants suggests how these practices may in ̄uence JAD eectiveness (Table 5). Producing and document- ing analytical models was an important outcome of using JAD in 75% of the projects. Yet better quality requirements de®nition was cited in only 30% of pro- jects; eciency of requirements de®nition and reaching consensus on requirements was cited in only 15% of the projects.<marker type="block"/> The JAD method was used at the three research sites in a wide range of project contexts, from a small, fo- cused project aimed at designing the user interfaces for a reporting system to a large, multi-year, process reengi- neering project in which legacy systems would be re- placed. At ®rst glance, it would appear that the JAD workshop approach was reasonably eective as a system speci®cation method. In 70% of the projects described by informants, the systems speci®cations developed in the JAD workshops were completely or partially applied in the next stages of the project (see Table 5). However, the incidence of this outcome varied with the size and complexity of the projects in which JAD was used. In all of the six small projects in which the JAD method was used, the speci®cations determined in the JAD work- shop were completely or partially implemented. In only six of the nine (67%) medium-sized projects and two out of the ®ve large projects (40%) were the results of the JAD workshop used in later development activities at all (see Table 5). Both the size and complexity of the project and the application of the JAD method in the overall systems development approach in ̄uenced JAD's eectiveness as a systems speci®cation method. For example, at Alpha a project team conducted 28 days of workshops with ex- ecutives, managers, and senior professionals to complete analytical and modeling activities speci®ed by the in- formation engineering methodology. Management later decided to forego large-scale replacement of legacy systems, choosing instead to focus on one application area and to buy a software package for this purpose. The work completed in the JAD sessions was only partially utilized because the analytic models developed in the workshops were oriented towards custom systems development. After the decision to limit the project's scope and buy a package, analysts extracted information for a request for proposal from the JAD workshop documentation. Considering the direction the project took, the IS project manager retrospectively questioned the eciency of using the JAD method in this project. A second example also illustrated the con ̄uent eects of project size and development approach on JAD ef- fectiveness. In a large project at Gamma, the IS project team held six to eight workshops lasting three to four<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> days each and involving personnel from district oces throughout the US. The team carried out the JAD method in nearly ``textbook form'' in this instance. The sessions generated multiple volumes documenting poli- cies, procedures, and work rules. The IS team, unsure how to apply these data to design the system, tabled the JAD documentation and instead hired consultants to carry out a year-long conceptual systems design and architecture study. Re ̄ecting on the decision to use the JAD approach for systems speci®cation, the IS project manager commented:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="76" page="6" column="1">220</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="77" page="6" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="79" page="6" column="1">3.3. Eects of project size and development approach</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">If I had to do this over again, I would not do it the same way. I would not have used the [JAD] pro- cessF F F Because of the size, the number of people we brought into the workshop, the volume of infor- mation generated was almost overwhelmingF F F It's like we skipped a step which we ended up having to go back and execute.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="6" column="2">A third example suggests that despite bene®cial eects resulting from JAD use, JAD may have little impact on project outcomes in complex, risky projects. In a project at Beta, a week-long JAD session was held to specify design requirements for developing a new transaction reporting system. After a six-month delay due to orga- nizational restructuring, a second JAD session was held to specify the data entity model for the application. In the research interview, the business project manager cited as outcomes of the JAD workshops improvements in relationships between IS and user personnel, which had been strained, and IS sta members' learning about the business process. The IS project manager cited more ecient de®nition of requirements and learning by business personnel about IS development as outcomes of JAD use. However, two months after the second workshop, no actions had been taken on the JAD design speci®cation. Instead, the user project manager was at- tempting to interest other organizational units in buying a software package. The IS personnel who had partici- pated in the JAD workshops were reassigned to a new business unit, nullifying bene®ts from learning and re- lationship building that had occurred in the JAD workshops. The informants who had participated in these pro- jects reported that the JAD workshops were well done, and they were generally supportive of the JAD method, yet the speci®cations that resulted from the JAD workshops had little or no utility in the future devel- opment phases of these projects. The observations of the IS project manager in the Gamma project succinctly re ̄ect this contradictory ®nding:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">In all these workshops, we did a great job. We had fabulous facilitation, we had documentation, we had great participation, and people felt really good</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="85" page="7" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="86" page="7" column="1">221</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">about the work that they were doing. It's only in retrospect that we ask, what were our real objec- tives, and did we actually accomplish those objec- tives?</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" page="7" column="1">Considering the cost of conducting such JAD work- shops in both IS personnels' and business users' time, the eciency and eectiveness of using the JAD method in such projects is questionable.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="89" page="7" column="1">4. Discussion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" page="7" column="1">The ®ndings of this exploratory study suggest that the three research sites realized modest improvements in systems development processes and outcomes by using the JAD method. Informants reported improvements in requirements de®nition, IS eciency, mutual learning between IS and users, and so on in 10±30% of the pro- jects examined. Systems development outcomes stem- med in large part from conducting speci®cation activities in the JAD workshop setting. That is, IS per- sonnel spent less time interviewing users individually or reconciling con ̄icting information, and users commu- nicated and negotiated with each other directly rather than through the systems analyst. The workshop envi- ronment was an information-rich setting which study participants believed had facilitated knowledge ex- change and learning, particularly when the facilitator successfully engaged all participants in the exercises. By working together and showing interest in each other's perspective, relationships between IS and business area personnel or between business groups improved in some instances. However, analysis of ®ndings also suggests that, through their JAD practices, the research sites limited the potential eectiveness of JAD as a software process improvement. User participation in JAD workshops was constrained by the limited time business area per- sonnel had available for workshops. JAD participants tended to be selected from the ranks of managers and sta personnel; as a result, actual system users often were not directly involved in the JAD workshops. Workshop activities focused on IS developers' models and terminology, and business area personnel, with little or no training, were expected to participate on those terms. Although modeling exercises were completed in the JAD sessions, the eectiveness and eciency of using a joint user/developer workshop to specify such models was questionable. Using the JAD method in larger projects did not seem to bene®t these complex and risky ventures; even system speci®cations and docu- mentation developed in the JAD sessions had limited value in these situations. Why did the three research sites practise the JAD method in ways that were likely to minimize bene®ts <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> from its use? The gaps between the espoused JAD method and JAD-in-practice did not appear to arise from a lack of understanding of JAD or poor imple- mentation of the JAD method at these organizations. In each company, a group of IS personnel received pro- fessional training in facilitation techniques and an in- house sta of full-time or part-time facilitators was created. After the ®rst years of use, organizational ex- periences with JAD were articulated and made available in IS development planning guides and manuals. The JAD method was integrated into the existing develop- ment environment through such actions and had be- come a well-established element of the IS development process at the three research sites at the time of the ®eld study. Instead, these adaptations of the JAD method in practice stemmed from unresolved con ̄icts between key assumptions underlying the espoused JAD method and the status quo IS development approach at each orga- nization. Routinized approaches to systems develop- ment which con ̄icted with the espoused JAD method were not recognized, challenged, and removed. In par- ticular, the assumption that users could participate full- time in JAD workshops was unrealistic in these orga- nizations. Over time, JAD practices conformed to this organizational constraint. Furthermore, JAD work- shops became the forum for specifying IS analytic models, based on the assumption that users could ef- fectively specify business requirements in IS developers' terminology. Finally, JAD workshops were used to specify such models, needed for custom, in-house de- velopment, even when make-or-buy decisions had not been made for a project. One implication of these ®ndings is that while the JAD method is intuitively appealing in concept, in practice it may not be eective as a systems development process improvement. Applying JAD in the prescribed manner may not be feasible because of organizational constraints on its practice, yet adapting JAD to ac- commodate these constraints limits its ecacy. This does not imply that on a project-by-project basis, or- ganizations cannot bene®t from JAD use. However, adapting the JAD method in practice to the constraints of the status quo IS development environment reduces its utility as a user involvement or system speci®cation method. This is particularly true if JAD is adapted without consideration of the consequences such changes may have for its value. If substantive changes in systems development out- comes through JAD use are desired, then JAD imple- mentors must ensure that the existing IS development process is consciously analyzed, and where appropriate, challenged. Managers charged with the responsibility of incorporating JAD methods might question, for ex- ample, decisions to exempt system users from work- shop participation or to extend workshop schedules to<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> allow part-time participation of business area person- nel. Without such re ̄ection and follow-up action, im- provements in systems quality, development time, and so on, from JAD use are likely to fall short of expec- tations. When organizational constraints on JAD practice cannot be changed, sustained improvement in the systems development process from JAD use is un- likely.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="92" page="8" column="1">222</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93" page="8" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="95" page="8" column="1">5. Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="8" column="1">JAD is an intuitively appealing system speci®cation method that encompasses approaches for enhancing user participation, expediting development activities, and improving the quality of systems speci®cations. The JAD method has been widely acclaimed, but little is actually known about its eectiveness in practice. In this ®eld study, JAD practices at three organizations were examined to determine how the espoused JAD method has been applied in practice and to assess how JAD practices in ̄uenced outcomes of its use. Findings sug- gest that the JAD method was most eective in small, clearly focused projects in which IS analytic models and/ or user interface design were speci®ed for custom sys- tems development. In large, complex projects, the JAD method was less eective and even inecient when used early in the project to collect information on require- ments, before decisions about project scope or devel- opment approach had been made. Additional research on JAD practice among a larger sample of organizations will be needed to identify the types of system speci®ca- tion activities that are feasible to conduct in a JAD workshop setting, particularly given users' limited time availability. JAD workshops were most often used to specify IS analytic models, even though users partici- pating in the workshops had diculty articulating business requirements in terms of these models. Further research will be needed to identify exercises, tools and techniques that can help users eectively participate in appropriate system modeling activities in a workshop setting. Empirical ®eld studies such as this one help build our understanding of how and why systems develop- ment methods do, or do not, work to improve the systems development process. Such studies are impor- tant because the real test of a method's ecacy ± the touchstone that tests its value ± is how the method ``holds up'' in practice. The JAD method is heralded by consultants and enthusiastically endorsed by organiza- tions experienced in its use, but the critical role that practice plays in realizing bene®cial outcomes from JAD tends to be overlooked amid such enthusiasm. The ®ndings of this study suggest that the JAD method <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> is dicult to sustain in practice because assumptions underlying the method con ̄ict with assumptions of the status quo development process in IS organizations, yet adapting the espoused method limits its usefulness. This was the case at the three research sites studied. Similarities in JAD practices at the research sites with reported practices at other companies in the JAD users group from which the sample was drawn suggest that the practices identi®ed here are not atypical and may even be quite common. However, the research sites are only a small convenience sample of organizations using JAD and does not statistically represent all companies using JAD. It is possible that other organizations have applied JAD in practice in ways that are closer to the espoused JAD method and have achieved more sub- stantial bene®ts as a result. Detailed ®eld studies at organizations claiming to use the JAD method as es- poused could provide an interesting counterpoint to these ®ndings and may highlight what changes in the status quo systems development process are required for eective JAD use.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="98" page="8" column="2">References</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="99" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Aiosa, F., 1989. The marriage of sales and technology. Best's Review (Health/Life) 90 (7), 46±48, 111. Andrews, D., 1991. JAD: A crucial dimension for rapid application development. Journal of Systems Management 42 (3), 23±27, 31. Bansler, J., Bùdker, K., 1993. A reappraisal of structured analysis: Design in an organizational context. ACM Transactions on Information Systems 11 (2), 165±193. Bradley, J., 1989. An educational experience at aetna. Datamation 35 (7), 46±47. Carmel, E., Whitaker, R., George, J., 1993. PD and joint application design: A Transatlantic Comparison. Communications of the ACM 36 (4), 40±48. Carmel, E., George, J., Nunamaker, Jr., J., 1995. Examining the process of electronic-JAD. Journal of End-User Computing 7 (1), 13±22. Duncan, M., 1990. JAD Sessions: Setting the tone. Computerworld 24 (13), 123. Jones, C., 1991. Applied Software Measurement: Assuring Productiv- ity and Quality, McGraw-Hill, New York. Keyes, J., 1989. System design with the user in mind. Datamation 35 (7), 48±50, 56. Kettelkut, M., 1997. Using JAD for Strategic Initiatives. Information Systems Management 14 (3), 29±36. Liou, Y., Chen, M., 1993. Using group support systems and joint application development for requirements speci®cation. Journal of Management Information Systems 10 (3), 25±41. Martin, J., 1990. Information Engineering, Book III: Design and Construction, Prentice-Hall, Englewood Clis, NJ, pp. 127±167. Miles, M., Huberman, A., 1994. Qualitative Data Analysis, Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA. Rush, G., 1985. A Fast way to de®ne systems requirements. Comput- erworld 19 (40), 11±16. Wood, J., Silver, D., 1995. Joint Application Development. Wiley, New York.</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100" page="9" column="1">E.J. Davidson / The Journal of Systems and Software 45 (1999) 215±223</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="101" page="9" column="1">223</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="102" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Dr. Elizabeth Davidson is an assistant professor in the Department of Decision Sciences at the College of Business Administration at the University of Hawaii, Manoa. Dr. Davidson worked for ®fteen years as a systems developer and project manager at several Fortune 500 ®rms before earning her Ph.D. in Management from the Sloan School</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="103" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">of Management at MIT. Her research and teaching interests include information systems development and software process improvement in organizations, clinical information systems, and organizational implications of technology implementation.</h1>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
