<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>db6d8c283b6accf0233e3b55e248f19060b147002701cf459d594da23bc80731</job>
    <base_name>62ep</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4302-0176-2_5</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2" confidence="possible">COMPETINO Quick Start Guide Vers.1.0</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" confidence="possible">Bräuniger GmbH</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Dr. Karl Slevogt Str.5 D-82362 Weilheim</name>
          <aff id="5">5</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">+49 881 64750 <email id="6">info@brauniger.com</email> www.brauniger.com Okt. 2004</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="8">-1-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="9">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="10">1 Operation 1.1 Turning the Unit On and Off</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11">The unit is switched on by pressing the key. You must confirm the switch on by pressing the “Enter” key. To switch it off you need to press the same key for three seconds. The unit will then display the question ‘Really switch off?’ Confirm by pressing “Enter”. After a long flight with short record intervals the calculation of the digital signature can take up to one or two minutes. Please wait until this process is finished. Press O/ESC key again to turn off the unit.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="12">1.2 Keypad</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible">User Screen 3</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="14">Choose a user selectable field</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible">User Screen 2</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">Menu</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" confidence="possible">User Screen 1 Nxt ↓ Fnc ↓ Mod Alt1 QNH/Gps Nxt ↓ ----</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">Main Setup =============== Factory Settings Opt. SW-Packages Main Setup Menu =============== Flightmemory Waypoints == ==============↑ Routes Restricted Areas Simulation Basic Settings ================↓</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" confidence="possible">Special Function</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible">Enter, accept</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="21">100% 75% 50% 25% 0%</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" confidence="possible">Choose a waypoint</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible">Choose a route Esc→Quit →Map display on/off</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="24">Keyboard functions above the line: Press briefly</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="25">functions below line: Press for 2 sec</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="26">-2-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="27">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28">1.3 Main Screen Remaining battery</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="29">Nbr. of reiceved satellites from the GPS system</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" confidence="possible">capacity of battery bank 1 and 2 User selectable field Unit of analogue vario Altitude Dig. Variometer Mode Digitale Variometer Analogue Variometer User selectable field User selectable field Function of F1 Function of F2 Information lines To toggle between the screens: Press briefly the Esc-button 1.4 Map Screen Restricted area Waypoint of a route with cylinder Restricted area Waypoint of a route with cylinder Track, of the actual flight Scale Altitude Digitale Variometer Function of F1 Function of F2 Information lines The flight route of saved flights also can be shown on the display and viewed.Once in the Flight Analysis the Show Map function is reached by pressing F1 . The screen-optimized flight route is shown on the display. (North is located at the top) Additionally, stored waypoints are plotted with a cross and name. The map scale is displayed too.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="31">The graph can now be changed as follows:</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="32">-3-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="33">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="34">F2: Zoom in: The map scale is gradually increased to approx. 0.5-1.0km. Thus, individual circles during a climbing period are clearly recognizable (This is dependent on the set recording interval).</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" confidence="possible">Fl: Zoom out:The map scale is gradually decreased until the screen display is optimized. Enter: From each graph back again to the screen optimized graph. ESC: Back to the main setup menu. All other keys cause the track in the current selection to be redrawn. Arrow keys: Pan: With these the plotted area can be shifted up, down, left and right. This function is enabled in flight memory mode only. During flight, the actual position is in the center of the map. If the position reaches a border, the map pans automatically.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37">Note: As the picture takes a few seconds to build up, depending on the amount of data, Wait and Ready appear on the status line as user information; if a zoom or pan key is touched during the process then it will be broken off and will start over again with new values. You can thus obtain the desired graph quickly. Even past flights can be graphed as long as they are still in the memory. <marker type="block"/> During flight, touching the ESC key briefly will toggle between the different screens. Vario and height appear digitally under the map. For Competition routes, the cylinder of the active waypoint, WP names, and a thin dotted line to the next WP are also displayed. During the flight the Zoom In/Out functions are accessible.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible">1.5 Main Setup Menu Flightmemory List of the flights in memory. Waypoints List of the waypoints with the posibility to edit Waypoints and coordinates Routes List of the routes with the posibility to edit Restricted Areas List of the restricted areas with the possibility to edit Simulation Here you can simulate most of the important flight parameters Basic Settings Here you can change the most important parameters Factory Settings Only for service Opt. SW-Packages Here you can enable SW packages you bought from Brauniger GmbH 1.6 Basic Settings</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39">A series of settings permit the unit to be programmed according to the user’s wishes. Every pilot can realize his/her own ideas. If too much information bogs you down and causes confusion, it is always possible to reset the unit at Basic Settings/ Init EEPROM, which are the manufacturer’s tested basic settings. You are basically starting again. But please note! All WP and routes will be deleted too. As a minimum, possible settings and default values will be shown at the setting points. Should these values be changed, you move to the change mode by pressing Enter. The value to be changed will blink and can be modified with the help of the ▼ and ▲ keys. Pressing the Enter key confirms the new value. Pressing the ESC key recalls the previous setting.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40">-4-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42">Term</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="43">Meaning</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="44">Factory Setting</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" confidence="possible">Display contrast Range 0 ... 100 % 70 % Record-Interval Time interval per recorded (track 10 Sec log)point range: 10....30 sec Recording mode Autom. or manual flight recording Aut. Digital Variomode Averager ; Averager time delay 1 sec 30 sec Vario tone Frequency of Climb and Sink tone, 1200 Hz ; 700 Hz Modulation, Pitch, Acoustic Integrator Mod = 5 ;Pi=3; 8 Audio threshold Fine tuning of climbing tone max 20 2 cm/sec cm Sink tone thres. Activation point of sink tone 0,8 m/s (ft/m) Vario/Spd delay Response time delay for Analogue 12 ( » 1,2 sec) Vario and Speed Stallspeed Use of stall alarm and altitude limit 0 km/h (mph) Spd corr. Vane Windwheel 70 ... 150 % correction 100 % Units Meter or feet; Km/h or mph or knots m ; km/h ; Grd C Temp.: Grd C or Grd F Coordinate Format * dd°mm,mmm or dd,ddddd or dd°mm,mmm dd°mm’ss” UTM ; Suisse Grid # Init GPS Set of a geodetic map system WGS84 Time Date Year Difference to UTC; Day, Month, Year Present Pilotname Pilot name entry; max 25 letters not set Glider type Name of glider for OLC not set Glider ID Glider registration for OLC not set Del all records Deletion of flight memory (all records) no Del all WP&amp; Rts Deletion of all WPs and Routes no Init EEPROM Back to factory settings No Init CTRs Reorganization of the memory 1.7 User selectable fields The Main Screen consists of 3 pages which can be toggled by a brief press on ►. In</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="46">each of them 3 user selectable fields can be choosen with the values hereinafter.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="47">-5-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="48">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49">Alt a. BG FL (ft)</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50">Safety height above the best glide path* Flight Level not adjustable by the user</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible">Dist CTR Distance to nearest flight restricted area* Airspeed Speed measured with the vane wheel, true air speed WindSpd Wind strength* Time Time Fl.Time Flight time since take off GND speed ground speed*(=GS) Spd-Diff Wind component (ground speed minus true airspeed)* Dist to WP Distance to chosen destination (waypoint)* Bearing Direction to chosen destination* Track Flight direction (course)* Temp Internal temperature Alt 2 Reference height (if desired can be set at 0) Alt 3 Cumulated gained height QNH hPa Air pressure in hector-Pascal L/D gnd Actual L/D over ground (=Ground Speed/Sink)* L/D air Actual L/D in air, only available with vane wheel connected L/D req L/D required to reach a WP* Dist to^ Distance to last thermal * Only active when the GPS receiver is switched 1.8 Battery management</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52">Two bar graph scales indicate the capacity of the batteries. The COMPETINO has 2 banks with 2 batteries each. Bank 1 must always be equipped. Bank 2 could remain free. However, we recommend to equip bank 2 also. As soon as the first bank is used up, the instrument switches automatically to the second bank. After switching ON, the unit will always start with bank1. After a long flight we recommend to insert the partly used batteries of bank 2 into bank 1 and to equip bank 2 with new batteries. Thus it is ensured that the instrument can use up the batteries always completely, without the danger of having empty batteries during a flight.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" confidence="possible">Bank 1</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" confidence="possible">Bank 1 Bank 2</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" confidence="possible">Bank 2</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56">The following battery types could be used 2 pieces per bank Alkaline High Power Batteries 1.5V Size AA. Estimated life time 2 * 13h = 26 h together 2 pieces per bank NiMH Accu 2100mAh, 1.2V Size AA. Estimated life time 2 * 11h = 22h together NiCd Accu works also, but they have clearly smaller capacities and are not pollution free.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" confidence="possible">Please dispose of the batteries properly.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="58">The estimated life time bases on normal temperature conditions. At low temperatures the capacity of batteries decrease a lot.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="59">-6-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="60">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="61">1.9 Data Exchange Via PC</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="62">The COMPETINO’s basic equipment includes a data cable for a serial PC interface (9 pol</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" confidence="possible">Sub D plug). Data transfer can occur in both directions. The connection occurs with: 57.600 baud; 1 startbit; 8 databit; 1 stopbit; no parity, Xon/Xoff The following can be read via this RS232 interface: Serial numbers and pilot names Waypoint list Route list A selected flight (track) The following can be uploaded to the 5020: Waypoints and routes; (CTRs soon)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65">Important: the unit must first be switched on before plugging in the connection cable to the unit and the computer. <marker type="block"/> Before you transfer the waypoints and route data switch the COMPETINO to the Setup Menu. You should make sure that the waypoints show up in the unit’s waypoint list before you transfer a route from your computer. If you wish to download flight data, switch the unit to the Flight memory mode, and display the desired flight on the Flight Analysis screen before transferring it to your computer. There are a number of PC programs on the market that allow communication with the COMPETINO. We recommend the program Flychart which you can download from the Brauniger Website www.brauniger.com</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" confidence="possible">Other programs that permit data transfer with the COMPETINO: Trackview (Freeware)Daniel Zuppinger (for OLC und CCC) www.softtoys.com/ Compe-GPS www.compegps.com Seeyou Program well liked by sailplane pilots www.seeyou.ws Checkin Christian Quest (particularly for competitions) Maxpunkte Free program from DHV for reading flight data for evaluation and submission to OLC. www.dhv.de/sport IQ-Online Freeware from our homepage; easy to use; for OLC application 1.10 Transferring New Firmware to the COMPETINO</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73">As is the case with many other new developments, particularly during the introduction phase, improvements or feature enhancements may be expected. Periodically Brauniger will post firmware updates at www.brauniger.com , which can be downloaded by the user free of charge, and then uploaded to the COMPETINO <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> Sometimes the Flasher will give an error. In this case, the cable must be unplugged, and the COMPETINO turned off before making another attempt to flash the memory.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="68">To be able to write to the COMPETINO’s flash memory with a PC, it is necessary to use a compressed file named “Flasher.zip” . In addition, the actual firmware to be uploaded must be obtained. It is called “Ctinovxxx.moc” which corresponds to the version X.XX. Both of these files are available from the download page at www.brauniger.com We recommend that you store all the related files in a separate subdirectory. After decompressing the ZIP file a number of files are created. Double clicking on the file</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="69">“flasher.exe” starts the program. Under “Setup”, the serial port (COM1 or COM2) can be</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="70">-7-</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71">Quick Start Guide COMPETINO</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="72">chosen. You select the file to be transferred with the extension “.moc” by pressing on the “Start” key. The data transfer starts automatically.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible">Important: Contrary to the instructions for data transfer of waypoints or routes, be sure that the COMPETINO is turned off when plugging the cable into the computer and the COMPETINO. Important: Never leave the PC cable hooked up to the unit when it is turned off. If this is done energy is consumed, and the battery can be drained. 2 Technical Data Measurements: 165 x 73 x 38 mm Weight: 286 grams (with 4 Alkaline batteries, without harness) Electrical supply: 2 or 4 alkaline batteries AA or Nickel metal hydride accumulator 2 Ah; 1.2V Battery life: &gt; 30 hrs with 4 alkaline batteries Altimeter: Max. 8000 m; 1 m (3 ft) steps Variometer: Analogue+/-8 m/s; (1600 ft/m); 0.2m/s (20 ft/m) steps Variometer Digital +/-70m/s; (14.000 ft/m); 0.1m/s (20 ft/m) steps Speed (wind wheel) Digital 0 - 150km/h (or mph or kts) 1 km/h steps Waypoints: 200 WP Routes: 20 routes with max. 30 WP in each Airspaces 10 CTR’s with 12 waypoints each Max. memory time: 5 hrs flying time at 10 sec intervals Number of track log points: 24 000 Number of registered flights: 100 Data memory and transfer according to the IGC format Screen resolution 240 x 160 Pixel (=1/8 VGA) or 38.400 pixel Operating temperature -15...45 °C</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75">Brackets for hang gliders and paragliders are available. The technical details may be altered without notification. Software upgrades can be made by downloading the latest firmware version from our homepage 3 Guarantee and liability Our instruments carry a 24-month guarantee. However, physical damage such as a broken casing or glass breakage as well as damage resulting from water landings are excluded from this guarantee. Bräuniger can accept no liability for faults arising from any abuse or unapproved use of your instruments.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible">WARNING In very rare cases it can happen that a flight instrument does not provide any data at all or the data is incorrect. Brauniger GmbH will not be held responsible for accepting any damage claims arising from a malfunctioning unit. Responsibility for ensuring the safe execution of his/her flights lies with the pilot alone.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="77">-8-</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter"/>
  </article>
</pdfx>
