<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>3fc62783386f80b8bc283719e0fccd46a7a8e002426b630a5c5afb565165fe96</job>
    <base_name>62sd</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2348144.2348169</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">New roles of Designers in Democratic Innovation: a case study in the Ingenuity of Ageing</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Yanki Lee</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Hong Kong Design Institute, China and Royal College of Art, London <email id="3">yankilee@hotmail.com</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">This paper discusses a study of a group of retired academics that are actively ageing on their university campus in China. We worked with this group of ingenious older people and conducted a series of Creative Dialogues and Design Festivals to see how designers accomplish infrastructuring and mobilization in design participatory innovation for an ageing population. Inspired by the idea of the design process as Things and the concept of community-of-practice, we analysed how they design their lives. We found important new roles for designers in the critique of design ideology and the identification of utopian elements from the participants.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="6" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Author Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">Design, ageing, participation, democratic innovation, ideology and utopia</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="14">Denny K. L. Ho</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="9" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Classification Keywords</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Design, Documentation. Experimentation, Human Factors, Theory</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">In a PD framework, the design process is generally understood as a problem solving process. Correspondingly, each user’s identity has been confirmed as experience and they are considered as content providers who could contribute much to design. Such problem-solving orientation has recently been challenged. Ehn (2008, 94) directed designers to take up a new role in the task of infrastructuring public things, and of supporting future appreciation and appropriation of design at use time. This view is a tricky re-relegation of designers from the role of active participants to that of supportive participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Bjorgvinsson, Ehn and Hillgren, 2010</xref>). It put designers involved in PD in the position of the designer of design-for-design and of design-in-use. Additionally, Ehn (2008) proposed a new conception of the design process in a way that the participation process as a design process is for the realisation   of   a   ‘socio- material   assembly’ conceived as Things. This could be interpreted  as  ‘the  outcome  of  the  design  process’  which   ‘is  always  a  thing  modifying  the   space of interaction for its users, ready for unexpected use, rich in aesthetic and cultural values, opening up for new ways of thinking and behaving’   (2008, 93). Conversely, design projects are things that have objectives, time lines, deliverables, etc., Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. PDC '12, August 12 - 16 2012, Roskilde, Denmark Copyright 2012 ACM 978-1-4503-1296-7/12/08 ...  $10.00</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="16" page="1" column="2">Department of Applied Social Sciences, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, China <email id="15">ssdenny@polyu.edu.hk</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" page="1" column="2">which ‘is   the   common   form   for   aligning   resources’. Of most important, since design projects could lead to new ways of interaction, the design process is characterised by uncertainty, and ambiguity and design projects could not be guided by any engineering perspective, which is rationalist in nature. They could not be informed by a top-down perspective, which would finally hinder adaptation to the changing conditions. This specific nature of design projects leads to the necessity of user involvement and PD approaches. Sometimes, users are considered more competent than designers in directing the development of a design process. This seems to be the reason why Manzini and Rizzo appraised the recent progressive impacts of some socio-material assemblies that are ‘emerging  processes  of   design   were   close   to   Ehn’s   definition   of   PD...the   proposed examples of bottom-up social innovation can be considered as particular cases of participatory design: a participatory design where, every so often, no professional  designers  are  involved’ (2012, 202). But we could see that the unit of analysis in this perspective is no longer subjects, like designers and participants, but design projects and Things. Ehn further characterised the social domain of the design process in which all parties are inevitably involved as an entangled design-game where participants, whoever they are, have constructed ‘a   socio-material design thing, a meaningful potentially controversial assembly, for and with the participants  in  a  project’ (2008, 94). Inspired   by   Wenger’s   concept   of   communities-of- practice’,   Ehn   argued   that, within the design process, there are many specific language-games carried out and there are many learning processes evolving between participants. One specific feature of the design process as a community-of-practice is the dimension of internal struggle, which reveals how participants appropriate devices and social relations. In our view, this idea bring designers to a new domain where designers have been assigned a fundamental obligation to design events, where controversial things are opened up to support multiple, heterogeneous and controversial design-games. Through our design case study of ‘triggering’ ageing innovation by aged people, we intend to demonstrate how designers taking up the duty of supporting a platform or infrastructure for negotiations can serve as the trigger and design activist of initiatives. We also intended to investigate if there were new roles for designers in relation to conflicts of interest and interpretations during the design process.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="18" page="1" column="2">77</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="19" page="2" column="1">THE CASE: ENABLING INGENIOUS OLDER PEOPLE TO DESIGN AGEING INNOVATION BY THEMSELVES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="2" column="1">We found a unique situation: in addition to 30,000 students and staff members, there are over 6,000 retirees still living on Tsinghua University campus in Beijing, Capital of China. Many elderly residents were ageing actively and this was due to a number of key factors. These residents had apartments for life, pensions equal to half of their previous salaries and more importantly well connected communities and a respected social status. Many are subject experts as well as mentors   of   China’s   current key political leaders in the Communist Party; the ruling party in the Chinese government. With all these resources, some even set up organisations for senior experts as part of a national movement of productive ageing. Their aim is to continue their life pattern of contribution to the people, party and nation. For example, the Tsinghua Association of Senior Scientists and Technicians was founded in 2005 and together with those from other universities, a website, www.china50plus.com was launched. It offers information for those over 50 and provides a web platform for retired experts to post their expertise and link with those looking for advice. As a team consisting of a design researcher and a sociologist, we are interested in how people design their own lives. It is even more interesting to apply this investigation to the ageing process because everyone is part of this process. We are amazed by these people who retired in their own communities, design and develop their own tools to tackle their ageing problems. We believe that when designing ageing innovation, it is very important to learn and design around the  ‘tools’  already in place by these ingenious older people. This learning process can then inspire new and appropriate ageing innovation for our future selves.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">Processes: two elements in building democratic innovation</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" page="2" column="1">While people-driven ageing-innovations are happening, the main question was: How PD could help them to transform their daily innovation into more inspiring ageing innovations for all? We introduced two methods to answer this question: Creative Dialogues to build trust We conducted Creative Dialogues with the group of ingenious people in their homes or work places in order to identify their matter of concern and their utopia, which, in our view, is the driving force of participants to get involved in PD processes. Those who we interviewed are from the network of the Tsinghua Association of Senior Scientists and Technicians and Tsinghua Gerontology Centre and they are locally famous for their new ways of retirement living. During our dialogue sessions, we had a number of tactics to identify their ideology and utopia, including (a) the encouragement of self-narratives to show the interviewees that in conflicts an actor will be entrenched in an ideological position which gives them no alternative ways of being. (b) the recognition of the importance of the positive elements of Other’s  lived  experience;;  (c) the recognition of positive elements in what is currently upheld by the Other in order to show how kinds of difference could give belief to the interviewer; (d) the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> identification of the Other in the sense that any ideology would   inevitably   position   an   Other   as   ‘competing’,   ‘less desirable’   and   even   ‘confrontational’, the establishment of the Other would help reinforce one’s identity in a community; (e)  the  concept  of  ‘emplotment’  is  introduced   to ask the interviewees to draw together the fragmentary episodes of their own life into a unified narrative through the  telling  of  one’s  life  story;;  and  (f) envisioning utopian alternatives which should be realisable (if not, it would turn out to be a fantasy) and not be fragmentary (if not, it would turn out to be subject to free reign). As Langdridge described, participants ‘must   be   guided   away   from   mere   fantasy and instead encouraged to focus step-by-step on practically realizable aspects of their utopian reconciliation, working back from their utopias to the present such that they can identify a route out of the conflict and/or better understand the nature of the conflict itself’ (2005, 230). Design festivals as a celebration for the exchange of ideas To enable older people to investigate their ingenuity of ageing, we explored the Design Festivals method: five pop-up design stores were set up in conjunction with traditional festivals in the Chinese calendar. These design interventions were on an ad hoc basis but there are three essential components/stages. (1) We highlighted the importance of traditional values like those of being respectful to our ancestors and history. (2) We took this as an opportunity to test if most retirees would take this chance to figure out innovative methods to show their respect to their community and their appreciation of unity. The festivals include the Spring Festival for the unity of families, the Qingming Festival, the festival to commemorate the dead, the Dragon Boat Festival, a festival with high appraisal of loyalty (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Fig 1</xref>), the Mid- Autumn Festival, September, a traditional festival for people to get together with their families and the Chong Yang Festival, which was also named as the Elderly Festival, underscoring one custom as it is observed in China, where the festival is also an opportunity to care for and appreciate the elderly. (3) We collected a series of innovative ideas/wishes, drafted by the elderly themselves. 1. Elders restaurant to maintain their health, 2. Greener burial method, e.g. tree burial 3. Local travel group 4. Internet club for the elders 5. Group exercise club 6. Green ageing 7. Class to learn how to take care of the old 8. Body donation advice 9. New ways to engage young people 10. Tomb and funeral service During the Design Festivals, participants kept using their own ideal picture to, on the one hand, evaluate the current situation on university campus and search innovative ways to realise the utopian dreams at the same time. Throughout the process, we found few disagreements and conflicts as participants had a strong inclination to do something for the imagined Tsinghuaian, people from<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Tsinghua University. Our organised activities revolved around the theme of their utopian dream of the Tsinghua residents ageing with dignity.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="25" page="2" column="2">78</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62sd.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62sd.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="28" page="3" column="1">Fig 1. Design Festival on Campus with help</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="unknown" id="29" page="3" column="1">of design students</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Findings: The concept of communal identity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">We explored how this communal identity shapes their daily practice and living through the terms of their Quality Of Live (QOL) profile: Being, Belongings and Becoming. We also used Ricoeur’s (1986) idea of ideology and utopia to analyse participants’ dreams and distorted vision of the world and developed the perspective to know why disagreements and conflicts occur. Being (who one is) As all of them were living within the campus, they kept a key identity of Tsinghuaian and one of the main changes after retirement was focusing more on their personal health. Their concern over personal health was about their own physical ability to continue their contribution to the university/nation. Many retirees are keen to keep fit and fully committed to maintaining their health. They used their run-down apartment building (four to five storey block with no lift) and took their old bicycles to poorly accessible communal areas to maintain fitness and flexibility. A good example is the retired electrical engineering professor: over the last 20 years, since his retirement, he has played Ping-Pong every day at 4pm. He was happy to play with anyone in the facility. He explained that, ‘Playing  ping  pong  is  good  for  my  body  as   well as meeting new and old friends!’  In addition, he and his wife, who was also a professor of engineering, had a habit of going to the Summer Palace, a national park next to the university, every morning. She expressed, ‘we come here every day between 8am and 11am when it is the best time  to  take  in  oxygen  for  our  bodies’.    Since she is not as fit as her husband, so she has developed her retirement life around singing. She enjoys singing with other retirees as well as performances at special events, e.g. she sang an English Christmas song for over 250 members of the Tsinghua Association of Senior Scientists and Technicians at their Chinese New Year Celebration party. This was conceived as one of the ways to contribute towards the Tsinghua community. For her, singing was the best activity for her physiological and psychological wellbeing. All interviewees showed that they held an imaginary status of Tsinghuaian that had a particular mission to contribute to the nation and to the people of China. This shows the ideological dimension of social imaginary. It</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" page="3" column="2">constitutes the Tsinghua community as an entity and reinforces the communal identity held by the interviewees. Belonging (connections with one's community) The second level of the QOL profile is about the sense of belonging to community and environment. In our analysis, the sense of belonging of the retirees has been granted by the identity of Tsinghuaian. This group of ingenious older people grew up together as classmates, colleagues and neighbours. They also went through the political transformation of China and learnt to live as a collective. Nevertheless, their social integration in Tsinghuaian is supported by the ideological tenets that Tsinghua University was one of the components of their nation,   the   People’s   Republic   of   China.      They   had   to   accomplish their lifelong contribution to the nation even when they are retired from formal academic positions. As they said, ‘once a Tsinghuaian, always a Tsinghuaian.’ They would not consider terminating their work and innovation. As we have argued, Tsinghuaian is a kind of imagined community in the sense that it is ideological, but the identity provides the claim to constitute an identifiable community, the Tsinghua community. This ideological image does not only create the ground for them to accept the legitimacy of the Tsinghua University but also the ground to accept the legitimacy of the political authority of the nation. As Tsinghuaian has long been motivated to focus on scientific discovery and innovation in order to maintain this imaginary status about their communal identity. For example, over the past 40 years, a professor of physics worked  as  a  nuclear  power  expert  under  the  government’s   agenda and contributed to military development. Retirement meant freedom for him, where he can work on self-initiated projects related to his own expertise. Originally trained as a physicist, in his second year of retirement, he invented a new method of X-ray body scanning, which got a national patent with investment to continue research for its applications. After eight years, he received a second round of investment and is working with young researchers to develop new social applications of this technology in the healthcare domain. He claimed that being a Tsinghua professor also entailed a continuation of innovation in order to live up to the ideal of scientific Tsinghuaian. Clearly, the identity of being a Tsinghuaian has not only legitimised the existence of Tsinghua as a community but also legitimised the authority of the nation. We see that the social imaginary of Tsinghuaian does not only constitute a distorted picture about the existence of a cohesive community but also provides a strong imagined community to which the retirees are attached socially. Through this attachment, they endorse both the legitimacy of the university but also the nation. Meanwhile it also constitutes the Other with which Tsinghuaian must compete. The ideological and social imagination in terms of Tsinghuaian results in a very positive social effect: social integration is maintained and motivation to design lives after retirement is groomed. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Becoming (achieving personal goals, hopes and aspirations) As we have argued, the dreams of utopia are important, as they would bring forth positive impacts on the motivation of people to seek social change. For our case, the utopia we could identify among the interviewees is a sense of becoming which is really about actions that go beyond individual expertise to transfer knowledge to everyone; helping others to age well. Professor Styling is well known in the community because she is very stylish; with good taste in clothing. Before retirement, she was a professor of micro-electrical engineering even though her original field is chemistry. She once explained to us her viewpoint of current education: ‘Students   are   now   trained   without   hands-on ability and they are incapable of solving diverse problems outside  their  own  expertise...  however,  when  we  studied,   we were trained with the principle of hands-on ability that can apply that to any subject.’   Since retirement, she has worked as the office manager for the Tsinghua Association of Senior Scientists and Technicians. Here she promoted the group and had active engagement with external organisations and current students. To her, she appeared to be dissatisfied with the current forms of knowledge transfer within tertiary education in China. Her viewpoint is this, when the university became ‘modern’, it would inevitably result in the dominance of administrative calculation and rational arrangement. Hence, hands-on teaching and job placement were no longer popular in modern teaching. It could be said as a fantasy if one expected to change such a strong tide of education philosophy.      But   her   ‘utopia’   appeared to be more manageable and achievable. She just designed more linkages between external organisations and current university students through which students could gain direct application experience and hands-on training at the workplace. Her dream of utopia, the restoration of the teaching method used in her good old days, motivated her to participate in communal activities.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="33" page="3" column="2">79</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="4" column="1">CONCLUSIONS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="4" column="1">These stories from retirees demonstrated that they have the motivation to design new ways of continuing the glory of being a Tsinghuaian, as a preserved or even distorted vision of their community. It is distorted, as Tsinghuaian is not a real or official entity. At the personal level, they have solved their basic needs of being, i.e. as retired people solving ageing problems. They have worked hard to make sure that they themselves are ageing well. Of most importance, they are also concerned about how their experiences can help others within the community and beyond. All these appeared supported by the non-congruence between the utopian ideal of Tsinghuaian and its current situation, and all these are also supported by the utopian and ideological social imaginary identity. As a group of ingenious people, they worked and stimulated each other to tackle persistent myths about old age and aged people, a culturally based fear of ageing. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> They were dissatisfied with the image of weak Tsinghuaian. It is clear that this unique situation of collective living has become an incubator that allows innovations to happen. They are constantly developing ways to maintain their quality of life (being, belonging and becoming). The way they achieve this is the formation of the ideological social imaginary in terms of community to which members have a strong sense of attachment and belonging. The role of designers here was to ensure the smooth process of program and service design born out in the Dialogues and Festivals for the common concern of the participants and their future. Tsinghuaian, and we could also attribute it to our highlighting of its utopian dimension, with which participants found no disagreement. In our view, focusing on the construction of the objectives of PD would reveal more the salience of the role of designers as ‘design triggers, codesign members and design activists’ (Manzini and Rizzo, 2011). In others words, designers’  roles  are tactical, they can even be reshaped as ‘developers,   facilitators,   and   generators’, depending on the cases (Lee, 2008). At the same time, throughout the design process, we do not aim at infrastructure, which refers to organised events through which the design process as Thing evolves on its own. Given that democratic innovation is an attempt to transform antagonism to agoism, a sense of social integration would help participants to foster a view that those who have different ideas and expectations are not one’s enemy, and to strengthen the belief that further negotiations and conflict reconciliation is possible.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="38" page="4" column="2">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" page="4" column="2">We would like to thank all the participants and collaborators of the project. The project was funded the funders:   UK’s   Department   of   Business,   Innovation   and   Skills (BIS) and the Helen Hamlyn Centre for Design, Royal College of Art. Thank you Claire Quinn for final /copy.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="40" page="4" column="2">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="41" page="4" column="2">Ehn, P. Participation in Design Things. PDC’  08,  p.  92- 101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="42" page="4" column="2">Bjorgvinsson, E., Ehn, P. and Hillgren, P. Participatory design  and  “democratizing  innovation”.    PDC’  10,  29- Nov.-2010. P. 41-50.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="43" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">Langdridge, D. Between Ideology and Utopia. Existential Analysis, Vol, 16(2):221-235. 2005.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="44" page="4" column="2">Lee, Y. Design participation tactics: the challenges and new roles for designers in the co-design process. CoDesign, Vol 4, 1;31-50. 2008.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="45" page="4" column="2">Manzini, E. and Rizzo, F. Small projects/large changes: Participatory design as an open participated process. CoDesign., Vol. 7(3-4), p. 199-215. 2012.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="46" page="4" column="2">Ricoeru, P. Lectures on Ideology and Utopia. Taylor, G.H. (ed). New York: Columbia University Press. 1986.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="47" page="4" column="2">80</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
