<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>89a1eea28488a5550aad6afc5d5cd15ea1bfedbefe025ccf1e8b8446c5e7d9e3</job>
    <base_name>62dq</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08468.x</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1" confidence="possible">ELSEVIER</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Information &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" confidence="possible">Research</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">An examination of designer and user perceptions of JAD and the traditional IS design methodology • a*</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="5" confidence="possible">R u s s e l l P u r v t s ' , V. S a m b a m u r t h y b</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">a Department of Management, College of Business Administration, University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL 32816-1400, USA b Information and Management Sciences, College of Business, Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL 32306-1042, USA</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7">Software design methodologies abound, with each claiming to be the solution for enhancing user participation in the systems analysis and design process. Joint applications design (JAD) is an approach that draws upon the strengths of group dynamics to facilitate requirements determination. JAD has been advocated for enhancing user participation and tapping user creativity in the systems design process. However, these claims are based on case studies and anecdotal evidence with limited empirical justification. This research compares the effects of the JAD and the traditional IS design methodology relative to the interactions between users and designers, consensus management, and user acceptance of the design specifications. This effort draws upon data from 94 pairs of designers and users associated with 57 different projects that utilized either the traditional IS design or JAD methodology. Results suggest that designers perceived JAD as being superior to the traditional IS design method with respect to the quality of user-designer interactions, effectiveness of consensus management, and user acceptance of design specifications. Users were less enamored on finding that JAD only promoted superior user-designer interactions. (© 1997 Elsevier Science B.V. Keywords: Information systems design; User-designer perceptions; development methodologies; Linear regression</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">User involvement is a critical requirement of the process of design and implementation of information systems in organizations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="9" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="10" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="11" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="12" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>]. User participation is believed to increase user acceptance by enabling development of realistic expectations about the proposed system, providing an environment for constructive negotiation on design issues, creating a spirit of system ownership, decreasing user resistance</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">*Corresponding author. Tel.: (407) 823-5684; fax: (407) 823- 5741; e-mail: <email id="14">purvis@pegasus.cc.ucf.edu</email>.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx16">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62dq.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="17" page="1" column="2">Semantic gap; Joint application design; Systems</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="1" column="2">to change, and building user commitment [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="18" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="19" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]. User participation is also believed to increase the quality of the system being developed by improving the users' understanding of the system, providing more complete and accurate information requirements, avoiding development of an unacceptable system, and providing necessary expertise about the organization and work processes that will be sup- ported by the system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="20" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="21" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>]. Spurred by the search for prospects of enhancing user participation, researchers and practitioners have evolved and evaluated the merits of a variety of development methodologies. An IS methodology is<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> a systematic approach for conducting analysis, design, testing, etc. of a software product. It usually consists of a set of guidelines, activities, techniques and tools, based on a particular philosophy of system development. The traditional IS design methodology is not a specific model as much as a composite of common factors found in the hundreds of published life cycle methodologies and thousands in use. It takes a top- down approach to evaluate the development process and the data flows that connect these processes. A crucial element of the traditional IS design methodology is that it limits user participation to a consultative role, where the bulk of the design decisions are made by the IS developer or analyst. Users provide their inputs primarily through one-on-one meetings with the designers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="26" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="27" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>]. Critics have suggested that the traditional IS design methodology suffers from short- comings in facilitating high quality interactions among users and IS designers. This is a particular problem when the information systems under development span multiple functional areas in organizations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="28" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="29" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]. Joint application design (JAD) is an alternative design methodology that has received prominent attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="30" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="31" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="32" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. In contrast with the traditional IS design methodology, JAD expands the scope of user participation to a representative role, where users collectively articulate, negotiate, and develop systems specifications. Typically, with JAD, user participation occurs through group meetings that employ a structured agenda, techniques for the effective management of group dynamics, and facilitators for managing</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="1" column="2">0378-7206/971517.00 © 1997 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved PH S-0378-7206(96)01087-7</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="24" page="2" column="1">124</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="2" column="1">R. Purvis, V Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> Summary of claims about the superiority of JAD over SDLC for behavioral effects Quality of user--designer interactions Enables technical people to learn about the business and business people to learn about the technology Improves communicationamong users, designers, developers, and other interested parties Increases the users' sense of commitment and ownership of the system Promotes cooperation, understanding, and teamwork among the various user groups and IS staff Effectiveness of consensus management Facilitates the lowering of political barriers between the applications development group and other groups that have a vested interest Facilitates the management of the politics of a project by increasing user commitment and involvementthrough consensus building Removes the information systems analyst from the role of resolving conflict between the users and facilitates the end-users in potential conflict to resolve their differences in the JAD workshop User acceptance of design specifications Results in systems that meet the end-users' needs better because the system comes from the users Harnesses the end-users into the design process and helps to avoid dissatisfied users</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx36">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62dq.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="2" column="2">creativity and conflict resolution among the participants. These meetings become the key event around which the rest of the systems design activities revolve. Prior case studies, anecdotal evidence, and claims made by the advocates of JAD attribute a variety of advantages to JAD over the traditional IS design methodology, primarily because of differences in how these methodologies promote user participation during the design and development process (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>). However, there have been few attempts at empirically verifying the superiority of JAD. This paper presents a study that compared users and designers on the effects of JAD and the traditional IS design methodology. The data were gathered from pairs of 94 designers, 94 users and 57 project managers that worked on 57 systems development projects employing either JAD or traditional IS design methodology.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="2" column="2">2. The research model</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="2" column="2">A systemic problem with prior comparisons of development methodologies is the difficulty of defin- ing, much less measuring, the 'success' of a methodology [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="40" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>]. Curtis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="41" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>] suggest that a deeper understanding of how specific tools, methods, and practices actually affect the nature of a systems development process could be obtained by targeting attention at the behavioral factors characterizing the design process. Communication behavior between users and designers is viewed as fundamental to the successful<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> development of information systems (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="45" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="46" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]). The underlying assumption in communication is that different parties bring different work styles, routines, approaches, and information use behaviors associated with their experience and organizational areas. This 'semantic gap' results in different ideas about the scope, specifications, and nature of the proposed application system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="47" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]. The greater the semantic gap, the greater the need for communication to achieve a convergence in understanding between users and designers on the specifications of the proposed system. Differences in user perceptions and expectations often promote conflict and politics during the design process. IS and group literatures suggest that this conflict is a critical variable in influencing team effectiveness. Potential for conflict is high in information systems that cut across departmental boundaries, especially when there exist tensions across departments in the form of relatively incompatible goals and differing criteria for success. In addition, users and designers often work together on projects that are under resource pressures and time constraints and face conflicts over priorities about the systems specifications and deliverables. If these conflicts are ignored in the rush toward an immediately workable</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="43" page="3" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy /Information &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="44" page="3" column="1">125</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="49" page="3" column="1">Design Approach</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">I Traditional Design ] Approach i JAD Methodology</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">//Quality of User-Designer Interactions ") ~ Effectiveness of Consensus " .~ Management</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="52" page="3" column="1">t</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="53" page="3" column="1">Figure 1:</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Control Variables Project Size (Staff-days) Pr~ect Size (Developmental Lost) Departmental Scope Project Complexity Designer's Confidence in the Methodology I Designer's Experience and l Knowledge with Methodology</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="55" page="3" column="1">The Research Model</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="56" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Fig. 1. The research model.</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62dq.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" page="3" column="2">solution, the system may be dramatically less useful and lead to additional problems, including user rejec- tion, or attempts at subversion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="57" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. When handled correctly, conflict within the design team is dialectic, or educational in nature. The experience is useful as team members learn from one another. Thus, the success of the systems design process is related to the ability to manage conflict and achieve consensus over a shared set of specifications. These two behaviors, communication and negotiation, are important social behaviors that strongly influence the systems design process. The impacts of a systems design methodology could be evaluated through an observa- tion of their effectiveness in promoting communication and negotiation among stakeholders of the proposed information system and their influence on users' acceptance of the design specifications. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>, our research utilizes three variables to evaluate the extent to which the traditional IS design methodology and JAD facilitate these behavioral objectives. The first two - quality of user- designer interactions and effectiveness of consensus management - are process-oriented measures of the behaviors, whereas the variable, user acceptance of design specifications, is an outcome-oriented measure</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Effects of the Design Process</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">i User Acceptance of Design Specifications l</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="62" page="3" column="2">. . . . . . . . . . r</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="4" column="1">126</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="4" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">of the behavioral impact of the systems design process. The quality of user-designer interactions captures the extent to which conditions necessary for effective communication occur during the design process. These conditions are: active user/designer participation, open and frank communication, user influence in the design process, user commitment to sharing information and knowledge, and a feeling of partnership between users and designers during the design process. These conditions allow users and designers to exchange their knowledge and views about the proposed system and revise their understanding through an exposure to others' ideas and perceptions. This allows users and designers to expand the domain of their initial knowledge and understanding, revise some of their initial assumptions and expectations, and develop a more complete understanding about the system [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="65" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. The effectiveness of consensus management refers to the extent to which the design process is characterized by counterproductive conflict and exercise of political manipulation by the involved actors. Mason and Mitroff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="66" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>] suggest that such a process also enables participants to negotiate their conflicts and differences more productively. To facilitate effective communication, the differences in users' expectations and the resultant conflict must be handled in a such way that diverse perspectives are not stifled, members' commitment is maintained, and group cohesiveness is built. The eruption of counterproductive conflict and political manipulation can hamper the ability of designers and users to engage in open and honest communication, learn from exposure to alternative perspectives, and negotiate differences toward a shared view of the design specifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="67" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>]. Finally, user acceptance of the design specifications is likely to depend on the degree to which effective communication and negotiation occurs during the design process. When the design process is characterized by high levels of communication and negotiation, the design group should be successful in managing the process in a way that individual members' opinions are not stifled and group cohesiveness is built and maintained. As a result, users should have favorable perceptions about the design specifications, perceive their overall objectives as being met by the design, and be more satisfied with the design specifications.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62dq.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="70" page="4" column="2">2.1. Control variables</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">Our research model also includes factors other than the design methodology that could influence the designers' and users' perceptions about the process and outcomes of systems design. To permit a useful comparison of effects of the two methodologies, these factors were included as control variables. Four of these factors, project size in staff days, project size in</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="72" page="4" column="2">development cost, departmental scope, and project</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">complexity are characteristics of the IS projects. Lit- erature on project management has identified these as being influential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="73" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="74" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="75" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]. Projects characterized by large staffs, high development costs, and a larger number of departments are expected to create more pressures and difficulties in communication, negotiation and the resulting user acceptance of the requirements. Similarly, project complexity is expected to affect the degree to which project members experience difficulties in managing the behaviors required for project success. The other two control factors are designers' con- in applying the design methodology and</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="77" page="4" column="2">fidence designer's experience with and knowledge of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">methodology. Indeed, while the traditional IS design methodology has been the paradigm for systems design for a long time, JAD is a relatively newer approach. Most IS designers should have a greater degree of knowledge, experience and confidence with the traditional IS design methodology. Further, the JAD approach is more complex, requiring the designers to blend a structured meeting agenda with visual aids, process facilitation, and group creativity and conflict resolution techniques for managing the session and evolving design specifications. The emer- ging literature suggests that IS designers' knowledge, experience, and confidence with the methodology are important factors associated with the beneficial use of the approach [2, 31 ].</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="79" page="4" column="2">3. Contrasting the features of traditional IS design and JAD methodologies</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">The two methodologies under comparison in this paper differ in how they permit the elicitation of user knowledge and support the behavioral processes of communication and negotiation. While the traditional</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="5" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="82" page="5" column="1">127</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">IS design method can use several methods of knowledge acquisition, the dominant approach is interview- ing. During one-on-one meetings, the designer attempts to understand critical work flows, factors that influence operations of the system, and the key documents, procedures, and policies of the system. As the designer attempts to construct design specifications from the volume of information gathered, two additional problems can arise: the conflicts in requirements posed by different users and incomplete knowledge that individual users possess concerning the IS design. The process is also hampered by problems such as slow communication, long feedback time, and a we-versus-they gap between users and designers. Instead of one-on-one interviews, JAD knowledge acquisition centers on structured meetings involving prominent users and designers of the proposed information system. The methodology attempts to utilize the power and creativity of group dynamics, whereby users and designers work as a team to analyze the requirements, generate innovative ideas, and make decisions that shape the system's design. Users and designers are collectively involved in the learning, communication, and negotiation processes, and they observe the evolution of the design specifications. The approach facilitates learning by exposing individual participants to the ideas and proposals posed by other participants. Such an exposure triggers synergy as participants build upon the ideas in an interactive manner and converge toward a shared set of expectations about the proposed information system. The structure of the JAD meetings is designed to facilitate effective communication among participants. Further, since some stakeholders are participants in the JAD session, the approach allows members to present differences in their expectations about the proposed design specifications and negotiate these differences constructively through the structure of the JAD meeting. Studies have indicated that groups are more effective at negotiating conflict through the use of structured group techniques, process facilitation, and an agenda. We anticipate that the JAD method will be perceived as facilitating richer quality interactions among users and designers. JAD involves collective interaction among users and designers in a group meeting, whereas the traditional methodology involves one-on- one interactions between the designer and individual</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx84">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62dq.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">users. When users have different perspectives about specifications of the proposed system, a group meeting enables richer exchange of viewpoints and expectations and facilitates the users and designers in developing a better understanding of alternative viewpoints and the nature of the final specifications of the proposed system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="85" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>]. Second, the effectiveness of a group meeting depends upon the ability to extract, use, and synthesize the potential contributions of group members during the process of group interaction. The group interaction process, and thereby group performance, is often impeded in the meaningful exchange of opinions, and synthesis of different viewpoints, by the existence of a variety of inhibitory barriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="86" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>]. Since JAD provides structures for managing the group meeting, it is expected to further enhance the richness of the user-designer interactions. Thus, we anticipate that:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">HI: The JAD methodology will be perceived as being superior to the traditional IS design methodology in its ability to facilitate richer user-designer interactions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Users and designers exhibit different perceptions about the nature and outcomes of the systems design and development process. Hence, our investigation focused attention upon both designers' and users' perceptions about the quality of user-designer interactions, effectiveness of consensus management, and user acceptance of the design specifications. Given this explicit focus, we offer two separate corollaries to this hypothesis:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Hla: Users will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in its ability to facilitate richer user-designer interactions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Hlb: Designers will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in its ability to facilitate richer user--designer interactions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Generally, structure, as available within the JAD approach, improves the quality of consensus management activities in groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="92" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>]. Process facilitation and an agenda are helpful in focusing members' attention on the productive resolution of conflict. In contrast, in the traditional IS approach, the design team is assigned a central role in reconciling the differences in expec-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="94" page="6" column="1">128</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="95" page="6" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="6" column="1">tations elicited from individual users in the one-on-one meetings. Since users are not collectively involved in a process of negotiation, effective consensus is not expected to result. Thus, we hypothesize that: <marker type="block"/> H2: The JAD method will be perceived as being superior to the traditional design methodology in its ability to facilitate consensus management.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Again we offer two corollaries:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" page="6" column="1">H2a: Users will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in facilitating effective consensus management. <marker type="block"/> H2b: Designers will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in facilitating effective consensus management.<marker type="block"/> Finally, we anticipate that since the JAD methodology facilitates richer user-designer interactions, it will lead to higher levels of user acceptance of the design specifications. Further, effective consensus management processes have been found to lead toward greater satisfaction with the product and process of the group activities. As a result, we anticipate that:<marker type="block"/> H3: The JAD methodology will be perceived as being superior to the traditional design methodology in the level of user acceptance of design specifications.<marker type="block"/> Again, we separate the effects in terms of the user and designer perceptions:<marker type="block"/> H3a: Users will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in the higher level of user acceptance of design specifications.<marker type="block"/> H3b: Designers will perceive the JAD methodology to be superior to the traditional design methodology in the higher level of user acceptance of design specifications.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="106" page="6" column="1">4. Research method</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" page="6" column="1">Data for the study were gathered through a questionnaire survey. The questionnaire was tested for face <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and content validity with a sample of 10 users and systems designers in a state government agency. This pilot test resulted in minor revisions to the item wording. The revised version of the questionnaire was used to gather the user and designer responses. Since the focus of our research is restricted to a comparison of the effects of JAD and traditional IS design methodology, we deemed a deliberate samp- ling strategy to be valid for selecting the population of projects for this research; this allowed us to impose control over the primary independent variable, the systems design methodology. First, we identified firms and projects that would form an appropriate sample. While a multitude of organizations existed that used the traditional IS design methodology, greater effort was required in identifying organizations that used the JAD methodology. A variety of sources, including the trade press and publications were scanned to identify the firms that had adopted the JAD design methodology. In addition, members of a JAD users group were solicited to participate in the study. Overall, a sample of 100 firms, representing industries such as utilities, transportation, insurance, and state government agen- cies, was generated. IS executives at these firms were contacted and informed of the study's objectives. The executives were asked to identify development projects that had been completed within the last twelve months, regardless of whether they were successful or not. Contact information about IS project leaders for the specific projects was also obtained. Affiliated project managers were contacted and requested to participate in the study. Detailed descrip- tions of JAD and the traditional IS design methodology were given to the project managers to ensure the integrity of the independent variable. The project managers were also asked to identify users and designers that had key roles in the systems design process. Detailed cues were given to the project managers so that they would identify appropriate team members to respond to the questionnaire. Next, we mailed questionnaires to the identified project team members. The project managers' questionnaire gathered data about the project characteristics while the user and designer questionnaires collected information on the perceptions of the key team members. Data from all three sources were required to form a complete case of observations for this research. In all, data were gathered from 57 projects, with most organiza-<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tions providing responses about a single project. 221 pairs of user-designer questionares were mailed and 94 pairs of responses were returned for a response rate of 42%. To strengthen the validity of the survey, the designers were asked to indicate the methodology used during the project by checking one of the two options, or by briefly describing their methodology under a third category, titled 'other.' Of the 57 projects, designers circled 'other' for three projects. In these cases, follow-up telephone calls with the designers and project managers revealed that the design methodology fit the definition of the traditional design methodology and these responses were retained for the analysis. Data on project size, project development cost, and departmental scope were obtained from the project managers. Data on project complexity were obtained from designers by asking them to indicate, on a 5-point Likert scale, the relative complexity of the specific project compared to other projects that they had worked on in the past. Data on the designers' confidence, experience, and working knowledge of the development methodology prior to the starting of the project, were gathered through single-item responses from the IS designers. For measuring user and designer perceptions about the quality of interactions, effectiveness of consensus management, and user acceptance of design specifications, 11 items were generated from a review of previous claims about JAD. Some of the items were framed as negative</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx108">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62dq.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="7" column="1">R. Purvis, V Sambamurthy /lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="111" page="7" column="1">129</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> Items for measurement of the perceived effects of design approaches Quality of user--designerinteractions (Cronbach's alpha=0.87) Factor Ioadings The design process during the design of the system encouraged active participation 0.81 Overall, communication during the system design was good between the users and IS designers 0.82 In general, the design process assisted the user in developing a good understanding of the system while it was 0.72 being designed The users were influential in the design process In general, the design process promoted a feeling of partnership between the users and IS designers 0.62 The design process generated user commitment during the system design effort 0.73 Effectiveness of consensus management (reverse scored) (Cronbach's alpha=0.81) The design process created counterproductive conflict between the users and IS designers 0.78 The design process promulgated politics between the IS designers and users that hindered the system design effort 0.78 L ser acceptance of design specifications (Cronbach's alpha=0.81) The overall objectives of the user were met by the system design 0.52 There was a high level of user acceptance for the system design 0.86 Overall, the users were satisfied with the system design 0.89 Note: The measures were gathered on a 5-point Likert scale with the cues ranging from 1 = strongly agree to 5 - strongly disagree.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx115">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62dq.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" page="7" column="2">statements to minimize the respondent bias toward agreement with every statement. Respondents were presented with a 5-point Likert scale, with cues ranging from 'strongly agree' to 'strongly disagree.' <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> illustrates the specific items used for the study.<marker type="block"/> Table 3 provides the demographics of the sample. Two-thirds of the projects involved new systems development and nearly half had approval from at least two or more departments. Overall, these characteristics indicate that the data were gathered on medium-to-large-scale projects. With respect to respondent characteristics, systems analysts and pro- grammer/analysts provided a large share of the responses about designer perceptions. The bulk of the responses about user perceptions was obtained from either the end-users of the IS or managers of an end-user function. Table 4 displays means and standard deviations on various control variables for projects utilizing JAD and the traditional IS design methodology. Significant differences were observed across the projects on all dimensions, except project size in staff-days. Projects utilizing the traditional design methodology were larger in terms of developmental cost and higher in complexity. However, projects utilizing the JAD methodology had secured approval from a larger number of</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="118" page="7" column="2">5. Analyses and results</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="120" page="8" column="1">130</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="121" page="8" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">40 10 4 3</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="123" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">30 12 4 11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="124" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">2 6 14 28 7</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">3 16 13 8 9 2 6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Table 3 Sample demographics Nature of projects (N=57) Type of project New system development Upgrade to an existing system Acquisition of software package Other Number of departments approving the budget One Two to three Four to five More than 5 Project size in staff-days 60 or less (less than 3 staff-months) 61-120 (3 to 6 staff-months) 121-200 (6 to 12 staff-months) 201-1,000 (12 to 60 staff-months) over 1,000 (over 60 staff-months) Project development cost $10,000 or less $10,001-$100,000 $100,001-$500,000 $500,001-$1,000,000 $1,000,001-$2,000,000 greater than $2,000,000 missing values Respondent Characteristics Designers (N=94) Systems analyst Programmer/Analyst Project leader Development manager IS director Other 0</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">26 28 24 10 3 3</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="8" column="1">user departments. This is important, because JAD methodology requires greater involvement and commitment o f effort from the users. Further, IS designers reported themselves as being less confident with the JAD approach and having lower experience with, and working knowledge of, the JAD method. These findings are expected, given differences in the relative duration of existence o f JAD compared to the traditional IS design methodology. Overall, these profile differences raise the possibi- lity that our sample finns were still building their knowledge and experience with JAD through its uti- lization on pilot projects with lower developmental cost and complexity, while applying the more familiar traditional IS design methodology on more expensive</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx129">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62dq.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Users (N=94) End-user Manager of an end-user function Director Other 0</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="131" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">59 27 6 2</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" page="8" column="2">and complex projects. This is consistent with norma- tive recommendations for the implementation of the JAD methodology in organizations. Before assessing the effects of the two design methodologies on dependent variables, factor analysis was used to verify that the questionnaire items were valid indicators of these variables. Two separate factor analyses were conducted, one based on user responses and the other on designer responses. The resulting factor structures were similar. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> shows results o f the factor analysis on designer responses. Almost all factor loadings are in excess o f 0.60, and internal consistencies measured using Cronbach alpha are above 0.80. These results provide support on the suitability of our questionnaire for measuring the user<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> and designer perceptions. Table 4 displays means and standard deviations on the measures of the dependent variables across the two design approaches. The measures of the three constructs representing designer perceptions exhibited strong intercorre- iations (all were significant at p&lt;0.05); similarly, measures of the constructs representing user perceptions also exhibited strong intercorrelations. Hence, a multivariate analysis of covariance (MANCOVA) strategy was adopted. This strategy allowed us to control the effects of project characteristics and designer confidence, experience, and knowledge by<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> including them as covariates. Two separate MANCOVA analyses were conducted, one with designer perceptions and the other with user perceptions as dependent variables. Table 5 displays the effects of the various control variables on designer and user perceptions; these effects were observed as covariate statistics in the MANCOVA analysis. The control variables appear to have a stronger effect on user perceptions. Favorable user perceptions occur when more departments outside the IS department approve of the project, when projects are larger in terms of staff-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="134" page="9" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="135" page="9" column="1">131</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="136" page="9" column="1">Table 4 Summary statistics on key study variables Summary statistics (means and standard deviations) on the control variables Traditional JAD Project size in staff-days 3.42 (0.97) 3.59 (0.92) Project size in cost * 3.52 (1.35) 2.80 (1.18) Project complexity * 1,98 (0.77) 2.19 (0.82) Departmental scope * 1.72 (1.03) 2.04 (1,20) Designer confidence in methodology * 2.11 (0.60) 2.76 (1.14) Designer experience with and 2,34 (0.77) 3.17 (1,26) knowledge of methodology *</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="137" page="9" column="1">Summary Statistics (Means and Standard Deviations) on the Dependent Variables</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="138" page="9" column="1">Designer perceptions Quality of user-designer interactions 2.56 (0.63) 1.91 (0.61) User acceptance of design specifications 2.00 (0.60) 1.64 (0.50) Effectiveness of consensus management 2.50 (0,88) 1,84 (0.52) User perceptions Quality of user-designer interactions 2.71 (1.02) 2.24 (0.70) User acceptance 2.08 (0.78) 2.11 (0.75) Effectiveness of consensus management 2.40 (1.09) 2.24 (0,64)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="139" page="9" column="1">Note: * Indicates significant differences between the SDLC and JAD projects at p&lt;0.10.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="141" page="9" column="1">'Fable 5 Results of testing for effects of control variables on perceptions of the design process and outcomes Designer perceptions Quality of interactions Effectiveness of consensus management User acceptance of design specifications User perceptions Quality of interactions 0.34 ** -0.15 -0.06 0.25 ** Effectiveness of consensus management 0.16 0.20 -0.04 0.43 ** User acceptance of design specifications 0.31 ** -0.11 0,17 0.21 *</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="142" page="9" column="1">Note: The statistics indicate the magnitude of the betas and thus the size of the effects of the control factors on the user and designer perceptions, * Significance of the associated t-statistic at p&lt;0.10. ** Significance of the associated t-statistic at p&lt;0.05.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx143">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62dq.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="144" page="9" column="2">Comments Higher score indicates larger project size Higher score indicates larger project size Lower score indicates higher complexity Higher score indicates larger scope Lower score indicates higher confidence Lower score indicates higher experience and knowledge</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="145" page="9" column="2">Lower score indicates higher quality interactions Lower score indicates better acceptance Lower score indicates more effective consensus management</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="146" page="9" column="2">Lower score indicates higher quality interactions Lower score indicates better acceptance Lower score indicates more effective consensus management</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="148" page="9" column="2">0.27 * 0,30 "* 0.46 **</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="149" page="9" column="2">0.11 -0,02 -0.06</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="150" page="10" column="1">132</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="151" page="10" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="152" page="10" column="1">Table 6 Results of testing for effects of design methodology on perceptions of the design process and outcomes Designer perceptions Overall Wilk's statistic: F----3.82, df=4,67, p=0.007 Univariate tests Quality of user-designer interactions F - 10.51, df= 1,70, p=0.002 * Effectiveness of consensus management F=9.63, df= 1,70, p=0.003 * User acceptance F=3.73, df= 1,70, p=0.06 * User perceptions Overall Wilk's statistic: F=3.28, df=4,69, p=0.016 Univariate tests Quality of user-designer interactions F=7.75, df=l,69, p=0.007 * Effectiveness of consensus management F = 1.83, df= 1,69, p=0.18 User acceptance F=2.07, df= 1,69, p=0.18 * Significant atp&lt;0.10.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">days, and when designers exhibit confidence in the design methodology. Table 6 displays the MANCOVA analysis results that pertain to effects of the design methodology on designer and user perceptions. For designer perceptions, significant differences were observed across all three perceptions (p&lt;0.10). Designers indicated that the JAD methodology facilitated higher quality user- designer interactions, more effective consensus management, and a better user acceptance of the design specifications. Thus, the analysis based on designers' perceptions appears to the hypothesized superiority of JAD over the traditional design methodology (Hypotheses Hlb, H2b, and H3b). With respect to the users' perceptions, however, no significant differences were detected in their belief in the effectiveness of consensus management and its result on acceptance of the design system. However, users did think that JAD produced higher quality user-designer interactions compared with the traditional IS methodology (significant differences at p&lt;0.05). Thus, support was found for hypothesis Hla, but not for hypotheses, H2a and H3a.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="154" page="10" column="1">6. Comparisons between user and designer responses</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Since the data were gathered from pairs of users and designers on specific projects, a paired t-test analysis was conducted to explore differences between user and designer perceptions of projects employing the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx156">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62dq.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">JAD and traditional design methodologies. Table 7 provides the results of the analysis. For projects employing the traditional IS design methodology, significant differences do not appear to exist between the users' and designers' perceptions. In fact, on the quality of user-designer interactions and effectiveness of consensus management, significant positive corre- lations existed between the users' and designers' perceptions. These results indicate that both users and designers shared similar perceptions about effects of the traditional IS design methodology on the design process. For the JAD methodology, significant differences were observed between perceptions of users and designers across all three dependent variables. Overall, the designers had more favorable perceptions of JAD than did the users. Significant negative correla- tions found between user and designer perceptions imply the existence of differences in their perceptions of the effects of JAD and the traditional IS design methodology. The two sets of analyses suggest that designers and users do not share similar levels of favorable perceptions about JAD. Our sample suggests that designers were less confident with the JAD methodology and possessed lower levels of experience and working knowledge than with the traditional IS design methodology (Table 4). Further, we can assume that designers' level of confidence with the design method was perceived by the users, and had a significant effect on users' perceptions of the beneficial value of the design methodology (Table 5). Taken together, these results suggest that lower levels of designer confidence</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="158" page="11" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/Information &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="159" page="11" column="1">133</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Table 7 Comparison between perceptions of users and designers Designers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="161" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">2.62 (0.58) 2.48 (0.88) 2.01 (0.60)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">1.90 (0.61) 1.84 (0.52) 1.64 (0.50)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Traditional IS design approach Quality of user--designer interactions Effectiveness of consensus management User acceptance JAD approach Quality of user-designer interactions Effectiveness of consensus management User acceptance * Correlations significant at p&lt;0.05. *~Correlations significant at p&lt;0.01.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" page="11" column="1">with the JAD method may be one reason for differences in designer-user perceptions about the effects of the method. Several reasons could be responsible for designers' lower levels of confidence. First, JAD is a complex methodology, requiring skills at planning, communicating, negotiating, and learning. While these skills are just as important in one-on-one interviews, designers are more likely to be able to cope with deficiencies in these skills in one-on-one interviews. Second, designers do not get to exercise and develop their skills at facilitation very often. JAD is usually employed on new development projects which are relatively rare and most often lengthy in project time. It can be years between projects when a designer can use JAD, let alone the span of time since formal training. Third, Davidson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="164" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] tound that designers often bend the advocated rules of JAD; for example, by shortening sessions to several hours, not involving actual system users in the JAD sessions, not training business area personnel on useful techniques, and continuing to use modeling and process techniques that are difficult for users to understand. Modifications to design norms and outcomes can be expected to be limited under these conditions.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="166" page="11" column="1">7. Discussion and conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="167" page="11" column="1">User participation is one of the dominant concerns in improving the nature of systems development processes in organizations. In this context, joint application design has been touted as overcoming the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx168">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62dq.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Users</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="170" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Correlation</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Comparison (paired t-test)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">2.72 (1.03) 2.39 (1.10) 2.09 (0.78)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">t=0.80, df=43, p=0.48 t=0.49, df=43, p=0.62 t=0.54, df=45, p=0.60</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="174" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">0.54 ** 0.25 * 0.12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="175" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">2.24 (0.70) 2.27 (0.64) 2.11 (0.75)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="176" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">t=2.06, df=44, p=0.04 * -0.46 ** t=3.24, df=44, p=0.002 ** -0.23 * t=3.21, df=46, p=0.002 ** -0.40 **</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" page="11" column="2">limitations of the traditional IS design methodology. While a variety of claims has been made about the superiority of the JAD approach, limited attempts have been made to verify these claims. This research study sought to examine the effects of the traditional design and the JAD approaches on the quality of user- designer interactions, effectiveness of consensus management, and user acceptance of design specifications. To facilitate comparison of effects, the study included key project characteristics and designers' confidence, experience, and working knowledge with the methodology as control variables and tapped both the designers' and users' perceptions about the design process and outcomes. Overall, the results provide only limited support for claims made about the perceived superiority of JAD over the traditional design methodology. Both users and designers agreed that the JAD methodology promoted greater and richer interactions (user participation and influence, partnerships, and good communication) among participants in the systems design process. In addition, designers perceived JAD to be superior in promoting effective consensus management and user acceptance. However, the users did not perceive any significant differences between the two methodologies on these two factors. Our analysis also revealed that designers were less confident with the JAD methodology and reported having less experience with and working knowledge of the JAD methodology, compared with the traditional IS design methodology. While designers perceived JAD to be beneficial despite their lower levels of confidence with the methodology, users appeared to be more skeptical of the methodology.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="178" page="12" column="1">134</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="179" page="12" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/lnformation &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="180" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">We speculate that different dynamics underlie users' and designers' perceptions about the effects of systems development methodologies. From the designer's point of view, JAD shortens the time required to gather information and enables them to transfer some of the responsibility for communication and negotiation to the users. Using one-on-one interviews necessitates designers to shoulder the responsibility of resolving conflicts in stakeholder design specifications and fill- ing in any missing design specifications. Users could be disenchanted with JAD for several reasons. First, it adds responsibility for communication and negotiation that occurs in JAD sessions which require users to confront differences in their expectations and collectively arrive at a shared view of the design specifications. Second, IS designers were not comfortable in facilitating JAD sessions which require the facilitator to be experienced in a variety of creativity and conflict management techniques. Third, previous research has shown that as JAD is imple- mented, it is usually adapted to the status quo, limiting the potential for substantial benefits. Many ISD organizations could be adopting JAD to enhance legiti- macy more than to benefit from tangible improvements. Finally, while JAD can reduce the time span required to gather information, the sessions usually require larger time commitments from users. This added commitment could be resented and viewed as wasteful by users. In conclusion, the eventual success of JAD will require gaining the same degree of enthusiasm and favorableness of perceptions from users as designers. This is particularly important since the success of the JAD approach depends upon active user participation and commitment.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="181" page="12" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="12" column="1">[1] C. Argyris and D.A. Schon, Organizational Learning, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1978.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="12" column="1">[2] J.H. August, Joint Application Design: The Group Session Approach to System Design, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Yourdon Press, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="12" column="1">[3] A.K. Baronas and M.R. Louis, "Restoring a sense of control during implementation: How user involvement leads to system acceptance," MIS Quarterly, 12(1), 1988, pp. 111- 123.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="12" column="1">[4] J. Baroudi, M.H. Olson and B. Ives, "An empirical study of the impact of user involvement on system usage and <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> information satisfaction," Communications of the ACM, 29(3), 1986, pp. 232-238.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="12" column="2">[5] B.W. Boehm, "A spiral model of software development and enhancement," Computer, 21, May, 1988, pp. 61-72.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="12" column="2">[6] R.P. Bostrum, "Successful application of communication techniques to improve the systems development process," Information and Management, 16(5), 1989, pp. 279-295.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" page="12" column="2">[7] B. Curtis, H. Krasner and N. Iscoe, "A field study of the software design process for large systems," Communications of the ACM, 31(11), 1988, pp. 1268-1287.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="12" column="2">[8] R.L. Daft and R.H. Lengel, "Organizational information requirements, media richness, and structural design," Management Science, 32(5), 1986, pp. 554--571.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="12" column="2">[9] E. Davidson, "An exploratory study of joint application design (JAD) in information systems delivery," Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference on Information Systems, J. Degrees, R. Bostrom and D. Robey (Eds.), Orlando, bL, Dec 5-8, 1993, pp. 271-283.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="12" column="2">[10] B. De Brabaoder and G. Thiers, "Successful information system development in relation to situational factors which affect effective communications between MIS-Users and EDP-Specialists," Management Science, 30(2), 1984, pp. 137-155.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="12" column="2">[1 I] M.S. Deutsch, "An exploratory analysis relating the software project management process to project success," IEEE Transactions of Engineering Management, 38(4), 1991, pp. 365-375.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="12" column="2">[12] E. Erran, R.D. Whitaker and J.E George, "PD and joint application design: A transatlantic comparison," Communications of the ACM, 36(4), 1993, pp. 40-47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="12" column="2">[13l R.A. Hirscheim, "User experience with and assessment of participative system design," MIS Quarterly, 9(4), 1985, pp. 295-303.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="12" column="2">[14] B. Ives and M.H. Olson, "User participation and MIS success: A review of research," Management Science, 30(5), 1984, pp. 586--603.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="12" column="2">[15] M.A. Janson, C.C. Woo and D.L. Smith, "Information systems development and communicative action theory," Information and Management, 25(1), 1993, pp. 59-72.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="12" column="2">[16] P.G.W. Keen, "Information systems and organizational change," Communications of the ACM, 24(1), 1981, pp. 24-33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="12" column="2">[17] A.L. Lederer, J. an Prasad, "Nine management guidelines for better cost estimating," Communications of the ACM, 35(2), 1992, pp. 51-59.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="12" column="2">[18] H.C. Lucas, Jr., Toward Creative Systems Design, Columbia University Press, New York, 1974.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="12" column="2">[19] L.M. Markus, "Power, politics, and MIS implementation," Communications of the ACM, 26(6), 1983, pp. 430-444.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="12" column="2">[20] L.M. Markus and N. Bjorn-Andersen, "Power over users: Its excercise by systems professionals," Communications of the ACM, 30, 1987, pp. 498-504.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="12" column="2">[21] J. Martin, Information Engineering, Book 1." Introduction, Prentice Hall: Englewood Cliffs, NJ, 1989.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="12" column="2">[22] J. Martin, Information Engineering, Book 111: Design and construction, Prentice Hall: Englewood Cliffs, NJ, 1990.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="13" column="1">[23] R.O. Mason and I. Mitroff, Challenging Strategic Planning Assumptions, John Wiley, NY, 1981.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="13" column="1">[241 J.E. McGrath, Groups: Interaction and performance, Pre- ntice-Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ, 1984.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="13" column="1">[25] E. Mumford, "Participative systems design: A structure and method," Systems, Objectives, and Solutions, 1(1), 1981, pp. 5-19.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="13" column="1">[26] J.K. Pinto and D.P. Slevin, "Critical factors in successful project implementation," IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 34, 1987, pp. 22-27.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" page="13" column="1">[271 L.H. Pelled and P.S. Adler, "Antecedents of intergroup conflict in multifunctional product development teams: A conceptual model," IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 41(1), 1994, pp. 21-28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" page="13" column="1">[28] H.O. Rychman, "Requirement definition techniques," Journal of Information Management, 8(3), 1987, pp. 17-21.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="13" column="1">[29] D. Robey and D.L. Farrow, "User participation in information systems development," Management Science, 1982, pp. 73-85.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="13" column="1">[30] V. Sambamurthy and M.S. Poole, "The effects of variations in GDSS capabilities on management of cognitive conflict in groups," Information Systems Research, 3(3), 1992, pp. 224- 251.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="13" column="1">[31] P. Tait and I. Vessey, "The effect of user participation on system success: A contingency approach," MIS Quarterly, 12(1), 1988, pp. 91-108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="13" column="1">[32] J. Wood and D. Silver, Joint Application Design, Chichester: John Wiley, 1989.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="13" column="1">[33J J. Wynekoop and N. Russo, "Systems development methodologies: Unanswered questions and the research-practice gap," Proceeding of the Fourteenth International Conference on Information Systems, J. Degross, R. Bostrom and D. Robey (Eds.), Orlando, FL, Dec 5-8, 1993, pp. 181-190. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Russell L. Purvis (Ph.D., Florida State University, 1994) is Assistant Professor of Management (MIS) at The University of Central Florida. His current research interests are focused on organizational efforts to plan, manage, and implement information technology. His most recent work has been on methods, techniques, and structures designed to improve the quality and productivity of systems development. His publications</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">have appeared in the Journal of Computer Information Systems and Journal of Information Technology Management.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="13" column="2">-- -- V. Sambamurthy (Ph.D., University of Minnesota, 1989) is Associate Professor of MIS at The Florida State University, His current research interests are focused on the design of organizations for effective use of technologies in their business strate- gies and operations. His publications have appeared in the Information __ Systems Research, Decision Sciences, European Journal of In-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">formation Systems, and Information and Management. He has co- authored three research monographs for the Financial Executives Research Foundation. Currently, he is an associate editor on the board of MIS Quarterly and also on the editorial Board of the Journal of Market-focussed Management.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx186">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62dq.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="206" page="13" column="1">R. Purvis, V. Sambamurthy/Information &amp; Management 32 (1997) 123-135</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="207" page="13" column="1">135</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx219">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dq.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62dq.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
