<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>19e6166655d18802e937cbe83b46e4808a280c0c690543e2ddba75241fb9e5af</job>
    <base_name>62ed</base_name>
    <doi>10.1016/j.compind.2012.02.012</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Contents lists available at SciVerse ScienceDirect Computers in Industry</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx3">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ed.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62ed.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/compind</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">A hierarchical classification of co-creation models and techniques to aid in product or service design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Muriati Mukhtar a</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Mohamed Nazul Ismail b</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Yazrina Yahya</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="9">a School of Information Technology, Faculty of Information Science and Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, 43600 UKM Bangi, Selangor, Malaysia b School of Computer Science, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Malaysia</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">A R T I C L E I N F O A B S T R A C T</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="11" page="1" column="1">Article history:</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Received 16 July 2011 Received in revised form 14 February 2012 Accepted 16 February 2012 Available online 7 April 2012</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="13" page="1" column="1">Keywords:</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Service Science Methodology Customer engagement Value Value in use</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="1">The roles of customers from passive users to collaborators in creating and extracting business value have given rise to customer co-creation techniques and value co-creation models. Although these techniques and models have been useful to researchers and businesses, they are unstructured. A classification is necessary so that research can be placed in proper context of one another. Via an examination of the literature and based on the concept of customer value hierarchy a classification of the different models and techniques of co-creation is developed. There are two implications for the classification. Firstly, it will aid in the research and understanding of the use of the various techniques and models. Secondly, it can assist in designing appropriate encounter processes as a basis for engaging customers and subsequently provide innovation for organizations. The paper concludes with an application of the classification to develop encounter processes in a learning management system. ß 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="16" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" page="1" column="1">Customers’ roles have evolved from those of passive users to one that contributes to successful innovations (cf. [27]). Ever since customers became the source of competitive advantage, business organizations have focused their attention to the issue of how to involve customers in the value chain, either as resources for ideas, co-developers or users of products or services. This is evidenced from the proliferation of various customer or user centred methodologies that are used to capture customer needs and requirements so as to embed and provide value (in the product or service) to the users. On the other hand there is an ongoing debate on several issues such as the definition, dimensions and attributes of customer value, mea- sures of customer value and not least the issues of customer– supplier integration, collaboration with customers and customer engagement. With the advent of the internet, the concept of the virtual customer (cf. [3]) has come into being and with that the tools to support virtual customer integration (cf. [21,36]). Evolving in tandem with the changing customer roles is the shift from the manufacturing based economy to the service based one. This has given rise to a new area of research which is</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18" page="1" column="1">ß</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">* Corresponding author. Tel.: +60 389216732; fax: +60 389256732. E-mail addresses: <email id="19">mm@ftsm.ukm.my</email>, <email id="20">muriatimukhtar@gmail.com</email> (M. Mukhtar). 0166-3615/$ – see front matter 2012 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. doi:10.1016/j.compind.2012.02.012</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx22">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ed.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62ed.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="23" page="1" column="2">b</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="1" column="2">termed Service Science. Service Science is a new emerging discipline that advocates an interdisciplinary approach to the study, design, and implementation of service systems, that is, complex systems in which specific arrangements of people and technologies take actions that provide value for others (cf. [53]). Although the beginnings of the area can be traced back to 2004, the motivations and the grounded theory were elaborated by Spohrer and Kwan (cf. [37]) under the name of Service Science Management and Engineering (SSME). The Service Science paradigm proposes that there is no need for the demarcation between products (goods) and services as products are just vehicles of service delivery. SSME or Service Science as a field had imposed a new way of thinking about organizations and its core competences. In the new proposed paradigm, customers now become a new source of competence for the organizations. This is in line with the evolutionary role of the customers from passive users to co-creators of value. The use of customers’ competence can be seen in industries such as software, which have moved from testing products in usability laboratories, to testing them in customer environments (cf. [27]). Taking off from the concept that all systems or organizations are in effect service organizations this new field has proposed a new set of logic which is termed the service dominant logic (cf. [40,41]). Under this new logic the customers are viewed as active players in the co- creation of value of products and services acquired. Hence under this new proposition the roles of the organizations are changing. It is now not enough only to embed value in services and</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="25" page="2" column="1">290</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="26" page="2" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="27" page="2" column="1">Table 1 The changing role of the customers.</caption>
        <content>
          <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="2">
            <thead class="table"/>
            <tbody>
              <tr class="table"/>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </content>
        <region class="TableInfo" id="28" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">Era</region>
        <region class="TableInfo" id="29" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">Customer roles</region>
      </region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">1970s, early 1980s The customer is an average statistic; groups of buyers are predetermined by the company. Products and services are created without much feedback. One-way communication. Late 1980s and early 1990s The customer is an individual statistic in a transaction. Shift from selling to helping via help desks, call centers, and customer service programs; identify problems from customers, then redesign products and services based on that feedback. Database marketing; two-way communication. 1990s Lifetime bonds with individual customers. Providing for customers through observation of users; identify solutions from lead users, and reconfigure products and services based on deep understanding of customers. Relationship marketing; two-way communication and access. Beyond 2000 The customer is not only an individual but also part of an emergent social and cultural fabric. Customers are developers of personalized experiences. Companies and lead customers have joint roles in education, shaping expectations, and co-creating market acceptance for products and services. Active dialogue with customers to shape expectations and create buzz. Multilevel access and communication. Adapted from Prahalad and Ramaswamy [cf. 27].</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="2" column="1">products but now the role of the organizations is also to ensure that the customer can extract value and hence experience the maximum benefit from using the product or service. This state of affairs and the emergence of SSME had pushed the issue of co-creation to the fore and requires us to relook at existing customer engagement approaches, models, frameworks and/or tools. We have to examine the roles and purposes of each of these methods. Besides fragmented work from Dahan et al. (cf. [3]), Fuller and Matzler (cf. [7]) and Sawhney et al. (cf. [36]), there is no other concerted effort to gather and classify these co-creation models in the context of product, service and systems development. Hence, research into this area looked disparate and unstructured. It is quite difficult to put the existing customer engagement models, framework and/or tools in the right context with each other and this state of affairs poses some problems to the novice researcher in the area of SSME. There is a need to classify them. In this paper it is posited that we first classify the models by looking at the level of issues identified and then to subsequently subdivide the models according to the customer value hierarchy model. In Section 2 we explain the use of a few terms that forms the context of the paper. In Section 3 we review the changing role of customers and the evolution of the competitive factors in a business environment. In Section 4 we examine literature from the area of customer value and also the literature on the models of co- creation from the areas of business, manufacturing and services. In Section 5 we present the classification of the models/tools based on the model of customer value hierarchy. In Section 6, we illustrate the use of the classification via a case study conducted. Section 7 concludes the paper.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="32" page="2" column="1">2. Context of the paper</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" page="2" column="1">Before we embark on the main discussion of the paper, it is pertinent that the context of the paper is clarified. This clarification concerned the use of the term customer and the use of the term service: <marker type="block"/> (i) The term customer in the literature can take the meaning of organizational customers, especially when one talks about supply chains. However, to scope the discussions carried out in this paper, we limit the meaning of the term customer to mean end users or consumers. This is similar to the view of customers as users in von Hippel (cf. [54]). (ii) The paper adopts the spirit of Service Science where there is no demarcation made between products and services. Products are seen as vehicles for service delivery. The car example as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">described in Vargo and Akaka (cf. [50]) is a case in point. Hence, in order not to lose sight of this view whilst at the same time not to ignore the current traditional connotations of the term ‘products’ and ‘services’, we have opted to use the voluminous phrase ‘product and/or services’ to embrace both viewpoints.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="36" page="2" column="2">3. Customer role and competition</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="2" column="2">In the beginning, customers as users of products and services were merely receivers of goods and services (cf. [52]). However as technology advances and the competition between firms escalate business organizations can provide customers with more choices. Hence, firms start to compete for the customers’ attention and started to engage customers in their product and/or service design in order to capture and subsequently enhance customer value. Customers’ then become a source of competitive advantage [cf. 43]. The advent of the Internet presented another catalyst for change in customers’ perceptions and demands. Nowadays perceptions and opinions about products and services are being shaped real time amongst customers via social networks, virtual communities, chat rooms and the ubiquitous instant messaging. Information diffusion is rapid and customers’ switching costs are reduced (cf. [49]). Once again provider organizations must be adept at handling and embracing these changes if they still want to win the competition. It is not enough for firms to concentrate only on market segmentation. They must now recognize the force of the individual customer. The role of the individual customer is becoming more important and firms must form close relationships with them in order to understand their needs and incorporating those needs in their product and/or service offering (cf. [48]). Once again firms have to re-examine their business models. The evolutionary role of the customers and the competitive models of the firm seemed to evolve hand in hand. This was captured by Prahalad and Ramaswamy (cf. [27]) who proposed that from being just an average statistic in the 70s, customers now are participating in active dialogue with provider firms and have joint roles in education, shaping expectations, and co-creating market acceptance for products and services. The 4 level model is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="2" column="2">4. Value and customer value</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="2" column="2">Value is elusive yet very important to business organizations and customers. Products or services that are deemed to be of no value will subsequently fail in the market. In this section we begin by giving a brief introduction of value and models of customer value.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="3" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="42" page="3" column="1">291</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="3" column="1">4.1. Value and customer value models</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" page="3" column="1">Research into customer value is both old and multifaceted. It is purported that the debate on the definition of value can be traced back to Aristotle in the 4th century BC (cf. [42]). Customer value models are numerous. The literature is abundant with such models as can be seen from an in-depth review of the literature into the history and classification of customer value models (cf. [15]) and also value models in business to business marketing (cf. [20]). A well known customer value model is the Customer Value Hierarchical Model as proposed by Woodruff (cf. [43]). Woodruff described the inadequacies that revolved around the concept of customer value. He discovered that defining customer value is an elusive endeavour. The literature reveals a diversity of meanings ranging from emotional bonds between customers and producers and to buyer’s perceptions to what is received. Woodruff highlighted that customer value concepts differ according to the circumstances within which customers think about value. He also highlighted that most customer research are geared towards the narrow point of view where value are frequently associated with product attributes. This is also pointed out in a more recent research by Kauppinen et al. (cf. [14]) who researched on requirements engineering for software intensive products where the focus is just on product features rather that other dimensions of customer value. In doing so, Woodruff asserted that other customer dimensions of value such as use consequences are left out. In an effort to tie all the diverging views on customer value to a common platform, he proposed a customer value hierarchy model. In his definition, customer value is a customer’s perceived preference for and evaluation of those product attributes, attribute performance and consequences arising from use that facilitates (or block) achieving the customers’ goals and purposes in use situations. The model is captured in the following <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>. Woodruff’s model is one of several means-ends model (cf. [15]). It started at the bottom of the hierarchy, where it is hypothesized that customers think about product as a bundle of attributes that is thought or perceived to deliver the in-use value or value in-use. Value in-use on the other hand is perceived to support the customers’ goals and purposes, in the highest level of the hierarchy. Similarly, looking from the top, customers’ goals and aspirations will influence them in their expectations of consequences or value in-use which in turn will influence them in determining which attributes are perceived as important to them. Attribute based satisfaction is a result of the realization of the desired attributes in the products and/or services. The realization of value-in use will lead to what is termed the consequence based satisfaction and finally the realization of the customers’ goals and purposes will lead to goal based satisfaction. Graf and Maas (cf. [8]) also examined the literature on value and customer value and highlighted the fact that it is multi faceted and an ongoing research area that is as dynamic as the whole concept of value itself. They asserted that however one wish to look at value, one particular fact that is central to the concept is that value is something that is experienced by the customer and not something that is proposed by the firm.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="46" page="3" column="1">4.2. Value as seen from the Service Science and business innovation literature</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="3" column="1">Traditionally value is created and embedded in the products or services. This is the basis of goods dominant logic, a termed coined by proponents of Service Science. It was hypothesized that this logic has severe limitations and led to the introduction a new kind of logic termed the service dominant logic (cf. [40]). Under this logic the customer is always a co-creator of value (cf. [45]). The role of the firm is only to offer value but not to deliver value. This means <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> that there is no value until an offering is used and the customer is an active participant in the extraction of value and also in experiencing the value offered (cf. [50]). As such value in the context of Service Science mainly referred to value in use as opposed to value in exchange which is prevalent in the goods dominant logic. Both of these factors are reiterated time and again as important value concepts in the Service Science literature for example Vargo and Lusch (cf. [40]) and also in marketing literature for example Prahalad and Ramaswamy (cf. [28]).</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="48" page="3" column="2">Desired Customer customer sa sfac on with value received value Customer’s Goal-based goals and sa sfac on purposes Desired Consequence- consequences based in use sa sfac on situa ons Desired A ribute based product sa sfac on a ributes and a ribute performance</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="49" page="3" column="2">Fig. 1. Customer value hierarchical model. Adapted from Woodruff et al. (cf. [43]).</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="51" page="3" column="2">5. Co-creation methodologies</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" page="3" column="2">Although the concept of value co-creation as proposed and made popular by Service Science is new, the idea of involving customers in the design process has been reported in the design literature and the literature on new product and/or services development. This is exemplified by the numerous methods classified under the banner of user centred design, a term attributed to Donald Norman in the 1980s and made famous in his book (cf. [23]). User centred design techniques include emphatic design, participatory method and paper prototyping. It is sometimes referred to techniques of co-production, co- construction, customer integration, customer engagement and collaboration and customization (cf. [34,3,21,35]). To make the distinction between the different models and techniques from these two streams of research, in this paper, co-creation techniques as described in the design literature is called customer co-creation techniques. This follows the term used by O’Hern et al. (cf. [46]) and Rindfleisch (cf. [47]). Those models that subscribe to <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> the concept of value co-creation as proposed by Service Science are called value co-creation models. Section 5.1 described the value co-creation models and Section 5.2 described the customer co-creation techniques.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="53" page="4" column="1">292</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54" page="4" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="4" column="1">5.1. Value co-creation models</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="4" column="1">In this section we are going to focus on the models that adhere to the value co-creation concept as proposed by Service Science. Here it is emphasized that the roles of customers are as value co- creators and there is no value until an offering is used. It also means that experience and perception are essential to value determina- tion (cf. [45]). In essence these models are concerned with the aspect of value in use as explained and captured by the service dominant logic (cf. [40,42]). This concept of co-creation is shared by Roser et al. (cf. [32]) who discovered that the views and definitions of co-creation are contextual in nature. Here co- creation is defined as processes that entail interactions and collaboration between people, rather than just involvement and co-creativity. Since, value co-creation takes place in the customers’ realm, value co-creation models must take into consideration customers’ use processes and their relationship to the goals or objectives of the customers. Models that subscribed to this view are mostly conceptual in nature and are described as follows: <marker type="block"/> a. The DART model The DART model is a landmark model for co-creation and was proposed by Prahalad and Ramaswamy (cf. [28]). The DART model stresses that the building blocks for co-creation is made up of four components. These are dialogue (D), access (A), risk assessment (R) and transparency (T). They asserted that a careful combination of these building blocks will result in better engagement of customers as collaborators in value creation. The DART model was applied in the development of the Nike Plus website (cf. [31]). b. Payne’s model Payne’s model (cf. [24]) fills the void of co-creation models for services. The framework involved three processes, namely the customer processes, the encounter processes and the supplier or provider processes. The customer processes identified customer goals as one of the important factor to be considered. They stipulated that their framework can be used by marketers in designing and structuring of relationships that forms the core of the co-creation processes. They also illustrated an instance where their framework was used to design a co- creation situation for a travel agent (cf. [24]) and in co-creating brands by applying it to a City Car Club (cf. [25]). c. Gronroos’s model Gronroos’s model (cf. [9]) explored the meaning and ramifications of the service dominant logic and identified the value fulfilment model which is based on the service dominant logic. The value fulfilment model stipulated that value fulfilment takes place during the interactions between suppliers and customers via the customers’ value generating processes. Thus, besides proposing value, firms can actively influence, via suitably designed interactions, how the value propositions made are fulfilled and experienced through the customer’s value creation.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="4" column="1">5.2. Customer co-creation techniques</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="4" column="1">Co-creation techniques are techniques that use customers as resource for ideas and/or as partners in co-developing or co- producing the products. User centred techniques which are a part of the human computer interface (HCI) arsenal are included in this class of techniques. They also include techniques in which <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> customers as end users of products, are used by firms to learn about product shortcomings and also in identifying new ideas for product improvement. In this section we are going review several methods. This review is by no means exhaustive. However it is deemed to be representative of the other techniques not covered by the review.<marker type="block"/> a. Participatory method Participatory method is believed to be the root for co- creation techniques (cf. [34]). In participatory design end users are treated as experts. The objective is to let end users and producers jointly create a product or a solution that will serve the end user better (cf. [38]). Implementing the participatory method usually involved some kind of a workshop. b. Emphatic design Emphatic design is a technique whereby the researchers will observe the users in their own environment while using the products and/or services. The objective of this method is to get at the latent user needs. This will form the basis for the development of better products and/or services that are suited to the users. Using sensors to aid the collection of data Intille et al. (cf. [11]) described how their PlaceLab is used to study the behaviour of users in natural settings so as to facilitate understanding of user behaviour. c. Co-designing Co-designing is a mixture between the emphatic design method and the participatory method (cf. [38]). In co-designing, the focus is on jointly articulating ideas and concepts via mock- ups, prototypes or by using other generative tools that will aid verbal or visual communication (cf. [33]). An exercise in co- designing is described by Berger et al. (cf. [1]). It is a study on Adidas and its customer base. d. Use of artefacts or prototypes Artefacts and prototypes are usually used to represent a yet non existing invention. Users are equipped with these artefacts and are asked to record their experience in using them to note any sudden realization of the novelty of the new invention and/ or service related to it. Kristensson et al. (cf. [17]) and Matthing et al. (cf. [19]) reported on the use this approach in their field experiments that was conducted in Sweden with end-user mobile phone services. A special type of prototype called the experience prototypes are used by Ikea with their experience rooms and Mercedes with their hyper reality rooms (cf. [4]). e. Personas and avatars The idea of using personas as representing the voice of the customer was illustrated by Microsoft (cf. [10,29,30]). They had developed complex personas of customers and based on these personas they developed their needs and requirements which formed the inputs in the software produced by Microsoft (cf. [30]). Avatars on the other hand are virtual characters that are created by real users. A lot of information can be gleaned from the characteristics of the avatars. For example, information pertaining to hair colour and styles as indicative of customers’ preferences and use them in hair care product development (cf. [16,13]) f. Laddering techniques of interviews The laddering technique of interview is a probing type of interview which aims at getting to the user value or goals in using products or services. The interview responses are then coded and analyzed. Subsequently Hierarchical Value Maps are developed. These maps can then be used as a basis to develop features of products or services. An example of use of this technique is in Sun et al. (cf. [39]) who identified the most important attributes, consequences, and values in using an e- learning system from the perspective of instructors.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> g. Living Labs The Living Lab concept originates from MIT Boston (cf. [5]). Niitamo et al. (cf. [22]) described a Living Lab as a user centric methodology that involved a business entity, users and other stakeholders that comes together to create, prototype and test a product, service, businesses or technologies in real life context such as large cities or rural areas. It is developed to utilize the co- creation potential of users (cf. [6]). Kusiak (cf. [18]) proposed a variant of the Living Lab which is termed the living innovation lab (LIL) that is designed to co-create artefacts with users. h. Lead user approach This method is used by Bragge et al. (cf. [2]) who proposed a framework that makes use of virtual communities to recruit lead users to aid in information systems development. Zhang et al. (cf. [44]) developed a web based platform that encouraged lead users who have strong interests in ceramics design to use PhotoShop and 3DS MAX software to design ceramics. i. Toolkits for ideas competition These types of competition provide avenues for companies to tap into customers’ ideas as input in the product development stages. As such the customers’ voice are taken into consideration when developing new products and/or services. In the ‘design your dream Ducati’ contest (cf. [36]) the customers’ are encouraged to submit their ideas about their future dream Ducatis. This provides valuable information to Ducati and can be used in their future designs. A similar effort is also developed in conjunction with Adidas (cf. [26]). j. Community based innovation method Communities of users are important sources of innovative ideas that can lead to new products or services. In this type of customer co-creation technique, customers are treated as resources for ideas and also as co-creators of the product or services. An example is the virtual lab (which is a web based interaction platform) developed for AUDI where participants designed their own individual infotainment consoles thereby supporting the development team in the selection of the most preferred product configurations (cf. [7]). A similar approach is reported by Hilgers et al. (cf. [55]) in improving the design of motorcycles.<marker type="block"/> Customer co-creation techniques as described in sub Section 5.2 are usually firm led. These methods serve as avenues to learn about and from customers. They are basically requirements elicitation methods to help firms design products and/or services required by the customers. Although they are successful in<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> capturing the requirements and subsequently embed them in the product attributes, they do not fully resolve the issues that arise during use situations of the products and/or services. This is because, no matter how comprehensive the requirements gathering techniques are and no matter how diligent they are carried out, they cannot take into consideration all cases and all situations of use. This means that they cannot cater for emergent use situations (cf. [51]). Hence, new models or methodologies that take into account different use situations must be considered. These are the issues tackled by the value co-creation models put forward in Section 5.1. The relationship between these techniques and models with respect to customer roles and customer value is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>. Thus a successful methodology for co-creation must be a combination of both the co-creation techniques and value co- creation models. The methodology for combining these techniques and models is embodied in the hierarchical classification as described in the next section.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="63" page="5" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="64" page="5" column="1">293</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="65" page="5" column="1">Table 2 Classification of co-creation methodologies based on customers’ role and value.</caption>
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="5">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Classification</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers’ role</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customer value (based on Woodruff’s model)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Customer co-creation techniques</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Participatory method</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers as co-producers, co-designers</td>
                    <td class="table"> Attribute based value</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Co-designing</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Artifacts and prototypes</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Lead user approach</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Personas and avatars</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers as resources of ideas; customers as sources of</td>
                    <td class="table"> Attribute based value</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Toolkit for ideas competition</td>
                    <td class="table"> (general) information</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Community based based innovation innovation</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers Customers as as resources resources for for ideas; ideas;</td>
                    <td class="table"> Attribute based value</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> Customers Customers as as co-creators co-creators of of products products</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Living Labs Labs</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers Customers as as co-creator co-creator of of products, products, tester tester and and users users of of products products</td>
                    <td class="table"> Attribute based value</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Emphatic design design</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers Customers as as end end users users and and buyers buyers</td>
                    <td class="table"> Attribute based value with some</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Laddering technique technique</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> focus on value in-use</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Value Value co-creation co-creation models models</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> DART model model</td>
                    <td class="table"> Customers Customers as as end end users, users, buyers buyers and and value value co-creators co-creators</td>
                    <td class="table"> Value in-use and goal based value</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Payne’s model model</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Gronroos’s model model</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="66" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Classification Customers’ role Customer value (based on Woodruff’s model) Customer co-creation techniques Participatory method Customers as co-producers, co-designers Attribute based value Co-designing Artifacts and prototypes Lead user approach Personas and avatars Customers as resources of ideas; customers as sources of Attribute based value Toolkit for ideas competition (general) information Community based innovation Customers as resources for ideas; Attribute based value Customers as co-creators of products Living Labs Customers as co-creator of products, tester and users of products Attribute based value Emphatic design Customers as end users and buyers Attribute based value with some Laddering technique focus on value in-use Value co-creation models DART model Customers as end users, buyers and value co-creators Value in-use and goal based value Payne’s model Gronroos’s model</region>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="5" column="2">6. Hierarchical classification of co-creation models and techniques</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="5" column="2">Thus far we have reviewed the literature on the different types of value co-creation techniques by the design literature and also the co-creation models as described by the Service Science literature. Although these two streams of literature deliberated and discussed about the concept of co-creation, they seemed disjointed. The literature on customer co-creation techniques describes methods by which customers can be integrated into the process of new products and/or services development. The information gleaned from these techniques is used to design the attributes of the new products and/or services. Via customer co- creation efforts it is hypothesized that satisfaction with product attributes will naturally lead to value in use. Most of the customer co-creation techniques described in the literature adhered to this hypothesis. The customers are engaged so that the developers or designers can elicit the product and/or service requirements. This is done in various ways and at various degrees of customer involvement as described in Section 5.2. Value co-creation models on the other hand focused on the value in use of the products and/ or services. The premise is that value is proposed and the customer is responsible to extract this value and the role of the firm is to ensure that this value can be enhanced by whatever means so as to give a unique product and/or service experience to the customers. Thus the main contention of the paper is to give structure to these seemingly diverging views on value and co-creation. It is <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> suggested here that this coherence can be obtained via Woodruff’s hierarchical model of customer value as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>. The posited classification via Woodruff’s model groups the co-creation methodologies into two separate groups, namely the value co- creation models and the customer co-creation techniques. The customer value hierarchical model as suggested by Woodruff [43] models the interactions between three types of customer values. It also describes the interrelationships between the different values. The three different levels of value can form the basis for the classification of the techniques that can be found in the design literature and also the models from the Service Science literature. Since the focus of the co-creation techniques are mostly on the realization of customers’ preferences of product attributes, they are techniques used to realize the attribute based value. This will lead to attribute based satisfaction. The customer co-creation techniques are firm led and hence is related to the firm’s processes and their ability to translate the customers’ requirements into product and/or service attributes. Here the customers are mainly as co-creators of products. Their roles are to provide ideas, co- design or co-produce and testers of products. This is depicted in the lower part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>. At the point of exchange the products and or/<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> services change hands and now lies in the customers’ space. Beyond the point of exchange the focus will be on value extraction. The customers’ roles are to consume and experience the products and/or services. Here customers’ processes will be responsible to extract the required value from the products and/or services by integrating all available resources. They will be the active participant in value co-creation. The role of the firm now is to facilitate the extraction or realization of value for each of the customers. Here value co-creation models from the Service Science literature that give importance to value in use and customer goals are useful. These models attach great importance to the roles of the firms in facilitating dialogue (as in the Dart model), understanding customers’ processes and goals (as in Payne’s model) and also the firm as a facilitator of value (as in Gronroos’s value fulfillment model). Via these models value in use and goal based value can be realized and this will lead to the consequence based satisfaction and goal based satisfaction as depicted in the upper part of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref> it can be seen that Woodruff’s model forms the core of the classification. It shows the overall relationship between the methodologies of co-creation, to the three levels of customer value and also the customer roles.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="73" page="6" column="1">294</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="74" page="6" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="75" page="6" column="1">Co-crea on Desired methodologies customer value Customer’s goals and purposes Value co- crea on models (sec on Desired 5.1) consequences in use situa ons Customer Desired co-crea on product techniques a ributes (sec on and 5.2) a ribute performance</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="76" page="6" column="1">Fig. 2. A hierarchical classification of co-creation models and techniques.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="80" page="6" column="2">Customer Customer roles sa sfac on with received value Goal-based sa sfac on Buy, consume and experience; ability to integrate available resources to experience the Consequence- product or based service sa sfac on (co-create value) Point of exchange A ribute Idea on and based Concept; sa sfac on Product Design and Tes ng (co-create product)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="84" page="7" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="85" page="7" column="1">295</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ed.page_007.image_03.png" thmb="62ed.page_007.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="87" page="7" column="1">Fig. 3. Value elicitation via the laddering technique.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="88" page="7" column="1">6.1. Application of the classification</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" page="7" column="1">The main objective for this work is to provide a classification for the literature on value, co-creation and value co-creation. The classification is developed by grouping the different techniques and models based on Woodruff’s novel customer value hierarchy model. The classification puts due importance to all levels of value, namely the attribute based value, value in use and goal based value. To realize the attribute based value one of the customer co- creation techniques (as described in Section 5.2) must be employed. It must be reasserted here that the technique forms the basis for requirements elicitation. The identified attributes will form the features of the proposed product and/or service. However, since embedding attributes into a product and/or service do not necessarily leads to the realization of value in use or goal based value, co-creation models as described in Section 5.1 must be applied. In this section, via a case scenario, it is shown that the classification can be used to develop a new methodology, by suitably combining existing co-creation techniques and models.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="90" page="7" column="1">6.1.1. Case: developing a learning management system (LMS) that supports value co-creation</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="7" column="1">This case scenario concerns the development of a learning management system (LMS). A learning management system is an example of a product-service system in that it is primarily a product that provides services, in this case to aid in learning. Traditionally the development of the LMS has been approached using the product paradigm whereby requirements elicitations are done in order to develop a LMS with the required attributes or features. The purpose of the case scenario is to exhibit the use of the hierarchical classification in aiding the development of a methodology for developing a learning management system that supports value co-creation. The methodology is described in three main phases as follows: Phase 1: Capturing requirements: In this phase all the stakeholders in the LMS such as students, instructors and policy makers <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> are roped in to elicit values that relate to learning needs, teaching needs, habits and goals. There are several ways that this can be done (as can be seen from Section 5.2). In this case we use the laddering interview technique and the paper prototype of the proposed system. The reason for using the laddering technique is so that we can elicit the values related to the stakeholders and the use of the paper prototype is so that we can enact an ‘‘in use situation’’ so that the stakeholders will have a feel of how the real system will affect their activities, thus enabling the system developer to identify the different ‘‘in use situations’’. This will help the developer in designing suitable encounter process/ interfaces that will enhance the value in use thus providing a unique learning experience to the student. The results from this phase (cf. [12]) will be used to design the attributes of the e- learning system and also to design the part of the system that will enhance the value in use. In this phase the users (stakeholders) of the LMS are used as resources for ideas and also as co-designer of the LMS. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 3</xref> shows some of the values elicited via the laddering technique. Phase 2: Designing the system: There are two parts of this phase. First is to design the attributes as needed by the stakeholders that were elicited in Phase 1. Second is to design relevant encounters or interfaces to facilitate the process of value co-creation and to enhance value in use. One model that can be used for this is the DART model. Using this model the learning management system must enable dialogue between all identified stakeholders (stu- dent–student, student–instructor, student–instructor–policy mak- er, etc.). This can be done via system notifications and alerts, chatting facilities, e-mails and forums. Access to identified learning or other relevant resources can be done by enabling the LMS to allow access to other academic sources on the Internet. Thus the LMS enables customization and personalization of learning to take place, making the learning experience unique to each individual student or other stakeholders. The users’ (stakeholders) role in this phase is as value co-creators. The system should be designed so that they are able to integrate all resources that will be beneficial in their learning. A suitable architecture that can be considered will<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> be the service oriented architecture. The Nike Plus website (cf. [31]) can be used as an example prototype. Phase 3: Testing and launch: The success of the proposed system will inherently depend on its ability to cater to the goals and use situations of the users. This will be as many and as varied as the number of users themselves. The usability and value in use of the system will have to be tested and evaluated. This is done through questionnaires distributed to the users of the prototype system to gauge the overall acceptance and value in use of the system. Feedback obtained is used to improve the system before it is launched for actual use.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="94" page="8" column="1">296</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="95" page="8" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="97" page="8" column="1">7. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99" page="8" column="1">This paper reports the journey of research that began with a look into the methodologies of co-creation. The journey has uncovered the seemingly diverging views on co-creation held by the community of design and that of Service Science. The design community mainly held the view that customers are sources for ideas and in this realm co-creation usually means co-designing, co- producing or co-developing product and/or service attributes. The emergence of the area of Service Science and the new view of the concept of value co-creation as value in use however, has succeeded in imploring the research community to re-examine and develop the underlying concepts, theory and methodologies of co-creation. This has become the motivation that has led us to analyze the concept of customer value and propelled us to search for a suitable customer value model that best capture the essence of value as adopted by both streams of research. It was asserted that it is necessary for this type of analysis to be carried out, so that research in the area will be more structured and will be more amenable to novice researchers who are looking for a suitable methodology to deploy in their respective research especially in the broad area of Service Science. The purported customer value model should be able to capture the essence of the differing techniques and models proposed by both streams of research. This means that it should cater for both the concept of co-creation of products and/or services and also the co-creation of value. In this paper it is posited that this can be done via Woodruff’s Hierarchical Model. The applicability of the proposed hierarchical classification is illustrated via a case study on the development of a learning management system. It should be noted however that the proposed classification is an initial effort. Although it can be applied to any specific product and/or service system, its main limitation is that it is still quite general. This means that there is no specific and detailed way on how to apply the classification for products, services or product-service systems, respectively. This will be the subject of our future work. The other limitation is that the applicability of the classification is highly dependent on the system developer’s insight and understanding of each of the methods described in Section 5. The above case scenario on the LMS illustrates this point. The chosen laddering techniques can be replaced by any other customer co-creation techniques and the DART model can be replaced by either the Gronroos’s or Payne’s models or combinations of them. Thus the main issue here is not in the choice of the specific models but in the realization of the purpose and role that each model plays in the process of creating products and/or services and to customer value. By suitably combining the techniques and models, multiple perspectives in product and/or service development can be realized thus allowing room for innovation. The proposed classification is also not intended to be exhaustive and final. Rather it should be viewed as a work in progress and as a living document. It is envisaged that refinements to the classification can be done as more methods are <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> developed. It is hoped that it will serve as a useful tool to aid in research and industry.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="100" page="8" column="2">References</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="102" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">[1] C. Berger, K. Moslein, F. Piller, R. Reichwald, Co-designing modes of cooperation at the customer interface: learning from exploratory research, European Management Review (2005) 1–18. [2] J. Bragge, T. Tuunanen, R. Marttiin, Inviting lead-users from virtual communities to co-create innovative IS services in a structured groupware environment, Service Science 1 (4) (2009) 241–255. [3] E. Dahan, J.R. Hauser, The virtual customer, Journal of Product Innovation Management 19 (2002) 332–353. [4] B. Edvardsson, B. Enquist, R. Johnston, Cocreating customer value through hyper- reality in the prepurchase service experience, Journal of Service Research (2005) 3–13. [5] M. Eriksson, V.-P. Niitamo, S. Kulkki, State-of-the-art in Utilizing Living Labs Approach to User-centric ICT Innovation – A European Approach, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://open" id="101">http://open</ext-link>- livinglabs.i2cat.cat/documents/SOA_LivingLabs.pdf, 2005 (last accessed 2010-01- 17). [6] A. Følstad, Towards a living lab for the development of online community services, The Electronic Journal for Virtual Organizations and Networks, Special Issue on Living Labs 10 (August) (2008) 47–58. [7] J. Fuller, K. Matzler, Virtual product experience and customer participation—a chance for customer-centred, really new products, Technovation 27 (2007) 378–387. [8] A. Graf, P. Maas, Customer value from a customer perspective: a comprehensive review, Journal fur Betriebswirtschaft (JfB) (2008) 1–20. [9] C. Gronroos, Service logic revisited: Who creates value? And who co-creates?, European Business Review 20 (4) (2008) 298–314. [10] J. Grudin, J. Pruitt, Personas, Participatory Design and Product Development: An Infrastructure for Engagement, 2002 research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/ jgrudin/.../personas/pdc2002.pdf (last accessed 2010-05-10). [11] S.S. Intille, K. Larson, J.S. Beaudin, J. Nawyn, T.E., Munguia, P. Kaushik, A living laboratory for the design and evaluation of ubiquitous computing technologies, in: Proceedings of CHI 2005, 2005, pp. 1–4. [12] M.N. Ismail, Y., Yahya, M., Mukhtar, M.S., Zakaria, A. Zahrawi, A service science approach for e-learning, in: Proceedings for the 4th International Symposium on Information Technology, 2010, pp. 304–307. [13] H.-S. Kang, H.-D. Yang, The visual characteristics of avatars in computer-mediated communication: comparison of internet relay chat and instant messenger, International Journal of Human-Computer Studies 64 (2006) 1173–1183. [14] M. Kauppinen, J. Savolainen, L. Lehtola, M. Komssi, H. Tohonen, A. Davis, From feature development to customer value creation, in: Proceedings of the 17th IEEE International Requirements Engineering Conference, 2009, pp. 275–280. [15] A.S. Khalifa, Customer value: a review of recent literature and an integrative configuration, Management Decision 42 (5) (2004) 645–666. [16] T. Kohler, K. Matzler, J. Fuller, Avatar-based innovation: Using virtual worlds for real-world innovation, Technovation 29 (6) (2009) 395–407. [17] P. Kristensson, J. Matthing, N. Johansson, Key strategies for the successful involvement of customers in the co-creation of new technology-based services, International Journal of Service Industry Management 19 (4) (2008) 474–491. [18] A. Kusiak, Innovation: the living laboratory perspective, Computer-Aided Design and Applications 4 (6) (2007) 863–876. [19] J. Matthing, B. Sande  ́ n, B. Edvardsson, New service development: learning from and with customers, International Journal of Service Industry Management 15 (5) (2004) 479–498. [20] K. Moller, Role of competences in creating customer value: a value creation logic approach, Industrial Marketing Management 35 (2006) 913–924. [21] S. Nambisan, Designing virtual customer environments for new product development: Toward a theory, Academy of Management Review 27 (3) (2002) 392–413. [22] V.-P. Niitamo, S. Kulkki, M. Eriksson, K.A. Hribernik, State-of-the-art and good practice in the field of living labs, in: Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Concurrent Enterprising: Innovative Products and Services through Collaborative Networks, 2006, pp. 349–357. [23] D. Norman, The Design of Everyday Things, Doubleday, New York, 1988. [24] A.F. Payne, K. Storbacka, P. Frow, Managing the co-creation of value, Journal of the Academy Marketing Science 36 (2008) 83–96. [25] A.F. Payne, K. Storbacka, P. Frow, S. Knox, Co-creating brands: diagnosing and designing the relationship experience, Journal of Business Research 62 (2009) 379–389. [26] F.T. Piller, D. Walcher, Toolkits for idea competitions: a novel method to integrate users in new product development, R&amp;D Management 36 (3) (2006) 307–318. [27] C.K. Prahalad, V. Ramaswamy, Co-opting customer competence, Harvard Business Review 78 (1) (2000) 79–87. [28] C.K. Prahalad, V. Ramaswamy, Co-creating unique value with customers, Strategy and Leadership 32 (3) (2004) 4–9. [29] J. Pruitt, J. Grudin, Personas: practice and theory, in: DUX’03 Proceedings of the 2003 Conference on Designing for User Experiences, pp. 1–15. [30] J. Pruitt, T. Adlin, The Persona Lifecycle Keeping People in Mind Throughout Product Design, Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, San Francisco, 2006. [31] V. Ramaswamy, Co-creating value through customers’ experiences: the Nike case, Strategy and Leadership 36 (5) (2008) 9–14.</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="9" column="1">M. Mukhtar et al. / Computers in Industry 63 (2012) 289–297</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="104" page="9" column="1">297</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="105" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">[32] T. Roser, A.H. Samson, E. Cruz-Valdivieso, Co-Creation: New Pathways to Value: An Overview, www.promisecorp.com/newpathways, 2009 (last accessed 2010- 05-21). [33] E.B.-N. Sanders, Generative tools for co-designing in scrivener, in: Ball, Woodlock (Eds.), Collaborative Design, Springer Verlag, London, 2000. [34] E.B-N. Sanders, P.J. Stappers, Co-creation and the new landscapes of design, CoDesign 14 (1) (2008) 5–18. [35] M. Sawhney, E. Prandelli, G. Verona, The power of innomediation, MIT Sloan Management Review 44 (2) (2003) 77–82. [36] M. Sawhney, G. Verona, E. Prandelli, Collaborating to create: the Internet as a platform for customer engagement in product innovation, Journal of Interactive Marketing 19 (4) (2005) 1–15. [37] J. Spohrer, S.K. Kwan, Service science, management, engineering and design (SSMED): an emerging discipline–outline and references, International Journal of Information Systems in the Service Sector 1 (3) (2009) 1–31. [38] M. Steen, L. Kuijt-Evers, J. Klok, Early user involvement in research and design projects – a review of methods and practices, in: Proceedings for the 23rd EGOS Colloquium, 2007, pp. 1–21. [39] P-C Sun, H.K. Cheng, G. Finger, Critical functionalities of a successful e-learning system—an analysis from instructors’ cognitive structure toward system usage, Decision Support Systems 48 (2009) 293–302. [40] S.L. Vargo, R.F. Lusch, Evolving to a new dominant logic for marketing, Journal of Marketing 68 (2004) 1–17. [41] S.L. Vargo, R.F. Lusch, Service-dominant logic: continuing the evolution, Journal of the Academy Marketing Science 36 (2008) 1–10. [42] S.L. Vargo, P.P. Maglio, M.A. Akaka, On value and value co-creation: a service systems and service logic perspective, European Management Journal 26 (2008) 145–152. [43] R.B. Woodruff, Customer value: the next source for competitive advantage, Journal of the Academy Marketing Science 25 (2) (1997) 139–153. [44] X. Zhang, C. Miao, Y. Li, H. Zhang, Beyond product customization: towards a conceptual framework for collaborative customer innovation, in: Proceedings of the 2008 12th International Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work in Design, 16–18 April, 2008, pp. 973–978. [45] R.F. Lusch, S.L. Vargo, M. O’Brien, Competing through service: insights from a service dominant logic, Journal of Retailing 83 (1) (2007) 5–18. [46] M. O’Hern, A. Rindfleisch, Customer Co-creation: A Typology and Research Agenda Working Paper 4, Thoughts on Innovation from the Wisconsin School of Business, 2008. [47] A. Rindfleisch, Customer co-creation: a typology and research agenda, in: N.K. Malhotra (Ed.), Review of Marketing Research, vol. 6, 2010, pp. 84–106. [48] G. Prastacos, K. So  ̈ derquist, Y. Spanos, L.V. Wassenhove, An integrated framework for managing change in the new competitive landscape, European Management Journal 20 (February (1)) (2002) 55–71. [49] G. Verona, E. Prandelli, A dynamic model of customer loyalty to sustain competitive advantage on the web, European Management Journal 20 (2002) 299–309 (3rd June). [50] S.L. Vargo, M.L. Akaka, Service-dominant logic as a foundation for Service Science: clarifications, Service Science 1 (1) (2009) 32–41. [51] K. Ueda, T. Takenaka, K. Fujita, Toward value co-creation in manufacturing and servicing, CIRP Journal of Manufacturing Science and Technology 1 (2008) 53–58.</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">[52] C.A. Lengnick-Hall, V. Claycomb, L.W. Inks, From recipient to contributor: exam- ining customer roles and experienced outcomes, European Journal of Marketing 34 (3/4) (2000) 359–383. [53] I.C.L. Ng, R. Maull, L. Smith, Embedding the new discipline of service science, the science of service systems, in: H. Demirkan, J.H. Spohrer, V. Krishna (Eds.), Volume in Service Science: Research and Innovations (SSRI) in the Service Economy Book Series, Springer, 2011, pp. 13–35. [54] E. von Hippel, Economics of product development by users: the impact of sticky local information, Management Science 44 (May (5)) (1998) 629–644. [55] M.G. Hilgers, S. Hong, R.H. Hallz, Designing motorcycles via the web: improved aesthetics and consumer preference, in: Proceedings of the 15th Americas Conference on Information Systems, 2009, pp. 1–14.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">Muriati Mukhtar is an associate professor at the School of Information Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia (UKM), Malaysia. She is currently the Head of the Industrial Computing research group in UKM. Her current research interests are service science, supply chain simulation and applications of information technology in small and medium enterprises.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx108">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ed.page_009.image_04.png" thmb="62ed.page_009.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="109" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">Mohamed Nazul Ismail is a doctoral student at the Faculty of Information Science and Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Malaysia. His research interests include value and value co-creation, learning management system, Means-End Chain Theory and Service-dominant logic. He holds a bachelor’s degree in computer science and a master in information technology from Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia and master of science in educational technology from Univesity Putra Malaysia, Malaysia. He is currently employed as a teachers’ educator at the Technical Teachers’ Training Institute of Malaysia, Malaysia. Yazrina Yahya received her Ph.D. in Intelligent Multimedia from Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, M.Sc. in Business System Analysis and Design from City University, London and B.Sc. in Computer Science from Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia. She is currently an Associate Professor at Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia. Her research interests include service science, application of value co-creation in modeling and development of information system, semantic web technologies, knowledge management and agent based system.</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx110">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ed.page_009.image_05.png" thmb="62ed.page_009.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
