<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>7fa89b0d8a5b117c387f5545c0d3db0db60cea1fee829efe1962f407180d668a</job>
    <base_name>62bz</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s0950-7051(00)00065-4</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Symmetry of ignorance, social creativity, and meta-design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">G. Fischer</name>
          <aff id="4">*</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="11" page="1" column="1">* Tel.: 11-303-492-1592; fax: 11-303-492-2844.</footnote>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">Center for LifeLong Learning &amp; Design (L 3 D), Department of Computer Science and Institute of Cognitive Science, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309, USA</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6">Complex design problems require more knowledge than any one single person can possess, and the knowledge relevant to a problem is often distributed and controversial. Rather than being a limiting factor, asymmetry of ignoranceo can provide the foundation for social creativity. Bringing different points of view together and trying to create a shared understanding among all stakeholders can lead to new insights, new ideas, and new artifacts. Social creativity can be supported by new media that allow owners of problems to contribute to framing and solving these problems. These new media need to be designed from a meta-design perspective by creating environments in which stakeholders can act as designers and be more than consumers. q 2000 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved. Keywords: Conceptual frameworks for creativity and cognition; Consumers; Designers; Impact of new media on design; Meta-design; Social creativity; Symmetry of ignorance</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" page="1" column="1">Creativity is often associated with art; our research work in the Center for LifeLong Learning &amp; Design (http:// www.cs.colorado.edu/~l3d/), however, is concerned with the creativity that is required in everyday work practice by emphasizing the importance of lifelong learning during these activities. The analysis of everyday design practices has shown that knowledge workers and designers have to engage in creative activities to cope with the unforeseen complexities of everyday, real-world tasks. This type of creativity is in most cases not historicaÐthat is, the activity or the product is not necessarily novel or original to a community of practice or society as a wholeÐbut psycho- logical, meaning it is personally novel and meaningful to the stakeholders who produced it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="8" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. Although analyzing outstanding creative people contribute toward establishing a framework for creativity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="9" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], understanding creativity in the context of everyday activities is equally important for letting people become more productive and create better work products. This paper explores three interrelated concepts: symmetry of ignorance, social creativity, and</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">E-mail address: <email id="12">grhard@cs.colorado.edu</email> (G. Fischer). q Derived from `Social creativity, symmetry of ignorance and Meta- Design', published in the Proceedings of the Third Conference on Creativity and Cognition, Loughborough, UK, October 10±13, 1999, pp. 115±123. Reproduced with permission from ACM q 1999.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="14" page="1" column="2">www.elsevier.com/locate/knosys</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="2">q</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="2">meta-design. These concepts are illustrated with examples developed in our research over the last 10 years.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="17" page="1" column="2">2. Symmetry of ignorance</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="34" page="2" column="2">2.2. Example 1 : symmetry of ignorance and high- functionality applications</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="2" column="2">HFA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="35" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>] such as Unix, MS-Of®ce, Photoshop, Eudora, etc., are used to model parts of existing worlds and to create new worlds. They are complex systems because they serve the needs of large and diverse user populations. If we ask 100 different people what features they would like to have in a particular application, we will end up with a very large number of features. The design of HFAs must address three problems: (1) the unused functionality must not get in the way; (2) unknown existing functionality must be accessible or delivered at times when it is needed; and (3) commonly used functionality should be not too dif®cult to be learned, used, and remembered. We have conducted a variety of empirical studies to determine the usage patterns of HFAs, their structure, and their associated help and learning mechanisms.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="37" page="2" column="2">2.2.2. Expertise in HFA</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" page="2" column="2">aExpertso (users who know everything about a system) no longer exist for HFAs. In such rich settings, being an aexperto is at best an attribute of a speci®c context, rather than a personal attribute. The different spaces of expertise (determined by individual interest) are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>. In this multi-kernel model, {D 1 , U i } means the area of functionality D 1 that is well known to a particular user U i ; for example: U 1 knows about the equation editor, U 2 knows about mail-merge functionality, U 3 uses a bibliography system for references, and U 4 is familiar with collaborative writing tools (D 4 represents the functionality of the system as a whole). The diagram graphically illustrates the asymmetry of ignoranceo among the users U 1 ±U 4 .</region>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="40" page="2" column="2">2.3. Example 2 : symmetry of ignorance: a new view of learning and collaborative knowledge construction</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="2" column="2">Accepting that most design problems are characterized by a asymmetry of ignoranceo leads to a different view of learning. In these contexts, relevant knowledge, which needs to be drawn out of and synthesized from the perspectives of the contributors, does not exist a priori and cannot simply be passed on by those who have it to those who need it. Therefore, approaches are required that view learning as collaborative knowledge construction [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="41" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. This view is in sharp contrast to the teaching cultures of our schools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="42" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>], by which teaching is often a®tted into a mold in which a single, presumably omniscient teacher explicitly tells or shows presumably unknowing learners something they presumably know nothing abouto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="43" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. A critical challenge is to reformulate and reconceptualize this impoverished and misleading conception. Such a teaching culture may be realistic for the early grades in schools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="44" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>], but it is obviously inadequate for learning processes for which knowledge is distributed among many stakeholders and<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> athe answero does not exist or is not known. Historically, the roles of teacher and learner were associated with a person; in settings characterized by the symmetry of ignorance, however, being a teacher or being a learner is associated only with a speci®c context. aOf®cialo teachers should feel comfortable becoming learners in many situations. Most learning that takes place outside of a traditional (instructionist) classroom can be characterized as follows: humans are engaged in some activity (some action such as working, collaboratively solving a problem, or playing), they experience a breakdown (i.e. a piece of lacking knowledge, a misunderstanding about the consequences of some of their assumptions, etc.), and they re ̄ect about the breakdown. Sch Èn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="50" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] calls this re ̄ection-in-action. Because self- re ̄ection is dif®cult, a human coach, a design critic, or a teacher can help the learner to identify the breakdown situation and to provide task-relevant information for re ̄ection. In our own work, we have explored the possibility of using computational critics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="51" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>] to provide some of this support when humans are not present. Critics make argumentation serve design; this is, they support learners in their own activities. Engagement and support for self-directed learning is critical when learning becomes an integral part of lifeÐ driven by our desire and need to understand something, or to get something done instead of solving a problem given in a classroom setting. Self-directed learning de-emphasizes teaching as a process in which a teacher tells something to a passive learner. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>, students may actively engage in teacher-provided homework, but they are passive because their control over the course of study is limited.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> In many situations, it is advantageous to give students the opportunity to direct their own learning to encourage motivation and the opportunity to acquire new knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="58" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. Therefore, teaching should instead focus on mutual dialogs and joint knowledge construction that is enhanced by the creation, discussion, and evolution of artifacts. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 3</xref>, the teacher's role shifts from being the conduit through which information is transmitted into being a coordinator, facilitator, and coach. A symmetry of ignorance perspective on learning and collaborative knowledge construction takes this a step further. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 4</xref> characterizes learning situations in which no participant takes the role of a teacher. It provides a model for learning in a knowledge society that is built upon distributed cognition, articulate learners, peer-to-peer learning, and incremental enhancement of information spaces by a community of practice. Mutual competency supported by objects-to-think-with (externalization of ideas, concepts, and goals), leads to settings and opportunities for learning by all participants. Communication breakdowns are experienced because the stakeholders belong to different work cultures, which use different norms, symbols, and representations. Rather than seeing the symmetry of ignorance as an obstacle during design, it should be seen as an opportunity for creativity. Having different viewpoints helps stakeholders discover alternatives and uncover tacit aspects of the problems with which they have to cope.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="46" page="3" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="47" page="3" column="1">529</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62bz.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="49" page="3" column="1">Fig. 2. Passive learning.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62bz.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="55" page="3" column="1">Fig. 3. Self-directed learning.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_003.image_02.png" thmb="62bz.page_003.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="57" page="3" column="2">Fig. 4. Symmetry of ignoranceÐlearning by creating shared understanding.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">The clashing point of two subjects, two disciplines, two cultures ought to produce creative chaos. ÐC.P. Snow 2.1. Design</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="1" column="2">Design problems are ill-de®ned and complex and must be treated as a auniverse of oneo [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="19" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]. Although designers often make use of speci®c, well-established knowledge from mathematics, science, and engineering, they also create new knowledge in the course of understanding the unique aspects of their problems. In this regard, design problem solving is an interdisciplinary activity, bringing together multiple perspectives from different areas of expertise. The predominant activity in designing complex systems is that participants teach and instruct each other [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="20" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. Because complex problems require more knowledge than any single person possesses, communication and collaboration among all the involved stakeholders are necessary; for example, domain experts understand the practice, and system designers know the technology. Communication breakdowns are often experienced because stakeholders belong- ing to different cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="21" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] use different norms, symbols,<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> and representations. Rather than viewing this symmetry of ignorance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="27" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>] (or aasymmetry of knowledgea) as an obstacle during design, we view it as an opportunity for creativity. The different viewpoints help in discovering alternatives and can help uncover tacit aspects of problems. When a domain reaches a point at which the knowledge for skillful professional practice cannot be acquired in a decade, specialization will increase, collaboration will become a necessity, and practitioners will make increasing use of refer- ence aids, such as printed and computational media supporting external cognition. Design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="28" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>] is one such domain par excel- lence. Complexity in design arises from the need to synthesize different perspectives of a problem, the management of large amounts of information relevant to a design task, and understanding the design decisions that have determined the long- term evolution of a designed artifact. Design problems are wicked and ill-de®ned; they are moving targets that often do not have solutions but only have resolutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="29" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>], and the context in which these problems exist is by nature characterized by change, con ̄ict, and multiple stakeholders. In many cases, the best we can strive for is not consensus, but informed compromises emerging from the con ̄icting arguments and goals among stakeholders. To exploit the symmetry of ignorance requires putting owners of problems in charge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="30" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], which will promote direct and meaningful interaction involving people in decisions that affect them. In order to bring important perspectives to the process of design, all stakeholders in the process should be designers and co-developers, not just consumers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="31" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]. End-users, as owners of problems, bring special perspectives to collaborative design activities that are of special importance for the framing of problems. The asymmetry of ignoranceo requires creating spaces and places that serve as boundary objects where different cultures can meet. Boundary objects serve as externalizations that capture distinct domains of human knowledge, and they have the potential to lead to an increase in socially shared cognition and practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="32" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. The following two sections apply the concept of symmetry of ignorance to two speci®c and quite different domains: as it occurs in the context of high-functionality applications, and as it provides an alternative view to the classroom view of learning.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="1" column="2">0950-7051/00/$ - see front matter q 2000 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved. PII: S 0950-705 1(00)00065-4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="24" page="2" column="1">528</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="2" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="26" page="2" column="1">Fig. 1. Distributed expertise in HFAs.</caption>
      </region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="3" column="2">3. Social creativity</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="3" column="2">The power of the unaided, individual mind is highly over- ratedÐathe Renaissance scholar does not exist anymore.o Much of our intelligence and creativity results from exploiting the symmetry of ignorance as a source of power. Although creative individuals are often thought of as working in isolation, the role of interaction and collaboration with other individuals is critical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="63" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]. Creative activity grows out of the relationship between an individual and the world of his or her work, and out of the ties between an individual and other human beings.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="65" page="4" column="1">530</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="66" page="4" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="67" page="4" column="1">3.1. Individual creativity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="4" column="1">Empowering individuals requires conceptual frameworks and computational environments that will give domain designers more independence from computer specialists. Past L 3 D research has developed conceptual frameworks to empower individuals by developing domain-oriented design environments (DODEs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="68" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>], which make the computer invisible, and bringing tasks to the forefront in a variety of different domains. By being domain-oriented, they support (1) breakdowns, (2) critics, and (3) learning on demand.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="4" column="1">3.1.1. Breakdowns</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" page="4" column="1">A system supporting creativity will be suf®ciently open- ended and complex that users will encounter breakdowns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="71" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="72" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. The system must provide means for allowing users to understand, extricate themselves, and learn from breakdowns. Rather than attempting to eliminate trouble, the system should help users manage troubles and exploit breakdowns as opportunities rather than failures. As any professional designer knows, breakdownsÐalthough at times costly and painfulÐoffer unique opportunities for re ̄ection and learning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="73" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>]. Breakdowns can occur at many levelsÐfor example, at the tool level (e.g. computational environments do not provide the functionality needed), and at the domain level (e.g. domain designers are lacking or overlooking some important domain knowledge). To exploit these opportunities, we have developed conceptual frameworks and innovative systems to support critiquing and learning on demand.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" page="4" column="1">3.1.2. Critics</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="4" column="1">Critiquing systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="76" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>] offer advice and information by supporting re ̄ection-in-action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="77" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>], thereby allowing users to explore the contextualized argumentation and design rationale associated with their actions. By using design environments, designers create artifacts that serve as externalizations of their thoughts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="78" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. These artifacts can be critiqued by computational critics, increasing the aback-talko of the design situation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="79" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>].</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="81" page="4" column="1">3.1.3. Learning on demand</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="4" column="1">Learning on demand [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="82" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>] allows designers to explore contextualized information that is directly relevant to their breakdown situations. New learning environments are needed to circumvent the dif®cult problems of coverage (i.e. trying to teach people everything that they may need to know in the future) and obsolescence (i.e. trying to predict what speci®c knowledge someone will need in the future). Learning on demand is the only viable strategy in a world where we cannot learn everything. It is a promising approach to supporting creativity for the following reasons: (1) it contextualizes learning by allowing it to be integrated into work rather than relegating it to a separate phase; (2) it lets learners see for themselves the usefulness of new<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> knowledge for actual problem situations, thereby increasing the motivation for learning new skills and information; and (3) it makes new information relevant to the task at hand, thereby leading to better decision making, better products, and better performance.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="85" page="4" column="2">3.2. Lack of support for collaborative design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="4" column="2">In designing artifacts, designers rely on the expertise of others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="86" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] by referring to textbooks, standards, legal constraints, and especially previous design efforts. Complex design projects force large and heterogeneous groups to work together on projects over long periods of time. Infor- mation repositories that support such projects should include not only knowledge about the design process but also knowledge about artifacts of that processÐparts used in designing artifacts, subassemblies previously created by other design efforts, and rationale for previous design decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="87" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. Designers generally have a limited awareness and understanding of how the work of other designers within the projectÐor in similar projectsÐis relevant to their own part of the design task. The large and growing discrepancy between the amount of such relevant knowledge and the amount any one designer can possibly remem- ber imposes a limit on progress in design. Overcoming this limit is a central challenge for developers of systems that support collaborative creativity. Distributed cognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="88" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>] emphasizes that the heart of intelligent human performance is not the individual human mind but (1) groups of minds in interaction with each other or (2) minds in interactions with tools and artifacts. It is important to understand the fundamental difference between these two aspects of distributed cognition. When at work between the individual human mind and artifacts (such as memory systems), distributed cognition often functions well because the knowledge an individual needs is distributed between that individual's head and the world (for example: an address book, a folder system of e-mail messages, a ®le system). But in the case of interaction among a group of minds, the problem arises that a group has no headÐthere- fore externalizations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="89" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] are critically more important for social creativity. Externalizations: (1) create a record of our mental efforts, one that is aoutside uso rather than vaguely in memory; and (2) represent situations that can talk back to us and form the basis for critique and negotiation.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="91" page="4" column="2">3.3. Knowledge creation, integration and dissemination</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" page="4" column="2">To make social creativity a reality, we need new forms of knowledge creation, integration, and dissemination based on the observation that the scarce commodity in the information age is not information but human resources to attend to this information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="92" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>].</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="94" page="4" column="2">3.3.1. Knowledge externalization</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="4" column="2">One aspect of supporting organizations and groups in creating knowledge is the externalization of an individual's <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tacit knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="98" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]. This is important for three reasons: (1) externalization causes us to begin to move from vague mental conceptualizations of an idea to a more concrete representation; (2) externalization provides a means for others to interact with, react to, negotiate around, and build upon the articulated knowledge; and (3) externalization provides an opportunity to create a common language of understanding. The use of external representations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="99" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] serves to focus discussions upon relevant aspects of the framing and understanding of the problem being studied and allows stakeholders to engage in a aconversation with the materialso of the design problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="100" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]. The ability to interact with the problem at hand and to have that situation atalk backo is a crucial mode of design. A principal challenge for social creativity is to capture a signi®cant portion of the knowledge generated by work done within a community. Experiences with organizational memories and collaborative work have exposed two barriers to capturing information: (1) individuals must perceive a direct bene®t in contributing to organizational memory that is large enough to outweigh the effort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="101" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>]; and (2) the effort required to contribute to organizational memory must be minimal so it will not interfere with performing the work at hand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="102" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>].</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="96" page="5" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="97" page="5" column="1">531</outsider>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="5" column="1">3.3.2. Knowledge integration</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" page="5" column="1">The challenge in social creativity is to integrate the various perspectives emerging from the symmetry of ignorance among articulate stakeholders. By supporting the process of re ̄ection within a shared context de®ned by the task at hand, opportunities can emerge from enhancing the creation of shared understanding. This process melds the information that is collaboratively constructed into the problem-solving context, informing the process as well as the stakeholders and allowing them to participate from a more enriched and meaningful perspective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="105" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>]. It also enhances the quality of the designed artifact due to the synergy of interaction that draws out ideas and perspectives in a conversational manner. The resulting, richly contextualized information is available for future stakeholders to draw upon, informing them not only about the surface level of the design but also about the deeper characteristics behind the design. Collaborative constructions result in work products that are enriched by the multiple perspectives of the participants. The information repositories and organizational memories that are created in these ways are no longer very large, impenetrable awrite-onlyo stores, but are actively integrated into the work processes and social practices of the community that constructs them.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="107" page="5" column="1">3.3.3. Knowledge dissemination</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" page="5" column="1">Humans seldom (if at all) explore large re ̄ection spaces (e.g. thousands of pages of documentation, design rationales, argumentation, etc.) in the abstract [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="108" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>], but do so to obtain information in response to breakdowns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="109" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] occur- ring in their design activities. Making information relevant<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> to the task at hand (rather than drowning users in decontex- tualized information) and supporting the interaction of multiple perspectives and the various strengths that each stakeholder brings to the task allow collaborative explora- tion of the knowledge and shared understanding of the problem. The knowledge is made to serve the process of collaborative design by providing athe `right' information at the `right' time and in the `right' wayo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="111" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>].</region>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="113" page="5" column="2">3.4. Example 3 : dynamic information spaces supporting social creativity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="5" column="2">There is a growing interest in dynamic information spaces. From the early conceptions of hypertext [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="114" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>] to the current excitement regarding the World Wide Web and open source developments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="115" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>], the potential to capture and manipulate dynamic information spaces has existed. DynaSites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="116" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>] is an environment for creating and evolving collections of Web-based information spaces that are open-ended and grow through the contributions of users thereby supporting social creativity. Within L 3 D, we have used DynaSites to develop a shared, evolvable glossary of concepts. The basic idea is that concepts are not ®xed entities, put involve over time, especially in work groups characterized by a symmetry of ignorance among the parti- cipating stakeholders. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 5</xref> illustrates this for the concept of abreakdownso (readers are encouraged to explore the glossary system at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://Seed.cs.colorado.edu/dynagloss." id="118">http://Seed.cs.colorado.edu/dynagloss.</ext-link> MakeGlossaryPage.fcgi). Another application of DynaSite in support of social creativity is a Virtual Library system developed in collaboration with a high school for collecting and sharing links to World Wide Web sites. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 6</xref> illustrates the library in action, which is built on top of the DynaSites substrate. The Virtual Library provides Workspaces for making notes and collecting and annotating stack items that can be grouped into Reserves. An instructor, for example, might create a reserve for an American Literature assignment containing sites about famous American authors (the DynaSites Virtual Library can be found at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://robin.bvsd.k12.co.us/" id="120">http://robin.bvsd.k12.co.us/</ext-link> virtlib/).</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="122" page="5" column="2">4. Meta-design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" page="5" column="2">A Chinese proverb says: aIf you give a person a ®sh, you provide food for a dayÐif you teach someone to ®sh, they will have food for a lifetime.o This saying can be extended by arguing that aif we can provide someone with the knowledge, the skill, and the tools for making a ®shing rod, we can feed the whole community.o Meta-design characterizes activities, processes, and objectives to create new media and environments that allow users to act as designers and be creative. This can be compared with the objective in art that focuses on the artist as the facilitator of the creative experience for users. In our work, we have explored a set of concepts and ideas for meta-design that are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 7</xref>.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> One of the fundamental problems of system design is to write software for millions of users (at design time; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 8</xref>), while making it work as if it were designed for each individual user (who is known only at use time). The need to support a broad class of different users leads to high- functionality applications with all their associated possibilities and problems. A feasible design strategy to support users in their own domain of knowledge is that system designers make assumptions about classes of users and sets of tasks in which they want to engageÐa design methodology leading to domain-oriented systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="130" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. An important objective of meta-design is that design spaces is created at design time provide users at use time with interesting and varied design possibilities. If the system is constantly adapting or is being adapted to users, use time becomes a different kind of design time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="131" class="deo:Reference">35</xref>]. The need for<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> meta-design is founded on the observation that design problems in the real world require open systems that users can modify and evolve. Because problems cannot be completely anticipated at design time (when the system is developed), users at use time will discover mismatches between their problems and the support that a system provides. A necessary, but not suf®cient condition for meta-design is that software systems must have features that permit users to create customizations and extensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="133" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>].</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="125" page="6" column="1">532</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="126" page="6" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_006.image_04.png" thmb="62bz.page_006.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="128" page="6" column="1">Fig. 5. DynaGlossÐa DynaSite environment supporting collaboratively evolved concept spaces.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="135" page="6" column="2">4.1. Example 4 : the envisionment and discovery collaboratory</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156" page="6" column="2">The Envisionment and Discovery Collaboratory (EDC) [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="136" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>] is a meta-design effort that acknowledges the asymmetry of ignoranceo as a fundamental design constraint. It<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> supports social creativity by empowering stakeholders to act as designersÐallowing them to create shared understanding, to contextualize information to the task at hand, and to create objects-to-think-with in collaborative design activities. The EDC framework (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cs.colorado.edu/" id="142">http://www.cs.colorado.edu/</ext-link> ~l3d/systems/EDC/) is applicable to different domains, but our initial effort has focused on the domains of urban planning and decision making, speci®cally in transportation planning and community development. The EDC is a meta-design approach with the goal of creating environments that are immersive and emergent.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> An immersive environment allows stakeholders to become deeply engaged in problem solving in the context of information, action, re ̄ection, and collaborations relevant to the situation, whereas an emergent environment addresses the need for this context to grow and evolve based on ongoing problem-solving activities. These intertwined concepts require the EDC to support stakeholders in (1) creating and capturing knowledge in the context of collaborative design activities; (2) sustaining the timeliness and utility of evolving information; (3) articulating their own knowledge in a form that other people can understand; (4)<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> enhancing existing knowledge with new knowledge; and (5) creating tools that help stakeholders think, and help analyze their constructions and artifacts. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9" id="151" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 9</xref> shows the current realization of the EDC environment supporting aaround-the-tableo interaction and contex- tualizing information in design activities. Individuals using the EDC convene around a computationally enhanced table, shown in the center of the ®gure. This table serves as the action space for the EDC. Currently realized as a touch- sensitive surface, the action space allows users to manipulate the computational simulation projected on the surface by interacting with the physical objects placed on the table. The table is  ̄anked by a second computer that drives the vertical touch-sensitive computational whiteboard serving as the EDC's re ̄ection space. In the ®gure, users are using the re ̄ection space to ®ll out a Web-based transportation survey that provides in part the information base associated with the model being constructed in the action space. The re ̄ection and action spaces are connected by communication between the two computers using the Web as a medium. The entire physical space, through the immersion of people within the representations of the problem-solving task, creates a prototype of an integrated, socio-technical<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> human±computer system. The open nature of the EDC supports integration of new constructions and differing perspectives into the environment. The dissemination of constructed knowledge is afforded through the EDC's WWW linkages between the action and re ̄ection spaces. These constructions can be shared in a distributed manner just as distributed information can be integrated through the re ̄ection space. The EDC represents a theory-based architecture and process model with three layers: (1) a domain-independent framework and architecture for integrated physical and computational environments that support creating shared understanding through collaborative design; (2) application domains, in which the domain-independent architecture is realized for a speci®c class of problems (for example, the application domain discussed in Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="155" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>] addresses decision problems of urban planning, speci®cally for transportation systems); and (3) speci®c applications created to contextualize an application domain to a concrete situation, such as transportation planning in the city of Boulder. The asymmetry of ignoranceo among the stakeholders in the EDC serves as a source for social creativity by providing users with many opportunities to construct their own situations and have control in the description of a problem. For example: neighbors can change the model and see how their changes affect the transportation system. They can place new buses along a bus route to increase bus frequency along the route; or they can move bus stops, change the bus route by moving appropriate pieces, and modify the behavior of the buses or traf®c lights. In the course of framing and solving their problems, neighbors may ®nd that the existing environment does not model some situations in which they are interested. The meta-design allows stakeholders to extend the system to meet the needs of unforeseen situations.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="138" page="7" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="139" page="7" column="1">533</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_007.image_05.png" thmb="62bz.page_007.image_05-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="141" page="7" column="1">Fig. 6. The DynaSites Virtual Library.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_007.image_06.png" thmb="62bz.page_007.image_06-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="145" page="7" column="1">Fig. 7. Concepts of meta-design.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="147" page="8" column="1">534</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="148" page="8" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_008.image_07.png" thmb="62bz.page_008.image_07-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="150" page="8" column="1">Fig. 8. Design and use time.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F9">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62bz.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="154" page="8" column="1">Fig. 9. The current prototype of the EDC.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="157" page="9" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="158" page="9" column="1">535</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F10">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="159" page="9" column="1">Fig. 10. Beyond binary choices.</caption>
          </region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="160" page="9" column="1">4.1.1. Computational substrates embedded in the EDC</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" page="9" column="1">To exploit the symmetry of ignorance and to support social creativity, the EDC incorporates a variety of computational mechanisms and substrates. The action space of the EDC is built using AgentSheets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="161" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>], a software environment for creating simulations and domain-oriented environments. AgentSheets applications include a collec- tion of autonomous computational processes, called agents, that are comprised of a look (their on-screen representation), and a programmed behavior. Agents in AgentSheets are programmed in Visual AgenTalk, a programming environment suitable for end-user programmers. The re ̄ection space in EDC is supported by DynaSites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="162" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>], which allows users to create extensible, Web-based information spaces (see Example 3 ). DynaSites provides computational support for collaborative working, learning, and knowledge construction by supporting these activities in a way that they can grow and be shaped over time by the people who use them. DynaSites information spaces are dynamic because their pages are built at use time (from a database) whereas typical Web sites are staticÐtheir links and displays are determined at design time. They differ from most Web sites because they are dynamic and evolvable by users.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="164" page="9" column="1">5. Assessment</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="170" page="9" column="1">The environments presented in this paper represent expli- cit attempts to instantiate and evaluate the adequacy and usefulness of a framework grounded in the concepts of symmetry of ignorance, social creativity, and meta-design. We live in a world where problems often require the collaboration of stakeholders from different communities, seeing the world from their individual perspectives, having their own background knowledge and their cognitive, computational and physical tools and artifacts. Exploiting the symmetry of ignorance as a source of power requires not only a willingness to talk to collaborators, but also externalizations that allow people to think and argue about and that help them to create incrementally a shared understanding of the design problem. An important technical challenge for social creativity is to capture the informal, situated problem-solving episodes that real people generate in solving real problems, which are <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> dif®cult for formal processes to anticipate or to capture. An important non-technical challenge for social creativity is to take motivation seriously. There must be an incentive to create social capital by rewarding stakeholders to be good citizens by contributing and receiving knowledge as a member of a community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="166" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>]. A necessary, but not suf®cient condition for meta-design is that software systems must have advanced features (developed at design time; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 8</xref>) that permit complex customizations and extensions by power users and local developers at use time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="168" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>]. Meta-design is supported by the seeding, evolutionary growth, reseeding model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="169" class="deo:Reference">39</xref>]. This process model allows and encourages designers to explicitly underdesign and underprescribe at design time and provide constructs and environments (e.g. Visual AgenTalk and DynaSites, mentioned above) for design support and situated interpretations and actions at use time. In a closed system, it is dif®cult or impossible for users to change the system to deal with new and unforeseen situations. System developers control additions and modi®cations, and when they are no longer present, the system cannot handle a new situation. This implies that users have to work around or outside such a closed system (or perhaps abandon the system altogether) when they encounter an unexpected situation.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="171" page="9" column="2">5.1. Consumers and designers</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="183" page="9" column="2">Meta-design is design for designers, not for consumers. By arguing for the desirability for humans to be designers [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="172" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>], it should be stated explicitly that there is nothing wrong with being a consumer. We can learn and enjoy many things in a consumer role (e.g. listening to a lecture, watching a tennis match, or attending a concert). It is a mistake to assume that being a consumer or being a designer has to be a binary choice. It is rather a continuum ranging from passive consumer, to active consumer, to end-user, to user, to power user [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="173" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>], to domain designer, to medium designer, all the way to meta-designer (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10" id="174" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 10</xref>, illustrat- ing this ®ner grain division of labor among software users). Problems occur when someone wants to be a designer but is forced to be a consumer, and when being a consumer becomes a universal habit and mindset that dominates a human life completely. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11" id="175" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 11</xref> shows the exploitation of the meta-design support<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> built into Microsoft Word with macros. The ®gure shows two macros: atranspose,o which transposes two characters, and aunwrap,o which unwraps text as shown in the screen image (the same text appears in two forms: in the top half as wrapped text and in the bottom half after the application of the macro in the unwrapped form). As argued above, although end-user programming and modi®cation components are necessary for meta-design environments, they by themselves are far from suf®cient. Our empirical investigations have shown that few users take advantage of the end-user modi®ability components provided by environments such as Microsoft Word, and even fewer users engage in exchan- ging their extensions with each others. Other communities (such as the open source code community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="181" class="deo:Reference">40</xref>] and Web-based community of practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="182" class="deo:Reference">41</xref>]) are better success examples to be analyzed for meta-design and social creativity. Our empirical observations and studies have clearly demonstrated that meta-design requires more than just technical facilities. The possibility of extending open systems will not take place within the ®rst few days or weeks of using them, but will require the long-term use of a system by owners of problems engaged in the cultivation of a rich repertoire of personally and socially meaningful artifacts. For example, we do not expect all users to become power users or local developers or to be interested in making radi- cal changes to the system. Their contributions will depend on the perceived bene®t of contributing, which involves the effort needed to make changes and the utility received for effecting changes.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="177" page="10" column="1">536</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="178" page="10" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F11">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bz.page_010.image_09.png" thmb="62bz.page_010.image_09-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="180" page="10" column="1">Fig. 11. Use of meta-design components in Microsoft Word.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="184" page="10" column="2">6. Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="185" page="10" column="2">Failing to make computation accessible with reasonable cognitive costs to all people will reduce people's creativity. Furthermore, it will prevent the emergence of computational environments that need to evolve through the active contributions from their users. The three concepts discussed in this paper (symmetry of ignorance, social creativity, and meta-design) provide a conceptual framework for understanding creativity and cognition and for fostering creativity in communities. The paper illustrated the guidance provided by and application of this framework to a number of systems that support social creativity by exploiting the symmetry of ignorance. These systems enhance conversations around shared, mutually understandable artifacts, and they allow stakeholders to learn with and from each other. Such meta-design environments allow stakeholders to act as designers, making it possible to deal with new requirements as they emerge during development, and thereby contributing to the integration of problem framing and problem solving as an important source for social creativity.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="186" page="10" column="2">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="190" page="10" column="2">The author thanks all the members of the L 3 D Center for their numerous contributions to this research. Special thanks to Ernie Arias, Hal Eden, Eric Scharff and Andy Gorman, who have been the major developers of the EDC, and to <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Jonathan Ostwald who has been the major developer of the DynaSite substrate. The research was supported by: (1) the National Science Foundation, grants REC-9631396 and IRI- 9711951; (2) Software Research Associates, Tokyo, Japan; and (3) PFU, Tokyo, Japan.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="188" page="11" column="1">G. Fischer / Knowledge-Based Systems 13 (2000) 527±537</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="189" page="11" column="1">537</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="191" page="11" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="11" column="1">[1] M. Boden, The Creative Mind: Myths &amp; Mechanisms, Basic Books, New York, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="11" column="1">[2] H. Gardner, Creating Minds, Basic Books, New York, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="11" column="1">[3] D.A. Sch Èn, The Re ̄ective Practitioner: How Professionals Think in Action, Basic Books, New York, 1983.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="11" column="1">[4] J. Greenbaum, M. Kyng (Eds.), Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, NJ, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="11" column="1">[5] C.P. Snow, The Two Cultures, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="11" column="1">[6] H. Rittel, Second-generation design methods, in: N. Cross (Ed.), Developments in Design Methodology, Wiley, New York, 1984, pp. 317±327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="11" column="1">[7] H.A. Simon, The Sciences of the Arti®cial, 3rd ed., The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="11" column="1">[8] E.G. Arias, Designing in a Design Community: Insights and Challenges, Proceedings of DIS'95 Symposium on Designing Interactive Systems: Processes, Practices, Methods, &amp; Techniques, 1995, pp. 259±263.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="11" column="1">[9] G. Fischer, Putting the owners of problems in charge with domain- oriented design environments, in: D. Gilmore, R. Winder, F. Detienne (Eds.), User-Centered Requirements for Software Engineering Environments, Springer, Heidelberg, 1994, pp. 297±306.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="11" column="1">[10] G. Fischer, Beyond `couch potatoes': from consumers to designers, in: IEEE (Ed.), Asia-Paci®c Computer and Human Interaction, APCHI'98, IEEE Computer Society, Silver Springs, MD, 1998, pp. 2±9.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="11" column="1">[11] L.B. Resnick, J.M. Levine, S.D. Teasley (Eds.), Perspectives on Socially Shared Cognition American Psychological Association, Washington, DC, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="11" column="1">[12] G. Fischer, User Modeling in Human±Computer Interaction, User Modeling and User-Adapted Interaction, Kluwer Academic, Dordrecht, 2000 (in press).</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="11" column="1">[13] M. Scardamalia, C. Bereiter, Computer support for knowledge- building communities, Journal of the Learning Sciences 3 (3) (1994) 265±283 (available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://carbon.cudenver.edu/" id="204">http://carbon.cudenver.edu/</ext-link>~bwilson/ building.html).</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="11" column="1">[14] I. Illich, Deschooling Society, Harper and Row, New York, 1971.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="11" column="1">[15] J. Bruner, The Culture of Education, Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA, 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="11" column="1">[16] E.D. Hirsch Jr., The Schools We Need And Why We Don't Have Them, First ed., Doubleday, New York, 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="11" column="1">[17] G. Fischer, K. Nakakoji, J. Ostwald, G. Stahl, T. Sumner, Embedding critics in design environments, in: M.T. Maybury, W. Wahlster (Eds.), Readings in Intelligent User Interfaces, Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco, CA, 1998, pp. 537±561.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="11" column="1">[18] G. Fischer, Supporting learning on demand with design environments, in: L. Birnbaum (Ed.), International Conference on the Learning Sciences (Evanston, IL), Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education, 1991, pp. 165±172.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="11" column="2">[19] D.C. Engelbart, Toward augmenting the human intellect and boosting our collective IQ, Communications of the ACM 38 (8) (1995) 30±33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" page="11" column="2">[20] G. Fischer, Domain-oriented design environments, Automated Software Engineering 1 (2) (1994) 177±203.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="11" column="2">[21] G. Fischer, Turning breakdowns into opportunities for creativity, Knowledge-Based Systems (Special Issue on Creativity and Cognition) 7 (4) (1994) 221±232.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="11" column="2">[22] K.R. Popper, Conjectures and Refutations, Harper &amp; Row and Hagerstown, New York, San Francisco, London, 1965.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="11" column="2">[23] H. Petroski, To Engineer Is Human: The Role of Failure in Successful Design, St. Martin's Press, New York, 1985.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="11" column="2">[24] P. Galegher, R. Kraut, C. Egido (Eds.), Intellectual Teamwork Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, NJ, 1990.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" page="11" column="2">[25] D.A. Norman, Things That Make Us Smart, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="11" column="2">[26] M. Polanyi, The Tacit Dimension, Doubleday, Garden City, NY, 1966.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="11" column="2">[27] J. Grudin, Groupware and social dynamics: eight challenges for developers, Communications of the ACM 37 (1) (1994) 92±105.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" page="11" column="2">[28] J.M. Carroll, M.B. Rosson, Paradox of the active user, in: J.M. Carroll (Ed.), Interfacing Thought: Cognitive Aspects of Human±Computer Interaction, The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1987, pp. 80±111.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="11" column="2">[29] J.S. Brown, P. Duguid, S. Haviland, Toward informed participation: six scenarios in search of democracy in the information age, The Aspen Institute Quarterly 6 (4) (1994) 49±73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="11" column="2">[30] T.P. Moran, J.M. Carroll (Eds.), Design Rationale: Concepts, Techniques, and Use Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, NJ, 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="11" column="2">[31] G. Fischer, K. Nakakoji, J. Ostwald, G. Stahl, T. Sumner, Embedding critics in design environments, in: M.T. Maybury, W. Wahlster (Eds.), Readings in Intelligent User Interfaces, Morgan Kaufmann, Los Altos, CA, 1998, pp. 537±559.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" page="11" column="2">[32] V. Bush, As we may think, Atlantic Monthly 176 (1) (1945) 101±108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" page="11" column="2">[33] T. O'Reilly, Lessons from open source software development, Communications of the ACM 42 (4) (1999) 33±37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" page="11" column="2">[34] J. Ostwald, DynaSites, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cs.colorado.edu/" id="227">http://www.cs.colorado.edu/</ext-link>~ostwald/ dynasites.html, 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="11" column="2">[35] A. Henderson, M. Kyng, There's no place like home: continuing design in use, in: J. Greenbaum, M. Kyng (Eds.), Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems, Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, NJ, 1991, pp. 219±240.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" page="11" column="2">[36] E.G. Arias, H. Eden, G. Fischer, A. Gorman, E. Scharff, Transcending the individual human mindÐcreating shared understanding through collaborative design, Transactions on Computer Human Interaction (2000) (in press; available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cs.colorado.edu/" id="230">http://www.cs.colorado.edu/</ext-link>~gerhard/ papers/tochi99.pdf).</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" page="11" column="2">[37] A. Repenning, AgentSheets, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.agentsheets.com/," id="232">http://www.agentsheets.com/,</ext-link> 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" page="11" column="2">[38] B.A. Nardi, A Small Matter of Programming, The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" page="11" column="2">[39] G. Fischer, Seeding, evolutionary growth and reseeding: constructing, capturing and evolving knowledge in domain-oriented design environments, Automated Software Engineering 5 (4) (1998) 447±464 (available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cs.colorado.edu/" id="235">http://www.cs.colorado.edu/</ext-link>~gerhard/papers/®nal- journal-sept30-97.pdf).</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" page="11" column="2">[40] E.S. Raymond, The Cathedral and the Bazaar, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www" id="237">http://www</ext-link>. tuxedo.org/~esr/writings/, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" page="11" column="2">[41] Expert-Exchange, 2000. At <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.experts-exchange.com" id="239">http://www.experts-exchange.com</ext-link>.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" page="11" column="2">[42] G. Fischer, E. Scharff, Learning technologies in support of self-directed learning, Journal of Interactive Media in Education 1998 (4) (1998) (available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www-jime.open.ac.uk/98/4)." id="241">http://www-jime.open.ac.uk/98/4).</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" page="11" column="2">[43] I. Illich, Tools for Conviviality, Harper and Row, New York, 1973.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="213" page="11" column="2">2.2.1. High-functionality applications (HFA)</h3>
        </section>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
