<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>288a495265ef2c38ce00e982680fc2f7498b99f1261b16fcb7fdee32beb3f887</job>
    <base_name>62gl</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-92160-8_28">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-33837-7</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Features Need Stories</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Sidney C. Bailin</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible">Knowledge Evolution, Inc., 1221 Connecticut Ave. NW, STE 3B, Washington DC 20036 , <email id="3">sbailin@kevol.com</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">We present an extension of the notion of feature models. An ontology of stories clarifies the meaning of potentially ambiguous features in situations where there is no unified domain model, and where candidates for reuse have varied provenance.</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">Keywords. features, domain model, story, ontology, evaluation.</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="15">S.H. Edwards</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="16">G. Kulczycki (Eds.): ICSR</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="17">LNCS</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="18">pp. 51–</name>
          <aff id="19">64</aff>
          <aff id="20">2009</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="21">. © Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg</name>
          <aff id="22">2009</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23">through an engineering analysis involving goals, priorities, and tradeoffs. Thus, knowledge reuse is closely related to the disciplines of engineering analysis. Such situations, however, often invite reuse not just of knowledge but of actual software, for the simple reason that the technical approaches are realized in software. Thus, there is a deep connection between software reuse and the process of engineering analysis—evaluating alternative technologies to meet a set of requirements. Conversely, any software reuse decision ought to involve an evaluation of alternatives. At a minimum, the question of make vs. buy (develop vs. reuse) should be addressed. Beyond that, if there are multiple candidates for reuse, or multiple features that may or may not be selected, then a systematic evaluation of tradeoffs ought to occur. But real-world reuse, lying somewhere between systematic and opportunistic, illustrates a limitation of feature models. Because it occurs without a unified domain model, the features considered in the tradeoff studies are not necessarily comparable from product to product, let alone from study to study. There is no controlled vocabulary with which to describe and evaluate the alternative solutions.</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1 Introduction</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">1.1 Features and Engineering Analysis</h2>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="24" page="2" column="1">1.2 Features and Ontologies</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="2" column="1">In a previous paper we described the use of ontologies to represent KAPTUR-style domain models: problems, alternatives solutions, their features, rationales, and tradeoffs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="25" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. We noted that ontology mismatches arise when there are many parochial models of a domain rather than one unified model, and we described a process of progressive resolution of mismatches. In the LIBRA method, this process of resolving models-in-conflict is viewed as the very essence of reuse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="26" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>]. Aspects of the parochial contexts can be formalized to provide enriched semantics for their respective feature sets. Using ontologies, which are intrinsically open-ended, we can add concepts for disambiguating features that have slightly different meanings in different contexts (see Section 4.1). But there is a point of diminishing returns at which formalization may not be appropriate, at least not until the domain reaches a certain level of maturity. The appropriate medium for capturing this context is, in such cases, narrative.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="2" column="1">1.3 What is a Story?</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" page="2" column="1">By story we mean a communication that speaks of characters responding to some situation. The characters need not be people; they can be organizations, systems, computers, software programs or even designs. Something about the initial situation is unstable and causes the characters to act. The actions change the situation, and what follows is a succession of situations requiring action, and actions taken in response. This is the forward movement of the story. The emphasis is on causation, or, from another point of view, rationale. Stories are an especially effective mode of communication because they draw the reader into the story world. This only happens, of course, if what is at stake for the characters is also a concern for the reader. When this happens, the immersive nature of the story and its forward movement give the communication an urgency and sense of reality that ordinary communications lack.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" page="1" column="1">This paper argues that feature models, while an essential tool for reuse in any domain, are not in themselves sufficient for the capture and communication of knowledge about variability. We argue that features carry a relatively small amount of semantics, if any at all, and that much of the intended semantics remain implicit in naming conventions, or tacit in experience, or undocumented in hearsay. We suggest that the missing semantics, addressing fine-grained questions of context, interface, function, performance, and rationale, can be usefully conveyed through stories attached to features. By story we mean something relatively specific, not simply a chunk of text. There are several attributes that make something a story, but one of the key attributes is that of being situated. In a story, context is (almost) everything. Examples of the kinds of stories we are looking for already exist in the user feedback sections of many web-based product catalogues. User feedback contributions, despite their unstructured form, tend to be highly situated and, thus, are often good examples of the notion of story we are advocating. Consumer assistance product reviews, on the other hand, are often much less situated; for this reason, they often fall short both in their sense of urgency and in the amount of crucial background information they provide. We are not simply advocating for stories. That is an argument we have made elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="8" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. Nor are we arguing here for a particular kind of feature model: that, too, we have addressed elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="9" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. In this paper we are specifically interested in the way in which stories can be used systematically to enrich the semantics of a feature model. At the core of this vision lies interplay between the formal and the informal. The bulk of the paper consists of a case study that involved the evaluation of alternative technologies for a particular function within a complex system of systems. We argue in Section 1.1 that the evaluation of alternative candidates is the essence of the reuse process. Our goal is not, however, to present a methodology for trade studies, but rather to explore the kind of contextual information that is necessary in order to perform such evaluations, and to draw conclusions from this about the structure and contents of domain models. Our conclusions are applicable to virtually any domain modeling method.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" page="1" column="1">Many opportunities for reuse occur in situations lacking a well-developed domain model, and in which the resources required for a full-scale domain analysis (not just money but also time) are unavailable. Such opportunities cannot take advantage of feature-based reuse methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="12" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] and product-line architectures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="13" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. Yet they are far more systematic than what is often termed opportunistic reuse. We will call this real-world reuse. These situations are often opportunities for knowledge reuse: the primary decision is to choose an existing, well-defined technical approach to solve a problem. The technical approach is typically selected</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="2" column="1">2 Case Study</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="2" column="1">We illustrate our arguments with a real case study that involved selecting software for use in a large, complex system of systems (SoS). The primary tradeoff was a make vs. buy decision; but, as we shall see, each of the alternatives involves some form of reuse. Salient features of the SoS, which will remain anonymous in this paper, include life-critical functions, high cost, and a complex network of stakeholders including multiple engineering and development organizations. The application we consider here is a relatively small part of the SoS, responsible for transmitting large volumes of structured data between two major SoS components. The data stream contains sequences of fields in many different data types and occurring with different frequencies. Different fields originate from <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> different sources, and are routed to other component systems belonging to different stakeholders. This is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>. We called this a compression trade study because the primary challenge is to transmit the data efficiently by compressing it into a compact form, then decompressing it upon receipt.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">System A</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">System B</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62gl.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62gl.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="37" page="3" column="1">Fig. 1. A data transmission application serves as a case study.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="3" column="1">2.1 Evaluation Criteria <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> shows the criteria used to evaluate the alternative compression technologies.</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> shows the criteria used to evaluate the alternative compression technologies.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Criterion Description Encoding / decoding speed Speed at which messages can be encoded into their compressed format and then decoded by the receiving end Encoding / decoding software Cost of acquiring and maintaining the software that performs the cost encoding and decoding Transmission speed Direct measure of the size of the compressed messages, which must be averaged over the likely variations in message types and content Interoperability Availability of the proposed encoding method on different systems, and the expected level of confidence that the implementations on different systems are compatible Learning curve / programming Complexity of an encoding method has a direct impact on the cost of complexity any project-developed software implementing the method, but it may also limit the range of available COTS implementations, and lessen confidence that the implementations are correct Maturity Assessed both temporally (how long the method has been in existence) and spatially (how widely it has been used) Tool availability Availability of software to perform the selected functions Tool reliability The level of confidence that the tool will perform its functions continuously and correctly, where continuity includes the traditional systems engineering notion of availability, while correctness refers to the satisfaction of functional and performance requirements (throughput/response time) Evolvability Includes the ability of the selected technology to handle evolution in the data stream contents, and the potential impact of evolution in the compression method itself (as in the evolution of standards) Risk General unknowns</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="43" page="3" column="1">Table 1. Evaluation criteria used in the case study.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="3" column="1">The evaluation criteria are not mutually independent, but each has a unique emphasis that warrants its being considered explicitly.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="46" page="4" column="1">2.2 Alternatives Considered <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> identifies the alternative methods that were evaluated:</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> identifies the alternative methods that were evaluated:</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Solution Description Custom packing maps The format of the data stream messages is defined explicitly in terms of the admissible fields, their sequencing, and their respective length Abstract Syntax Notation ASN.1 is an international standard for describing structured data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="49" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>]; (ASN.1) Packed Encoding Rules the PER is part of the standard that provides for a compact binary (PER) encoding of such data Fast Infoset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="50" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] An international standard for binary encoding of data represented in the Extensible Markup Language (XML) Lempel-Ziv (LZ) compression A family of compression technique used by tools such as WinZip [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="51" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] and Gzip Efficient XML Interchange An emerging recommendation of the World-Wide Web Consortium (EXI) (W3C) for binary encoding of XML data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="52" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="54" page="4" column="1">Table 2. Alternative solutions considered in the case study.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" page="4" column="1">These alternatives represent the gamut from the conventional approach for such systems as previously developed (custom packing maps), through international standards (ASN.1 and Fast Infoset) and widely used file compression techniques (LZ), to a recent W3C recommendation for binary XML transfers (EXI). The alternatives vary significantly in their levels of maturity, but there is a logic to their consideration. The custom packing map approach is the organization’s legacy approach for this type of system. ASN.1 and XML are the two primary standards for expressing structured data outside of programming and formal specification languages. There are several standard encodings for ASN.1, but PER is the primary encoding for efficient binary data transfer. Similarly, Fast Infoset is a current standard for binary encoding of XML, while EXI is an emerging standard for the same purpose, whose definition has itself taken into account many of the alternatives. Finally, LZ compression is widely used in a variety of tools familiar to the engineers responsible for designing and implementing the system. Further complicating the study is the role of another international standard that would govern the way in which a custom packing map would be specified. To some extent this mitigates the “custom” nature of this alternative (as does the fact that it, alone among the alternatives, draws heavily from the organization’s past experience).</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="4" column="1">3 Reuse in the Case Study</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="4" column="1">The case study does not sound like a typical reuse scenario. There is no repository of reusable components, and no domain model from which systems can be instantiated through a selection of appropriate features. Nevertheless, the case study illustrates what we are calling real world reuse. It is an example of reuse because each of the alternative solutions is a form of reuse. This is clear in the case of the off-the-shelf candidates; perhaps less obvious, but equally true, is reuse in the case of the custom packing map, which is the approach the organization had used in all previous systems. At the very least, if a custom packing map were to be adopted, fundamental design concepts from prior systems would be reused; more likely, there would be adaptation of existing source code as well. Why, then, does the case study appear to be more like a conventional engineering design analysis than a case of reuse? One reason is that the evaluation was performed not at the level of functionally equivalent alternatives (for example, alternative implementations of the ASN.1 PER), but rather at the level of alternative functional approaches. Formally, however, this is no different from conventional reuse: we have a specification at a certain level of abstraction, and the candidates for reuse are alternative realizations of the specification. In this case, we lack a unified feature model for characterizing the alternative solutions. But the evaluation criteria serve, in effect, as features. Conversely, in a feature-based reuse process, the features <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> may be considered evaluation criteria in the selection of a solution. Viewed in this way, every tradeoff analysis creates a kind of domain model, but each model is usually unique to the analysis; they are not easily compared, which makes it difficult to base decisions on prior analyses that were performed in different contexts.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="5" column="1">3.1 Features with Values</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="5" column="1">One objection to viewing evaluation criteria as features is that the criteria are attributes with values, while features are often viewed as things to be selected, i.e., the candidate either has the feature or it does not. This effectively restricts features to attributes with values in a finite enumeration set (such as Boolean- valued attributes). It is an arbitrary limitation that dispenses with information essential to specifying or evaluating reusability. For example, an efficiency feature could take values in an enumeration set consisting of the time- complexity classes such as Logarithmic, Linear, Polynomial, etc. But it might equally well take the form of more detailed testing results that graph specific response times against different inputs. The studies we consulted follow the latter approach—rightly so, because they tested different classes and distributions of input. The efficiency feature carries implicit semantics that must be made explicit for proper comprehension.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="61" page="5" column="1">4 Integrating Multiple Feature Models</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="5" column="1">Having identified the alternative solutions and the criteria for evaluating them, we studied the literature to see what was already known. There was a substantial body of prior work on just this problem, but none of the studies we found used exactly the same set of candidate solutions and none used exactly the same evaluation criteria. The studies varied in their scope, in the level of rigor, and in the detailed definition of features (especially performance features). Not surprisingly, the studies also differed from each other in their conclusions. As an example, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref> lists the criteria from a study by Qing&amp;Adams along with their respective priorities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="63" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>].</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Criterion Priority High Compression Ratio Required Low Processing Overhead Required No Semantic Ambiguity Required 3rd Party API Support Desirable</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="66" page="5" column="1">Table 3. Evaluation criteria considered by Qing&amp;Adams.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="5" column="1">These criteria resemble ours but are somewhat different. High compression rate is effectively synonymous with our transmission speed criterion, while low processing overhead corresponds to our encode/decode speed. We implicitly required that all the candidates be semantically unambiguous, but we did not specify this explicitly. Finally, their 3rd party API support could facilitate our interoperability, and could improve our tool availability; but their criterion is more specific and does not necessarily imply ours. The alternative solutions considered by Qing&amp;Adams are also similar but not identical to our set, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Table 4</xref>. Of the four evaluation criteria in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>, the latter two (no semantic ambiguity and 3 rd part API support) were quickly disposed of as being satisfied by all candidates, leaving compression ratio and processing overhead as the focus of the study. Most of the other studies focused on these two criteria, as well. The meaning of the terms, however, varied from study to study.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Solution Description Gzip and Bzip Bzip is an alternative compression algorithm using Burrows- Wheeler methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="70" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>] wbXML WAP Binary XML, developed by the Open Mobile Alliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="71" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Solution Description ASN.1 Apparently the PER encoding although this is not clear wbXML + Zip wbXML encoding followed by Gzip or Bzip compression ASN.1 + Zip ASN.1 encoding followed by Gzip or Bzip XML Binary Optimized W3C recommendation dating from 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="73" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>] Packaging (XOP): Message Transmission W3C recommendation for binary message transmission especially in Optimization Mechanism the context of the Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="74" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] (MTOM) XMill Open source XML compressor that claims better performance than (for example) Gzip [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="75" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="77" page="6" column="1">Table 4. Candidate solutions considered by Qing&amp;Adams.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="6" column="1">Now we look at some of the criteria used by the EXI committee. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Table 5</xref> shows 7 out of the 21 criteria they applied: those that correspond or are closely related to our criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="79" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>].</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Criterion Description Compactness Amount of compression a particular format achieves when encoding data model items. Forward compatibility Supports the evolution of data models and allows corresponding implementation of layered standards. Implementation cost How much time does it take for a solitary programmer to implement sufficiently robust processing of the format (the so-called Desperate Perl Hacker measure). Platform neutrality Not significantly more optimal for processing on some computing platforms or architectures than on others Processing efficiency Speed at which a new format can be generated and/or consumed for processing. It covers serialization, parsing and data binding. Transport independence Only assumptions of transport service are "error-free and ordered delivery of messages without any arbitrary restrictions on the message length". Widespread adoption Has been implemented on a greater range and number of devices and used in a wider variety of applications.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T5">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="82" page="6" column="1">Table 5. Subset of evaluation criteria used by the W3C EXI committee.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="6" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Table 6</xref> illustrates the relationships between the criteria used in our case study and those used by the EXI committee. Some of them—such as widespread adoption—are intrinsically “soft” in that they admit of varying interpretations. For these, the value of elaborating the meaning with stories may be obvious. For example, what were the experiences of projects that adopted the technology? To drive our argument home, however, we focus on one particular feature that should, on the face of it, be relatively well-defined: compactness.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Our Criterion Relation EXI Criterion Encoding / decoding speed Synonymous with Processing efficiency Encoding / decoding software Includes off-the-shelf purchase Implementation cost cost cost as alternative to Transmission speed Effectively synonymous with Compactness Interoperability Enhanced by Platform neutrality Transport independence Learning curve / programming Increases Implementation cost complexity Maturity Indicated by Widespread adoption</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx86">
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="6" page="7">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Our Criterion</th>
                  <th class="table"> Relation</th>
                  <th class="table"> EXI Criterion</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Tool availability</td>
                  <td class="table"> Indicated by</td>
                  <td class="table"> Widespread adoption</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Tool reliability</td>
                  <td class="table"> Weakly indicated by</td>
                  <td class="table"> Widespread adoption</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Evolvability</td>
                  <td class="table"> Partially supported by</td>
                  <td class="table"> Forward compatibility</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="87" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Our Criterion Relation EXI Criterion Tool availability Indicated by Widespread adoption Tool reliability Weakly indicated by Widespread adoption Evolvability Partially supported by Forward compatibility</region>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="88" page="7" column="1">Table 6. Relationships between our evaluation criteria and those of the EXI study.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="89" page="7" column="1">4.1 Semantics of the Compactness Feature</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" page="7" column="1">The term compactness is ambiguous because it must cover a wide range of inputs. If we had only one input instance, compactness could be reduced to a positive integer-valued attribute, namely the size of the output. In reality, though, it must represent an aggregate assessment over a set of inputs. Resolving the ambiguity requires deciding on the sample inputs to use, the classes in which to group them, and the kind of aggregation to perform, e.g., averages, distributions, peaks, or some other measure. For example, Qing&amp;Adams used as input 9 files from the Extensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) conformance test suite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="90" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>], ranging in size from 2KB to 1MB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="91" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. Mundy et al created a custom application for exchanging attribute certificates to compare XML and ASN.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="92" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>], while Cokus&amp;Winkowsi created test sets to resemble the exchange of binary formatted military messages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="93" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. The EXI study involved a detailed definition of widely varying use cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="94" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>], while Augeri et al created a corpus modeled on the widely used Canterbury corpus for compression evaluations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="95" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="96" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>]. How do we compare, contrast, and aggregate such various tests? Viewing a feature model as part of an ontology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="97" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>], we can create placeholders in which to add the relevant information. For example, the alternative candidates can have a property test results, which are then linked to the relevant features of the candidate as well as to the test set employed, as illustrated in Figure2. This provides a unified view of the past studies. It does not, however, provide much help in comparing the different results. How should one understand the differences in test sets? The EXI tests, for example, correspond to a set of 18 use cases, including Metadata in broadcast systems, Floating point arrays in the energy industry, X3D graphics compression, serialization, and transmission, Web services for small devices, Web services within the enterprise, etc.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">hasTestResults obtainedUsing Candidate Test Results Test Set hasFeature indicates Compactness</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="100" page="7" column="1">Fig. 2. The open-world character of an ontology allows us to add contextual information to a feature model.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" page="7" column="1">We could add use cases as first-class objects and associate them with the corresponding test sets. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> illustrates part of the resulting ontology. We can take this further by elaborating the Scenario class in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> with properties specifying the functions performed, their relative importance (e.g., required vs. desirable), and their performance attributes. But this does not necessarily help in comparing the results of the different studies. The Canterbury corpus, for example, is not defined in terms of use cases, and its classification of input files is quite unlike the EXI classification. They are really different ontologies. Simply aggregating them provides little insight into the significance of using one test corpus vs. another. A similar issue arises in representing the test results. Some of the studies we consulted present a set of curves—one per candidate—graphing compressed size against original size. But Augeri et al average the<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> results over all test sets and present additional analysis of the test set attributes that were contributing factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="104" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. Should these distinctions be modeled in the Test Results class of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>?</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">supports hasRationale Test Set Use Case Justification occursIn describedBy involves Domain Stakeholder Scenario</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="108" page="8" column="1">Fig. 3. The feature model can be enriched with an endless amount of contextual information.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" page="8" column="1">A further source of ambiguity is the instrumentation software itself. Different studies may yield different results in part because of different instrumentation software. A discussion in one of the EXI documents illustrates the issues: The results presented here come from a stored snapshot that has been judged sufficiently stable for making decisions. Even so, there is still some variation in the results. This is a concern especially with the C-based candidates that may exhibit enormous and inexplicable variance between different test documents. It is therefore likely that there are still some problems with how the test framework's Java code interacts with the C code of the candidates. Accordingly, the results from the C-based candidates were filtered more carefully, by eliminating results for individual documents that were obviously incorrect. In addition, the stableness review of the results paid careful attention to any improvements in these candidates in particular. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="109" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] We could address this by adding classes of instrumentation, linking them to the test results in a manner similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>. But should we? There will always be important contextual information that has not been modeled, that could in principle be modeled, but that would be expensive to model. The alternative is to decorate the feature model with informal elaborations: commentary, explanation, and discussion. The relationships between the formal entities serve to coordinate these informal elaborations into a coherent story that answers questions of the form, Who, Why, What, and How.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="112" page="8" column="1">5 Elaborating the Feature Model with Stories</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" page="8" column="1">Deciding where to draw the line between formalization and informal elaboration must take account of the goals of the model. In our case study, the purpose of the elaborated feature model is to help us choose one of the alternatives listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>. So let us see how this plays out. Transmission speed being one of the criteria, we consult the Compactness feature, which is effectively equivalent to transmission speed. But Compactness cannot be summarized in a single value. Instead, from the Compactness feature of a given candidate, we can trace back along the indicates relationship in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> to see those test results that tell us something about this candidate’s level of success in compressing various inputs. There may be many such test results for this one candidate, including tests by different organizations or individuals, using different test sets, different methodologies, and different instrumentation. Each test result should point to this information. In the simplest case, a single candidate outperforms all the other candidates, i.e., it consistently produces the smallest output over all test sets in all of the recorded tests. In that case, we can easily say that this candidate scores highest with respect to transmission speed. But of course that is not likely. It is even less likely that we can also identify a clear second-place candidate, third-place candidate, etc., which we would like to do because transmission speed is only one of ten evaluation criteria.<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> Instead, we have to start asking questions, the answers to which start to provide us with a coherent story. For example:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">• Which test sets (if any) resemble our expected data? • Are the results consistent for those test sets? • Is the provenance of the test results credible?</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" page="9" column="1">If the answers to any of these questions are less than conclusive—for example, if we are uncertain whether any test set closely resembles our data, or the results are not consistent, or the provenance is doubtful—then we have to delve deeper, asking more questions:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">• What was the context of a test? • Who did the test, and what do we know of their agenda? • Was the methodology rigorous? • What is the source of inconsistency between this and the tests from other sources?</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" page="9" column="1">The answers to such questions may or may not be found in the elaborated feature model shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>, depending on how far one takes the model elaboration. The questions, however, are definitely not modeled explicitly. This illustrates a common problem with ontologies: they may be rich in information, but they tend not to be self-explanatory. Many ontologies suffer from an absence of documentation about why the information is there, and how to use it. This is where stories enter, because the emphasis in a story is on rationale. The persistent question, Why? is what distinguishes a story from a mere report. For example, rather than just telling us that a particular test set was modeled on the Canterbury corpus, it would tell us why the Canterbury corpus was used. Without knowing this we cannot fairly assess whether the test results are relevant to our problem. More generally, we would like the elaborated feature model to guide us to the following types of information:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="123" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">• Who are the stakeholders? • What are they trying to achieve? Why? • Why is it non-trivial—what barriers must they overcome? • What did they do to overcome these barriers? • Were they successful? Why? • Did some barriers remain, or new ones appear?</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="9" column="1">The last three question may be iterated until, eventually, success (or, perhaps, failure) is declared. For example, the Compactness feature for EXI can point us to the URI for the EXI evaluation, which in turn points to earlier documents addressing the above questions. This is the skeletal structure of a story. But more than that is possible. The questions actually suggest an ontology of stories, consisting (for example) of actors, goals, barriers, actions, and rationales. Discussions about candidates for reuse can be marked up to indicate explicitly the actors, goals, barriers, etc. that have been involved in developing, using, and reusing the candidates. The feature model can use such markup to point us to the information we need. This is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref> for the Compactness feature of the EXI alternative.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="126" page="9" column="1">6 Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="9" column="1">Feature models are a powerful way to achieve reuse in well established domains, such as those admitting of a product line architecture. But much reuse occurs in situations where there is no unified domain model; rather, the candidates for reuse and the available knowledge about them have varied provenance. In such situations, features are less well-defined, and their meanings need to be elaborated through additional context. <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> Stories, by definition, are situated in context and emphasize rationale. They therefore provide an effective way of enriching a feature model with the necessary context. We have illustrated this through a case study involving the transmission of structured data between two systems.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="132" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/T" id="129">http://www.w3.org/T</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xbc-" id="130">http://www.w3.org/TR/xbc-</ext-link> R/2009/WD-exi- <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/XML/EXI" id="131">http://www.w3.org/XML/EXI</ext-link> properties/#compactness evaluation-20090407/ /public-status.html</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">assessedBy performedBy Feature Evaluation Stakeholders yields employs motivatedBy Test Results Method Goals mayCauseRevisionOf mayCauseRevisionOf</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="137" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-exi-" id="134">http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-exi-</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/2003/09/" id="135">http://www.w3.org/2003/09/</ext-link> evaluation-20090407/#compactness- <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xbc-" id="136">http://www.w3.org/TR/xbc-</ext-link> xmlap/xml-binary-wg- results measurement/ charter.html</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="138" page="10" column="1">Fig. 4. By incorporating story tags in the elaborated feature model we can guide the potential re-user directly to relevant information.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="139" page="10" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="10" column="1">[1] Bailin, S. Diagrams and design stories. Machine Graphics and Vision, Vol. 12, No. 1, 2003.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="10" column="1">[2] Bailin, S., Moore, M., Bentz, R., and Bewtra, M. KAPTUR: Knowledge acquisition for preservation of tradeoffs and underlying rationales. In Proceedings of the Fifth Knowledge-Based Software Assistant Conference. Rome Laboratory, September 1990.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="10" column="1">[3] Kang, K., Cohen, S., Hess, J., Novak, W., Peterson, A. Feature-Oriented Domain Analysis (FODA) Feasibility Study. Carnegie Mellon University Software Engineering Institute Technical Report CMU/SEI-90-TR-021.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="10" column="1">[4] van der Linden, F., Schmid, K., Rommes, E. Software Product Lines in Action: The Best Industrial Practice in Product Line Engineering. Springer, 2007.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="10" column="1">[5] Bailin, S. Software reuse as ontology negotiation. Software Reuse: Methods, Techniques and Tools. Springer LNCS 3107/2004, pages 242-253.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="10" column="1">[6] Bailin, S., Simos, M., Levine, L., Creps, R. Learning and Inquiry-Based Reuse Adoption (LIBRA). Wiley-IEEE Press, 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="10" column="1">[7] Abstract Syntax Notation: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.asn1.org" id="146">http://www.asn1.org</ext-link>.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="10" column="1">[8] Sandoz, P., Triglia, A., Pericas-Geersten, S. Fast Infoset. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://java.sun.com/developer/technicalArticles/xml/fastinfoset/." id="148">http://java.sun.com/developer/technicalArticles/xml/fastinfoset/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="10" column="1">[9] Ziv, J. and Lempel; A. A Universal Algorithm for Sequential Data Compression, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 23(3), pp.337-343, May 1977.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="10" column="1">[10] Efficient XML Interchange: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/XML/EXI/." id="151">http://www.w3.org/XML/EXI/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="10" column="1">[11] Qing, X., and Adams, C. “A comparison of compression techniques for XML-based security policies in mobile computing environments.” Ottawa Workshop on New Challenges for Access Control, April 27, 2005.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="10" column="1">[12] Bzip: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.bzip.org/" id="154">http://www.bzip.org/</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" page="10" column="1">[13] WAP Binary XML: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wbxml/." id="156">http://www.w3.org/TR/wbxml/.</ext-link> [14] XML-binary Optimized Packaging: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xop10/." id="157">http://www.w3.org/TR/xop10/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="10" column="1">[15] SOAP Message Transmission Optimization Mechanism: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/soap12-mtom/" id="159">http://www.w3.org/TR/soap12-mtom/</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="10" column="1">[16] XMill: an Efficient compressor for XML. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.liefke.com/hartmut/xmill/xmill.html" id="161">http://www.liefke.com/hartmut/xmill/xmill.html</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="10" column="1">[17] Bournez, C (ed.) “Efficient XML Interchange Evaluation”. W3C Working Draft, 7 April, 2009. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-evaluation" id="163">http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-evaluation</ext-link> .</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="11" column="1">[18] OASIS eXtensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) TC, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.oasis" id="165">http://www.oasis</ext-link>- open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=xacml</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="11" column="1">[19] Mundy, D.P., Chadwick, D. and Smith, A. “Comparing the Performance of Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1) vs. eXtensible Markup Language (XML)”. Terena Networking Conference 2008 / CARNet Users' Conference 2008, May 19-22, 2008, Zagreb, Croatia.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="11" column="1">[20] Cokus, M. and Winkiwski, D. “XML Sizing and Compression Study For Military Wireless Data”, XML 2002.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="11" column="1">[21] XML Binary Characterization Use Cases: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2005/NOTE-xbc-use-cases-20050331/." id="169">http://www.w3.org/TR/2005/NOTE-xbc-use-cases-20050331/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="11" column="1">[22] Augeri, C.J., Bulutoglu, D.A., Mullins, B.E., Baldwin, R.O. “An Analysis of XML Compression Efficiency”. Proceedings of the 2007 Workshop on Experimental Computer Science, San Diego, California.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="11" column="1">[23] The Canterbury Corpus: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://corpus.canterbury.ac.nz/." id="172">http://corpus.canterbury.ac.nz/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="11" column="1">[24] Efficient XML Interchange Measurements Note: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/WD-exi-measurements-" id="174">http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/WD-exi-measurements-</ext-link> 20070725/ .</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
