<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>151aa89438bf5a9e7b089302a2e2d029149195d16e1912b6bed45268d32eeb77</job>
    <base_name>62kp</base_name>
    <doi>10.1080/0144929X.2011.563794</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library] On: 11 July 2013, At: 07:45 Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis Informa Ltd Registered in England and Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered office: Mortimer House, 37-41</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Mortimer Street, London W1T 3JH, UK</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/tbit20" id="3">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/tbit20</ext-link></region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">Storytelling Group – a co-design method for service design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">a</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">b</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx8">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kp.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62kp.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="9">a b a Anu Kankainen</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="10">Kirsikka Vaajakallio</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="11">Vesa Kantola</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="12">Tuuli Mattelmäki Helsinki Institute for Information Technology HIIT</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="13">PO Box</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="14">Aalto</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="15">Finland Aalto University School of Art</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="16">Design</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="17">Hämeentie 135 C</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="18">FIN</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="19">Helsinki</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="20">Finland Published online: 19 Apr 2011.</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="30">Anu Kankainen</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="31">Kirsikka Vaajakallio</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="32">Vesa Kantola &amp; Tuuli Mattelmki (2012) Storytelling Group – a co- design method for service design</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="33">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="34">DOI: 10.1080/0144929X.2011.563794 http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0144929X.2011.</name></contrib></contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="21">To cite</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">this article:</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="35">To link</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="36">to this article:</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="37">PLEASE</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="38">SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="39">Taylor in the</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="40">are not should any or the This</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="41">form to</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="42" confidence="possible">&amp; Francis makes every effort to ensure the accuracy of all the information (the “Content”) contained publications on our platform. However, Taylor &amp; Francis, our agents, and our licensors make no representations or warranties whatsoever as to the accuracy, completeness, or suitability for any purpose Content. Any opinions and views expressed in this publication are the opinions and views of the authors, the views of or endorsed by Taylor &amp; Francis. The accuracy of the Content should not be relied upon be independently verified with primary sources of information. Taylor and Francis shall not be liable losses, actions, claims, proceedings, demands, costs, expenses, damages, and other liabilities whatsoever howsoever caused arising directly or indirectly in connection with, in relation to or arising out of the use Content. article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial or systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, or distribution in any anyone is expressly forbidden. Terms &amp; Conditions of access and use can be found at http:// www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-conditions</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="43">b</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="44">of the and and for</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="45">of</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="46">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology Vol. 31, No. 3, March 2012, 221–230</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" confidence="possible">Storytelling Group – a co-design method for service design Anu Kankainen a *, Kirsikka Vaajakallio b , Vesa Kantola a a Helsinki Institute for Information Technology HIIT, PO Box 19800, 00076 Aalto, Finland; b Aalto University School of Art and Design, Ha ̈meentie 135 C, FIN-00560 Helsinki, Finland (Received 26 February 2010; final version received 9 February 2011) In this article, we will introduce a co-design method called Storytelling Group that has been developed and tested in three service design cases. Storytelling Group combines collaborative scenario building and focus group discussions. It inspires service design by providing different types of user information: a fictive story of a customer journey is created to illustrate a ‘what if’ world, users tell real-life stories about their service experiences, users come up with new service ideas, and they are also asked about their opinions and attitudes in a focus-group type of discussion. The method was developed for service design cases where a longer time perspective has an important role. Moreover, the method is a quick start for actual design work but still includes users in the process. Keywords: service design; co-design; storytelling; user research</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="48" page="2" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="2" column="1">In this article, we present a co-design method called Storytelling Group. Many user-centred and participatory design (PD) approaches have been developed to investigate user needs. We do not argue that traditional methods such as observations focusing on user practices in their socio-cultural contexts are not suitable for service design. However, a longer time perspective in certain service customer relationships, such as in the banking and insurance field, and the request of service providers to have concrete design results as early as possible have inspired us to explore alternative techniques. When designing services, one has to understand that service is a process (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>) and not a single use situation or task. The customer journey is one of the concepts applied in service design to emphasise and define the process. It aims to describe the process of experiencing service through different touch points from the customer’s point of view. Sometimes these touch points are not even provided by the same service provider. Service providers are typically networked, as can be seen in the example of air travel. The service journey could describe how a person books a flight through an Internet service provided by a travel agency, how the person accesses the airport by public transportation, the procedure of checking in and enjoying a cup of coffee before the flight and finally the collecting of the luggage at the destination. Through the customer journey description, a service designer can create an overall picture of</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="52" page="2" column="1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email id="51">anu.kankainen@hiit.fi</email></region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">and Tuuli Mattelma  ̈ ki b</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="2" column="2">the service experience and its components instead of focusing on individual details in each phase. Services can vary greatly in how important a part time plays. An amusement park service can be an once- in-a-lifetime experience, but with an insurance company one typically wants to have a longer relationship. Services are also often experienced and accessed through multiple channels. A banking service is most often accessed through ATMs, Internet bank sites and also by telephone or actually going to the bank and interacting face-to-face with the personnel. Service is thus typically part of a larger network of elements in the life of the consumer. When seeking improvements or potential new service ideas, one should look widely at the ecosystem of services and how they might be combined into new offerings. Service design is often about identifying new service combinations and finding new partnerships. The service mindset should focus on ‘the process of assisting customers in their own value creation process’ according to Vargo and Lusch (2008, p. 258).</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="55" page="2" column="2">1.1. Storytelling and service design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" page="2" column="2">As described, services are often networked in many ways. They are also dynamic, that is, the customer and the service provider both influence the service experience that is co-created and experienced in the interaction. Services are thus flexible in nature and have a great deal of openness that needs to be managed. Services are sometimes compared to theatre (e.g. in <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Mossberg and Nissen Johanssen (2007)</xref>), where the whole system works as a staged performance: the stage is peopled with trained actors, the customers experience the performance in the audience and the backstage people offer invisible support. This meta- phor emphasises the well-trained actors and the importance of rehearsing (and good directors). Again, the need for various stakeholders in the development of services is also emphasised. This complexity poses challenges to designers and decision-makers to envision and prototype services. Narratives can therefore be helpful tools for handling this complexity:<marker type="block"/> Moreover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Blomqvist and Holmlid (2009)</xref> propose that storytelling could be one way forward in developing techniques for service design. We have identified at least three reasons for considering narratives in service design:</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="59" page="2" column="2">ISSN 0144-929X print/ISSN 1362-3001 online Ó 2012 Taylor &amp; Francis <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0144929X.2011.563794" id="57">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0144929X.2011.563794</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com" id="58">http://www.tandfonline.com</ext-link></outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="60" page="3" column="1">222</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="61" page="3" column="1">A. Kankainen et al.</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="64" page="3" column="1">‘When you put all these things together, with elements from architecture, physical design, electronic technology from software, how do you actually prototype an idea for a service, and it seems that really, it’s about storytelling, it’s about narrative.’ (Bill Moggridge, keynote at the Danish CIID conference Service Design Symposium, May 2008)</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">(1) First, stories are gathered from users to inform and inspire design. The methods often used include observations, design probes and interviews. Interpretations of user data are also often communicated to design through narratives such as personas and scenarios of current actions. (2) The second reason pertains to storytelling in prototyping services, as referred to by Moggridge. Storytelling is used as means to formulate a design driver that facilitates the style and overall design of a service. A story serves as a linking thread to connect various details together from architecture and environment design to communication, marketing and customer experience. (3) The third reason relates to using storytelling to create and manage contexts in which experiences happen. Storytelling is thus a tool to create a specific image, to differentiate from other similar services and to create and main- tain an attraction, an experience that triggers the imagination. Storytelling is often seen as related to thematic concepts such as the Hard Rock Cafe  ́ restaurant chain, but, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Mossberg and Nissen Johanssen (2007)</xref> emphasise that at the organisational level storytelling is more. At the organisational strategic level, a story can explain why the company exists and</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">how it creates profit; at the marketing level, the story explains how the company and its product are differentiated and the third level of using stories deals with how people in the company communicate who they are and how they should realise their visions. At this level, the story can even create a specific feeling of ‘us’.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="3" column="2">1.1.1. Stories from users to inform and inspire service design</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" page="3" column="2">When conducting the literature review on narrative user research methods for service design, we were surprised that there are few articles on such methods. Scenarios and storyboards are widely used in service design, but they are often created by the designers ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Diana et al. 2009</xref>). In general, various theatre methods such as Forum Theatre have been applied in design processes for instance to mimic current situations, to envision future alternatives, to trigger discussion and to test design ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Brandt and Grunnet 2000</xref>). In Fictional Inquiry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Dindler and Iversen 2007</xref>), narratives and deliberate staging are used to create an imaginative place in which design collaboration unfolds. Fictional Inquiry has been used, for example, to co-design mobile outdoor games (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Verhaegh et al. 2006</xref>) and to co-design pervasive technologies for learning environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Dindler et al. 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Strom (2007)</xref> has reported on how he has used user stories with emotions and conflicts in industrial software projects. He conducted user studies in the field and wrote stories based on the studies. In these field studies, he used the so-called sense-making methodology, which focuses on situations where users experience the largest problems instead of going through all steps of their work processes. Strom’s method could perhaps be used to improve certain service touch points by focusing on the problems the customer faces with them. However, according to our experience, user stories can reveal opportunities that can be missed if only focusing on problems. Therefore, going through the whole customer journey from both positive and negative perspectives has its benefits. Two of the authors of this article (Ma  ̈ kela  ̈ and Mattelma  ̈ ki 2002) had earlier developed a storytelling technique that was piloted in designing mobile phones and their accessories. A group of users were invited to a storytelling session. They were asked to tell stories about their mobile phone experiences in general. As inspiration they were given postcards that triggered storytelling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). The stories that were gathered from users with this technique were random memories of the users using mobile phones in specific situations.<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> There was no time perspective; the stories were simply about single use situations. However, the mobile phone designers were able to proceed with concepting new mobile phone features and accessories on the basis of the stories, which were presented in the form of storyboards. If this method was applied to service design, its weakness is that it concentrates on certain use situations in the past and not on service moments in the future where the service could be part of a value creation process. The future is left for the designers to imagine and is thus not co-designed with users. The method could perhaps be adjusted for gathering user stories on a specific existing service where the target for improvement is focused on critical service moments (moments-of-truth). In fact, when designing the method, the authors were inspired by the critical incident technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Flanagan 1954</xref>).</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="79" page="4" column="1">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="4" column="1">223</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx81">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kp.page_004.image_02.png" thmb="62kp.page_004.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            </region>
            <region class="unknown" id="83" page="4" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>. Examples of postcards used in previous storytelling method developed by two of the authors (Ma  ̈ kela  ̈ and Mattelma  ̈ ki 2002).</region>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="86" page="4" column="1">1.2. Co-design principle</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" page="4" column="1">Besides being based on narratives, the Storytelling Group technique presented later in this article is based on co-design principles as well. Co-design is a design approach that highlights collaboration, and it is related to the traditions of PD. It typically refers to an activity <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> in which potential users are empowered to bring their ideas into the design of new solutions. The notion of co-design is also conceived as a collaborative knowledge sharing and creating process in which the skills and experiences of various participants are brought together to reach novel solutions (Mattelma  ̈ ki 2007). The original political ideology of PD in 1970s Scandinavia to promote workplace democracy has weakened somewhat, while emphasis on creative collaboration in multidisciplinary group work has come to the fore. Due to this shift in overall aim, the term PD has been partially replaced by the term co- design, also used in this article. However, our co- design approach has adopted PD principles such as (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Shuler and Namioka 1993</xref>): (1) cooperative design, where both designers and users bring competence into the design process; (2) familiarity, resemblance of situations and design tools to existing practices; (3) understanding practice as starting point; (4) experi- mentation with the future and (5) learning as a part of the design process. In this article, co-design refers to a particular gathering where at least two persons are at one moment bound regarding place and time. It is not a spontaneous action or a practical working together with colleagues in the design studio. Rather, it can be described as a social occasion that is typically programmed in advanced, possesses an agenda and has pre-established unfolding of phases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Goffman 1963</xref>). In co-designing, the roles of professional designers or design researchers may vary from active participants to almost invisible facilitators. However, regardless of the variations, two fundamental needs remain to enhance participants’ creative thinking and to support dialogue between participants. Thus, one of the cornerstones of co-design is facilitating creative and generative collaboration (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Brandt 2006</xref>). As Johansson (2005, p. 17) points out that the challenge faced in co-design is that the ‘trained designer may use a pen and a piece of paper to illustrate his ideas while other stakeholders need other kinds of design material to be able to sketch’. In the Storytelling Group method, teams of four to six people tell a story about an imagined person and his/her relationship with a certain service during a customer journey. Thus, the aim of this method is to bring together different actors and provide a common ground for this group of people with various backgrounds and interests. The storytelling structure is seen as having potential to create a relaxed atmosphere and encourage the participants to envision dream situations without the boundaries of current technology and practices.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="92" page="5" column="1">224</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93" page="5" column="1">A. Kankainen et al.</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="94" page="5" column="1">2. Storytelling Group method principles</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" page="5" column="1">The Storytelling Group method takes into account the complexity of services in various ways:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">. it focuses on the customer journey . it has a time perspective . it takes into account multiple channels that the users can use when interacting with the service . it allows the users to talk about the needed service ecosystem in their life. In other words, it does not focus only on the service under design but during the storytelling the participants naturally talk about the other services they need in their life situation and as a part of their everyday practices. . it takes into account the social interaction that happens both when using the service and as part of the value creation process where the service is involved.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="5" column="1">Storytelling Group combines scenario building and focus group discussions. It encourages the participants to create fictive stories of customer journeys (scenario building) and to tell real-life stories about their experiences that ground their motivations for future experiences. It brings all parties – users, designers, researchers and services providers – around the same table. It is therefore a co-design technique as well. Moreover, it allows service designers and service providers to ask about users’ opinions and attitudes towards the service under design (in a focus group discussion). Consequently, Storytelling Group informs and inspires service design in several ways. It provides different types of user information and service concept ideas:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">. During the Storytelling Group session, a fictive story (scenario) of a certain customer journey is created. The story describes the dream situation – the ‘what if’ world. The scenario illustrates what the users would like to experience with the service under design. It is a customer journey over a certain time period defined by the session participants. It includes character profiles that have a role in the customer journey, service moments that the characters will have, multiple service channels (e.g. e-mail, Facebook, etc.) that the characters use when interacting with the service, and interactions the characters have with each other. All these are also created by the participants. This story creation is guided by a moderator, and it is visualised on a large piece of paper displaying a timeline (see Figures 2 and 3).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kp.page_005.image_03.png" thmb="62kp.page_005.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="100" page="5" column="2">Figure 2.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" page="5" column="2">A Storytelling Group. The moderator (on the right) is documenting the created story on the large paper with a timeline. The creative secretary (service designer) is sitting next to him (on the right) and is participating in the discussions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kp.page_005.image_04.png" thmb="62kp.page_005.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="103" page="5" column="2">Figure 3. A timeline paper used in a Storytelling Group gathering.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">The moderator can facilitate the storytelling by placing branching points on the timeline before the session starts (e.g. a social media service that has 100 users at start-up should have over 100,000 users by the middle of the story). . At the same time, the fictive story of the customer journey is created, the participants are encouraged to tell real-life stories about their own experiences that somehow relate to the fictive story. The real-life stories help to understand why the users want the fictive story to proceed as they suggest and what motivates them to use the service. . During the fictive story creation, usually, the participants also come up with new service, touch point or service evidence ideas. . The role of the ‘creative secretary’ is to ask relevant questions related to the service (users’ attitudes, opinions, concept/feature ideas) during the story creation. After the story has been completed, the creative secretary can also ask the users wrap-up questions related to the service. It is thus the responsibility of this ‘creative secretary’ (service designer or service provider) to grasp topics of interest and find out more about them; this person must therefore be sensitive to possible design openings. Without the creative</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="105" page="6" column="1">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="106" page="6" column="1">225</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">secretary, this layer of knowledge stays at a rather superficial level.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="6" column="1">2.1. Different types of realism</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" page="6" column="1">Since imagination is embedded in the narrative structure of the Storytelling Group method, there is the question of reliability of the knowledge gained through the fictive scenario building: can it be handled as trustworthy information to inform design? Many approaches, such as Strom’s (2007), wish to draw out participants’ experiences with and knowledge on certain topics and utilise these individual insights as sources for design concepts. In Storytelling Group, there are two types of realism: (1) some personal experiences are ‘hidden’ into the overall fictive storyline thus becoming collaborative sketching material in Johansson’s (2005) terms and (2) some personal experiences are shared by telling real-life stories that can be considered non-fictive and are easier to accept as trustworthy information. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Sanders and Dandavate (1999)</xref> propose different levels of user knowledge in which design is interested: explicit, observable, tacit and latent. Explicit knowledge refers to things that people tell, for example, in interviews, whereas some knowledge resides in people’s actions, practices and environment and can be ap- proached by observing what people do and how they use things. The latter two types of knowledge include people’s tacit knowledge, dreams and feelings, which are often unconscious and thus most difficult to reveal. Our assumption is that fictive story creation is one way to explore these tacit and latent dreams and feelings. The increasing interest in user experience has widened the focus in user studies to cover all four areas of information that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Sanders and Dandavate (1999)</xref> define. As a result, traditional user study methods, such as interviews, observations, and focus groups do not suffice: there has been a need to develop more creative and collaborative approaches such as probes, make tools and design games to supplement the user understanding gained by traditional methods. These new methods are also called innovative methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Hanington 2003</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Keinonen (2009)</xref>, the aim of innovative methods is often to speculate upon future designs rather than seek reliable and valid explanations for existing practices or attitudes.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="114" page="6" column="1">2.2. Relation to other user research methods</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="6" column="1">Ethnographic methods applied in design (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Wasson 2002</xref>) focus on understanding and explaining current practices. They do not usually envision future designs, which are often created after the user data analysis by the design team. When using ethnographic<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> methods, the focus should not only be on a certain task and tool but also on the whole process of use – the practices – including all stakeholders in a certain socio- cultural context. This process-focused approach suits well with service design thinking (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Vargo and Lusch 2008</xref>). However, in order to investigate the development of certain customer journeys and practices related to them, one should conduct ethnographic research for an extensive or nearly impossibly long time in some cases. For example, customer relationships related to insurance or banking may begin already before the baby is born and continue during his/her whole life. Ethnographic methods in this context are difficult to apply if one is to understand the whole process of value creation with the service. Moreover, service design practitioners in their customer projects often face the pressure of designing something concrete already at the beginning of the project with little input from user research. One ethnographic-based design research method, the moving with magic thing technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Iacucci et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Kankainen 2006</xref>), is exceptional since it envisions the future in real-life contexts; nonetheless, it also lacks the longer time perspective. The Storytelling Group method aims to tackle this time-span challenge in service design. One of the approaches worthy of mention that is geared to gather subjective views on people’s experiences for design is probes (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Gaver et al. 1999</xref>, Mattelma  ̈ ki 2006), which is often also mentioned as belonging in the toolbox of service design. Probes are based on self-documentation and often include open questions and diaries and such, for gathering contextual insights, opinions, and stories and to envision potential design ideas. They are typically complemen- ted with interviews for gathering further details. Some of the probes techniques, such as diaries, can include a time and process perspective. The stories and envi- sioned design potentials are typically reported by individuals who do not know what other participants have been documenting and thus lack an interactive or collective element. In Storytelling Group, participants collectively share stories and are inspired and facilitated by each other’s stories. The challenging side of collective storytelling, when compared to probes, is the group dynamics that may intimidate some participants, as well as the lack of contextuality, aspects generally mentioned as weaknesses of focus groups. Hence, the Storytelling Group method has similar elements to a focus group method, albeit the storytelling part of the Storytelling Group method focuses more on people’s tacit dreams and feelings whereas focus group discussions are more about explicit user information according to Sanders and Dandavate’s (1999) definition. Focus groups are appropriate for understanding motivations, attitudes, opinions and<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> first impressions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Kuniavsky 2003</xref>). In a Storytelling Group session, the role of the creative secretary is to ask focus-group type questions. According to Kuniavsky (2003), focus group planning should include carefully chosen topics and a thoughtfully written discussion guide. The creative secretary in a Storytelling Group session, however, does not define the discussion themes in advance as the facilitator of a focus group session does: the themes and questions the creative secretary asks evolve in line with the storytelling, from more general themes towards more focused and contextual design ideas. The storytelling structure introduces new topics along the way, thus focusing the discussion little by little. In the Storytelling Group gathering, the discussion themes thus arise from the fictive customer journey story created together with the participants. After the facilitator has given the overall framing that positions the story in relation to a certain general theme such as a bank loan, the participants are the ones who introduce topics for discussion and story. Sometimes the creative secretary may also bring in certain topics for conversation. In a Storytelling Group gathering, scenario building is initiated by defining the main characters of the story. The character creation works as an ‘ice breaker’ before starting to create collaboratively the customer journey story, but it also somewhat directs what kind of story is created. The aim is not to create user profiles that could be treated as trustworthy user data. In our cases, we have not included the characters in our analysis phase. However, in future, it is worth exploring if we could better utilise character creation as a part of Storytelling Group, since fictional characters have proven to be useful in co-design approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Triantafyllakos et al. 2010</xref>). Fictional characters in co-design gatherings are somewhat different from personas. In user-centred design, personas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Cooper 1999</xref>) is one of the methods often used to share user understanding within a design team by utilising visual and textual descriptions of potential user characteristics, lifestyles, needs and limitations. Cooper’s basic advice regarding personas is: ‘Develop a precise description of our user and what he wishes to accomplish.’ They are typically created based on a user study, which may include methods such as interviews, observations and probes as well as surveys. There is a particular technique that has been developed for analysing user data in order to create personas, and following Cooper, several others have developed the method further to meet particular design needs. Persona descriptions have also been represented in various formats from posters to booklets and even images on beer classes in order to communicate user understanding inside large organisations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Pruitt and Grudin 2003</xref>).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="122" page="7" column="1">226</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="123" page="7" column="1">A. Kankainen et al.</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="129" page="7" column="2">3. Our process of developing the Storytelling Group method</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" page="7" column="2">The Storytelling Group method has been developed and tested in three service design cases: (1) banking services, (2) congratulatory services within social media and (3) a social video service. During these cases, four Storytelling Group sessions were organised altogether with 10 groups, having altogether 45 service users participating. The sessions were conducted in late 2009 and early 2010 in the capital area of Helsinki. In the following sections, we will briefly describe the service design cases where we applied the method and explain the process of how the method has evolved to what it is now.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="131" page="7" column="2">3.1. First case: banking services</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="135" page="7" column="2">The aim in the first case, banking services, was to increase designers’ and service providers’ understanding of changing user needs over a long customer relationship. The intention was not to invent new banking services but to improve existing ones. Chan- ging customer relationships offer an important perspective on banking services that should address people’s needs according to their varying life situations. Banking services in particular can carry a long life span: the customer journey or relationship may last tens of years. In the insurance business, for example, an insurance contract is often made with the bank when one moves to one’s first dwelling. Situations may change over the years and various types of insurance policies may be required, for example, when one begins to cohabitate or to buy one’s own home. Accidents may happen at home, requiring an insurance claim, and so on. In summary, service moments and customer relationships with the bank depend on life stages as well as specific life events. The Storytelling Group technique aims to tackle both eventualities. In the two Storytelling Group sessions, in this particular case, the aim was to create a setting in which the service providers, design consultants and potential end users could meet and envision the bank services as a lifelong customer journey. In the first session, all the stakeholders were represented, but the designers and service providers did not have pre-defined roles in the Storytelling Group. The service providers mainly acted as customers or service personnel during the story creation. The designers for the most part simply observed and made notes. The moderator’s task was to guide the storytelling. During the session, we noticed that the service users started to naturally tell real-life stories about their experiences with banking services. The service providers and designers found them very interesting, and, moreover, new service ideas <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> emerged. Therefore, we decided to facilitate those experiences as well in the second session. In the first session, two of the design researchers began to participate unintentionally. One had been the moderator and another was taking notes. The one taking notes, however, noticed the difficulties the moderator had with handling story creation, concept ideas and facilitating real-life storytelling. The note taker then began to take a more active role that we later called a ‘creative secretary’. She facilitated the real-life storytelling and also asked focus-group type questions about opinions, attitudes and service concepts. Since we thought that we should adopt a more active role as designers and define a clearer role for service providers, before the second session we proposed that one would take the role of creative secretary. This proposal worked well. In the second session, however, we did not have a wrap-up discussion facilitated by the creative secretary, which was felt a lack by the designers. This was added to the method in the second service design case. In this case, the Storytelling Group method proved to be most useful for gathering users’ real-life stories related to certain customer journeys and hearing about their attitudes towards certain possible changing service events. The service provider representatives regarded the gatherings as learning situations, gaining better customer understanding that went beyond the ongoing service design project. The service designers in that particular project were very much inspired by the users’ real-life stories and opinions and came up with concrete service design solutions based on them.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="133" page="8" column="1">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="134" page="8" column="1">227</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="136" page="8" column="1">3.2. Second case: services within social media</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" page="8" column="1">In the second case, the aim was to explore the kinds of motivations and attitudes people have regarding new services within social media that would enhance congratulatory occasions or sharing celebrations. The service provider and designers were also interested in current use situations and new service concept ideas. We organised the third Storytelling Group session with three different groups. All three groups included on average five social media users and a service designer, as well as one design researcher acting as moderator. Moreover, one of the groups also had the service provider participating. She was there to detect possible service concept ideas and ask more focus-group type questions about them. In all groups, service designers had a clear role as creative secretary, and they were instructed beforehand about their role. We also reserved time for wrap-up discussions with the groups for the creative secretaries. One group included the designer who had by chance participated in our first case and was therefore <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> experienced with the method and this group provided the most interesting and relevant user information. The designer managed to guide the ‘focus group’ discussion, detect ideas for interesting concepts, and ask deeper questions about them, as well as facilitate real- life storytelling. He also facilitated the wrap-up discussion. Less-experienced designers were more passive in other groups and the user information from those groups was not as rich; nevertheless, real- life storytelling and concept ideas came naturally also in these groups. Focus-group type discussions on attitudes and opinions did not occur for the most part. However, the service provider was ultimately also very interested in attitudes and opinions since they were entering a new service domain. In this case, the Storytelling Group method turned out to be most useful in generating service concept ideas. In fact, it was decided that one of the ideas that emerged in the gathering would be prototyped further by the service designers. Moreover, the service providers were very interested in the overall customer understanding (real-life stories and attitudes towards possible changes in services), and therefore, much effort was expended on analysis and reporting by the researchers.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="139" page="8" column="2">3.3. Third case: social video service</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" page="8" column="2">In the third case, we explored a social video service concept. Its development was in its early stages: the first prototype was about to be built. The aim was to discover how to further develop the concept so that it would attract a large number of users over time. We organised a Storytelling Group session with three groups having five service users in each and a moderator. It was intended that each group would also have had a service provider acting as creative secretary, but in the end only one group included a service provider besides the moderator due to illness. The lack of creative secretary was prominent in the other two groups since the moderator has neither the time nor the capacity to deepen the discussions on interesting topics that arose during the story creation and the discussions were very short. What was new in this case was that we deliberately inserted several branching points on the timeline for the story creation. The story was begun, so that the service had only four users; the participants then needed to proceed in storytelling so that the service could gain 100 users, then 10,000 users and finally 100,000 users. They needed to imagine what the service provider had to do in order to attract a certain number of users as well as what the four main characters in the story were doing while the service was evolving. This process worked very well and triggered discussions <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> among others on the importance of word-of-mouth marketing and if the service could be free or a paid service. In this case, the Storytelling Group method provided high-level directions for the service design. Afterwards, the service provider representative stated that he would have liked to also receive more detailed user feedback on the service interactions, but he understood that he should have presented the concept to the participants in more detail in the first place. However, this was not possible since the concept design was only in the early phases, and there was no interaction design material to present in the gathering. Moreover, the lack of creative secretaries in two of the groups may also have influenced the level of detail into which the discussions could go.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="141" page="9" column="1">228</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="142" page="9" column="1">A. Kankainen et al.</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="144" page="9" column="1">4. Instructions for conducting Storytelling Groups</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="145" page="9" column="1">4.1. Running a successful storyline workshop, cooperation between two facilitators</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="148" page="9" column="1">According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Lundberg and Arvola (2007)</xref>, an extra ‘creative facilitator’ is needed in collaborative design workshops besides a ‘normal facilitator’. This is because the facilitator himself cannot run all the necessary documentation during the workshop, and he is very often pushing his own ideas while running a workshop. Based on our experience of running Storytelling Group, we have come to the same conclusion as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Lundberg and Arvola (2007)</xref>. We named this creative facilitator more frankly as a creative secretary to emphasise the difference from the moderator, who takes care of story flow. The responsibilities of the creative secretary are important, as pointed out in our case descriptions. (S)he is observing the hidden possibilities in the story world, which is created by the group, and (s)he can interrupt the story flow or the organisation of the story events of the group. The profession of designer provides a suitable background for the secretary, because designers can generally see the opportunities of the story world both at a technological and a social level. However, the service provider can also act as creative secretary alongside the designer. For the service provider, participation is as important as hearing the real-life stories and concept ideas from the service users, according to our experience. Moreover, the service users can ask more detailed questions about the service from the service provider during the session.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="149" page="9" column="1">4.2. Other issues to consider</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="9" column="1">To run a successful storyline workshop, a peaceful room with, for example, fruit and beverages on the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> table is needed. Drinks and fruit offer the opportunity for the group members to think and pause. The group members can thereby stand long periods of waiting to make their own contribution to the story world without feelings of frustration. The act of listening is a very important aspect of the workshop. The long silence of a group member can suddenly provide a very important twist to the story events and change the story world once the silent member takes the initiative. A sense of humour is also important during the workshops. There is a point where the group begins working hard, which can be tangibly sensed. (The experienced moderator of our workshops had even stated, ‘Now it is starting!’ to his group, which made the group laugh.) At this point, the process can continue at a new, more intensive level. According to our experience, a group of approximately five service users, a moderator, a designer and a service provider needs 90 minutes to complete one to two stories (depending on how active the creative secretaries are in facilitating focus-group type discussions). In addition, the group needs 15 minutes at the beginning to get to know each other and the moderator to tell them what they will do, and 30 minutes at the end for wrap-up discussion. One Storytelling Group session thus lasts approximately 2.5 h. As described earlier, we have had maximum three different groups in the same session. We have therefore been able to invite maximum 15 users to the same session at the same time, which requires three moderators and three creative secretaries. At the same time, this has saved time in practical arrangements. We have also noticed that the most inspiring and active group is the one where the service users have a very similar background. In some cases, it might be feasible to have users from different age and life stages if the service is such that there is interaction between users with different backgrounds (e.g. an extended family interacting with the service). However, the moderator and the creative secretary then need to take everyone’s perspective into account in the storytelling and discussions.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="152" page="9" column="2">4.3. Steps to moderate a Storytelling Group</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156" page="9" column="2">When making preparations for a Storytelling Group gathering, choose a theme, for example, a particular customer journey, which is relevant for your design project. It will be used as the base for the storyline, for example, ‘the lifespan of a bank loan’ or ‘a surprise related to acknowledging a friend in social media’. Build a game board by drawing a timeline on the paper. Create additional game materials that may support the conversation or illustrate events in the story. These may include service evidence (in the case <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> of the bank loan marketing brochures and contract forms may introduce new situations and issues into the discussion) or symbols that illustrate multiple channels related to the service (mobile phone, computer, office, letter, etc.) The additional game materials can be placed on the table to trigger the imagination, but they are not compulsory. To successfully moderate a Storytelling Group, the moderator needs to have clear instructions for everyone. Before the session, the moderator needs to also brief the creative secretaries about their role. In the group, it is advised that the moderator takes the following steps:</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="154" page="10" column="1">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="155" page="10" column="1">229</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">(1) Ask everyone to introduce themselves. (2) Ask permission to video record the session for documenting and analysis purposes. (3) Tell the group what they will do and what the participants’ roles are in the storytelling. (4) Give the theme of the customer journey (e.g. home insurance) to the participants. (5) Ask the participants to think about and describe who the main characters are in the story that would use the service (age, gender, livelihood, hobbies, place of residence, family and friends). (6) Take a large piece of paper showing the timeline and possible branching points. Mark the years when the story starts and ends with post-it notes on the timeline. Discuss this with the participants. Be ready to extend or shorten the timeline if the story requires. (7) Ask the participants to tell how the story starts, what motivates the characters to start using the service. Write down the events in the story on post-it notes and place them on the timeline. Move them if the participants wish. (8) Encourage the participants to tell the story to the end by taking into account the branching points. Ask them to also use different channels (e-mail, Facebook, etc.) in the story if relevant. Write down the channels on post-it notes. Together with the creative secretary encourage the users to tell their own real-life stories. Give room for the creative secretary to ask questions as well. (9) When the story is ready on the timeline, go through it with the group so that the users are role-playing the characters. If the group is not particularly relaxed or talkative go through the story yourself. (10) Ask the creative secretary to facilitate the wrap-up on the insights and concept ideas s/he had during the storytelling. (11) Repeat 3 to 9 if you have time.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="158" page="10" column="2">4.4. Analysis and reporting</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" page="10" column="2">Since the method provides a different type of user information, we determined that the best way to proceed with the data after the sessions is to write transcriptions from the video recordings. The moderators and creative secretaries can subsequently have a workshop where the transcriptions are reviewed and insights from them are written on post-it notes. The insights are placed on the wall and categorised in the form of an affinity diagram (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Beyer and Holtzblatt, 1998</xref>). The affinity diagram itself is already very valuable input for the design process. The designers can take with them the most interesting findings already from the workshop and do not need to wait for the report to be finished. We have, irregardless, written a report that includes current use situations from real-life stories, ‘what if’ use situations from the story, motivations, opinions and attitudes, and service ideas. The report includes many user quotes from the transcriptions in order to enhance empathy. The report is something that designers and service providers can return to even when the actual case is over. Moreover, it can be sent to a wider audience in their respective organisations.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="161" page="10" column="2">5. Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" page="10" column="2">Having tested the Storytelling Group method in three service design cases that were at differing stages of design, we feel that the method is very flexible and can provide concrete input for service design as well as enhance overall customer understanding. According to our experience, there are at least three aspects in the Storytelling Group method that makes it suitable for service design:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">(1) it allows an exploration of customer journeys also with a very long-time perspective (2) it makes it possible to explore the whole needed service ecosystem as part of people’s everyday practices (3) it combines user research and future-oriented design, so it is easier to argue for service design projects where designers should have concrete design results from the very beginning.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="167" page="10" column="2">However, we see some challenges with the method. First, the method requires more personnel than a regular focus group. Second, the method requires the creative secretary who is experienced with identifying design opportunities from user stories and being able to guide focus group type of discussions. However, these two requirements are compensated by the varied type of user information that can meet different needs in service design processes. <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Third challenge of the method lies in the different types of realism with which it deals. If the service provider and the designer accept that some of the user information the method provides is collaboratively created not only explicitly stated user requirements but also subjective desires and dreams that can be utilised as inspiration, the method is then appropriate.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="165" page="11" column="1">230</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="166" page="11" column="1">A. Kankainen et al.</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="168" page="11" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">We want to thank Tekes (the Finnish Funding Agency for Technology and Innovation) and the companies that have been funding our research: Kone, OP, Palmu Inc, Idean and Sanoma Entertainment. The research was conducted in two Tekes projects: eXtreme Design and Social Video. We would also thank all the other partners of these projects. Moreover, special thanks to Peter Kaario, Sofia Johansson, Elina Noppari and Sami Vihavainen who participated in organising and moderating the Storytelling Group sessions with us.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="170" page="11" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="11" column="1">Beyer, H. and Holtzblatt, K., 1998. Contextual design: defining customer-centered systems. San Francisco: Morgan Kaufmann.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="11" column="1">Blomqvist, J. and Holmlid, S., 2009. Exemplars in service design. In: the proceedings of nordic service design conference, November 2009, Oslo.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="11" column="1">Brandt, E., 2006. Designing exploratory design games: a framework for participation in participatory design? In: the proceedings of participatory design conference 2006, 1–5 August 2006. Italia: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="11" column="1">Brandt, E. and Grunnet, C., 2000. Evoking the future: drama and props in user centered design. In: the proceedings of the participatory design conference 2000, 28 November–1 December 2000, New York, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Cooper, A., 1999. The inmates are running the asylum. USA: Macmillan.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="11" column="1">Diana, C., Pacenti, E., and Tassi, R., 2009. Visualities. Communication tools for (service) design. In: the proceedings of first Nordic conference on service design and service innovation, 24–26 November 2009, Oslo, Norway.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="11" column="1">Dindler, C., et al., 2005. Mission from Mars: a method for exploring user requirements for children in a narrative space. In: the proceedings of the 2005 conference on interaction design and children, 8–10 June, Boulder, CO, 40–47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="11" column="1">Dindler, C. and Iversen, O., 2007. Fictional inquiry – design collaboration in shared narrative space. International Journal of CoDesign, 3 (4), 213–234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="11" column="1">Flanagan, J.C., 1954. The critical incident technique. Psychological Bulletin, 51 (4), 327–358.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="11" column="1">Goffman, E., 1963. Behavior in public places: notes on the social organization of gatherings. New York: The Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="11" column="1">Gaver, W., Dunne, T., and Pacenti, E., 1999. Cultural probes. Interactions, 6 (1), 21–29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="11" column="1">Hanington, B.M., 2003. Methods in the making: a perspective on the state of human research in design. Design Issues, 9 (4), 9–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="11" column="1">Iacucci, G., Kuutti, K., and Ranta, M., 2000. On the move with a magic thing: role playing in the design of mobile services and devices. In: the Proceeding of the DIS2000, designing interactive systems, 17–19 August. New York: ACM Press, 193–202.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="11" column="2">Johansson, M., 2005. Participatory inquiry – collaborative design. Thesis (PhD). School of Engineering, Blekinge Institute of Technology, Sweden.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="11" column="2">Kankainen, A., 2006. Finding uses for new technology. Moving with a magic thing. User Experience, 5 (3), 4–6.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="11" column="2">Keinonen, T., 2009. Design method – instrument, competence of agenda? Multiple ways to design research. In: Swiss design research network symposium 09, 12–13 November 2009, Lugano, Switzerland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="11" column="2">Kuniavsky, M., 2003. Observing the user experience. A practitioner’s guide to user research. San Francisco: Morgan Kaufmann Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="11" column="2">Lundberg, J. and Arvola, M., 2007. Lessons learned from facilitation in collaborative design. In: the proceedings of AUIC2007, 30 January–2 February, Ballarat, Australia.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Mattelma  ̈ ki, T., 2006. Design probes. Thesis (PhD), Publication Series of the University of Art and Design Helsinki A69, Finland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Mattelma  ̈ ki, T., 2007. Yhteissuunnittelu ja osallistuva suunnittelu. In: E. Kaasinen and L. Norros, eds. A  ̈ lykka ̈iden ympa  ̈risto ̈jen suunnittelu. Kohti ekologista systeemiajattelua. Helsinki: Teknologiainfo Teknova, 231–236.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Ma  ̈ kela  ̈ , A. and Mattelma  ̈ ki, T., 2002. Collecting stories on user experiences to inspire design – a pilot. In: W.S. Green and P. Jordan, eds. Pleasure with products: beyond usability. London: Taylor &amp; Francis, 333–344.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="11" column="2">Mossberg, L. and Nissen Johanssen, E., 2007. Storytelling Marknadsfo ̈ring I upplevelseindustrin. Pozkal Poland: Studentlitteratur.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="11" column="2">Pruitt, J. and Grudin, J., 2003. Personas: practice and theory. In: the proceedings of the 2003 conference on designing for user experience, San Francisco.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Sanders, E.B.-N. and Dandavate, U., 1999. Design for experiencing: new tools. In: the proceedings of the first international conference on design and emotion. Delft, The Netherlands: Delft University of Technology.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="11" column="2">Shuler, D. and Namioka, A. eds., 1993. Participatory design. Principles and practices. Hillsdale, NJ: LEA Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">Strom, G., 2007. Stories with emotions and conflicts drive development of better interactions in industrial software projects. In: the proceedings of the 19th Australasian conference on computer-human interaction, OzCHI 2007, 28–30 November 2007, Adelaide, Australia. New York, NY: ACM press, 115–121.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="11" column="2">Triantafyllakos, G., Palaigeorgiou, G., and Tsoukalas, I.A., 2010. Fictional characters in participatory design sessions: introducing the ‘design alter egos’ technique. Interacting with Computers, 22 (3), 165–175.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="11" column="2">Vargo, S. and Lusch, R., 2008. From goods to service(s): divergences and convergences of logics. Industrial Mar- keting Management, 37, 254–259.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="11" column="2">Verhaegh, J., et al., 2006. On the design of Camelot, an outdoor game for children. In: the proceedings of the 2006 conference on interaction design and children. ACM press, 9–16.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="11" column="2">Wasson, C., 2002. Collaborative work: integrating the roles of ethnographers and designers. In: S. Squires and B.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="11" column="2">Byrne, eds. Creating breakthrough ideas: the collaboration of anthropologists and designers in the product development industry. Westport: Bergein Garvey.</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
