<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>97a61162675ace3dbbc33fb5fbf2a625c9c78abb1c94bdde509eb34232de5cad</job>
    <base_name>62si</base_name>
    <doi>10.1007/978-1-84996-223-0_1</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">1 Researching Digital Design</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Dagny Stuedahl</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Andrew Morrison</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Christina Mörtberg</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Tone Bratteteig</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="7" confidence="possible">The emerging field of digital design research is heterogeneous, encompassing a multiplicity of practices, theories and methods. One source of this heterogeneity is that design as a concept takes different meanings in the context of different design practices, be it the design of software, urban spaces, web pages or industrial products; as does ‘the digital’ when integrated within different types of design. Another source of heterogeneity is the variety of research traditions, theories and methodologies that meet in digital design research. This book explores the multiplicity and heterogeneity of ‘digital things’, design practices, and (inter) disciplinary approaches. In this introductory chapter we seek to map out the positions we come from and how we try to confront and combine them. In many respects, digital design research emerges in a space between several well-established design disciplines related to the digital. In taking up the emerging and dynamic qualities and aspects of digital design, we draw on selected perspectives from informatics, science and technology studies, and ‘new media’, and communication studies. The viewpoint we bring from informatics is firmly anchored in Participatory Design (PD) and Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW) which, from their beginnings, focused on how digital technologies become embedded in human practices – situated use. This not only challenges the engineering approach to design but also the traditional focus on the product of design. The humanities bring to digital design research their interest in understanding how the digital shapes cultural modes and means of expression. Several developments strengthen the connections between these perspectives, each of which has its own history of inter- disciplinarity. One concerns the ‘naturalization’ of digital technologies in society and culture, which makes it impossible to isolate digital design from the larger socio-cultural context in which it occurs. Connected to this is the fact that the ‘users’ and uses of digital design have changed – from professionals in different work environments and computing specialists to the broad range of people engaging in ‘social computing’, gaming, art, as well as applications that support citizens’ participation in their communities. Finally, the technologies studied in digital design research are emerging and further evolve with use. This makes it necessary to pay attention to how social and cultural aspects are inscribed in the technologies.</article-title>
      </title-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6" page="1" column="1">The emerging field of digital design research is heterogeneous, encompassing a multiplicity of practices, theories and methods. One source of this heterogeneity is that design as a concept takes different meanings in the context of different design practices, be it the design of software, urban spaces, web pages or industrial products; as does ‘the digital’ when integrated within different types of design. Another source of heterogeneity is the variety of research traditions, theories and methodologies that meet in digital design research. This book explores the multiplicity and heterogeneity of ‘digital things’, design practices, and (inter) disciplinary approaches. In this introductory chapter we seek to map out the positions we come from and how we try to confront and combine them. In many respects, digital design research emerges in a space between several well-established design disciplines related to the digital. In taking up the emerging and dynamic qualities and aspects of digital design, we draw on selected perspectives from informatics, science and technology studies, and ‘new media’, and communication studies. The viewpoint we bring from informatics is firmly anchored in Participatory Design (PD) and Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW) which, from their beginnings, focused on how digital technologies become embedded in human practices – situated use. This not only challenges the engineering approach to design but also the traditional focus on the product of design. The humanities bring to digital design research their interest in understanding how the digital shapes cultural modes and means of expression. Several developments strengthen the connections between these perspectives, each of which has its own history of inter- disciplinarity. One concerns the ‘naturalization’ of digital technologies in society and culture, which makes it impossible to isolate digital design from the larger socio-cultural context in which it occurs. Connected to this is the fact that the ‘users’ and uses of digital design have changed – from professionals in different work environments and computing specialists to the broad range of people engaging in ‘social computing’, gaming, art, as well as applications that support citizens’ participation in their communities. Finally, the technologies studied in digital design research are emerging and further evolve with use. This makes it necessary to pay attention to how social and cultural aspects are inscribed in the technologies.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="8" page="1" column="1">3</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="9" page="1" column="1">I. Wagner et al. (eds.), Exploring Digital Design: Multi-Disciplinary Design Practices, Computer Supported Cooperative Work, DOI 10.1007/978-1-84996-223-0_1, © Springer-Verlag London Limited 2010</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="10" page="2" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" page="2" column="1">The design research presented in this book is grounded in a set of interdisciplinary research projects. Some of these engage with technology design, some are centred on understanding user experiences, while others focus on the development of design-related theories. These projects provide the main material for the book. Their diversity illustrates the diversity of digital design research. Their discussion from multiple disciplinary perspectives provides means of understanding better the meeting points and differences between approaches ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1.1" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1.1</xref>).<marker type="block"/> One of the projects we discuss is about participatory design, which aims at designing a mobile system to allow severely ill children to report symptoms and problems to the clinicians. Another project explores rhetoric and the concept of genre to design for location-based simulations, cartography and encyclopaedic information. A third project, also participatory in its approach, focuses on the design of mixed reality tools and a tangible user interface in support of collaborative urban planning. Two projects engage in and reflect on ‘communication design’, involving museum visitors in exhibitions with mobile telephones and social media; utilizing digital technologies in a dance performance. In Exploring Digital Design we ask how we can frame and unpack our multiple understandings of digital tools and environments and the practices and expressions<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> that digital technologies enable. What is the nature of the knowledge about the digital that our perspectives can build? how can practice-based research from humanities and informatics conjoin (and diverge) in the practices and analyses of digital design? Are our findings different from those of other, related fields, such as visual design or urban planning, and in which ways do our specific theoretical and methodological approaches contribute to this? What are the relationships between modes of knowing and analysis drawn from the insights and practices of, respectively, designers and researchers? Do the conceptual and methodological encounters we undertake in this book open up fruitful theoretical and methodological venues, and, if yes, how can these be taken further into new digital design (research) projects? The collection of chapters in this book is geared towards a multidisciplinary audi- ence of researchers and designers. For researchers, it offers a range of approaches, concepts and methods for inquiry into digital design. For designers, it reveals some of the ways in which design research into the digital may be framed theoretically and carried out in practice. The book also has, as a core readership, graduate students in various disciplines, emphasizing distinctions between and connections across disciplinary domains that take time to get to know deeply and use in research. The book has two main parts. The first looks into research practices, theoretical frameworks and a diversity of methods. The second examines specific topics and cases that involve both digital design products and processes. The title Exploring Digital Design highlights the importance we place on transgressing disciplinary boundaries and relations in reforming digital design research. When mapping out our disciplinary homes and the multiplicity of our approaches, confronting and combining, we realize that it is impossible and maybe even not desirable to ‘speak in one voice’. Our research into digital design presents and argues for perspectives that are positioned at the margins of many disciplines as well as in between them. Our basic groundings in informatics and the humanities are themselves interdisciplinary positions within these disciplinary frameworks.<marker type="block"/> The role of the digital in societal daily life, the possibilities of participation and the access to information that today’s digital technologies represent, is no longer only about the use of a computer or a well-defined artefact. It is about participating in society, it is about marking and tagging, manipulating and interacting, creating and enjoying – and it is about being connected in informational and communicational relations. The digital comes into being through human and social agency, even where the computational may be designed for automation or for system-generated configurations. We argue that the ‘digital’ itself has to be understood as design material, as concretized layers of abstractions and representations, which are part of material and discursive practices (see Chapter 2). Digital design calls for an expanded concept of design, as working with the digital is different from other forms of designing. The digital opens up a discussion between<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> research approaches grounded in technological design and in socio-cultural and humanistic inquiries. This is not entirely new. Twenty years ago the Scandinavian tradition had already located design in the larger social, cultural, political context of use (nygaard 1986, 1996), inviting practitioners from different disciplines to provide insights into the design and use of digital artefacts, systems, and media. Also, connections between informatics and the humanities have a long history. Linguistics, semiotics and philosophy of language are important in developing programming languages, while sociolinguistics and, for example, Speech Act Theory have played a role in the development of computer support for collaboration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Flores et al. 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Winograd 1979</xref>). In this book we strive to take a step further. On the one hand, we do so by looking at digital design through the lens of a broader range of research traditions relevant to the understanding of design practice and the situated use of digital designs (see Chapter 3). On the other hand, we move from ‘classical’ studies of systems design in support of specific work practices to emerging fields of digital design. This also calls for a reframing of the notion of use, shifting attention from a narrow concept of product use to the context and practices of use. Design is a situated social practice, and the designed artefacts can only be fully understood in use. Taking into account the evolving and often-participatory character of digital designs, we even have to consider designing for design after design, the design that users carry out in use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Ehn 2007</xref>; Telier et al. (forthcoming)). We can also look at situated use as where the idea behind the artefact and the reality of use meet. The explorations in digital design also lead us to revisit the political and ethical issues that receive attention at the meeting ground between informatics and the critical social sciences. The commitment of Participatory Design (PD) to enhancing users’ autonomy implies the responsibility to design in ways that enables people to understand the systems they are part of, and puts an emphasis on transparency and critique as parts of digital design (van der <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Velden et al. 2009</xref>). The political and ethical sides of PD resonate with political art, which seeks to express elements of provocation as well as reflection. This focus on autonomy and political analysis characterizes the multidisciplinary areas of PD and Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), where researchers and designers question the technology from a deep understanding of the context, in which it will be integrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Bjerknes and Bratteteig 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Bowers et al. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Luff and heath 1998</xref>). researchers in digital design need to understand a range of design practices, sometimes even participate as designers in the practices they research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Bjerknes and Bratteteig 1987</xref>). research in CSCW is concerned with how understandings of material practices can inform design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Schmidt and Bannon 1992</xref>; randall et al. 2007). Both use and design are studied as collaborative practices, and the empirical and theoretical studies of such practices constitute the basis for designing better computer support for work (see Chapter 4). research in PD involves users as co-designers in the design process as a way to design artefacts and systems that the users themselves consider of benefit to their activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Ehn 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Bjerknes and Bratteteig 1995</xref>). Participation in the design process has been seen as a strategy for giving users more power of decision in design, and a range of methods for PD has been developed<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> (greenbaum and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Kyng 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Bødker et al. 2004</xref>). As technology changes, so does technology design and use. PD and CSCW change when the technology opens up for new kinds of functions and interactions and when the use contexts reach beyond work contexts to include other social arenas. hence, PD has been extended to new fields, yielding creative design ideas for ubiquitous computing, embodied interaction, mobility, and conviviality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Wagner et al. 2009</xref>). These commitments are unfortunately still not a mainstream view in informatics. however, many of the inventions in informatics stem from stretching the technology to meet the wishes and needs of the real world. Understanding the contextual complexities opens up a whole range of new design ideas. We have to add here that foundational to PD and CSCW is a deep commitment to socially embedding technologies in human practice and that both fields of research make use of a diversity of social science methods, among them ethnography. There is a strong overlap with the humanities here, which will also be made visible in the book. humanistic and socio-cultural approaches to the digital represent a variety of perspectives and theories, partly interdisciplinary and partly with a strong disciplinary history. In this book we draw on new Media Studies and Cultural Studies that partly embed Science and Technology Studies (STS) perspectives, emphasizing connections to performance and electronic art. Moving on from an early concern with media and communication, especially literary hypertext (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Landow 1992</xref>) and aesthetics, humanists have questioned the relation between humans and computer interfaces based on concepts such as meaning making, mediation, identity, and related historical and philosophical connections. Scholars in the humanities have joined colleagues from other domains in building interdisciplinary design perspectives where attention is given to new ‘textual’ environments (hayles 1999; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Bolter 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Skjulstad 2007</xref>), the design and analysis of environments that transverse mode, time and space (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Lemke 2002</xref>, 2005), as well as multimodal discourses related to the digital (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Morrison 2010</xref>). This has included tropes and genres of gaming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Corneliussen and Walker 2008</xref>), mixed reality artistic expressions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Birringer 2002</xref>; hansen 2006; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Morrison et al. 2009</xref>), and performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Schiller 2006</xref>). There is a bulk of studies on identity, youth and digitally mediated communication – online and via mobile devices, including the so-called social media (Lundby 2009). The humanities also engage in research on designing digital conceptual tools for mediated meaning making in museums (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Pierroux 2008</xref>), digital environments for experiences and engagement with cultural heritage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Stuedahl 2009</xref>), as well as discursive and communicative digital environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Morrison 2010</xref>). An additional area where such connections are being made is in the uptake of digital technologies in practices and studies of literacy and learning, where digital discourses are seen as both learning and communication design (see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Morrison 2003</xref>). The new media environments are no longer restricted to ‘texts’ and ‘screens’ but involve physical artefacts and the human body within physical space, as well as their connections to the digital. This means a shift from written and spoken text to other modes of expression and perception and requires the development of methods of multimodal analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Morrison 2010</xref>). At the same time, we notice changing understandings of the role of form that require a distributed aesthetics, which deals<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> with the endless relaying of practices and experiences that are related to the digital. This gives us an understanding of mediations as based on loops of dispersal instead of singular ‘end use’ of information. We therefore need to talk about formations rather than form related to the media we study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Munster and Lovink 2005</xref>). These formations include processes of social network formations, which obviously challenge the classical, individual ways of thinking in the humanities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Andersen 2005</xref>).<marker type="block"/> These works in ‘new media studies’, multimodal discourse and performance, have not been widely cited in digital design research, nor have they often been accessed in reference to digital design established in CSCW and PD. This is one of the connections we try to shape in this book. While the objects of study do not differ so much from those undertaken from a PD and CSCW perspective, there is a difference in focus and epistemological grounding. A humanist approach to understanding these new media environments spans design issues like information architecture, web design, structure, and aes- thetic functions to the dynamics of mediated communication, the interplay between using and producing, with a focus on articulation and interpretation. It is especially in the contact zones between humanistic views and technology studies that digital design research shows the potential of humanistic inquiry, and the ways an already complex multidisciplinarity can open out to further complementarity and reflexivity through new design practices and their critiques.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> The various views we propose in this book point to different layers and methods of analysis that the complexity of digital products demands (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1.2" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1.2</xref>). The illustration is suggested as an overview for our readers to navigate with and between the concepts and practices on which we build. This is not an invitation to eclecticism, and we argue for considering the epistemological and ontological bases when trying to merge and mix different theories and approaches. These perspectives will be presented in more depth throughout the book, in par- ticular in Chapters 2–4, where readers can find more references to core literature.<marker type="block"/> From an anthropologist’s point of view, hastrup (2005) points to design being traditionally defined as belonging to creative approaches to knowledge construction in arts. She emphasizes that, as knowledge in general can be understood in multiple ways, we also can understand design knowledge as created in different ways. hence, there are a variety of possibilities to connect design and research. Within CSCW research there is an ongoing debate about ethnography and how it contributes to design, and if studies of work and technology can be considered design research. A similar discussion needs to be conducted in the humanities. Knowledge construction in design and design research can be approached in multiple ways, and the question of what we know should be tightly connected with questions of how we know it. reflexivity in research is a must when it comes to the kind of multidisciplinary projects we consider in this book. The different research traditions we build on represent different views on what we know, what we can know, and how we know it. here, we briefly discuss if and how such multidisciplinary reflexivity can be anchored in digital design. We start with noting that reflexivity differs from the notion of reflection, which is used in design studies. The seminal work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Schön (1983, 1987)</xref>, in which he described design as a reflective process, serves as a starting point. Schön distin- guished between reflection-in-action: part of the action (‘thinking on our feet’), and reflection-on-action: after the action, and developed an epistemology of reflective practice. reflection-on-practice, Schön states, yields a critical view on how the designer’s own tacit understanding may have affected the design work. Several of the design research approaches presented in this book have long traditions with this kind of reflection. PD research, for example, emphasizes discussions about how alternative and even conflicting views among users and designers are voiced and given power. This includes reflection on the political and ethical premises for so doing, as well as on the practical and emotional constraints such a practice meets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Bjerknes and Bratteteig 1987</xref>, 1988). The humanities traditionally pay attention to the past rather than present and future events. The temporal and spatial detachment of the researcher and the studied object results in after-the-fact reflection, not unlike reflection-on-action. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Liestøl (2003)</xref> introduces the notion of pre-reflection, indicating two steps of reflection:<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> reflection related to the process of modifying and reflection related to the reception of the modified. These two reflective steps define the details of a humanistic reflective process and help humanists discuss the practice of reflexivity in digital design research. reflexive explorations in the humanities consider, for example, the notion of culture, on which digital designs and their analysis are based. They include a critical reflection on the grounding of research in semiotics and different discourse theories. The distinction between reflection and reflexivity is relevant for understanding the encounters of multiple disciplines that this book explores. reflection focuses on understanding the assumptions, biases, and perspectives that underlie the research, and it is such self-inspection that a ‘reflective practitioner’ of research or design is expected to undertake. But reflection requires moving a step further from this reflected positionality of the researcher in order to make his/her self-invisibility visible (haraway 1997). reflexivity, goes beyond self-vision, and includes epistemological questions and contextual conditions of understanding that are at work, and how these are rooted in practices of collaboration and negotiation, as well as in decisions affecting the exclusion and inclusion of perspectives. Weber (2003: ix) states that reflexive researchers consider ‘the interplay between the research methods they have a propensity to employ in their work and the sort of theories they build to account for the phenomena that are in their focus’. This book attempts a reflexive exploration of the diversity of approaches to digital design research that we seek to confront and combine. The intention of this book has not been to generate a synthesized, grand and unified theory of (digital) design. The authors have different and mixed academic backgrounds: informatics, information systems, pedagogy, anthropology, discourse analysis, linguistics, semiotics (new) media studies and literary theory, among others. We strongly believe that this diversity is a strength when moving into critical and reflective analysis of digital design and its contexts of construction and use. none of the perspectives or theories put forward in this book claims priority over others. The fact that our research is grounded in different epistemological traditions has been one of the main challenges in writing collaboratively.<marker type="block"/> The book has two main parts. In the first part, we discuss how changes in technology inform digital design research practices, methods and theories. These descriptions of change provide a background for engaging in multidisciplinary dialogues aimed at developing a better conceptual grip on the relations and meetings within and between disciplinary views. A considerable collaborative composition and multidisciplinary authorship stands behind this first part of the book. In Chapter 2, ‘research Practices in Digital Design’, we discuss changes in design research practices that are related to the digital. By presenting four different design cases, the chapter demonstrates how research by designing is explored in<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> relation to several practical design challenges, involving different design objectives and disciplinary perspectives. The chapter describes the PD approach used for the design of a mobile interaction device for seriously ill children in hospitals. The second case covers the design of a novel interface for embodied and tangible interaction that weaves together the technical and human activity. The third case concerns the design of a multi-level interface as part of a multidisciplinary research project in choreography, digital media and learning. The fourth case takes up chil- dren’s interactions with mobile phones in a cultural historical museum setting with a focus on social media. The last part of the chapter introduces some concepts from design research that we find useful for describing design practices. In Chapter 3, ‘Analytical Perspectives’, we provide an overview of selected theories and approaches to digital design research that may be applied in inquiry into its emergent and multidisciplinary character. We outline and explain key concepts and their relevance for understanding digital design practice, drawing on CSCW, informatics, the humanities, the social sciences and their different traditions. The chapter argues that, while we may draw on accepted disciplinary knowledge, digital technology-enhanced design and its contexts, uses and communicative potentials are in need of further theorizing that integrates the interplay of theory and practice. Each of the main sections moves to connect, but also extend, a general design research literature and to do so with respect to already-mapped areas in which digital design is researched. Aspects of the perspectives that are presented in this chapter are taken up and further contextualized and explored in the second part of the book. Methodological perspectives in digital design are discussed in Chapter 4, entitled ‘Methods that Matter in Digital Design research’. These methodological perspectives are grounded in the conceptual analysis, construction, and reflection undertaken in the previous chapters. In this chapter we describe design methods from a range of disciplinary origins, and we show how they can be applied to digital design, combining them in novel ways. Concrete examples from projects are given for each of the methods so as to enable readers to understand how, and with what results, they have been used in different contexts. Again, elements of these methods are taken up in the second part of the book. In the second part of the book, we have assembled a set of individual contributions that have been written to illustrate selected aspects of digital design research. Several of the chapters are co-authored, reflecting the arguments for multidisciplinarity outlined above. All the contributions explore the connection between research and practice in the field of digital design. We offer these chapters as instances of our own grapplings with emerging fields and complex design problems. They are also reflexive takes on research methods in digital design research. In Chapter 5, entitled ‘A Matter of Digital Materiality’, Tone Bratteteig discusses understandings of digital material and its implications for designing and building digital artefacts and systems. Bratteteig discusses software and hardware as materials for design, and argues that the digital has characteristics that influence the design process as well as the tools used in the design. The chapter proposes some basic properties of digital electronic systems, and examines their consequences for<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> the possibilities and limitations of digital design. The chapter discusses how the digital also characterizes digital design results, artefacts, systems and media, and how conceptualizations of the digital enhance our understanding of our digital environment. Finally, these views are taken back to the design process, to reflect on how the digital material influences the design process. relations between genre and design are discussed by gunnar Liestøl in Chapter 6, ‘On Mobility, Localization and the Possibility of Digital genre Design’. This chapter concerns a potential convergence of mobility, broadband and positioning technologies. genre design is suggested as a possible method, based on a model of genre constitution (and change), including the context of situation and formal and substantive features that are informed by studies in rhetoric, now transposed to digital design through the notion of inventio or heuretics. A prototype of such an approach is presented with respect to web-based learning and the media types that offered means for building digital genres. This is connected to the convergence of cartography and the changing character of encyclopaedias and travel guides. The chapter closes with examples of the suggested genre of ‘situated simulations’, referring to a Viking ship excavation and burial mound, and an ancient greek battle site. Both explorations indicate the importance of sketching and creativity in the ongoing design of digital genres informed by theories and textual and communicative legacies in the humanities. In Chapter 7, ‘Unreal Estate: Digital Design and Mediation in Marketing Urban residency’, Andrew Morrison and Synne Skjulstad venture into one of the intriguing yet elusive qualities of the digital: it is ‘immaterial’ but has textual materiality that is a critical part of the design for engaged participation. The authors unpack the term ‘unreal estate’, one they have coined to refer to hyperreal digital simulation on the web that markets new urban residency. Digital tools are used to design new apart- ments, to market them and to mediate their sale and circulation, as part of the wider digital cultural industries. These digital simulations are generated to project and market these as-yet-unbuilt properties. The online texts are examples of digitally designed and mediated persuasive discourse that, from a communication design view, connects textual aspects to mediated use. The researchers discuss this in terms of tertiary artefacts drawn from Activity Theory, multimodal discourse theory, textual analysis and social semiotics, while yet placing considerably more weight on the digital. The chapter contributes a communication design perspective to the under- researched area of digital branding and online advertising. Matters of designing for discursive performativity are addressed in Chapter 8, ‘Whisperings in the Undergrowth: Communication Design, Online Social networking and Discursive Performativity’, by Andrew Morrison, Even Westvang and Simen Skogsrud. This chapter concerns the design and analysis of the emerging domain of digital design and communication related to social software. The chapter is itself a rhetorical experiment. It is co-compiled by a researcher and two designers with a long history of collaboration in different settings related to digital design. The text toggles between expository, analytic discourse, contextual descriptions, screen grabs and quotations. The chapter situates the development and iterative designing of a calendaring and social networking software application called<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> Underskog for use in a capital city. Theories from applied linguistics and post- structuralist discourse studies are connected to the practice of programmer-designers, and situated within a sociocultural approach to digital design and ‘new media’. The chapter demonstrates that digitally mediated communication is itself an emergent partner of design for digitally mediated meaning making. Digital design also encourages a focus on sustainability and long-term perspectives in design. This is discussed by Christina Mörtberg, Dagny Stuedahl and Pirjo Elovaara in Chapter 9, ‘Designing for Sustainable Ways of Living with Technologies’. With a focus on standards, formats and routines, the chapter discusses social and cultural aspects of sustainable design and use of digital technologies. The chapter builds on Donna haraway’s actor-network theory, formulated in the shape of a cat’s cradle, in discussions of examples from research projects related to a municipal accounts department and a cultural heritage reconstruction. These projects are analy- sed in order to unfold different layers of social and cultural sustainability as a design principle that can be applied. The projects also relate sustainability to design and use. The chapter argues that social and cultural aspects of traditions and values play a role for standards surviving in the long term by addressing the question: how can we anchor social and cultural sustainability as a principle inside design practice? The last chapter, ‘Epilogue: A Multidisciplinary Take on Design’ is added as an afterthought of the book’s two parts: the inter- and multidisciplinary Part I aiming to build a common ground across and beyond our disciplinary starting points, and Part II where we illustrate how deep disciplinary knowledge offers new insights to the transdisciplinary field of digital design. We are particularly proud that this book combines humanities and informatics in new ways and thus moves digital design research forward. We have entitled the book Exploring Digital Design. The title refers to our view that research into digital design needs to acknowledge established practices and be open to importing new concepts and methods. Appreciating the close relations between design and design research, digital design research also takes on its own logic as design and research processes unfold. We expect that readers find things they know but also new arguments, some text that is easy and some that offers challenges, obvious points and more intricate arguments. Above all, we hope that our readers will appreciate the diversity and multiperspectival reasoning that we suggest for research exploring digital design.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1.1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62si.page_002.image_01.png" thmb="62si.page_002.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="14" page="2" column="1">Fig. 1.1 Digital designs span a variety of situated practices and uses. From top left to right: Location-based simulations with smart phones; children producing their own ‘readings’ of cultural historical museum; investigation of design of tangible user interfaces; and children testing a mobile hospital system prototype in a real-life setting</caption>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="16" page="2" column="1">4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="17" page="3" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="19" page="3" column="1">Perspectives on Research into Digital Design</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="21" page="3" column="1">5</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="22" page="4" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="35" page="4" column="1">6</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="5" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="55" page="5" column="1">7</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="6" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1.2">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62si.page_006.image_02.png" thmb="62si.page_006.image_02-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="61" page="6" column="1">Fig. 1.2 Outline of our multidisciplinary approaches to digital design research</caption>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="6" column="1">8</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="7" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="67" page="7" column="1">Reflexivity in Multidisciplinary Design Research</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="72" page="7" column="1">9</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="73" page="8" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="75" page="8" column="1">Outline of the Book</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="77" page="8" column="1">10</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="78" page="9" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="9" column="1">11</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="10" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="83" page="10" column="1">12</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="84" page="11" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="86" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="11" column="1">Andersen, P.B. (2005). Activity-based design. European Journal of Information Systems archive, 15(1), 9–25.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="11" column="1">Birringer, J. (2002). Dance and media technologies. PAJ: A Journal of Performance and Art Jan 2002 (PAJ 70), 24 (1), 84–93.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="89" page="11" column="1">Bjerknes, g., &amp; Bratteteig, T. (1987). Florence in wonderland. System development with nurses. In g. Bjerknes, P. Ehn &amp; M. Kyng (Eds.), Computers and democracy. A Scandinavian challenge (pp. 279–296). Aldershot: Avebury.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="11" column="1">Bjerknes, g., &amp; Bratteteig, T. (1988). The memoirs of two survivors— or evaluation of a computer system for cooperative work. In I. greif (Ed.), Proceedings of the 1988 ACM conference <marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> on computer-supported cooperative work, Portland, Oregon, USA (pp. 167–177). new York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" page="12" column="1">Bjerknes, g., &amp; Bratteteig, T. (1995). User participation and democracy. A discussion of Scandinavian research on systems development. Scandinavian Journal of Information Systems, 7(1), 73–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Bolter, J.D. (2001). Writing space: Computers, hypertext, and the remediation of print. Mahwah, n.J: Lawrence Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" page="12" column="1">Bowers, J., Button, g., &amp; Sharrock, W. (1995). Workflow from within and without: technology and cooperative work on the print industry shopfloor. In h. Marmolin, Y. Sundblad &amp; K. Schmidt (Eds.), Proceedings of the fourth conference on European conference on computer- supported cooperative work (ECSCW ’95), Stockholm, Sweden (pp. 51–66). norwell, MA: Kluwer.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="97" page="12" column="1">Bødker, K., Kensing, F., &amp; Simonsen, J. (2004). Participatory IT design: Designing for business and workplace realities. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="98" page="12" column="1">Corneliussen, h. g., &amp; Walker J. (Eds. 2008). Digital culture, play, and adentity: A world of warcraft reader. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="12" column="1">Ehn, P. (1989). Work-oriented design of computer artifacts. hillsdale, n J: Lawrence Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="100" page="12" column="1">Ehn, P. (2007). Design av alla? [Design by all?]. In S. Ilstedt hjelm (Ed.), Under ytan [Under the surface] (pp. 76–95). Stockholm: raster Förlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="101" page="12" column="1">Flores, F.; graves; M., hartfield, B., &amp; Winograd, T. (1988). Computer systems and the design of organizational interaction. Transactions on Office Information Systems, 6 (1–2), 153–172.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" page="12" column="1">greenbaum, J., &amp; Kyng, M. (Eds.). (1991). Design at work: Cooperative design of computer systems. hillsdale, nJ: Lawrence Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="103" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">hansen, M. B.n. (2006). Embodiment: the machinic and the human. Theory, Culture &amp; Society, 23 (2-3), 297–306.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="105" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">haraway, D. J. (1997). <email id="104">Modest_witness@second_millenium</email>. Female man©_meets_ oncomouseTM: Feminism and technoscience. new York and London: routledge.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">hastrup, K. (2005): Designforskning: Mellem materialitet og socialitet. Center for Designforskning, Copenhagen, Art Academy Architectural highschool, September 2005.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">hayles. C. (1999). How we became posthuman: Virtual bodies in cybernetics, literature and informatics. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" page="12" column="1">Landow, g. P. (1992). Hypertext: The convergence of contemporary critical theory and technology. Baltimore MD: The Johns hopkins University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" page="12" column="1">Lemke, J. (2002). Travels in hypermodality. Visual Communication, 1 (3), 229–325.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="12" column="1">Lemke, J. (2005). Place, pace &amp; meaning: Multimedia chronotopes. In S. norris &amp; r. Jones (Eds.), Discourse in action: Introducing mediated discourse analysis (pp. 110–112). routledge: London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" page="12" column="1">Liestøl, g. (2003). gameplay — from synthesis to analysis (and vice versa). Topics of construction and interpretation in digital media. In g. Liestøl, A. Morrison &amp; T. rasmussen (Eds.), Digital media revisited. Theoretical and conceptual innovations in digital domains (pp. 389–413). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Luff, P., &amp; heath, C. (1998). Mobility in collaboration. In I. greif (Ed.), Proceedings of the 1988 ACM conference on computer-supported cooperative work, Portland, Oregon, USA (pp. 305–331). new York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" page="12" column="1">Lundby, K. (Ed., 2008). Digital storytelling, mediatized stories: Self-representation in New Media. new York: Peter Lang.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" page="12" column="1">Morrison, A. (2003). From oracy to electracies: hypernarrative, place and multimodal discourses in learning. In g. Liestøl, A. Morrison &amp; T. rasmussen (Eds.), Digital media revisited: Theoretical and conceptual innovation in digital domains (pp. 115–154). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="115" page="12" column="1">Morrison, A. (2010). Composing multiply: Multimodal mediating artifacts, scopes of articulation and matters of alignment. In A. Morrison (Ed.), Inside multimodal composition. Cresskill nJ: hampton Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="116" page="12" column="1">Morrison, A., Andersson, g., Brečević, r., &amp; Skjulstad, S. (2009). Disquiet in the plasma. Digital Creativity, 20 (1–2), 3–20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" page="13" column="1">Munster, A., &amp; Lovink, g. (2005). Theses on distributed aesthetics. Or, what a network is not. Fibreculture Journal, Issue 7. Available on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue7/issue7_munster_" id="119">http://journal.fibreculture.org/issue7/issue7_munster_</ext-link> lovink.html</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">nygaard, K. (1986). Program Development as a Social Activity. In Information processing 86: proceedings of the IFIP 10th world computer congress, Dublin, Ireland (pp. 189-198). Amsterdam: north-holland.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">nygaard, K. (1996). “Those Were the Days”? Or “herioc Times Are here Again”?, IrIS Opening speech 10. August 1996, Scandinavian Journal of Information Systems, 8 (2), 91–108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="123" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Pierroux, P. (2008) Extending meaning from museum visits through the use of wikis and mobile blogging. In Proceedings international perspectives in the learning sciences (ICLS 2008), Utrecht, The netherlands, June 24–28 (9–11.)</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="124" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">randall, D.W., harper, r., &amp; rouncefield, M. (2007). Fieldwork for design: Theory and practice. London: Springer.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Schiller, g. (2006). Kinaesthetic traces across material forms: Stretching the screen’s stage. In S. Broadhurst &amp; J. Machon (Eds.), Performance and technology: Practices of verbal embodiment and interactivity (pp. 100–111). Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="126" page="13" column="1">Schmidt, K., &amp; L. Bannon (1992). Taking CSCW seriously. Supporting articulation work. Computer Supported Cooperative Work: The Journal of Collaborative Computing, 1(1), 7–40.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="127" page="13" column="1">Schön, D (1983). The reflective practitioner. How professionals think in action. new York: Basic Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="128" page="13" column="1">Schön, D. (1987). Educating the reflective practitioner. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="129" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Skjulstad, S. (2007). Communication design and motion graphics on the web. In Journal of Media Practice, 8(3), 359–378. doi: 10.1386/jmpr.8.3.359_1</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="13" column="1">Stuedahl, D. (2009). Digital Cultural heritage Engagement - A new research Field for Ethnology. Ethnologia Scandinavica. 39, 67–81.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="13" column="1">Telier, A. (T. Binder, P. Ehn, g. De Michelis, g. Jacucci, P. Linde, &amp; I. Wagner). (forthcoming). Design things. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="13" column="1">van der Velden, M., Bratteteig, T., Finken, S., &amp; Mörtberg, C. (2009). Autonomy and automation in an information society for all. In J. Molka-Danielsen (Ed.), Proceedings of the 32nd information systems research seminar in Scandinavia, IRIS 32, Inclusive Design, Molde University College, Molde, norway, August 9–12, 2009. ISBn 978-82-7962-120-1.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="13" column="1">Wagner, I., Basile, M., Ehrenstrasser, L. Maquil, V., Terrn, J.-J., &amp; Wagner, M. (2009). Supporting community engagement in the city: urban planning in the Mr-tent. In J. M. Carroll (Ed.), Proceedings of the fourth international conference on communities and technologies (C&amp;T ’09), University Park, PA, USA (pp. 185–194). new York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="13" column="1">Weber, r. (2003). The reflexive researcher. Editors comment, MIS Quarterly, 27 (4), v–xi.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="13" column="1">Winograd, T. (1979). Beyond programming languages. Communications of the ACM, 22(7), 391–401.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91" page="11" column="1">13</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92" page="12" column="1">ExPLOrIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="117" page="12" column="1">14</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="118" page="13" column="1">rESEArChIng DIgITAL DESIgn</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="136" page="13" column="1">15</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
