<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>56f1d06cbe03ff2f5c4310268ddc33c9744a6a96453b48d49acfd42f4dc50ffa</job>
    <base_name>62ik</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/iwc/iws016</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">© The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of The British Computer Society. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: <email id="1">journals.permissions@oup.com</email> doi:10.1093/iwc/iws016</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Theatre, PlayDoh and Comic Strips: Designing Organic User Interfaces with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Janet C. Read</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Daniel Fitton</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Matthew Horton</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="8">Child Computer Interaction Group, University of Central Lancashire, Preston PR1 2HE, UK ∗ Corresponding author: <email id="7">jcread@uclan.ac.uk</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="10" confidence="possible">This paper presents the process and outputs from a participatory design activity with secondary school children whose task was to design organic user interfaces (OUIs) for use in energy-aware applications. Although experienced in participatory design sessions with children and teenagers, the design team faced three new challenges in this work: how to convey the idea of OUIs, how to facilitate the pupils to design OUIs and how to interpret the OUI design ideas. To convey the ideas of OUI, the Obstructed Theatre method, used in other studies with children and teenagers, was used. In this work, the salient features of the OUI conveyed in the theatre were: its malleability, its potential to bend and change shape, its association with the body and its novelty. To facilitate the design, three scenarios of increasing user interface complexity were conveyed in the theatre; and three different media (i) slime and pipe cleaners, (ii) PlayDoh and small Lego bricks, (iii) fabric and sticky shapes that afforded the creation of designs representing future organic interactive technologies were deployed. To enable the design team to make sense of the resulting designs, a Comic Strip approach was used to capture the changes in the designs as they demonstrated interaction. The paper explores this work from three perspectives; first, the effectiveness of the Obstructed Theatre approach to convey requirements of OUIs, secondly, the effectiveness of the three media used in the design sessions to encourage design solutions for OUIs and thirdly, the quality and relevance of the design ideas generated in the sessions and communicated to the design team using the Comic Strips and their applicability to other contexts. The paper concludes with some thoughts on methods and materials that could be used to encourage design ideas for OUIs and offers some of the participants more innovative ideas for the research and development community. STUDY HIGHLIGHTS • Identification of key challenges for carrying out participatory design of OUIs • The creation of three tools to carry out participatory design of OUI with teenagers • An extensive study using novel materials to inspire the design of OUIs • A rich set of 27 diverse organic user interface design ideas Keywords: design methods; teenagers; participatory design; organic user interfaces; energy use; children; adolescents Special Issue Editors: Audrey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Girouard, Roel Vertegaal &amp; Ivan Poupyrev Received 6 October 2011</xref>; Accepted 29 October 2012</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="1">Desktop computing is not exactly disappearing, but it is seeing its position threatened as devices become smaller, more mobile <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and are used less and less in the usual desktop settings. In recent times, sales of smartphones have exceeded sales of PCs; this trend was foreseen by the interaction design and the computing<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> community who spent considerable time and effort on understanding how to design mobile technologies long before they became mainstream (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Wilcox et al., 1997</xref>). In fact, early papers envisioning new technologies are a feature of the Human Computer interaction (HCI) community where it is commonplace to look beyond now and into the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Norman, 2002</xref>). Organic user interfaces (OUIs) currently belong to what is described as ‘the near future space’ in terms of design. The technology is there to create, albeit clunky, workable versions of OUIs. Examples can be seen in the prototyped ideas of several innovators including (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="19" class="deo:Reference">Co and Pashenkov, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Lepinski and Vertegaal, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Lahey et al., 2011</xref>). As a new research field and as a design space that is still to be fully explored, even the definition of what makes an OUI is still changing. In 1995, Mackinlay et al. defined an OUI as something that grew: in 2006, OUIs were described by Holman et al. as ‘interfaces that respect, and are inspired by, the natural laws of physics, biology, and human cognition following the principles of fluidity, intuitiveness, robustness, and calmness’. In 2007, Vertegaal wrote that ‘The Input Device Is The Output Device (TIDISTOD), Form dynamically follows Flow of activities of the human body, and Function equals Form’. A year later, in 2008, Vertegaal and Poupyrev, in the introduction to a special edition of the Communications of the ACM, summed up the then current thinking by presenting the following three themes that, in their mind, defined OUIs: • Input equals output—where the display is the input device • Function equals form—where the display can take on any form • Form follows flow—where displays can change their shape These three themes certainly apply to OUIs but alone might perhaps be interpreted a little restrictively. When they are coupled with other definitions including Holman and Vertegaal’s (2008) definition, which reads ‘an organic user interface is a computer interface that uses a non planar display as a primary means of output. When flexible, OUIs have the ability to become the data on display through deformation, either via manipulation or actuation. Their fluid physics-based graphics are shaped through multi-touch and bi-manual gestures’, one starts to get a sense of something that is shape changing, malleable, flexible and fluid.As with all new areas, settlement on a definition will take time, but with recent specialised workshops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Girouard et al., 2011</xref>) and panels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Vertegaal and Poupyrev, 2009</xref>) clarity and consensus on OUIs will ultimately emerge. In the meantime it is reasonable to say that the area of OUI is described even if not defined. Without formal definitions, it is still possible to move towards an understanding of a field on the basis of the products it generates; OUIs that have been designed include illuminating clay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Piper et al., 2002</xref>), paper windows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Holman et al., 2005</xref>) and displays from cloth (Lepinski and Vertegaal, 2011)—these all give a direction to the field and suggest examples of possible instances.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> So, in 2012, the field is partially described and the technology can be built. The challenge is on to find the ‘sweet spot’ for the OUI, the application that puts it into the marketplace and into the mainstream. There are several approaches to the design, one is to incubate ideas in a design-rich space, another is to be more participatory and to go to the ‘would be users’ of technology and seek their insights. Both approaches have merits; the use of participatory approaches is especially well suited to novel and emerging areas. In designing the future, there is a good reason to ask the ideas from those who will inhabit it, hence, in this paper, it is teenagers (some of these were high school children (adolescents) aged 11 and 12 but this group, in many situations, are colloquially referred to as teenagers even though they are not technically in their teens and so, in order to be able to describe the two groups together the general term teenager is used), rather than adults, who are approached and charged with this task—to design organics user interfaces. Previous studies on engaging with teenagers and children in near future design have shown this process to be beneficial when concerned with other new technologies but to date no-one has looked at the participatory design, with teenagers of different ages, of OUIs. This paper addresses this gap and contributes some user-generated ideas for OUIs, some reflections on the difficulties associated with designing in this area and some methods that can be used in future design studies of this nature.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="14" page="1" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="15" page="2" column="1">184</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="16" page="2" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
      <section class="deo:RelatedWork">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="2" column="2">2. RELATED WORK</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" page="2" column="2">Having end users participate in the design of their eventual artefacts is a facet of a user-centred approach to design ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Blomberg and Henderson, 1990</xref>). Originally inspired by the work of the participatory design and socio-technical design researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Muller, 1991</xref>), the involvement of end users in early ideation and in specific design tasks is now firmly embedded in HCI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Grudin and Pruitt, 2002</xref>). This practice is differently described as co-design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Churchman, 1968</xref>), as design partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Druin et al., 1999</xref>) and as informant design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Scaife et al., 1997</xref>). Each of these approaches varies in its motivations and focus but the core aspect of all is the engagement with the user group and the facilitation of design activities by research teams who deliberately delegate much of the design activity and power to the participating user team. As participatory approaches have become more commonplace, many researchers have sought to develop methods to facilitate the process, as reported in the review paper by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Jensen and Skov (2005)</xref>, and have sought to investigate and develop techniques and tools for the interpretation of the design artefacts that may be produced (for example see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Visser et al., 2005</xref>). Much of this work has been carried out by the interaction design and children community where it is postulated that the involvement of children, as end users and as informants, is especially pertinent as their ideas may be some distance from the ideas of adult designers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Druin, 1999</xref>). This caveat can also be applied to teenagers, given that<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> teenagers populate their own worlds with a language and a behaviour that can seem very alien to adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Matthews et al., 1998</xref>). In looking for methods to use in design work with teenagers, the researcher has to look in both directions, to work with adults and to work with children. Participation of end users in design sessions, though lauded, is not without its critics. Several authors point to weaknesses in this approach including relying too much on the ‘amateur’ design ideas, the introduction of too much bias from the research team at the start of and during the session, a lack of understanding of the influence of materials used in the design process on the ideas created and bias or uncertainty in interpreting these ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Blomberg and Henderson, 1990</xref>). Researchers can overcome the first (and to some extent the last) of these problems by ensuring that they come to a design session, and come to evaluate the products from a design session, with an open mind, that they treat the design ideas that are produced with caution. Specific methods to minimize too much reliance on ‘amateur’ designs include the Bluebells approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Kelly et al., 2006</xref>) where the design team go to the potential end users in a staged way, with iterations as early designs are refined, then as designs are drafted and later as the detail is sought. In this method, as with many other iterative methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Scaife et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Druin et al., 1999</xref>), the research team are encouraged to not see early design ideas as things that can be built. The concern of bias, the difficulties of interpretation of ideas and the influence of materials are less well documented; these facets are explored in the following three sections.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="39" page="2" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="40" page="3" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="41" page="3" column="1">185</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="48" page="3" column="1">2.1. Bias from the research team</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="3" column="1">Bias from the research team can be introduced at various stages, but is commonly noted at the beginning of a session where the context is introduced. This is especially a problem with design sessions with children where, in order to make a complex concept understandable, the design team often suggest an example and then, once that example is used, the children all hook onto that it and are unable to think divergently. The Obstructed Theatre method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Read et al., 2010</xref>), inspired by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Briggs and Oliver (2008)</xref> (described and motivated in more detail further on in this paper), has been designed to at least partially overcome that problem by conveying salient features a product embodies through a usage scenario without giving any clues as to what the eventual product may look like. This method has been used with younger children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Read et al., 2010</xref>), but the method for creating a theatre script, and its use with teenagers and for an uncharted design idea like OUI, has not been explored.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" page="3" column="1">2.2. Problems with communicating results from participatory design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="3" column="1">Having obtained designs, especially when these are from children, it can sometimes be very hard to work out what they <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> are representing, this is especially problematic when the child is trying to show interactivity in the design as by and large the design team use non-interactive design tools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Tan, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Duh and Chen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Mazzone et al., 2010</xref>). One approach, seen in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Svanaes and Seland (2004)</xref>, is to have the designers act out their findings at the end of the session; another, as reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Moraveji et al. (2007)</xref>, is to annotate design outputs and capture a sequence of design stages. This is also a method partially employed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Katterfeldt and Schelhowe (2008)</xref> who designed a tool to let children capture the design stages on camera and then facilitated the annotation of transitions using text. Generally, the process of conveying design ‘changes’ is not reported in the literature. Methods are scantily mentioned leaving researchers with no real sense of what works and what does not. In the specific area of OUIs, the challenge of showing the changes is magnified due to the potential elasticity and fluidity of the designed solution.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="3" column="2">2.3. Children and teenagers doing design and the materials they use</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="3" column="2">There are a good number of studies where children have engaged in the design of away from the desktop technologies. The complexity and scope of these studies can be aligned in two ways, in the potential interactivity and uncertainty of the design space and in the choice of prototyping materials. The extent to which materials affect the design activity is under researched but, as pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Svanaes and Seland (2004)</xref>, who write ‘prototype materials have a strong impact both on the resulting form and on its imagined functionality’, as the complexity of the intended product increases and its use becomes more and more difficult to model, so much more does this relationship need to be understood. The marriage of materials and technology can be considered in three areas, those where children have designed tabletop and surface applications, those where they have designed mobile and small tablet applications and those where they have designed tangible, ubiquitous or other solutions. In considering how these designs move towards an understanding of how to design for organic interfaces, the approach taken here is incremental—that the first challenge, of surfaces, deals with portraying potentially more than one interaction at a time, that the second may also incorporate gestures and motions with the device(s) as and that the third, tangible or ubiquitous, may also involve actions around, or with, multiple devices as well as the possibility that the physical situation or location of the interactive artefact might affect its behaviours. Studies where children have designed tabletop and surface applications include <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Kelly et al. (2006)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Fails et al. (2010)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Read (2009)</xref>; in all these, and in keeping with the flat aspect of the design space, most of the materials used were paper and cardboard and other two-dimensional artefacts. In this realm it is also possible to use the technology in the design activity as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Rick et al. (2009)</xref>. Children have also been reported<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> using paper and cardboard to design mobile phone products in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Mazzone et al. (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Glasemann et al. (2010)</xref>. Children designing large interactive play spaces is explored in several papers including <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Cassim and Dong (2007)</xref>, in which school children used paper prototyping to design masks, interactive trees and magnetic fields, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Dindler et al. (2010)</xref>, where museum interactive spaces were designed largely with paper and post it notes. Smaller interactive applications, of a more tangible nature, seem to have suited more imaginative materials, and have included wearables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Labrune and MacKay, 2006</xref>) which were designed using actual interactive wearable kits, and shopping buddies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Weiss et al., 2008</xref>) for which clay was used. The impact of the materials on the ultimate designs is often remarked on in design studies, but little is done to unpick the effect that materials have on design. In the design of OUIs, new materials were implied, and thus, a study of their use in design was considered valuable.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="69" page="3" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="70" page="4" column="1">186</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71" page="4" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="79" page="4" column="1">2.4. Participatory design of OUIs</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="4" column="1">In the specific area of OUIs, there have been no studies to date that have attempted participatory design with any group of users. Recent innovations in OUI, including the cloth displays of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Lepinski and Vertegaal (2011)</xref> and the paper phone of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Lahey et al. (2011)</xref>, have been inspired from theory and from earlier work that has informed the field, like, for example Wobbrock et al.’s (2009) work on gestures. The study reported in this paper therefore is especially novel and is also very timely. It specifically seeks to gather innovative and potentially crazy design ideas from high school pupils (referred to collectively for the remainder of this paper as teenagers in line with the colloquial use of this term (in preference to adolescents)), whilst removing as much bias as possible from the research team, opening up the design space as much as possible, and minimizing uncertainty in interpreting and evaluating the ideas produced. The challenges, for the generation and ideation of these new products, would be to convey the idea of an organic interface, to provide appropriate materials for the design stage and to understand the designs once they were documented.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="83" page="4" column="1">3. RESEARCH STUDY: DESIGNING OUIS FOR ENERGY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86" page="4" column="1">The design study described here is situated in the context of the design of a personal technology for teenagers that could be used to at least alert teenagers about energy use and in the best case could change the way they think about energy with a view to an overall reduction in, or realignment of, their usage. This design brief was associated with a project that the research team was working on at the time of this study; the rationale for that study is not explored here as this paper is focussing on the design process, the design ideas and the extent to which teenagers can <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> engage in the participatory design of OUIs. Interested readers can explore the specifics in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Read et al. (2011)</xref>. The energy design brief suited the project team in the design of OUIs in that it was reasonably familiar to the group of school pupils engaging in the design activity and it was also possible to clearly articulate several different possible dimensions of interactivity.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="87" page="4" column="2">3.1. Research approach</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" page="4" column="2">The study intended to engage several groups of teenagers, during school classes, in an activity to sketch out ideas for OUIs. Furthermore, it wanted to explore how OUIs could be described without giving too much away, to identify a good method for capturing interactivity and behaviours in the organic designs and to also investigate the effect that different prototyping materials might have on the design process. In order to do this, the study required the design and creation of two research tools and required decisions to be made about the materials that would be used. The first research tool was the introductory theatre that was needed to set the scene, the second was the documentation for use during the design activity that would both record the design process and capture feedback on the design session. These two artefacts such as the Obstructed Theatre and the Comic Strips and the choices of, and rationale for, the materials to be used are explained in the following three sections.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="89" page="4" column="2">3.1.1. The obstructed theatre</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" page="4" column="2">As outlined in Section 2.1, Obstructed Theatre is a method, first used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Read et al. (2010)</xref>, that assists a research team in setting out requirements for the design in a controlled way that minimizes bias and suggestion. Based on work by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Briggs and Oliver (2008)</xref>, who in turn took their inspiration from Grudin and Pruitt’s (2002) positioning of the inspiration taken from people and from Blythe and Wright’s (2006) appropriation of this ideal in their use of pastiche scenarios in design, the method has been adapted to be used as an introduction to a design session and has previously, in a pilot study, been shown to successfully work (to the extent that it initiated a design session) with children. The method relies on the design team coming together ahead of the design session to distil the ‘features’ that might exist in the design solution and then to create a script around these features that allows them to be articulated to the participatory design team in a way that no design solutions are presented. In addition, the script is required to fit the context of the work, to be understandable to the participatory design team and to be sufficiently brief so as not to take too much time away from the design session. For the method to work well, the research team have to have a clear understanding of the context of the design and a good empathy with the intended audience. Having created a script, one or more ‘actor(s)’ is (are) recruited who is (are) close to the problem context. Whilst gathering a verbal script is relatively straightforward, recruiting teenagers and children to be filmed acting is quite problematic and so, where it suits, the<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> recorded voice is played over an animation. As the aim in this work was to assist teenagers in the design of personal OUIs— these interfaces would be used to convey information about energy use to the teenagers using them—the physical aspects, the interactivity and the functions of the intended devices all had to be considered. In addition, the research team has to decide what will be hidden and what will be told. The point of the ‘obstruction’ in obstructed theatre is to only show the ‘must haves’ or the constraints in order that design ideas are kept as free as possible. For this specific instance, physically the interface needed to be indicated in close proximity to the humans. Organic features that the research team wanted to convey included that the interface might be malleable (so may want to be touched), might convey information (so may want to be looked at in use), could be interacted with (so might change on being touched/handled/spoken to etc.), might move or change shape (possibly on its own) and could perhaps be folded or manipulated (so may require specific physical actions to be performed on it). The context of the use of this technology was in technology use and information and alerts—to this end three different scenarios were considered. Specifically the interface could interrupt and alert a teenager as to some energy<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> use or some information, could react to some very simple interaction with it by showing information about energy use (in some form to be determined) and would allow queries (for example answering the question—how much energy do my hair straighteners use if they are on for two hours) by the use of complex interactions. It was envisioned that the device being designed would be with the teenagers during their usual hours and could be used outside or inside.<marker type="block"/> The obstructed theatre script. The Obstructed Theatre used in this work therefore consistent of a voice recording of a script (detailed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>) and a cartoon-style animation (shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>) created independently in Adobe Flash; these two were combined in post-production. The animation was created by a teen informant as was the initial voice recording. This was later re-recorded by the research team in order to improve the sound quality (see Section 3.4 for the rationale for this).</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93" page="4" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94" page="5" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="95" page="5" column="1">187</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_005.image_01.png" thmb="62ik.page_005.image_01-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="97" page="5" column="1">Figure 1. Script for Obstructed Theatre</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="103" page="5" column="2">3.1.2. Design documentation: comic strips</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" page="5" column="2">As noted in Section 2.2, when judging the efficacy of participatory design processes and evaluating the outputs, it is always preferable to gather information during the session in addition to the information that is available at the end. Various <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> methods exist to do this, these include the taking of video footage, capturing information on logging sheets and on camera as well as having the observers take notes. In studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Tan (2007)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Svanaes and Seland (2004)</xref>, Ketterfeldt and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Schelhowe (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Weiss et al. (2008)</xref>, different methods were used to capture the interactivity of the designs; most of these used video or replay of ideas. With teenagers, it can be difficult to find focus and time for each group to re-present their findings at the end of the session and the management of this sort of ‘talk-back’ is complicated, in addition, when the design is being made with a single malleable artefact, for example Play Doh, as opposed to a set of sketches being presented in a storyboard fashion, the product may change during design with return to its original state, for replay, being difficult. Inspiration for our work in tracking the design process and the changes in the eventual product during interaction was taken from two child-friendly but effective methods as found in Weiss et al.’s (2008) use of inventor cards where the child placed his or her design on a card and then described what it did and Moraveji et al.’s (2007) use of comic boarding where, although not used in the same context as in this study, comics were used with a professional artist to assist in the telling of a narrative. To facilitate the design communication and tracking process, we therefore developed a Comic Strips approach that would use appropriate ‘event joiners’ that would indicate either the passage of time or an input—showing a transition from one state or another and a set of and ‘output descriptors’ that would add context to the next image of the designed product demonstrating sound or other outputs. In developing these event joiners and output descriptors, the script and scenarios for the design session would be referenced. These tools would be provided to the participating students ahead of the design session to ensure that they captured the ‘stages’ of the interactivity they were designing. The plan was for the participants to lay out the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> script words ahead of the design activity and then photograph a changing interface interspersed with the ‘event joiners and output descriptors’.<marker type="block"/> The comic strips made. Reading through the scenario and the script for the Obstructed Theatre, a set of ‘event joiners’ and ‘output descriptions’ for the specific design case were derived. Event joiners included ‘Before’, ‘Sometime later’, ‘Oops – check this out’ and output descriptors like ‘Hardly any energy used’ and ‘Loads of Energy used’ were made. These could be linked to the three scenarios of intended use (as described briefly in the introduction to Section 3 (and explained further in Section 3.2)). Initially, to use these prompts, they were printed on a single sheet with the expectation that the teenagers would separate them up before use, in a second follow on study; the same prompts were printed one to a page (as justified in Section 3.4). Examples of the sheets are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>. In addition, as paper products were being created to facilitate the capturing of information, the design team decided to add two questions to the sheets to gather feedback from the design groups as to their views of the obstructed theatre.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="105" page="5" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="106" page="6" column="1">188</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="6" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_006.image_02.png" thmb="62ik.page_006.image_02-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="109" page="6" column="1">Figure 2. Screen shot from Obstructed Theatre</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="118" page="6" column="2">3.1.3. Materials for organic design</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="129" page="6" column="2">In deciding what materials to use, the design team wanted to facilitate organic design and also wanted to move away from paper, card and even clay.After a brainstorming session, coupled with a practical rationalization, three sets of materials were chosen for use. Each set of materials had a primary material (that was mainly viewed as the organic prop) and a secondary material (that was intended to help assist in the use of the primary). The three primary materials were chosen for their different affordances but were also considered by the design team to be along hierarchy of potential to be more, or less organic than each other. This positioning on the hierarchy is explored in more detail as the materials are explained. <marker type="block"/> Slime and pipe cleaners (slime). Slime, being very fluid, was chosen as a highly organic design material (the notion of fluidity in the context of Organic Interfaces is discussed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Holman and Vertegaal (2008)</xref>). With its semi-fluidic state it allows exploration into liquid interfaces, a space that is far harder to envisage with the other materials in the study.A key drawback of its use, however, is the inability to create solid forms or complex designs due to its tendency to return to its natural state. Pipe cleaners were therefore provided as a complimentary material to add the possibility of solid forms and to help restrict the movement of the slime if and where desired.<marker type="block"/> PlayDoh and Lego (PlayDoh). The malleability of PlayDoh (a soft putty like substance used primarily by young children) enables the creation of organic interfaces with the possibility of demonstrating changes in shape, as discussed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Piper et al. (2002)</xref>. It can be used to create complex shapes and objects, to represent other substances and is easily combined with other<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> materials. Combining this with another versatile material, Lego, meant groups using this combination potentially had huge scope for their designs with their understanding of organic interfaces and imaginations being the greatest barrier.<marker type="block"/> Material and Sticky shapes. Materials have been indicated as useful in organic contexts and so these were provided in the form of felt, ribbon and fabrics that could be cut, stuck or used however the group desired. Fabric interfaces have been described as highly organic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Lepinski and Vertegaal, 2011</xref>), allowing, as they do, the exploration of concepts such as wearable computing and looking at how interfaces can be embedded into clothing, bags and other accessories. Sticky shapes that could simply and quickly be attached to the material were provided as a secondary material.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="124" page="6" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="125" page="7" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="126" page="7" column="1">189</outsider>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="130" page="7" column="1">3.2. Study procedure</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" page="7" column="1">The overall research study was carried out in two phases, an initial study with two different age groups of teenagers and then a follow-up on study with a single age group a few weeks later. The second study was used to refine the methods and to add context from another location to the overall understanding. This section describes the aspects of the procedures that remained constant throughout. The studies took place in school classrooms in which the children would have otherwise had a timetabled lesson. At the beginning of each study, the research team gave an introduction to the purpose of the session, introduced the concept of OUIs and described the design task (using a PowerPoint presentation as a prop). A brief example was then provided to illustrate how the design documentation provided should be used create a Comic Strip using pictures with prompts to illustrate the changes in state of the designs created. During the introduction, the Obstructed Theatre video was shown. The Obstructed Theatre script implied three key pieces of functionality relating to energy use, the ability to provide an alert, the ability to compare energy use with others and the ability to query energy use in detail. In the design task, these were separated into three corresponding design scenarios described to the participants as follows: • Alert—you are out and your energy device want to tell you something (energy use is very good or very bad) • Friends—you want to find out how well you are doing with your energy and compare with a friend • Product—you want to see how much energy something uses (e.g. using a tumble dryer to dry your clothes, going on an XBox360 for 3 hours etc.) and find out about your own energy use. Following the introduction, the participants (in each class) were split, by the class teacher, into nine groups with two or three participants per group. Nine groups were indicated in order to ensure that each set of materials was used in the context of <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> each scenario; the combinations of materials and scenarios are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>. Following the introductory stage (which took around five minutes), the materials were then handed out to each group, together with a design sheet. The groups then recorded their understanding of the purpose of the design session on the sheet before beginning the design task. During the task, the researchers moved between the groups to ensure participants understood their task and that the designs were recorded clearly and unambiguously (being very careful not to bias or influence the designs). During recording, cameras were provided and either the students (especially in the initial study) or the researchers (more often in the follow on study) used these to record the work. At the end of the session, each group was asked to write a few words on how they felt the obstructed theatre video helped, or did not help, with the design activity.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="132" page="7" column="2">Table 1. Groupings of materials used in the study Group Materials Scenario A Slime and pipe cleaners Alert B Playdoh and lego Alert C Material and stickers Alert D Slime and pipe cleaners Friends E Playdoh and lego Friends F Material and stickers Friends G Slime and pipe cleaners Product H Playdoh and lego Product I Material and stickers Product</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_007.image_03.png" thmb="62ik.page_007.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="134" page="7" column="2">Figure 3. Potential routes to the final designs</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="137" page="7" column="2">3.3. Analysing the designs</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="7" column="2">Prior to considering the results of the study, two possible approaches were identified for participants reaching a design, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>. The first approach was that the participant would begin by exploring the materials before then considering how these materials could be used to create a design to fit the appropriate scenario; the second approach would be to first conceive a design and then to attempt to create it using the materials.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> also shows how the two approaches could lead to different end points in that each approach could end in the creation of an organic or non-organic design. Thus, there were four paths identified. As highlighted in the introduction, there is not yet a single unified definition of what an organic interface is or should be. However, early publications in this emerging area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Mackinlay et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Holman et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Vertegaal and Poupyrev, 2008</xref>) give common underlying themes which include: • Organically inspired non-planar forms • The form is the user interface (for both input and output) • Shape changing (for both input through manipulation and output through actuation). The decision was made that these three themes would be used to classify any designs that would be created in the studies as organic or non-organic. For example, if a design attempted to emulate an existing fixed-form device such as mobile phone in a simplistic way would be considered non-organic. Where a design showed elements of the above themes, utilizing the affordances of the materials and involving form in the user interaction or utilizing the change in shape as user input/output, this would be considered organic. As the overall goal of the design session was to facilitate the design of OUIs which were inspired by the affordances of the materials, in relation to this goal, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> shows the four endpoints from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> ranked in preferential order. The paths and endpoints were coded (as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>); these codes are described in more detail in the following: • MDO (Material inspiring Design resulting in Organic) was seen by the research team to be the ideal route a group would take through the design process and it was hoped that this would appear in the results to be the most common. This path would indicate that the materials used in the study had added something to the understanding or organicness and had thus actively inspired the design. • DMO (Design using Material resulting in Organic) was seen as less ideal with the design of the study aimed at the organic materials inspiring the design. That said, designs appearing to have been led by a design concept rather than the materials but still containing organic elements</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="140" page="7" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="141" page="8" column="1">190</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="142" page="8" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="143" page="8" column="1">Table 2. Ranking and codes for potential endpoints of designs Rank End point Code 1 Organic design where material inspires MDO design 2 Organic design where design uses the DMO materials 3 Non-organic design where design uses DM¬ O the materials 4 Non-organic design where material MD¬ O inspires design</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">were preferable to designs that did not contain organic elements as they showed some understanding of organic design concepts. • DM¬O (Design using Material resulting in non-Organic) was seen as the better of the non-organic design routes. It is to be expected that if a design is led from a design idea that the material used to show that idea may not be intended to be organic even if they are in their natural state. • MD¬O (Material inspiring Design resulting in non- Organic) highlights the worst-case scenario in the design session that would occur if a group appeared to inspire their design with the materials provided but then managed to produce a design that was not organic. This may appear odd, given that the design may have started from the materials but it is the lack of understanding of the organicness of the materials that leads this case to be the worst-case. In the case above (DM¬O) the students have potentially designed a good non-organic idea and have ‘made do’ with the materials (which should be inspiring organic ideas) to convey that idea—in this last case, the designs have begun with organic materials but have even then still not resulted in organic design ideas.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="153" page="8" column="2">3.4. Initial study</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154" page="8" column="2">This first study was carried out in a secondary school in the North of the UK with pupils from two classes in different age groups, one was a year 7 class (aged 11 and 12) with 28 pupils, and the other a year 10 class (aged 14 and 15) with 18 pupils. Present in each session were three researchers and one teacher, each session was 55 min long and was carried out in a science lab classroom. Cameras were given to each group to record the designs. The Obstructed Theatre shown was created entirely by a teen informant. Each design session was undertaken as described in Section 3.2; there were no exceptional events. The participants enjoyed the sessions and all stayed on task for the time allocated.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="155" page="8" column="2">3.4.1. Results</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" page="8" column="2">For each class, the products created by the groups were analysed by the research team using the endpoints and paths described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="156" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>. Each design was then assigned the endpoint code that best highlighted the design path taken by that group. The summarized results are shown in Tables 3 and 4. From these results it can be seen that the majority of groups (78%) did manage to add some element of an OUI into their design. There was no difference in the number of designs between the two age groups that had organic elements to them and also, as predicted, none of the designs using slime were deemed to be non-organic, these non-organic designs were split evenly between PlayDoh and materials. The three different scenarios also do not appear to affect the ability to create organic designs as all scenarios had examples of organic and non-organic designs.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="158" page="8" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159" page="9" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="160" page="9" column="1">191</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T3">
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="161" page="9" column="1">Table 3. Year 7 coded results</caption>
              <content>
                <table class="DoCO:Table" number="3" page="9">
                  <thead class="table"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> Group</td>
                      <td class="table"> Designs</td>
                      <td class="table"> Rank</td>
                      <td class="table"> Code</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> A</td>
                      <td class="table"> Hand-held energy monitor</td>
                      <td class="table"> 3</td>
                      <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> B</td>
                      <td class="table"> Slime splats you on high</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> energy use</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> C</td>
                      <td class="table"> Exclamation mark, text</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> changes colour like a traffic</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> light and shape</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> D</td>
                      <td class="table"> Ring that changes colour like</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> traffic light and gives</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> electric shock on high</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> energy use</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> E</td>
                      <td class="table"> Robot with screen that makes</td>
                      <td class="table"> 2</td>
                      <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> sound</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> F</td>
                      <td class="table"> Fabric display that changes</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> from tick to cross with</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> other icons, green to red</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> also</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> G</td>
                      <td class="table"> Toilet where water changes</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> colour from red to green</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> H</td>
                      <td class="table"> Wrist worn energy monitor</td>
                      <td class="table"> 2</td>
                      <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> that looks like a face</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> I</td>
                      <td class="table"> Fabric device, starts on</td>
                      <td class="table"> 3</td>
                      <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> energy use and slider for</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table.strange">
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"> interaction</td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                      <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </content>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="162" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Group Designs Rank Code A Hand-held energy monitor 3 DMO B Slime splats you on high 1 MDO energy use C Exclamation mark, text 1 MDO changes colour like a traffic light and shape D Ring that changes colour like 1 MDO traffic light and gives electric shock on high energy use E Robot with screen that makes 2 DMO sound F Fabric display that changes 1 MDO from tick to cross with other icons, green to red also G Toilet where water changes 1 MDO colour from red to green H Wrist worn energy monitor 2 DMO that looks like a face I Fabric device, starts on 3 DMO energy use and slider for interaction</region>
            </region>
            <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T4">
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="163" page="9" column="1">Table 4. Year 10 coded results</caption>
              <content>
                <table class="DoCO:Table" number="4" page="9">
                  <thead class="table"/>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> Group</td>
                      <td class="table"> Rank</td>
                      <td class="table"> Code</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> A</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> B</td>
                      <td class="table"> 2</td>
                      <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> C</td>
                      <td class="table"> 3</td>
                      <td class="table"> DM¬ O</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr class="table">
                      <td class="table"> D</td>
                      <td class="table"> 1</td>
                      <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
              </content>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="164" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Group A B</region>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="165" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Rank Code 1 MDO 2 DMO</region>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="166" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">C</region>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="167" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">3 DM¬ O</region>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="168" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">D</region>
              <region class="TableInfo" id="169" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">1 MDO</region>
            </region>
            <region class="unknown" id="170" page="9" column="1">Designs Smiley face in playdoh Smiley slime, changes to a ball and if too bad launches at you Wearable energy man can be attached to bag or coat Slime has numbers appear in it show energy usage, changes to red when high numbers E Mobile device, connect to 4 MD¬ O friends to compare F Touchpad wearable 2 DMO indicator with audio G Green red flubber, like pet 1 MDO from film H Device that calculate energy 2 DMO use, shows device and molds into numbers to show energy use I Headband with Jewels 1 MDO which fall off the worse your energy gets</region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_009.image_04.png" thmb="62ik.page_009.image_04-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="172" page="9" column="2">Figure 4. Group I Year 10 design</caption>
            </region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_009.image_05.png" thmb="62ik.page_009.image_05-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="174" page="9" column="2">Figure 5. Group E Year 7 designs</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="175" page="9" column="2">3.4.2. Example designs</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="191" page="9" column="2">In order to better understand the analysis process employed at this stage, and to identify some of the context, an example is provided, in the next section, of a design from each of the four design paths. In some of these images, the use of Comic Strips as joiners is seen. <marker type="block"/> MDO. Group I in Year 10 created a headband with jewels on that fell off the worse your energy use was. The group was provided with ribbon (which was frequently used by all groups to create headbands whether part of their designs or not). The idea of the headband disintegrating due to bad energy was seen as a good example of an organic concept (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>).<marker type="block"/> DMO. Group E in Year 7 created a robot that displayed energy readings on a display and which also had sounds. The device put its thumb up if the energy use was better than a friend. This device showed evidence of being device led with the PlayDoh materials used only to show the design. The movements and interactions shown by the design were deemed to have organic concepts included (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="179" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>).<marker type="block"/> DM¬O. Group I in Year 7 created a device based upon a traditional hand-held concept with traditional input and output technologies such as sliders and speakers. Although the device was made from material, there was no evidence that the device was meant to be material from the photographs or notes taken during the session. It was deemed to be a classic case of designing familiar technologies using the material provided (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="181" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>).<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> MD¬O. Group C in Year 10 were the only group (from this study) deemed to have followed this MD-O path. This group created a wearable energy man who could be attached to a bag or coat. This design appears to have been created main due to the shapes of the stick shapes provided using one of the materials as a backing. This is an alert device where the chest of the energy man changes from green to red as energy use increases. It was decided that this device did not contain any organic elements even the materials were used to come up with the design (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="190" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>).</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="183" page="9" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="184" page="10" column="1">192</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="185" page="10" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_010.image_06.png" thmb="62ik.page_010.image_06-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="187" page="10" column="1">Figure 6. Group I Year 7 design</caption>
            </region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_010.image_07.png" thmb="62ik.page_010.image_07-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="189" page="10" column="1">Figure 7. Group C Year 10 designs</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="192" page="10" column="2">3.4.3. Use of the methods of Obstructed Theatre and Comic Strips</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="193" page="10" column="2">During and after the study, the participating pupils were asked about Obstructed Theatre. Most had managed to understand what had to be done, but there were some difficulties with the volume of the recording (reported by 60% of groups). It had been expected that the teenagers would find the concept of OUI difficult; this was born out by the fact that 56% of the respondents indicated some confusion at the start of the activity. Evaluation of the Comic Strip activity was based on correct usage—only 17% of the groups made use of the prompts that were given with a further 22% groups making their own prompts. Sixty-one per cent of the groups failed to use any prompts at all and simply took a series of photographs, which made interpretation difficult for the research team.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="194" page="10" column="2">3.5. Follow-up study</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214" page="10" column="2">From the shortcomings (of the Obstructed Theatre method and the Comic Strips) of the initial study, as described in the previous section, several aspects of the method were revised for a follow-up study. An improved Obstructed Theatre video was made using the same script and animation, but with greatly improved audio quality. The design documentation proforma used for the Comic Strip aspect of the study was redesigned (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>) with the same first page, but it then included subsequent pages with a caption at the top and a large rectangle below for the design to be placed and photographed (simplifying the photographing of a design with an associated caption). In this study, we chose not to give the cameras to the groups, and to take the photographs ourselves, as in the first study the availability of the cameras distracted the participants from the design task and the photographs they took were often of poor quality. This follow-up study was carried out in a different secondary school in the North of the UK with pupils from one year 8 class<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> (aged 12 and 13) with 21 pupils. Present in the session was two researchers and one teacher. The session was 50 min long and was carried out in an art classroom. As described above in the detail of the initial study, the pupils were again put into nine groups and were given the introduction as per the previous study (with improved audio for the obstructed theatre). The pupils all participated with enthusiasm and stayed on task.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_010.image_08.png" thmb="62ik.page_010.image_08-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="198" page="10" column="2">Figure 8. Examples of the design documentation with the adapted Comic Strip detail</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="199" page="10" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="200" page="11" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="201" page="11" column="1">193</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T5">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="202" page="11" column="1">Table 5. Year 8 coded results</caption>
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="5" page="11">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Group</td>
                    <td class="table"> Rank</td>
                    <td class="table"> Code</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> A</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1</td>
                    <td class="table"> MDO</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> B</td>
                    <td class="table"> 2</td>
                    <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> C</td>
                    <td class="table"> 2</td>
                    <td class="table"> DMO</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> D</td>
                    <td class="table"> 4</td>
                    <td class="table"> MD¬ O</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> E</td>
                    <td class="table"> 3</td>
                    <td class="table"> DM¬ O</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="203" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Group A</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="204" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Rank Code 1 MDO</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="205" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">B</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="206" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">2 DMO</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="207" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">C</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="208" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">2 DMO</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="209" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">D</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="210" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">4 MD¬ O</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="211" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">E</region>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="212" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">3 DM¬ O</region>
          </region>
          <region class="unknown" id="213" page="11" column="1">Designs Slime pool changes colour (red, green), gets bigger and smaller Pink energy ornament with colour changing sign post Roll up fabric laptop with webcam and keyboard Pots of slime connected by a wire to compare Green energy motorbike with screen for energy feedback and scanner F Fabric faces that talk, hold 2 DMO hands to compare energy use G Slime with energy 4 MD¬ O thermometer indicators for showing and comparing energy use H Handheld energy scanner 3 DM¬ O with led and smiley face display I Plugs into Xbox to reduce its 4 MD¬ O energy use</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="215" page="11" column="1">3.5.1. Results</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="217" page="11" column="1">In the same way as in the initial study, the results were analysed and coded. The same researchers did the coding in both instances. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5" id="216" class="deo:Reference">Table 5</xref> shows the coded results for the designs produced by these pupils. It can be seen that less than half of the groups in this study produced designs that were deemed to have organic elements. The proportion of designs that were deemed to be design led, rather than material led was also greater than in the initial study. This difference is explored later in the paper.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="218" page="11" column="1">3.5.2. Example designs</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="238" page="11" column="1">Examples of designs from this group from each of the four design paths are provided in this section. <marker type="block"/> MDO. Group A created a contained slime pool where the slime is green when the users energy use is good (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9" id="220" class="deo:Reference">Figure 9</xref>). As<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the users’ energy use increases, the slime turns red and the pool opens up into two. The idea of the slime changing colour and the device changing size and shape is definitely an organic design, and without experimenting with the materials first is unlikely to have been conceived.<marker type="block"/> DMO. Group C created a roll up fabric laptop with an integrated keyboard and laptop (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Figure 10</xref>). Although the laptop retains the tradition shape and form of a laptop, the group has understood the concept of an organic design. The research team concluded that it was highly unlikely that given material a group would come up with the idea of a laptop and therefore the design was considered organic and created with the materials provided.<marker type="block"/> DM¬O. Group H created a hand-held energy scanner with led numeric and smiley face display (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11" id="229" class="deo:Reference">Figure 11</xref>). This device is clearly based around a traditional hand-held device using<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> non-organic inputs and outputs. The design was clearly the inspiration for this group with the materials being used as a way to create it rather than inspire it.<marker type="block"/> MD¬O. Group D only managed to come up with two pots of slime that were linked together by a wire (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12" id="237" class="deo:Reference">Figure 12</xref>). They had no knowledge of what the slime could do or how it could be used and could not communicate to the researcher team what happened when the slime was linked together. With so little information or thought for the product, the research concluded the design could not be classified as organic.</region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F9">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_011.image_09.png" thmb="62ik.page_011.image_09-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="223" page="11" column="2">Figure 9. Group A design</caption>
            </region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F10">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_011.image_10.png" thmb="62ik.page_011.image_10-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="225" page="11" column="2">Figure 10. Group C design</caption>
            </region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="231" page="11" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="232" page="12" column="1">194</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="233" page="12" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F11">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62ik.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="235" page="12" column="1">Figure 11. Group H design</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="239" page="12" column="1">3.5.3. Use of the methods of Obstructed Theatre and Comic Strips</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="243" page="12" column="1">The enhancements to the Obstructed Theatre appeared to have a positive effect on informing the children on how to complete the task and on their understanding of the concept of an OUI. On being asked, only 14% of the participants stated that they were confused as to what the task was asking compared with 56% in the initial study. Eighty-nine per cent of the groups gave a positive response to the question asking whether the Obstructed Theatre was helpful and no group had issues with the sound. In terms of demonstrating the interactivity and changing of their designs, 66% of the groups used the improved design <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> documentation to better create Comic Stripped design details— 22% of the groups only produced one photo but they still used the documentation to do this, implying that the structured reporting was helpful to most of the students.</region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F12">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_012.image_11.png" thmb="62ik.page_012.image_11-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="242" page="12" column="2">Figure 12. Group D design</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="244" page="12" column="2">4. DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="245" page="12" column="2">The two studies were sufficiently similar to be compared and contrasted as each used essentially the same instructions, the same materials and similar reporting methods. The discussion of the results is presented here in three parts. The first part considers the extent to which the materials used could be seen as ‘organic user interface design friendly’. This section explores the difficulties and opportunities for designing OUIs in a participatory way. The second section considers the actual designs produced by the children and explores some of the ideas for OUIs that can be developed from this study; this section also considers why the second school may have produced less organic ideas than the first. In the third section, the methodological aspects of the work are discussed including a critique of the tools used.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="246" page="12" column="2">4.1. Designing OUIs</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" page="12" column="2">The study provided us with insights into the effectiveness of using the different sets of materials to inspire the design of OUIs. The slime, although popular with the teenagers, appeared to be difficult as a design tool. Groups struggled to capture their ideas due to the issues stated above. Several groups based ideas around the slime attacking users if their energy usage was too high and appeared to enjoy demonstrating this. The idea of the slime changing shape and/or size was apparent from the designs although this did not translate well into the photographs the groups took of their work. Some groups ignored the slime altogether, instead focusing on designs that could be made with the pipe cleaners such as rings that changed colour dependent on energy use. Pipe cleaners were used more as a tool to enhance the abilities of the slime, such as slime that displayed the amount <marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> of energy used in numbers and the electric charge of slime that shocked people who were using too much energy. Although PlayDoh and Lego had the biggest potential for designs, the majority of the designs created were based around the PlayDoh being used to form a hand-held device with the Lego used as buttons, displays, speakers or lights. This highlighted a lack of understanding of the concept of an OUI. Others designs included robots and watches which again showed the groups creating devices based around object and technologies that already exist that showed a limited, or lack of, organic capabilities. Only one device created using this combination displayed organic concepts, that being a PlayDoh face that changed facial expressions depending on energy use. The groups using fabric showed similarities in their design ideas to the groups that used the PlayDoh. Half of the groups used a large sheet of fabric as the body of a hand-held device with many using the stick on shapes to simulate features such as buttons, sliders, displays and lights and therefore again missing the concept of an OUI. Some groups did state their devices were wearable or material based but with others it was hard to distinguish whether the designs were supposed to be material by design or were simply hand-held devices made out of the materials provided. Ideas that showed some understanding of the requirements included an exclamation mark that changed colour and shape depending on energy use, and a headband covered with jewels where the jewels fell off the worse your energy use is.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="248" page="12" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="249" page="13" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="250" page="13" column="1">195</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F13">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62ik.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="252" page="13" column="1">Figure 13. Material led non-organic designs</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="254" page="13" column="1">4.2. OUIs Ideas</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="258" page="13" column="1">The results from this study support the idea that teenagers can design OUIs using a participatory design approach. The organic contribution to each design varied greatly and was an area of strong debate between the design team. This led to the research team re-reading the literature on OUIs many times due to differing interpretations or what was, and was not, organic. This inconsistency re-raised the question of whether an OUI has been defined. The school used in the follow-up study was situated in a relatively socially deprived area whereas the school in the initial study was in a more affluent area. This social difference may have been a significant factor in the differences in results; <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> another explanation might have been the group sizes in the second school where relatively young children mostly worked in groups of two as opposed to all the children in the first study from the lower age group being in groups of three—younger participants may need larger groups than older participants in these sort of design activities. For whatever reasons, although the teenagers in the follow-up study were provided with a better understanding of what an OUI they appeared less able to ‘think outside the box’ than the teenagers in the initial study. The barrier of technologies that already existed coupled with a lack of imagination was evident in a large proportion of their designs. Groups, particularly those using the slime, struggled to comprehend how they could these materials to design devices for the scenarios they were given. With the second school, there was also a greater proportion of designs that followed our worst-case design path (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13" id="256" class="deo:Reference">Figure 13</xref>) where the material was used as a product for a non-organic, non-material inspired design. Group G created thermometers to show the different energy use of different people. This in itself met the scenario brief better but the slime appeared to be just a platform for the thermometers to lie on and served no other purpose. Group I struggled to envisage how the materials they were given could be used to create design products. They created a device that when attached to an XBox apparently lowered its power consumption. This did not really follow the design brief and it appeared the group had just stuck some shapes on the piece of material with no real thought to what they were designing. Although there were less organic design produced in the follow-up study, there were still some good ideas to surface from the groups that produced organic concepts (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Figure 14</xref>). Group B created a pink energy ornament with a sign that changed colour to inform the user of their current energy use. Group F created a fabric energy device that could talk (with moving mouths and eyes) and tell you about the energy use. The device could also hold hands with another device to compare the energy use of the owners.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="259" page="13" column="2">4.3. Obstructed Theatre, Comic Strips and other method discussion</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="274" page="13" column="2">The second study was carried out using an improved Obstructed Theatre video and improved design documentation for the <marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Comic Strips given to the pupils. The feedback from the Obstructed Theatre greatly improved and it was noted by the research team that there were less queries from the groups about what they had to do than in the first study. The photos received from the sessions better followed a Comic Strip approach also as more photos of the designs in different states were captured than in Study 1. The success of the enhancements to the session was not emulated in the results however as the pupils in this class produced less designs with organic concepts than the previous study and less designs appeared to be inspired by the materials but rather design led.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Figure 15</xref> shows the distribution of codes across the 18 designs in the initial study and supports the ranking assigned to the scenarios given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="272" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16" id="273" class="deo:Reference">Figure 16</xref> shows the distribution of codes across the nine designs in the follow-up study. Only one of the designs in this study followed the desired approach of a material inspired the design that was organic. Three of the designs followed the worst- case path in that their designs were inspired by the material but did not have organic concepts in the design.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="261" page="13" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="262" page="14" column="1">196</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="263" page="14" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F14">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62ik.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="265" page="14" column="1">Figure 14. Organic designs</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F15">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62ik.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="267" page="14" column="1">Figure 15. Distribution of codes across designs in the initial study</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F16">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ik.page_014.image_16.png" thmb="62ik.page_014.image_16-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="269" page="14" column="1">Figure 16. Distribution of codes across designs in study two</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="275" page="14" column="2">5. CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="280" page="14" column="2">The work presented in this paper is the first of its kind to explore the participatory design of OUIs with teenagers. Three unique challenges were raised and addressed. The challenge of conveying the concept of an OUI to teenagers was addressed through the use of the Obstructed Theatre method (discussed in Section 3.1.1). The challenge of facilitating the design of OUIs was addressed through the use of three unique sets of materials used in the design process (slime and pipe-cleaners, Play-Doh and Lego, fabric and fasteners; discussed in Section 3.1.3). The challenge of interpreting the design ideas was addressed through the use of design documentation (discussed in Section 3.1.2) supporting the creation of Comic Strips combining photographs of the designs with textual prompts to gather not only the design, but also how it changed during usage. The studies generated a wide variety of novel designs utilizing the affordances of the materials (these are summarized in Tables 3–5), two-thirds of the designs produced could be classified as being ‘organic’ (as discussed in Section 4.1). While these designs are grounded in the context of three energy awareness scenarios (energy alert, energy comparison and energy calculation; as described in Section 3.2), they provide a rich set of OUI possibilities that are applicable in other contexts. Even the designs classified as non-Organic were novel and unexpected design solutions. The Obstructed Theatre method proved useful to the participants in the study for improving understanding of the design task (when the theatre was conveyed successfully). The materials used in the studies occasionally proved distracting for the teenage participants (most notably the slime), but from the designs produced it is clear that they encouraged the participants to explore new and unusual design possibilities. Each design was classified as being driven by the affordances of the materials or driven by a design through which the materials were expressed, and of the designs classified as ‘organic’ over half of these were driven by the materials. The Comic Strips technique, allowing the interaction with the design to be captured, was only partially used as intended by participants. Every design was photographed in the ‘before’ state, but &lt;50% of designs had subsequent pictures; this was perhaps due to the time restrictions placed on the studies. This work has shown encouraging results from the use of Obstructed Theatre, organic design materials and Comic Strip <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> approaches in the participatory design of OUIs with teenagers. While the use of these approaches was refined after the initial study for follow-up study, there is still much to be learned about their use from extending this initial work. A more detailed exploration of the teenage participants’ perception of the Obstructed Theatre and its influence on the resulting designs is needed. The role of organic materials in the creation of the designs has been distinguished as either inspiring or facilitating, in both of these roles the use of different materials may have given different results. Further insights are needed to more clearly understand the impact of the materials on the final designs through these two roles. This work will be extended in two distinct directions: the most suitable designs for energy devices will be identified and taken forward within the project with which this work is associated. Further studies refining the methods and approaches used here will be carried out to gain a deeper understanding of how they can most effectively be used.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="277" page="14" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="278" page="15" column="1">Designing OUIs with Young Adolescent and Teenage Participants</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="279" page="15" column="1">197</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="281" page="15" column="1">ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="282" page="15" column="1">The pupils from the two schools participating in this work are acknowledged for their work on this project.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="283" page="15" column="1">FUNDING</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="284" page="15" column="1">Funding from the RCUK on terms of the Digital Economy and the Energy themes is acknowledged.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="285" page="15" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="286" page="15" column="1">Blomberg, J. L. and Henderson, A. (1990) Reflections on Participatory Design: Lessons from the Trillium Experience. In Proc. CHI’09. ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="287" page="15" column="1">Blythe, M. A. and Wright, P. C. (2006) Pastiche scenarios: fiction as a resource for user centred design. Interact. Comput., 18, 1139–1164.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="288" page="15" column="1">Briggs, P. and Oliver, P. L. (2008) Biometric Daemons: Authentication via Electronic Pets, pp. 2423–2432. In Proc. CHI 2008. ACM Press, Florence, Italy.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="289" page="15" column="1">Cassim, J. and Dong, H. (2007) Empowering Designers and User: Case Studies from the DBA Inclusive Design Challenge. Gower Publishing, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="290" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Churchman, C. W. (1968) The Systems Approach. Delaconte Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="291" page="15" column="1">Co, E. and Pashenkov, N. (2008) Emerging display technologies for organic user interfaces. Commun. ACM, 51, 45–47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="292" page="15" column="1">Dindler, C., Iversen, O. S., Smith, R. and Veerasawmy, R. (2010) Participatory Design at the Museum: Inquiring into Children’s Everyday Engagement in Cultural Heritage. In Proc. 22nd Conf. Computer–Human Interaction Special Interest Group of Australia on Computer-Human Interaction, Pp. 72–79. ACM Press, Brisbane, Australia.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="293" page="15" column="2">Druin, A. 1999. "Cooperative Inquiry: Developing New Technologies for Children with Children, pp. 592–599. ACM Press, Florence, Italy. in CHI99</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="294" page="15" column="2">Druin, A., Bederson, B., Boltman, A., Miura, A., Knotts-Callaghan, D. and Platt, M. (1999) Children as Our Technology Design Partners. In Druin A. (ed.) The Design of Children’s Technology, pp. 51–72. Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="295" page="15" column="2">Duh, H. B.-L. and Chen, V. H.-H. (2010) Fantasies in Narration: Narrating the Requirements of Children in Mobile Gaming Design. In Proc. 7th Int. Conf. Advances in Computer Entertainment Technology, pp. 3–6. ACM Press, Taipei, Taiwan.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="296" page="15" column="2">Fails, J. A., Druin, A., and Guha, M. L. (2010) Mobile Collaboration: Collaboratively Reading and Creating Children’s Stories on Mobile Devices. In Proc. 9th Int. Conf. Interaction Design and Children, pp. 20–29. ACM Press, Barcelona, Spain.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="297" page="15" column="2">Girouard, A., Vertegaal, R. and Poupyrev, I. (2011) Second International Workshop on Organic User Interfaces. In Proc. 5th Int. Conf. Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction, pp. 381– 384. ACM Press, Funchal, Portugal.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="298" page="15" column="2">Glasemann, M., Kanstrup, A. M. and Ryberg, T. (2010) Making Chocolate-covered Broccoli: Designing a Mobile Learning Game about Food forYoung People with Diabetes. In Proc. 8thACM Conf. Designing Interactive Systems, pp. 262–271. ACM Press, Aarhus, Denmark.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="299" page="15" column="2">Grudin, J. and Pruitt, J. (2002) Personas, Participatory Design and Product Development: An Infrastructure for Engagement. In PDC’02, pp. 144–161. ACM Press, Malmo, Sweden.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="301" page="15" column="2">Holman, D., Diehl, J., Karrer, T. and Borchers, J. (2006) Organic user interfaces. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://media.informatik.rwth-aachen.de/organic.html," id="300">http://media.informatik.rwth-aachen.de/organic.html,</ext-link> (accessed August 6, 2011).</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="302" page="15" column="2">Holman, D. and Vertegaal, R. (2008) Organic user interfaces: designing computers in any way, shape, or form. Commun. ACM, 51, 48–55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="303" page="15" column="2">Holman, D., Vertegaal, R., Altosaar, M., Troje, N. and Johns, D. (2005) Paper Windows: Interaction Techniques for Digital Paper. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 591–599. ACM Press, Portland, OR, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="304" page="15" column="2">Jensen, J. J. and Skov, M. B. (2005) A Review of Research Methods in Children’s Technology Design. In IDC 2005, pp. 80–87. ACM Press, Boulder, CO.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="305" page="15" column="2">Katterfeldt, E.-S. and Schelhowe, H. (2008) A Modelling Tool to Support Children Making Their Ideas Work. In Proc. 7th Int. Conf. Int. Design and Children, pp. 218–225. ACM Press, Chicago, IL, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="306" page="15" column="2">Kelly, S. R., Mazzone, E., Horton, M. and Read, J. C. (2006) Bluebells: A Design Method for Child-Centred Product Development. In NordiChi 2006. ACM Press, Oslo.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="307" page="15" column="2">Labrune, J.-B. and MacKay, W. (2006) Telebeads: Social Network Mnemonics for Teenagers. In IDC’06. ACM Press, Tampere, Finland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="308" page="15" column="2">Lahey, B., Girouard, A., Burleson, W. and Vertegaal, R. (2011) PaperPhone: Understanding the Use of Bend Gestures in Mobile Devices with Flexible Electronic Paper Displays. In Proceedings of the 2011 Annual Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 1303–1312. ACM Press, Vancouver, BC, Canada.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="312" page="16" column="1">Lepinski, J. and Vertegaal, R. (2011) Cloth Displays: Interacting with Drapable Textile Screens. In Proc. Fifth Int. Conf. Tangible, Embedded, and Embodied Interaction, pp. 285–288. ACM Press, Funchal, Portugal.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="313" page="16" column="1">Mackinlay, J. D., Rao, R. and Card, S. K. (1995). An organic user interface for searching citation links. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Denver, USA (CHI’95), Irvin R. Katz, Robert Mack, Linn Marks, Mary Beth Rosson, and Jakob Nielsen (Eds.). pp. 67–73. ACM Press, Addison- Wesley Publishing Co.: New York, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="314" page="16" column="1">Matthews, H., Limb, M. and Percy-Smith, B. (1998) Changing worlds: the microgeographies of young teenagers. Tijdschrift Econ. Soc. Ge., 89, 193–202.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="315" page="16" column="1">Mazzone, E., Ivari, N., Tikkanen, R., Read, J. C. and Beale, R. (2010) Considering Context, Content, Management, and Engagement in Design Activities with Children. In IDC2010, pp. 108–117. ACM Press, Barcelona.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="316" page="16" column="1">Mazzone, E, Read, J. C. and Beale, R. (2008) Understanding Children’s Contributions During Informant Design. In Proc. of the 22nd British HCI Group Annual Conference on People and Computers: Culture, Creativity, Interaction – Volume 2, Liverpool, UK (BCS- HCI ’08), Vol. 2., pp. 61–64. British Computer Society, Swinton, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="317" page="16" column="1">Moraveji, N., Li, J., Ding, J., O’Kelley, P. and Woolf, S. (2007) Comicboarding: Using Comics as Proxies for Participatory Design with Children. In CHI 2007, pp. 1371–1372. ACM Press, San Jose, CA, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="318" page="16" column="1">Muller, M. J. (1991) PICTIVE—An Exploration of Participatory Design. In CHI ’91, pp. 225–231. ACM Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="319" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Norman, D. A. (2002) The Design of Everyday Things. Basic Books, New York, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="320" page="16" column="1">Piper, B., Ratti, C. and Ishii, H. (2002) Illuminating Clay: A 3- D Tangible Interface for Landscape Analysis. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human factors in computing systems: Changing our world, changing ourselves, pp. 355–362. ACM Press, Minneapolis, MN, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="321" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Read, J. C. (2009) Warp Speed Design: a Rapid Design Method for Use with Children. In CHI 2009, pp. 4681–4686. ACM Press, Boston, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="322" page="16" column="1">Read, J. C., Fitton, D., Cowan, B. Beale, R., Guo, Y. and Horton, M. (2011) Understanding and Designing Cool Technologies for Teenagers. In CHI2011, vol. 2, pp. 1567–1572. ACM Press, Vancouver, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="323" page="16" column="1">Read, J. C., Fitton, D. and Mazzone, E. (2010) Using Obstructed Theatre with Child Designers to Convey Requirements. In CHI2010. ACM Press, Atlanta, GA, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="324" page="16" column="2">Rick, J., Harris, A., Marshall, P., Fleck, R., Yuill, N. and Rogers, Y. (2009) Children Designing Together on a Multi-touch Tabletop: an Analysis of Spatial Orientation and User Interactions. In Proc. of 8th International Conference on Interaction Design and Children, Como, Italy (IDC ’09), pp. 106–114. New York: ACM Press: New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="325" page="16" column="2">Scaife, M., Rogers, Y., Aldrich, F. and Davies, M. (1997) Designing for or Designing with? Informant Design for Interactive Learning Environments. In CHI ’97,pp. 343–350. ACM Press, Atlanta.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="326" page="16" column="2">Svanaes, D. and Seland, G. (2004) Putting the Users Center Stage: Role Playing and Low-fi Prototyping Enable End Users to Design Mobile Systems. In CHI 2004, pp. 479–486. ACM Press, Vienna, Austria.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="327" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">Tan, M. (2007) Teaching and Language Corpora—The Debate. Lingua Lingu., 5, 119–129.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="328" page="16" column="2">Vertegaal, R. and Poupyrev, I. (2008) Organic user interfaces: introduction to special issue. Commun. ACM, 6, 26–30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="329" page="16" column="2">Vertegaal, R. (2007) Organic User Interfaces (Oui!): Designing Computers in Any Way Shape or Form. In Proc. 6th Int. Conf. Unconventional Computation, pp. 28–28. Springer, Kingston, Canada.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="330" page="16" column="2">Vertegaal, R. and Poupyrev, I. (2009) Eek! a Mouse! Organic User Interfaces: Tangible, Transitive Materials and Programmable Reality. In Proc. 27th Int. Conf. Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 3313–3316. ACM Press, Boston, MA, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="331" page="16" column="2">Visser, F. S., van der Lugt, R. and Stappers, P. J. (2005) Participatory Design Needs Participatory Communication: New Tools for Sharing User Insights in the Product Innovation Process. In Proc. of 9th European Conference on Creativity and Innovation, Lodz, Poland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="332" page="16" column="2">Weiss, A., Wurhofer, D., Bernhaupt, R., Beck, E. and Tscheligi, M. (2008) This Is a Flying Shopping Trolley: a Case Study of Participatory Design with Children in a Shopping Context. In Proc. Tenth Anniversary Conf. Participatory Design 2008, pp. 254–257. Indiana University, Bloomington, IN.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="333" page="16" column="2">Wilcox, L. D., Schilit, B. N. and Sawhney, N. (1997) Dynomite: a Dynamically Organized Ink and Audio Notebook. In CHI’97 Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, pp. 186– 193. ACM Press, Atlanta, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="334" page="16" column="2">Wobbrock, J. O., Morris, M. R. and Wilson, A. D. (2009) User- Defined Gestures for Surface Computing, pp. 1083–1092. In Proc. of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Boston, USA (CHI ’09). ACM Press, New York, USA.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="309" page="15" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="310" page="16" column="1">198</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="311" page="16" column="1">Janet C. Read et al.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="335" page="16" column="2">Interacting with Computers, Vol. 25 No. 2, 2013</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
