<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e44a73688ab6f5ce6188066b0217f94a0be82a69017a112e2319952b46813bc5</job>
    <base_name>62bo</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.2753/mis0742-1222220402">http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1499224.1499236</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Multi-party Information Systems Development: The Challenge of Cross-Boundary Collaboration</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Thesis Proposal</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">Author:</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Natalia Levina</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6" confidence="possible">Massachusetts Institute of Technology Sloan School of Management Information Technologies Group Address: Massachusetts Institute of Technology Sloan School of Management Room E53-324 50 Memorial Drive Cambridge, MA 02142-1347 USA Phone: +1 (617) 258 5582 Fax: +1 (617) 258 7579 Email: <email id="5">natalia@mit.edu</email> Keywords: Organizational Communication, Organizational Learning, Ethnography, IS Development Methods and Tools, Requirements Analysis, Outsourcing IS, Boundary Objects (not in the categorization), Communicative Genres (not in categorization). Accepted at the International Conference on Information Systems Doctoral Consortium, Brisbane, Australia, Dec 7th-9th, 2000. Do not distribute without the author's permission.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="7">1</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="8">Multi-party Information Systems Development: The Challenge of Cross-Boundary Collaboration Abstract</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9">IS development has always involved multiple stakeholders, but IS literature has traditionally focused on communication issues between two groups: technical developers and users. With changes in technology and the increased strategic role of IS applications, the number and diversity of stakeholders on IS projects has increased significantly. Problems of integrating the knowledge of multiple stakeholders are particularly acute in the E-commerce arena because of the novelty of this area of activity and the constant technological and business changes within it. People from diverse walks of life—business strategists, technologists, graphic designers, marketers—now need to work together to invent new E-commerce applications. In my dissertation research I conduct an ethnographic field study of a multi-party development project in an Internet consulting organization to understand how people collaborate across social boundaries to achieve results. In answering this question, I first draw on the literature of communities of practice, organizational culture, and social identity to understand the nature of social boundaries in organizations. I then use the lens of communicative genres, traditionally applied within a single community of practice, to understand the issues and conflicts that arise when different social groups have to communicate across boundaries. I then explore the role of boundary objects—shared artifacts that relate to the practices of multiple social groups—in cross-boundary communication practices. This research makes a first step towards developing an integrated perspective on how people share knowledge across boundaries by emphasizing the role of communicative norms, knowledge representations, and individual actors in cross-boundary collaboration practices.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="10">2</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="3" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="3" column="1">The literature on knowledge management and innovation places primary importance on the role of sharing diverse knowledge ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Kogut and Zander, 1992</xref>; Liebeskind, et al., 1996; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Nonaka, 1994</xref>). In this view innovation is based on successful integration of diverse knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Kogut and Zander, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Nonaka, 1994</xref>; von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 1994</xref>). The success of an Information System (IS) development effort has traditionally been associated with the effective combination of the business knowledge of users with the technical knowledge of IS professionals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Marcus, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Gash, 1994</xref>). With changes in technology and the increased strategic role of IS applications, the number and diversity of stakeholders on IS projects has increased significantly. Problems of integrating the knowledge of multiple stakeholders are particularly acute in the E-commerce arena because of the novelty of this area of activity and the constant technological and business changes within it. People from diverse walks of life—business strategists, technologists, graphic designers, marketers—now need to work together to invent new E-commerce applications. Moreover, with the growth of IS outsourcing, building information systems frequently involves various external organizations. Knowledge sharing across organizational boundaries in IS outsourcing is a critical factor in making outsourcing relationships work (Koh, et al., 1999). In short, the success of multi-party IS development efforts is dependent on the effective sharing of diverse knowledge across multiple social boundaries.<marker type="block"/> My dissertation research addresses the question of how participants on multi-party IS development projects collaborate across social boundaries to achieve results. It relies on an ethnographic field study of an Internet consulting firm looking at how this firm and its clients deal with cross-boundary collaboration challenges.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">The following section discusses the literature on social boundaries, communicative genres, and boundary objects. Subsequent chapters discuss research questions, the study methodology, the research setting, expected contributions, and some anticipated challenges.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="22" page="3" column="1">Theoretical Foundation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Social Boundaries In order to understand knowledge sharing in heterogeneous environments, it is necessary to first clarify the nature of the heterogeneity that is creating challenges in collaboration.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="3" column="1">The question of heterogeneity in organization has been traditionally addressed through the lens of organizational culture. This socio-cultural view is focused on uncovering shared interpretations derived from multiple interactions among people ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Van Maanen and Barley, 1985</xref>). Over the years, the literature on organizational culture has shifted focus from that on cultural unity of an organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Schein, 1992</xref>) to that of cultural fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Martin, 1992</xref>). Some researchers outright deny cultural unity arguing that<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> organizations consist of subcultures that are used as a differentiation mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Van Maanen and Barley, 1985</xref>). Others argue that organizational culture is in a constant state of flux and ambiguity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Martin, 1992</xref>). Still others argue that culture is complex and multi- faceted:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="28" page="3" column="1">3</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Members of an organization are unlikely to be restricted in their membership to one single culture or subculture because people may identify with their gender, ethnic background, parent and spouse roles, sports, club, city, the university from which they hold a degree, profession, department, division, work organization, geographical region, industry, national, or greater region such as Europe, America, and Asia. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Sackmann, 1997</xref>: p. 2).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="4" column="1">In this “complex” culture view, researchers have to focus on those cultural contexts that are salient to the circumstance ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Sackmann, 1997</xref>: p. 37). The “complex” view provides us with some insights on boundaries: “boundaries between people appear and disappear, as they are marked or ignored depending on the ideas, interests, and identities that are at stake and the setting in which the interaction takes place” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Ybema, 1997</xref>: p. 164).<marker type="block"/> While the cultural perspective acknowledges multiple types of heterogeneity, it leaves us with the question of how to identify and differentiate salient boundaries. Social identity theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Tajfel, 1978</xref>) along with social distance theory (Park, 1950) have been traditionally used to define boundaries. These perspectives view boundaries as “physical, temporal, emotional, cognitive, and/or relational limits that define entities as separate from one another” (Ashforth, et al., 2000: p. 474). Boundaries are viewed as "mental fences" that help individuals simplify and order the environment (Ashforth, et al., 2000: p. 474). The research on social identity has focused on issues of individual identification with the group (in-group) as opposed to other groups (out-group) showing that this differentiation has a strong influence on how individuals perceive other individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Suzuki, 1998</xref>). This research has also focused on how an individual integrates multiple identities and which identities are more salient in given circumstances (Ashforth, et al., 2000). While social identity theory does not pay attention to knowledge shared by the group, it does offer some useful insights into the investigation of the knowledge sharing question. In particular, it offers: 1) clarity and versatility of the definition of a boundary and 2) insights into psychological difficulties that organizational actors experience in sharing knowledge across boundaries; and 3) insights about which identities (boundaries) are most salient in a given context (although on an individual rather than a group level). These are useful insights yet there is still a need for the understanding of boundaries among social groups.<marker type="block"/> The ambiguity in the cultural perspective has been critiqued by practice theorists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Giddens, 1984</xref>). Practice theory argues that the controversy within the socio-cultural perspective stems from the futile attempt to unambiguously define “shared interpretations” or “shared assumptions” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Lave, 1988; Lave and Wenger, 1991</xref>;Wenger, 1998). As some have pointed out, the values, assumptions, and interpretations that organizational actors draw upon change depending on the context of action (Martin,<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> 1992). To resolve the controversy in the cultural perspective, practice theory researchers emphasize the context of everyday practices denying the ability to formulate rules (including "shared assumptions") that are outside those practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Giddens, 1984</xref>; Lave, 1988). Moreover, practice theory, particularly in the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu (1977; 1998; 1992)</xref>, might be especially suitable for understanding the nature of social boundaries because it focuses on the differences among social groups. This is a relational theory that defines social space by the differences in dispositions:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="44" page="4" column="1">4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">... the main idea is that to exist within a social space, to occupy a point or to be an individual within a social space, is to differ, to be different. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1998</xref>: p. 9).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="5" column="1">The practice theory perspective has given rise to the notion of “communities of practice” ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Lave and Wenger, 1991</xref>), which is at the mainstream of the knowledge management literature. Communities of practice are seen as "groups of interdependent participants providing a work context within which members construct both shared identities and the social context that helps those identities be shared" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 2000</xref>: p. 9). The research on communities of practice has focused primarily on the study of homogeneous communities rather than on differences in social practices across or within communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid (2000)</xref> noted this shortcoming in prior community of practice studies arguing that knowledge is “sticky” as well as “leaky”. While it “leaks” within communities, it becomes “sticky” in transferring across communities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (1997)</xref> has looked at the issues of "sticky" knowledge by analyzing knowledge sharing practices associated with functional boundaries of product development teams. The functional boundaries considered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (1997)</xref> are demarcated by the differences in objects and ends of each group as the group addresses a given product development problem. While these practice theory based accounts have addressed the shortcoming of the cultural literature by shifting the focus from shared assumptions to practices, they have only done so in relation to the functional boundary. Other important boundaries between industries, organizations, project teams, gender groups, national identities, and age groups that have been the focus of the culture literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Sackmann, 1997</xref>) and social identity research (Ashforth, et al., 2000) have not been examined.<marker type="block"/> In this study, I adopt a practice theory perspective as it has proved to be useful in both understanding IS design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski, 2000</xref>) and studies of collaboration in organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Bechky, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Lave, 1988; Lave and Wenger, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Yates, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Schultze, 2000</xref>). I also propose to draw on the cultural and social identity perspectives to develop a broader practice theory notion of social boundaries. For example, the psychological view on social identity is surprisingly compatible with practice-theory notions. In fact, both see the formation of social identity as an outcome of association with a social group defining social identity only in terms of the differences among groups rather than intrinsic characteristics of a group. It will be an empirical matter to investigate how these different perspectives can be usefully combined to address my research question.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> Communicative Genres Collaboration in organizations unfolds through communicative practices of organizational actors (Weick, 1987). The concept of “communicative genre” has proved to be useful in understanding communication practices in software development teams as they adopt new communication media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Yates, 1994</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Yates (1994)</xref> define “genres of organizational communication as socially recognized types of communicative actions--such as memos, meetings, expense forms, training seminars--that are habitually enacted by members of a community to realize particular social purposes” (p. 542). I propose to extend the notion of “communicative genre” to account for the communication practices that are enacted at the boundary of several social groups. Prior studies on communicative genres focused on genres traced through electronic medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Yates, 1994</xref>; Yates, et al., 1999), the research question in this study requires an examination of both electronic and non-electronic genres. Finally, this study will focus on the evolution of the genres over the project lifetime focusing on how genres used within social groups relate to genres used to communicate across group boundaries.<marker type="block"/> One other important advantage that the communicative genre lens offers is the ability to judge genre effectiveness. Based on the definition of a communicative genre, there are two modes of failure associated with it: 1) the lack of agreement about the purpose and form of the genre (when these are not socially recognized by all parties); and 2) failing to achieve the socially recognized purposes of the genre in its enactment. The ability to define genre effectiveness is a useful tool in addressing the broader question of effective collaboration on projects.<marker type="block"/> Boundary Objects It is well known in both the practitioner and academic literature that IS development professionals rely on schematics and prototypes to communicate with system users. Formal knowledge representations are used to capture user requirements and to serve as communication medium for project team members (Agarwal, et al., 2000). For example, requirements documents are traditional representations of business stakeholders’ requirements as well as the resource constraints of developers. Within development teams they are typically used to share the knowledge between business analysts and programmers. Representations like these can be seen as “boundary objects” because they can be used to negotiate solutions in collaborative problem solving. Boundary objects have been defined as objects that are “both plastic enough to adapt to the local needs and constraints of several parties employing them, yet robust enough to maintain a common identity across sites” (Star, 1989:46).<marker type="block"/> The concept of boundary objects comes from the social studies of science. Researchers in this field have found that heterogeneous scientific communities routinely employ boundary objects in their collaborative problem solving (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Star, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer, 1989</xref>). Boundary objects have also been found to be useful in engineering product development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Bechky, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>; Henderson, 1991) and medical classification systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Bowker and Star, 1994</xref>; Bowker, et al., 1996). In the IS literature, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Boland and Tenkasi (1995)</xref> suggest that while narratives play a critical role in creating knowledge</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="69" page="5" column="1">5</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="83" page="6" column="1">6</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">within professional communities, boundary objects are critical for sharing knowledge across communities. Boundary objects have been found to be effective in combating knowledge sharing challenges because they made the contextual and tacit character of an individual’s knowledge more accessible and visible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>). They have also been seen to function as power tokens by enlarging knowledge boundaries between functions and creating a common investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" page="7" column="1">In this study, I will investigate the role of boundary objects in cross-boundary communicative genres. Traditionally, the genre literature has emphasized the norms of communication and the role of actors rather than the knowledge representations used in communicative practices. Our insights will be strengthened by combining the two perspectives. For example, the prior boundary objects literature has pointed to the difficulty of creating effective boundary objects (Henderson, 1991), while several studies have indicated that effective boundary objects should be concrete, in that they should be tied to the specific terms and concepts of the problem in practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Bechky, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>). However, it is the concreteness of the boundary object that often makes it too restrictive to allow for different, novel interpretations of the problem (Henderson, 1991). The communicative genre lens will allow me to investigate the relationship between various characteristics of boundary objects, the norms of communication developed around them, and the role of actors involved in creating and using them.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="90" page="7" column="1">Research Questions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">The practical challenges associated with collaboration in diverse environments have led me to investigate the following question: how do participants on multi-party IS development projects communicate across social boundaries to achieve results ? Prior literature suggests that the following specific questions should be useful in building a framework that addresses this question: 1. What is the nature of the social boundaries in and across organizations? 2. Which communicative genres emerge in multi-party IS development settings? 3. How do communicative genres evolve over the lifetime of an IS project? 4. What role do boundary objects play in cross-boundary communicative genres on IS projects? 5. Which communicative genres are effective in increasing the quality of IS project outcomes?</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="92" page="7" column="1">Asking these specific questions will not only address my main research question, but will also help me build the tools for addressing other research questions in the future.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="93" page="7" column="1">Research Methodology</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="7" column="1">The study of knowledge sharing calls for the use of interpretive methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Baroudi, 1991</xref>) as knowledge is deeply imbedded in organizational practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>). To learn how knowledge is shared in IS development settings I have conducted an ethnographic field study of an Internet consulting firm. Internet consulting firms routinely deal with knowledge sharing challenges in their work with clients and within their cross-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="97" page="7" column="1">7</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">disciplinary teams. For nine months I have been collecting data from four different observational settings within this firm: 1) a training program for new employees; 2) a strategic planning phase of a client project; 3) a requirements gathering and prototype development phase of the same client project; and 4) multiple projects at a Research and Development (R&amp;D) group. Multiple observational settings allow me to compare different group practices. Most of my data collection consisted of on-site observations of the everyday life of participants. Ethnographic techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Agar, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Van Maanen, 1979</xref>) will be used to collect the data. Systematic iterative coding of the data will be used to develop a grounded theoretical model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Glaser and Strauss, 1967</xref>). I have visited the site four days a week on average since December 1999, attending meetings, collecting documentation, shadowing, and interviewing people from client and consulting organizations. To develop the notion of social boundaries, I have gathered data on different characteristics of actors involved in interactions - demographic data on individuals, their professional backgrounds, etc.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" page="8" column="1">To understand the development and enactment of communicative genres, I kept detailed notes of actor's everyday practices. I spent the bulk of my time observing meetings. I also shadowed individuals to see how their individual work practices influence their communication practices. In interviews, I asked participants about their communication practices in other work environments as well as about their individual purposes in communicating.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">To identify boundary objects, I have kept track of various tangible knowledge representations used in practice. This is because tangibility, “the ability to hold and manipulate an object,” is a key characteristic of boundary objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>). I am taking a broad view of tangibility to include electronic representations because they can be manipulated just like non-electronic ones. After examining numerous tangible representations, I am identifying those matching the definition of boundary objects. I have completed my data collection in September 2000. As of today, the initial thematic analysis and coding of data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Glaser and Strauss, 1967</xref>) has produced some emergent categories, which I am further investigating through systematic collection, coding, and analysis.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="106" page="8" column="1">Expected Theoretical Contributions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" page="8" column="1">This research will contribute to our understanding of IS development by focusing on communication and knowledge sharing practices on IS projects. This is an important new topic in IS research (Kumar, et al., 1998; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Wastell, 1999</xref>). This study will investigate collaboration practices of a wide group of developers, system owners, and users, working in a novel E-commerce arena, which will lead to a discovery of new issues and solutions. By using the boundary objects lens I hope to shed light on the role of formal system</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="109" page="8" column="1">8</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">representations in communication practices of IS project team members (Agarwal, et al., 2000). This investigation is particularly important in an IS outsourcing environment, helping us understand how vendors and clients can learn from each other (Koh, et al., 1999). This research will also extend our understanding of boundary objects in organizations. First, it will broaden prior focus of boundary object research beyond functional or professional boundaries. Second, it will enrich our understanding of boundary objects by situating them in the context of communication genres. This will help shed light on how characteristics of boundary objects relate to communicative norms and the roles of individuals.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" page="9" column="1">This work will also help extend the communicative genre concept into heterogeneous environments. Such extension will also help better understand communicative genre evolution and failure because multi-party settings are likely to challenge established genres. Understanding the use of cross-boundary communicative genres can shed light on collaboration mechanisms beyond boundary objects such as sharing narratives, creating common languages, and engaging boundary spanners.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Implications of this study will also contribute to the Computer-Supported Collaborative Work field by showing the adequacies and inadequacies of current process technology in supporting collaboration through boundary objects. Such analysis can further inform the development of more effective collaborative support tools.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="120" page="9" column="1">This research will begin developing an integrative perspective on many issues that fall under the umbrella of collaboration in heterogeneous environments. Similar issues appear in studies of virtual, cross-functional, multi-organizational, and culturally diverse work settings. Most of the studies focus on knowledge sharing across professional groups (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Bechky, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Sitkin and Brown, 1999</xref>). Work on outsourcing and innovation addresses issues of sharing knowledge across organizational boundaries (e.g., Koh, et al., 1999; von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 1994</xref>). Others study the role of national culture in communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Suzuki, 1998</xref>). Yet others focus on organizational unit boundaries (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Dixon, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Szulanski, 1995</xref>). A useful cross-pollination of ideas occurs when these diverse organizational research streams are drawn under a unifying lens of collaboration across boundaries.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="121" page="9" column="1">Expected Practical Implications</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="9" column="1">This research will have implications for the development of software engineering methodologies aimed at representing diverse knowledge in systems design. For example, object-oriented analysis methods propose that business customers and strategists share knowledge with technologists by describing the behavior of users through key business objects ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Jacobson, 1993</xref>). Are these representations effective as boundary objects? Findings from my research may suggest how new software engineering methodologies can be created around useful boundary objects and communicative genres.<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> Organizational members spend a lot of time creating various knowledge representations and then communicating around them in meetings. "Death by PowerPoint" is a familiar expression in the consulting world. Given the resource investment that creating and using knowledge representations entails, there is value in examining and reflecting on which communication practices are more useful for achieving project goals. The theory developed here will help organizational members engage in such reflection.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="124" page="9" column="1">9</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="126" page="10" column="1">Challenges</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="10" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="127" class="deo:Reference">The challenge for the coming months will be to catalogue and analyze an estimated 2000</xref> typewritten pages of data from the study. In analyzing the data set, one of the key challenges lies in making meaningful comparisons between the R&amp;D group observations and the project team observations. Operationalizing communicative genres previously used in archival studies in an ethnographic study is also challenging. My most important theoretical challenges are in clarifying the nature of social boundaries and clarifying the concept of concreteness which, while central to boundary object research not yet been deeply understood. Finally, I see a challenge in integrating my work with the mainstream IS literature on IS analysis and design.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="129" page="10" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" page="10" column="1">My dissertation research will advance our understanding of knowledge sharing and communication practices on multi-party product development projects as people learn to deal with a variety of social boundaries. Because communication practices are deeply embedded in the day-to-day life of practitioners they are often left unexamined despite the large amount of common frustration that they create. To understand these practices, I will first clarify the nature of heterogeneity that creates barriers to knowledge sharing by drawing on the literatures of practice theory, organizational culture, and social identity. Then I will apply and extend the notions of communicative genres and boundary objects into the multi-party IS development setting. An artful combination of these two perspectives should offer new insights into organizational theory and IS research. This work will have implications for IS Development practices, the study of multi-party collaboration in general, and the design of collaboration technologies.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="131" page="10" column="1">10</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="132" page="11" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="11" column="1">Agar, M. The professional stranger : an informal introduction to ethnography, Academic Press, New York, NY, 1980.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="11" column="1">Agarwal, R., De, P., Sinha, A. and Tanniru, M. "On the usability of OO representations," Communications of the ACM (43:10), 2000, pp. 83-9.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="11" column="1">Ashforth, B.E., Kreiner, G.E. and Fugate, M. "All in a Day's Work: Boundaries and Micro Role Transitions," The Academy of Management Review (25:3), 2000, pp. 472- 491.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Bechky, B.A. "Crossing Occupational Boundaries: Communication and Learning on a Production Floor," unpublished Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation, Stanford University, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="11" column="1">Boland, R.J., Jr. and Tenkasi, R.V. "Perspective making and perspective taking in communities of knowing," Organization Science (6:4), 1995, pp. 350-372.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="11" column="1">Bourdieu, P. Outline of a theory of practice, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge ; New York, 1977.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="11" column="1">Bourdieu, P. Practical reason : on the theory of action, Stanford University Press, Stanford, Calif., 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="11" column="1">Bourdieu, P. and Wacquant, L.J.D. An invitation to reflexive sociology, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1992.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Bowker, G. and Star, S.L. "Knowledge and Information in International Information Management: Problems of Classification and Coding," In Information Acumen: The Understanding and Use of Knowledge in Modern Business, L. Bud-Frierman (Ed.), Routledge, London, 1994, pp. 187-213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="11" column="1">Bowker, G., Timmermans, S. and Star, S.L. "Infrastructure and Organizational Transformations: Classifying Nurses' Work," In Information Technology and Changes in Organizational Work, W. J. Orlikowski, G. Walsham, M. R. Jones and J. I. DeGross (Ed.), Chapman and Hall, London, UK, 1996, pp. 344-369.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="11" column="1">Brown, J.S. and Duguid, P. "Organizational Learning and Communities of Practice: Toward a Unified View of Working, Learning, and Innovation," Organization Science (2:1), 1991, pp. 40-57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="11" column="1">Brown, J.S. and Duguid, P. "Knowledge and Organization: A Social-Practice Perspective," Organization Science (Forthcoming), 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="12" column="1">Carlile, P.R. "Understanding Knowledge Transformation In Product Development: Making Knowledge Manifest Through Boundary Objects," unpublished Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation, University Of Michigan, 1997.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="12" column="1">Dixon, N.M. Common knowledge : how companies thrive by sharing what they know, Harvard Business School Press, Boston, 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="12" column="1">Giddens, A. The constitution of society : outline of the theory of structuration, University of California Press, Berkeley, 1984.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="12" column="1">Glaser, B.G. and Strauss, A.L. The discovery of grounded theory; strategies for qualitative research, Aldine Pub. Co., Chicago, IL, 1967. Henderson, K. "Flexible Sketches and Inflexible Data Bases: Visual Communication Conscription Devices, and Boundary Objects in Design Engineering," Science, Technology, &amp; Human Value (16:4), 1991, pp. 448-473.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="12" column="1">Jacobson, I. Object-oriented software engineering : a use case driven approach, ACM Press, New York, NY, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" page="12" column="1">Kogut, B. and Zander, U. "Knowledge of the Firm, Combinative Capabilities, and the Replication of Technology," Organization Science (3:3), 1992, pp. 383-397.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="12" column="1">Koh, C., Tay, C. and Ang, S. "Managing Vendor-Client Expectations in IT Outsourcing: A Psychological Contract Perspective," Proceedings of the Proceedings of the Twentieth International Conference on Information Systems, Charlotte, NC, 1999, pp. 512-518.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="12" column="1">Kumar, K., van Dissel, H. and Bielli, P. "The Merchant of Prato revisited: toward a third rationality of information systems," MIS Quarterly (22:2), 1998, pp. 199-226. Lave, J. Cognition in practice : mind, mathematics, and culture in everyday life, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge ; New York, 1988.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="12" column="1">Lave, J. and Wenger, E. Situated learning: legitimate peripheral participation, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, England, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="12" column="1">Liebeskind, J.P., Oliver, A.L., Zucker, L. and Brewer, M. "Social networks, learning, and flexibility: Sourcing scientific knowledge in new biotechnology firms," Organization Science (7:4), 1996, pp. 428-443.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" page="12" column="1">Marcus, M.L. "Power, Politics, and MIS Implementation," Communications of the ACM (26:6), 1983, pp. 430-444. <marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> Martin, J. Cultures in organizations : three perspectives, Oxford University Press, New York, 1992.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="13" column="1">Nonaka, I. "A dynamic theory of organizational knowledge creation," Organization Science (5:1), 1994, pp. 14-37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="13" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. "The Duality of Technology: Rethinking the Concept of Technology in Organizations," Organization Science (3:3), 1992, pp. 398-427.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="13" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. "Knowledgeability in Practice: Towards a Perspective on Organizational Knowing," Working Paper MIT Sloan School of Management, 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="13" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. and Baroudi, J.J. "Studying Information Technology in Organizations: Research Approaches and Assumptions," Information Systems Research (2:1), 1991, pp. 143-169.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="13" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. and Gash, D.C. "Technological Frames: Making Sense of Information Technology in Organizations," ACM Transactions on Information Systems (12:2), 1994, pp. 174-207.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="13" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. and Yates, J. "Genre repertoire: The structuring of communicative practices in organizations," Administrative Science Quarterly (39:4), 1994, pp. 541-574. Park, R.E. Race and culture, Free Press, Glencoe, Il., 1950.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="13" column="1">Sackmann, S. Cultural complexity in organizations: inherent contrasts and contradictions, Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, Calif., 1997.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="13" column="1">Schein, E.H. Organizational culture and leadership, Jossey-Bass, San Francisco, CA, 1992.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="13" column="1">Schultze, U. "A confessional account of an ethnography about knowledge work," MIS Quarterly (24:1), 2000, pp. 3-6.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="13" column="1">Sitkin, S.B. and Brown, J.S. "Fostering the Coupling of Generative Differences: Creating Space for Pluralism," Proceedings of the Academy of Management 1999 Conference,</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Chicago, IL, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Star, S.L. "The Structure of Ill-Structured Solutions: Boundary Objects and Heterogeneous Distributed Problem Solving," In Readings in Distributed Artificial Intelligence, M. Huhn and L. Gasser (Ed.), Morgan Kaufman, Menlo Park, CA, 1989, pp.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">37-54.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="14" column="1">Star, S.L. and Griesemer, J.R. "Institutional Ecology, 'Translations' and Boundary Objects: Amateurs and Professionals in Berkeley's Museum of Vertebrate Zoology 1907- 39," Social Studies of Science (19), 1989, pp. 387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="14" column="1">Suzuki, S. "In-Group and Out-Group Communication Patterns in International Organizations: Implications for Social Identity Theory," Communication Research (25:2), 1998, pp. 154-182.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="14" column="1">Szulanski, G. "Unpacking stickiness: An empirical investigation of the barriers to transfer best practices inside the firm," Academy of Management Journal :Best Papers Proceedings 1995), 1995, pp. 437-441.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="14" column="1">Tajfel, H. Differentiation between social groups: studies in the social psychology of intergroup relations, Published in cooperation with European Association of Experimental Social Psychology by Academic Press, London ; New York, 1978.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="14" column="1">Van Maanen, J. "The Fact of Fiction in Organizational Ethnography," Administrative Science Quarterly (24), 1979, pp. 539-550.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="14" column="1">Van Maanen, J. and Barley, S. "Cultural Organization: Fragments of a Theory," In Organizational Culture, P. Frost, L. F. Moore, M. R. Louis, C. C. Lundberg and J. Martin (Ed.), Sage, Newbury Park, 1985, pp. 31-53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="14" column="1">von Hippel, E. ""Sticky information" and the locus of problem solving: Implications for innovation," Management Science (40:4), 1994, pp. 429-439.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="14" column="1">Wastell, D. "Learning dysfunctions in information systems development: overcoming the social defenses with transitional objects," MIS Quarterly (23:4), 1999, pp. 581-600.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="14" column="1">Weick, K. "Theorizing about Organizational Communication," In Handbook of</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="14" column="1">Organizational Communication, F. Jablin, L. Putnam, K. Roberts and L. Porter (Ed.), Sage, Newbury Park, CA, 1987, pp. 97-122.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="14" column="1">Wenger, E. Communities of practice: learning, meaning, and identity, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K.; New York, N.Y., 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="14" column="1">Yates, J., Orlikowski, W.J. and Okamura, K. "Explicit and Implicit Structuring of Genres in Electronic Communication: Reinforcement and Change of Social Interaction," Organizational Science (10:1), 1999, pp. 83-103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="14" column="1">Ybema, S.B. "Telling Tales: Contrasts and Commonalities Within the Organization of an Amusement Park -- Confronting and Combining Different Perspectives," In Cultural Complexity in Organizations, S. Sackmann (Ed.), Sage, Thousand Oaks, 1997, pp. 160-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">186.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="145" page="11" column="1">11</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="157" page="12" column="1">12</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="172" page="13" column="1">13</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="187" page="14" column="1">14</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
