<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>a6885d94733bfa5d58d19233d978cd999d7e47ee40908b7b6cb9f6c18a8fb8ee</job>
    <base_name>62pn</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-94-010-0868-6_54">http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/581710.581712</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">CONSTRUCTED REPRESENTATIONS AND THEIR FUNCTIONS IN COMPUTATIONAL MODELS OF DESIGNING</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">The Key Centre of Design Computing and Cognition Department of Architectural and Design Science University of Sydney NSW 2006 Australia e-mail: {john, <email id="3">rob}@arch.usyd.edu.au</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6">This paper re-examines the conclusions made by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="5" class="deo:Reference">Schön and Wiggins in 1992</xref> that computers were unable to reproduce processes crucial to designing. We propose that recent developments in artificial intelligence and design computing put us in a position where we can begin to computationally model designing as conceived by Schön and Wiggins. We present a computational model of designing using situated processes that construct representations. We show how constructed representations support computational processes that model the different kinds of seeing reported in designing. We also present recently developed computational processes that can identify unexpected consequences of design actions using adaptive novelty detection.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="1">In the paper “Kinds of Seeing and their Functions in Designing” Schön and Wiggins discussed how designers see their on-going designs in different ways and how these kinds of seeing affect the design process ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="8" class="deo:Reference">Schön and Wiggins, 1992</xref>). The studies provide evidence that different kinds of seeing are essential to the intertwined processes of designing and discovering within and between design episodes. Schön and Wiggins enumerated three kinds of seeing, literal apprehension of representations, apprehension of figures, and appreciative judgements of quality. To these different kinds of seeing they also added the recognition of unintended consequences of design actions. More recent protocol studies have provided additional evidence that unexpected discoveries play an important role in designing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Suwa, Gero et al., 1998</xref>). In the concluding remarks of their paper, Schön and Wiggins made the following statement regarding the potential impact of their understanding of designing to the future of development of computationally models:<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> "When we think of designing ... as a conversation with materials conducted in the medium of drawing and crucially dependent on seeing, we are bound to attend to processes that computers are unable — at least presently unable — to reproduce: the perception of figures or gestalts, the appreciation of qualities, the recognition of unintended consequences of moves." Recent developments in design computing and artificial intelligence put us in a position where it is now possible to re-examine whether computers are now able to begin to model designing as conceived by Schön and Wiggins. Computational processes already exist for the perception of figures and gestalts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Gero and Yan, 1994</xref>), the appreciation of qualities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Soufi and Edmonds, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Reffat and Gero, 1998</xref>). We present here additional processes capable of recognizing unintended consequences of actions. Throughout this paper, reference to perception, appreciation and recognition within computational systems is assumed to mean the generation of appropriate representations to process figures, qualities and consequences within the limitations of the design system's goals. The remainder of this paper will examine various aspects of a recently developed computational model of designing. Section 2 introduces constructed representations as they our defined for this work. In Section 3 we examine the creative design process of emergence and its relationship to expectations in learning agents and the concept of novelty. Section 4 presents an experimental implementation of the computational model. Subsection 4.5 introduces the computationally processes of novelty detection used to recognise unintended consequences of actions. Section 5 gives a demonstration of an experimental implementation learning of a new drawing action for a novel emergent shape.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="11" page="2" column="1">202</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="12" page="2" column="1">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="17" page="2" column="1">2. Constructed Representations</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" page="2" column="1">We refer to constructed representations throughout this paper to differentiate representations produced by situated computational processes from fixed representations traditionally used in CAAD systems. Unlike fixed representations, constructed representations can have many interpretations of a design depending on the situation of the design agent. Human designers use drawings to construct representations in response to goals and experiences during designing. As Mitchell points out the ambiguity of drawings plays an important role in this. “... design is not description of what is, it is exploration of what might be. Drawings are valuable precisely because they are rich in suggestions of what might be ... Thus the meaning of a drawing is not adequately captured by imposing one structure on it.” ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Mitchell, 1990</xref>)<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> Constructed representations take advantage of the ambiguity of drawings to support the “suggestions of what might be” for computational processes. Constructed representations are determined with respect to current design goals, strategies and knowledge learned from previous similar experiences. Learning plays an important role in processes that construct representations.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="20" page="3" column="1">C ONSTRUCTED R EPRESENTATIONS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="21" page="3" column="1">203</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" page="3" column="1">2.1. SITUATEDNESS</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="3" column="1">Situatedness holds that “where you are when you do what you do matters” ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Clancey, 1997</xref>). Situatedness is an important concept for designers, human or otherwise. Designing is fundamentally a situated act because it is concerned with changing the world within which it operates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Gero, 1999</xref>). Constructed representations situate computational design processes. Perceptual processes construct representations that are appropriate for a particular moment in time according to the current focus of interest determined by the accumulated knowledge of a design agent. As a consequence, constructed representations allow non-learning design processes to be sensitive to the design situation. Situated perceptual processes may construct many representations from a single fixed representation of a design. To support the construction of new representations of a design it is often useful to choose an intermediary representation that relaxes some constraints. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> illustrates how the infinite maximal line representation of a building can support many constructed representations each highlighting a different aspect of the design.<marker type="block"/> Choosing which representations to construct and the importance of each representation can be problematic because importance varies from situation to<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> situation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Waltz, 1999</xref>). We propose that design emergence is an appropriate means of determining the importance of constructed representations.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx28">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pn.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62pn.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="unknown" id="29" page="3" column="1">b. c. d. e. f. g. h. i. j.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="31" page="3" column="1">Figure 1. Multiple representations of a house generated using the infinite maximal line representation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Reffat and Gero 1998</xref>).</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="33" page="4" column="1">204</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="34" page="4" column="1">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="37" page="4" column="1">3. Emergence, Expectations and Novelty</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="4" column="1">Design emergence has become the focus of much attention in the design computing research field in recent years as one of only a small number of design processes that can expand a design space and hence facilitate creative designing ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Gero, 1990</xref>). We use the term design emergence to differentiate the creative design process of emergence from its meanings in other fields of research, e.g. artificial life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Cariani, 1991</xref>). Design emergence is the recognition of unintended consequences that Schön and Wiggins mentioned We use the definition of design emergence given by Gero: emergence is the process of making implicit features explicit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Gero, 1992</xref>). Hence, design emergence is defined relative to a conceptual model of the design situation held by an observer. It has been suggested that drawing can be considered as a means of externalising a conceptual model in order to look at it afresh and facilitate the process of emergence: “... we all externalise in order to find out what it is we have in our heads ... We produce something in order to compare it with incoming data ... It is through this externalisation process that we are able to know what we believe about the world.” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Cohen, 1983</xref>) Design emergence is therefore a process of constructing new representations of existing beliefs to make explicit features of those beliefs that were previously only implicit. Drawings afford designers the opportunity to construct new representations of their beliefs and test their expectations. Expectations provide a basis for comparison between a designer’s beliefs and reality. Differences between the designer’s expectations and observations can be used to isolate, and subsequently explicitly represent, aspects the products and processes of designing that were partially or completely misunderstood. A designer can thereby learn an explicit representation of the effects of a design action previously defined implicitly in its mechanics. This is the model of design emergence that Schön and Wiggins referred to when they wrote about the “the recognition of unintended consequences of moves”. For example,<marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the emergence of shapes where drawing two overlapping squares implicitly define three emergent shapes that can be perceived by considering the spaces bounded by the lines, i.e. the intersection and differences of the two squares.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> A computational model of design emergence must therefore include processes that monitor both the products and the processes of designing. Designing has to be monitored in order to detect significant changes in representation that indicate the addition of new knowledge. Determining the significance of changes in representation is a vital part of the process of design emergence. We present one approach to monitoring for design emergence by gauging the novelty of constructed representations.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="45" page="5" column="1">C ONSTRUCTED R EPRESENTATIONS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="46" page="5" column="1">205</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="47" page="5" column="1">(a) (b) (c)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="48" page="5" column="1">Figure 2. An illustration of shape emergence: (a) the two squares drawn, (b) the Gestalt figure formed, (c) the three emergent shapes perceived.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" page="5" column="1">3.1. NOVELTY</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="5" column="1">We define the novelty of constructed representations as the combination of its newness and its utility within a situation. Our definition of novelty is therefore related to situated creativity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Suwa, Gero et al., 1998</xref>), and hence to Boden’s concepts of psychological creativity and historical creativity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Boden, 1991</xref>). The definition of creative designing as the expansion of a design space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Gero, 1990</xref>) leads us to a generally useful property of novel representations to support emergence. To be novel within the context of creative designing, a constructed representation must expand the conceptual state space of a design agent. Situations that could not have been predicted by the design agent from previous experience, and hence expand its conceptual state space, are defined as novel. Situations that could have been predicted from previous experiences, despite never having actually been experienced directly, are not novel under this definition. Interestingly, situated design systems that recollect previous situations dynamically by constructing representations can find previous experiences novel on a second encounter due the effects on memory of intervening experiences.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="55" page="6" column="1">206</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="6" column="1">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="57" page="6" column="1">4. Sketch: A Computational Exploration</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="6" column="1">Sketch is an experimental system developed to explore the potential of various technologies to model simple creativity using emergence. Sketch constructs representations that capture different aspects of the ongoing design situation. The computational system can be broken down into a generative subsystem that executes drawing actions and four layers of perceptual processes each layer corresponding to the different kinds of seeing as described by Schön and Wiggins. The perceptual layers are labelled from the lowest to the highest: literal syntactic apprehension, emergent syntactic apprehension, semantic appreciation and novelty detection.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="6" column="1">4.1. DRAWING ACTIONS</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="6" column="1">Sketch supports two types of drawing action, shape drawing actions and affine transformations. Drawing actions can be specified either by the generative computational subsystem or by a human operator. Shape drawing actions consist of a number of horizontal and vertical line drawing actions that have been grouped together to form a closed boundary around a central location. Affine transformations affect the whole canvas and are used to quickly reproduce a drawn shape into new locations and orientations. A bitmap image is used as a canvas for all drawing actions as it is a convenient representation to pass on to perceptual processes.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="61" page="6" column="1">4.2. LITERAL SYNTACTIC APPREHENSION</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="6" column="1">The literal syntactic layer contains the most primitive representations of the current design, i.e. bitmap images of the regions of interest of the design canvas. The determination of the regions of interest is done at higher levels of the hierarchy. The representations constructed within this layer are considered to be analogous to the literal apprehension of drawings by human designers. The computational model of literal apprehension of shapes is the simplest of the perceptual processes. Literal apprehension of shapes is achieved by categorizing bitmap images of regions of interest using a self-organizing map neural network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Kohonen, 1997</xref>). The self-organizing map constructs a classification of bitmap images representing shapes. Images are categorized by comparing them against previously learned classifications to identify the best matching category. The classification is then updated by adjusting the network’s representation (i.e. its synaptic connection weights) to better capture the features of the new image. The self-organizing map learns continuously in this way throughout the design process, updating its classification of images to cover the shapes found.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="7" column="1">C ONSTRUCTED R EPRESENTATIONS</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="65" page="7" column="1">207</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="66" page="7" column="1">4.3. EMERGENT SYNTACTIC APPREHENSION</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="7" column="1">The emergent syntactic apprehension layer processes construct emergent figures and gestalts not explicitly represented in the literal syntactic apprehension layer. This layer makes use of horizontal and vertical edge representations, infinite maximal line representations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Gero and Yan, 1994</xref>) and bounded space representations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Soufi and Edmonds, 1995</xref>). The emergent syntactic layer produces bitmap images suitable for further analysis to produce design actions for novel emergent shapes. Modelling the apprehension of figures is more complex than the literal apprehension of shapes because it requires image processing for feature detection to support the generation of the edge, infinite maximal line and bounded space representations before recognition of emergent shapes can be done. However, the learning process is exactly the same as for literal apprehension, using a self-organizing map to construct a classification of the emergent figures.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="7" column="1">4.4. SEMANTIC APPRECIATION</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="7" column="1">The semantic appreciation layer provides processes for the evaluating literal and emergent syntactic descriptions to produce appreciative judgements of qualities, e.g. geometric relationships between shapes. Syntactic perceptual processes provide the inputs to the construction of semantic representations that model appreciative judgements of quality. The semantic appreciation processes compare original and transformed versions of an image pixel-by-pixel to produce quantitative measures of geometric qualities, e.g. rotational symmetry, reflectional symmetry etc.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="72" page="7" column="1">4.5. NOVELTY DETECTION</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="7" column="1">The novelty detection layer contains the adaptive novelty detection processes that recognize unexpected consequences of design actions. Literal syntactic, emergent syntactic and semantic representations are used as the inputs to the adaptive novelty detection processes. Adaptive novelty detection uses the expectations and associated confidences generated by learning systems to construct representations of the relationships between perceptions and construct expectations of the consequences of taking design actions. We have developed implementations of adaptive novelty detection processes that monitor the representations constructed by several different types of neural networks, e.g. self-organising maps, back-propagation networks, recurrent Hopfield networks and several ART-based networks. Many neural networks construct expectations during learning while only some provide an associated confidence, e.g. ARTMAP networks ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Carpenter, Grossberg et al., 1991</xref>). Neural<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> networks that do not provide measures of confidence require additional monitoring.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="8" column="1">208</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="76" page="8" column="1">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="8" column="1">5. An Example Problem</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="8" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> shows a screenshot of an early implementation of Sketch in operation. The number of representations constructed has been limited to literal pixel values, horizontal and vertical edges, bounded spaces and novelty. However, this reduced set of representations is sufficient to demonstrate the important design skill of learning a new drawing action for a novel emergent shape.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pn.page_008.image_02.png" thmb="62pn.page_008.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="82" page="8" column="1">Figure 3. A screenshot of Sketch in operation showing the current design and the representations constructed.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="83" page="8" column="1">5.1. FINDING REGIONS OF INTEREST</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="8" column="1">In order to find emergent shapes Sketch first has to be able to identify regions of interest in the input image. The current implementation analyses the entire drawing canvas to find closed spaces and produces a number of fixation points at the centre of each one. Each fixation point is used to extract a set of smaller bitmap images of the surrounding area that is used for input to the perceptual processes.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="85" page="8" column="1">5.2. PERCEIVING EMERGENT SHAPES</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="8" column="1">The perceptual processes of Sketch are designed to identify novel emergent shapes. Adaptive novelty detection compares input bounded space representations with representations the best matching shapes previously categorized by a self-organising map. Adaptive novelty detection also compares representations constructed by learning systems from bounded shapes with those constructed from literal pixel values and edges. Representations are <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> assigned measures of novelty proportional to the measures of contradiction calculated between pairings. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> shows that, at the current fixation point, the inputs and the representations constructed by the literal and bounded space learning systems contradict. The input bounded space representation shows a rotated L-shape while the learning systems have both constructed equivalent representations of a square. Novelty is measured proportional to the highest confidence of the two learning systems, which in this case is the confidence of the literal apprehension learning system.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="87" page="9" column="1">C ONSTRUCTED R EPRESENTATIONS</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="88" page="9" column="1">209</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="91" page="9" column="1">5.3. LEARNING NEW DRAWING ACTIONS</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" page="9" column="1">Sketch can learn new design actions during the design process to enable it to draw novel emergent shapes that have been discovered. Sketch computationally models an interest in reproducing novel emergent shapes. It has been designed to isolate and analyse significantly novel shapes to produce a sequence of line drawing actions relative to the current fixation point that are grouped together into a new drawing action. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> shows that the novel emergent rotated L-shaped figure perceived by the bounded space processes has been analysed and an image of the boundary of the emergent shape has been generated. Scanning the boundary image, row-by-row and column-by-column, making note of the end points of line-coloured pixels produces a set of line drawing actions. The line drawing actions are grouped together into a shape drawing action that represents the novel emergent shape and is added to the repertoire of drawing actions available.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="94" page="9" column="1">6. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="9" column="1">In this paper we have introduced constructed representations. We have paid particular attention to the role of learning in processes that construct representations and examined constructed representations called expectations that support the processes of adaptive novelty detection. We have demonstrated with an implementation some of the functions that constructed representations can support. In particular, we have examined the role of expectations and adaptive novelty detection in the process of learning of novel emergent shapes by providing a basis for the recognition of unexpected consequences of design actions. This paper presents work that took as its starting point the cognitive studies of designers by Schön and Wiggins. The computational system developed has built upon previous work in design computing with the addition of adaptive novelty detection processes to produce a system that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Schön and Wiggins believed could not be produced in 1992</xref>.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="97" page="10" column="1">210</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="98" page="10" column="1">JOHN S. GERO AND ROBERT SAUNDERS</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="99" page="10" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" page="10" column="1">This research is supported by a University of Sydney Postgraduate Award. The ideas in this paper have benefited from discussions with the members of the Key Centre of Design Computing and Cognition.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="101" page="10" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" page="10" column="1">Boden, M.: 1991, The Creative Mind, Myths and Mechanisms, Cardinal, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="103" page="10" column="1">Cariani, P.: 1991, Emergence and artificial life, in C. G. Langton, C. Taylor, J. D. Farmer and S. Rasmussen (eds), Artificial Life II, Addison-Wesley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="104" page="10" column="1">Carpenter, G. A., S. Grossberg, et al.: 1991, ARTMAP: Supervised real-time learning and classification of nonstationary data by a self-organizing neural network, Neural Networks 4: 565-588.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="105" page="10" column="1">Clancey, W. J.: 1997, Situated Cognition, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" page="10" column="1">Cohen, H.: 1983, Harold Cohen: Catalogue, Tate Gallery, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" page="10" column="1">Gero, J. S.: 1990, Design prototypes: a knowledge representation schema for design, AI Magazine 11(4): 24-36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" page="10" column="1">Gero, J. S.: 1992, Creativity, emergence and evolution in design, in J. S. Gero and F. Sudweeks (eds), Computational Models of Creative Design, Key Centre of Design Computing, University of Sydney, Sydney, pp. 1-28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" page="10" column="1">Gero, J. S.: 1999, Recent design science research: Constructive memory in design thinking, Architectural Science Review 42: 3-5.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="10" column="1">Gero, J. S. and M. Yan: 1994, Shape emergence by symbolic reasoning, Environment and Planning B: Planning and Design 21: 191-212.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" page="10" column="1">Kohonen, T.: 1997, Self-Organizing Maps, Springer, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" page="10" column="1">Mitchell, W. J.: 1990, Introduction: a new agenda for computer-aided design, in McCullogh, Mitchell and Purcell (eds), The Electronic Design Studio, MIT Press, Cambridge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" page="10" column="1">Reffat, R. and J. S. Gero: 1998, Learning about shape semantics: A situated learning approach, in T. Sasada, S. Yamaguchi, M. Morozumi, A. Kaga and R. Homma (eds), CAADRIA'98, CAADRIA, Kumomoto, Japan, pp. 375-384.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" page="10" column="1">Schön, D. A. and G. Wiggins: 1992, Kinds of seeing and their functions in designing, Design Studies 13(2): 135-156.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="115" page="10" column="1">Soufi, B. and E. Edmonds: 1995, A framework for the description and representation of emergent shapes, in M. Tan and R. Teh (eds), The Global Design Studio, National University of Singapore, Singapore.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="116" page="10" column="1">Suwa, M., J. S. Gero, et al.: 1998, Unexpected discoveries and s-inventions of design requirements: A key to creative designs, in J. S. Gero and M. L. Maher (eds), Computational Models of Creative Design IV, The Key Centre of Design Computing and Cognition, University of Sydney.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Waltz, D.: 1999, The Importance of Importance, AI Magazine, Fall, 20(3): 19-35.</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
