<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>1ec832247d08c50cbbd1d3d15032916292472dcb9ce9ea66f03c57a1c5607769</job>
    <base_name>62q7</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.13165/st-13-3-1-08">http://dx.doi.org/10.1057/9781137361509.0009</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="outsider" id="1">7</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">14 5</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Co-creation: New pathways to value An overview</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="4">5</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">5</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="6">5</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">4 9 9 9 4 4 4 9 7</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="8">4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="9">18</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="10">10</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="11">18 11 11 11 18 18 2 3</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="12">7</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="13">4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">3</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="15">8 8 3 8</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">3</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="17">6 6</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="18">4</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="19">6</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="20">22</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21">22</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx22">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62q7.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23">Contents</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24">01</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25">02 Introduction / 03 Summary: new pathways to value</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="26">the co-creation space co-creation</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">04 Contexts: the drivers of co-creation / 07 Definitions: 10 Origins: the intellectual roots of co-creation 13 Benefits: the impact of co-creation / 16 Success: managing 18 Future challenges / 19 Appendix / 20 References</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28">1 2 3 4 5</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="29">6</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="30">7</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="31">8</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="32">9 10 11 12 13</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="33">14</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="34">15</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="35">16</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="36">17 18 19 20 21</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="37">22</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="38">23</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="39">24</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="40">25 26 27 28 29</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="41">30</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="42">31</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="43">32</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="44">33 34 35 36 37</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="45">38</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="46">39</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="47">40</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="48">41 42 43 44 45</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="49">46</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="50">47</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="51">48</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="52">49</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="53">50</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="54">51</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="55">52</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="56">53</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="57">54</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="58">55</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="59">56</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx60">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62q7.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="61">Introduction</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="62">02</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="63">axioms support the innovation and</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="64">used fairly strong whiff LSE Enterprise to subject and help</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="65">value</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="66">go some way</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="67">What if we truly believed that... 1 we are all creative 2 breakthroughs come from unreasonable requests 3 the real source of results is relationships At Promise we do. We also think that these emergence of co-creation as a new approach to customer involvement. But we’ve noticed that co-creation as a term is indiscriminately and that, if anything, there’s a of scepticism in the air. That’s why we asked take a look at what’s been written on the trace the origins and future of co-creation. We think that co-creation is hard to ignore because, under the right conditions, it helps companies build and reduce risk, in areas including strategy, innovation and new product development. We hope this report will add to the debate and to making the case for a co-created future for businesses. Dr Nick Coates Research Director, Promise.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="68">The report you’re reading is a summary building on research undertaken by the LSE Enterprise team. You can download the full report from our website at: www.promisecorp.com/newpathways</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62q7.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="70">Summary: new pathways to value</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71">03</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="72">we’ve reviewed, of conceptual the knots. the</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="73">creativity, with, rather combination of knowledge</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="74">or</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="75">of people</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="76">rather achieve wider</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="77">Co-creation is a new discipline. In the sources we’ve found a wealth of applications, but a lack clarity. This report aims to disentangle some of We think this report is important because it stresses value of co-creation as... 1 Creative: co-creation is a form of collaborative that’s initiated by firms to enable innovation than simply for their customers 2 A rich mix: co-creation draws on a management and marketing approaches, the psychoanalytic tradition, and processes related to innovation, and group decision-making 3 A facilitated process: co-creation thrives on fantasy, play and creativity, but the role of the facilitator facilitating organisation is often overlooked 4 All about relationships: we stress the importance focusing on the quality of the interactions between rather than on technologies per se 5 A learning process: we need to intertwine knowledge and processes in an overall co-creation framework, than just enabling co-creativity, if we want to organisational impact</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="78">2008 to February 2009 by a team consisting of Patrick Humphreys, Alain Samson, Thorsten Roser and Eidi Cruz-Valdivieso.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="79">A brief note on the report: the document you’re reading is a summary of the full research report published separately. The content has been produced by a team from</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="80">LSE Enterprise, based on a review of articles published in the top business, management and social sciences journals. The research was undertaken from September</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx81">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62q7.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="82">Contexts: the drivers of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83">04</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="84">Businesses in today’s economy have to continuously reinvent themselves in order to adapt to increasingly complex and dynamic market realities. Standardisation makes it difficult for companies to differentiate themselves from competitors. Markets are more fragmented than they used to be; and consumers have unprecedented access to information and networks. At the same time technologies have created new modes of production and innovation that enable and encourage greater degrees of participation and collaboration.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible">The challenge for brands Consumers are both demanding greater levels of personalisation in their consumption experience and placing businesses under increasing pressure to co-create value with them. This is reinforced by consumers &gt; seeking and accessing information online, across geographic boundaries &gt; providing unsolicited feedback to companies &gt; engaging in thematic consumer communities, including those fostering consumer word-of-mouth &gt; ‘Experimenting’ or co-creating with other consumers to find their own solutions to problems i</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86">The co-creation revolution The aim of co-creation is to enhance organisational knowledge processes by involving the customer in the creation of meaning and value. Co-creation blurs the boundaries of the firm by ‘outsourcing’ innovation and value creation to the customer. Co-creation transforms the consumer into an active partner for the creation of future value. This mutual relationship affects both consumer and company. It re-shapes the way in which we think, interact and innovate. Customers are increasingly becoming change agents of the firm, as well as the actual owners of organisations’ main means of production: knowledge. For the firm, involving consumers in the value-chain leads to a blurring of boundaries between research and development, marketing and consumer research.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="87">Co-creation cannot be safely ignored by companies who want to succeed in today’s marketplace.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="88">A trend that’s hard to ignore While the strategic benefits of co-creation may be evident, we need an understanding of how co-creation practices differ from other forms of customer involvement. What we can say is that co-creation offers a highly promising and more holistic, approach to value creation. Despite the fact that some of the theoretical and empirical foundations of co-creation still have to be developed, co-creation cannot be safely ignored by companies who want to succeed in today’s marketplace.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx89">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62q7.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="90">Contexts: the drivers of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="91">05</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92">Invention for the Blink generation</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="93">Innovation is starting to recognise the value of and implicit knowledge, opening up products processes, and creating active dialogues with consumers.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" confidence="possible">1 Forethought and intuition The way we understand invention is changing. For social scientist Nigel Thrift ii , the shift can be epitomised by 3 trends: (1) the mobilisation of forethought (2) the co-creation of commodities with consumers by activating their ingenuity, and (3) the construction of a space that fosters innovation. Forethought, according to Thrift, can be viewed as a form of tacit knowledge rather than explicit, formal knowledge derived from cognitive processes. Increasingly, businesses have come to value intuition or implicit thought (see for example Malcolm Gladwell’s bestselling book Blink) as a source of expertise. This is especially true for large companies. 2 The collective intelligence of consumers At the same time, consumer knowledge, derived from experience, is increasingly being viewed as a key asset. Companies are designing and marketing products in ways that appeal more to the emotional side of consumers. According to this view, co-creation between firms and customers, as well as production and consumption, is about tapping successfully into the collective intelligence of consumers. Aided by information technology, which makes interaction spaces like online user communities possible, co-creation allows for a continuous process in which products are tuned or recast.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95">3 The dominance of ‘value co-creation’ Invention or innovation, however, is just one aspect of co-creation. In fact, co-creation has been associated with a rather mixed bag of thinking in the business and marketing literature, ranging from innovation with customers to the ‘experience economy’ The concept of ‘co-creation of value’ has become a dominant idea. It occurs whenever consumers interact with companies or products and thereby have an active role in the shaping of their experience and ultimately value perception. This understanding builds on forms of dialogue that are on the rise and evident in a range of situations. For example, increasing numbers of patients bring in their own knowledge when discussing diagnoses and treatment options with healthcare providers. In software development, beta testing with users has been practised for a number of years, and has become easier with the internet. If infrastructures for an ongoing dialogue with customers are in place, managers can add value by harnessing consumer competence, managing personalised experiences and shaping expectations. iii</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="96">intuition to reshaping</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="97">Full spectrum customer involvement: the Nike approach iv &gt; Involving customers in dialogue, both individually or as part of thematic communities &gt; Generating ideas from consumers about product improvements, including options for the customisation of Nike products &gt; A competition for a select group of customers to design a new Nike shoe &gt; Co-design and customisation of shoes on ‘Nike ID’ web site &gt; Creating a social networking site, Joga.com, which included user generated content that allowed the upload of videos showing off individuals’ soccer skills &gt; Sponsoring experiences like soccer competitions &gt; iPod sport kit and sensor that can be placed in Nike shoes and connected to an iPod, which then provides workout-based voice feedback or particular songs to keep the runner going &gt; Helping customers develop good training methods that reduce the risk of injury Identifying the co-creative elements in this wide range of customer involvement activities is one aim of this report.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx98">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62q7.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="99">Contexts: the drivers of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100">06</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="101">The way this new age of invention engages consumers recognises a shift in marketing thinking towards service- dominant logic and the experience economy.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible">The Experience Economy Both dialogue and experience are key ingredients of consumer-brand relationships. Some have argued that the product is now ‘no more than an artefact around which customers have experiences, vi a view which took centre-stage in Pine &amp; Gilmore’s The Experience Economy (1999). vii However, Prahalad and Ramaswamy argue that we need a deeper, more integrated approach that goes beyond ‘staging experiences, outsourcing activities or marginal customisation. Throughout the supplier-customer relationship, consumer-company interactions must provide compelling experiences with different dimensions of choice. From the perspective of innovation, this means that companies have to abandon the traditional mindset of ‘company think’ (e.g. R&amp;D, manufacturing, marketing and sales, etc.) leading to the development of ‘feature rich’ and ‘experience poor’ products, in favour of ‘customer think’ (e.g. lifestyle, expectations, needs &amp; desires, etc.). viii</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="103">‘The customer is always a co-creator of value’</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="104">Online communities: co-creating LEGO The creation of (online) communities by consumers centred around a particular product category or brand can provide both a problem and opportunity to companies. The key for some companies is to become participants themselves or facilitators of otherwise naturally- occurring customer communities.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible">Service-Dominant Logic Instead of value or utility embedded in goods, the new Service-Dominant (S-D) logic focuses on the co-creation of values and relationships. People are no longer seen as buying either goods or services, but products that provide a service and value that depends on customer experience. This means far- reaching implications for companies’ understanding of customers:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="106">turning it into managed or facilitated co-creativity and mass customisation. In the late 1990s, the LEGO company started listening to the adult LEGO communities of practice LUGNET (the LEGO Users Group Network) and the newsgroup rec.toys.lego. LUGNET then created a forum specifically for direct communication between its members and LEGO Direct employees. Within the LUGNET community, users create virtual and real worlds out of LEGO blocks, by use of a CAD-based configuration system.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="107">From To Passive buyers &gt; Active agents Listening &gt; Dialogue Consumers as buyers &gt; Consumers as resources Researching need &gt; Understanding experiences Reliance on experts &gt; Consumer knowledge</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="108">sales. Today, the LEGO company offers both personalisation and co-creation opportunities to its target customers of 4-12 year-olds. Customers can engage in virtual design and building with the option of buying a manufactured version. Virtual models can be shared with other LEGO community members. In some cases, designs are appropriated by LEGO for mass production, with design recognition given to the creator. xii</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="109">The sportkiting community is one example where this has happened , while LEGO is one of the most frequently mentioned cases of a company that successfully harnessed consumers’ independent creativity by</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="110">Not surprisingly, the LEGO company began to look into possibilities of harnessing the potential of this community and its processes to support LEGO product usability among younger audiences, as well as marketing and</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx111">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62q7.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="112">Definitions: the co-creation space</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="113">07</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="114">Towards a definition of co-creation</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="115">Currently views and definitions of co-creation to context and according to disciplinary outlook.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="116">differ from context For example...</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117">1 Marketing theory has used co-creation quite broadly as any form customer involvement in the construction of product or brand experience and consequently perceived value.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" confidence="possible">2 Innovation management has highlighted the type of co-creation between companies and consumers that may occur in the beginning of the value chain, namely early product development stages.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="119">3 The internet community appears to have been more interested in not only consumer empowerment through co-innovation, but also the democratic potential of mass collaboration tools like Wikipedia.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="120">banner</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="121">Source Gloor and Cooper, 2007</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="122">Nambisan and Nambisan, 2008 / Sawhney et al, 2005 Sawhney et al, 2005</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="123">Blazevic &amp; Lievens, 2008 Wikström, 1996 Zwick et al., 2008 Blazevic &amp; Lievens, 2008 / Sawhney, 2002 Prahalad &amp; Ramaswamy, 2004</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="124" confidence="possible">The table below illustrates some of the ranges of applications discussed under the co-creation Selected co-creation examples mentioned by commentators xiii Company Name Co-creation example BMW ‘M division’ for customisation of cars, also leading to general product improvements; engineering challenges: collaboration between customers and BMW engineers Ducati Tech Café Virtual Customer Environment for product conceptualisation Eli Lilly Internet-based platform to support collaborative innovation involving pharma customers (patients doctors, clinicians, researchers, health care providers) IBM Worldwide partner innovation centres to facilitate collaborative innovation IKEA Customers can design their own kitchens in interaction with a trained sales representative LEGO LEGO Factory for personalised LEGO models and sharing/ co-creation of virtual LEGO models with other consumers P&amp;G P&amp;G Advisor programme where consumers contribute to product development (try new items and provide qualitative feedback) Philips Electronics Collaborated with software ‘hackers’ for re-programming of ‘Pronto’ universal remote control by providing access to programme files, codes and other information PSK (‘Centre for Creative Art’) Co-creation as a strategic tool for organisation learning and innovation Samsung Virtual Product Launch Center’ to enlist customers’ help in diffusion of new product information; shaping peer customers’ purchase behaviour Starbucks Business model where value is in experience</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="125">Chung, 2009 Nambisan and Nambisan, 2008 Lusch et al, 2006</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="126">Threadless.com</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="127">Elofson &amp; Robinson, 2007</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="128">Unilever</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="129">(determined by the customer) Customers that submit, inspect, and approve t-shirt graphic designs Involving consumers in co-creation of concepts, packaging, advertising and activation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="130">Medeiros and Needham, 2008</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx131">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62q7.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="132">Definitions: the co-creation space</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="133">08</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="134">The co-creation family of concepts</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="135">Associated concepts and approaches, such as (e.g. Linux operating system), mass ID), user-generated content (e.g. youtube.com),</region>
      <disp-formula class="DoCO:FormulaBox" id="F1">
        <label class="DoCO:Label" id="136">1</label>
        <content class="DoCO:Formula" id="137" confidence="possible">(e.g. Ikea), mass-collaboration innovation (e.g. Airbus) all contain an element purpose-driven innovation (2) consumer involvement or (3) cross-boundary collaboration.</content>
      </disp-formula>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" confidence="possible">So what do we think co-creation really means? One way of answering this question is by introducing two dimensions: 1 The role of the firm: is the process more consumer-led or producer-led? While mass collaboration may be mainly user-driven, other approaches tend to be initiated and orchestrated by the firm. Co-creation matrix Product type (value): Standard</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="139">open innovation customisation (e.g. Nike co-production and collaborative of either</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140" confidence="possible">2 The type of value created: is it standardised value (benefiting all customers), customised value (e.g. mass customisation of goods or services) or personalised value (e.g. as in co-produced services)? By applying these two filters we can start to see how co-creation can be distinguished from related concepts. The map below illustrates where co-creation sits and how all concepts depart from mass production: Consumer led Mass collaboration (Wikinomics)</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="141">generated</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="142">User content</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="143">Product type (value): Personalised</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="144" confidence="possible">Co-creation (co-innovation) Co-production</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="145">Personalisation (’Tailor made’)</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="146">Mass customisation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="147">Mass production</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="148">Producer led</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx149">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62q7.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="150">Definitions: the co-creation space</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="151">09</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="152">Carving out a space for co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="153">a third with</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="154">All co-creation approaches share two main features: a) the expansion of product or organisational boundaries and b) the involvement of the consumer. Co-creation as collaborative innovation with customers adds dimension c) a focus on co-creating new values customers that is initiated by the firm.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="155">A new definition for co-creation</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156">According to our stricter definition, co-creation as an active, creative and social process entails: 1 Connections: interactions between people, such as companies and customers, not interactions between consumers and products only 2 Collaboration, rather than just involvement 3 Co-creativity, not simply co-construction or co-production</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" confidence="possible">Co-creation of value in the business and marketing literature has been discussed as an interaction between either consumers only, consumers and products, or customers and businesses, stressing different levels of creativity or impact at different points in the value chain. We agree with Prahalad and Ramaswamy’s more stringent definition of co-creation, but also more popular conceptions that stress collaboration, indicating a need for not only compelling experiences, but a truly creative involvement of customers. We also stress the need for social structures to support the quality of interactions necessary for co-creation to succeed.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="158">Co-creation is creative and based on collaboration between producers users, that is the firm to</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="159">an active, social process, and initiated by generate value</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="160">for customers.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx161">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62q7.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="162">Origins: the intellectual roots of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="163">10</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="164">Co-creation can be seen as a coming-together of aspects</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" confidence="possible">of marketing and management theory, psychology and techniques derived from group decision-making, innovation and knowledge processes. 1 Co-creation and the Ultimately, decision-making is psychoanalytic tradition a key process relating to how perceptions are formed and how experience is rendered by and among customers. These decisions result not just in experiences, but representations of information and knowledge re- produced and ‘owned’ by the consumer. How co-creation can create decision markets involving vast numbers of networked consumers needs further exploration.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="166">innovation</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="167">Co-creation in practice</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168">At the heart of co-creation are techniques for creative play which resemble both group-decision making and psychotherapy. Co-creation in business environments eliminates the boundary between the firm and its customers; just as in psychotherapy analyst and analysand are able to be both subject and object as they reflect on their desires, identities and wishes. Co-creation also acknowledges consumers’ subjectivity, which is inherently idiosyncratic, contextual and experience-based. Co-creation facilitates the relationship between customer and company, while creating shared meaning and a common sense of purpose. Since the free, ‘safe’ and unhindered space is not normally available in social environments, such as formal organisations, co-creation is driven by facilitation. By staging encounters (both off- and online), facilitators foster the transitional space necessary for co- creativity to unfold and succeed.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="169">Co-creation of Value</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="170">2 Co-creation as decision-making processes</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" confidence="possible">Value= personalised meaning Marketing &amp; Business Co-creation Co-creation of Value of Meaning Marketing Psychology &amp; R&amp;D Sociology</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="172">Cross-disciplinary Co-creation processes Co-creativity Decision making support Innovation &amp; Change management Leadership</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible">Co-creation can also be understood as a decision-making support system in which the customer becomes involved in decision-making geared towards the co-creation of (future) value. The customer has to be provided with a space in which he can make his/her own decisions. At the same time, the firm has to learn from naturally occurring group decision-making processes, as well as from the contexts in which these occur.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="174">Intellectual Lineage of Co-creation as Collaborative Innovation between Firm and Customers</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx175">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62q7.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="176">Origins: the intellectual roots of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="177">11</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="178">Co-creation as knowledge process Co-creation also represents a new</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="179">Making the customer a co-producer or co-creator aims to generate</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="180">trend in innovation practice, marketing innovation and customer relationship management. In a technology-enabled world of connected consumers, the consumer holds increasing know- how. xiv Consumers are no longer passive recipients of brand offers, but able to accept or reject company claims based on their own experience and knowledge. xv This is especially evident in the context of product reviews, brand identification and loyalty, as well as corporate reputation and social responsibility.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="181">It is not just the frequency of interaction, but the quality of the relationship that companies form with and facilitate their customers, which will knowledge is created, shared and transferred.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="182">Co-creativity: more than just crowdsourcing Our definition sees co-creation as more than the kind of tightly- staged processes of which firm-initiated ‘crowdsourcing’ competitions are a good example. For example, the world’s first DVD-by-mail service, Netflix, has staged a competition (www. netflixprize.com) ‘to substantially improve the accuracy of predictions about how much someone is going to love a movie based on their movie preferences’ To win the grand prize, contestants have to improve</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="183">more value than through traditional transactions. This implies a longer process of relationship-building and it is generally assumed that a breakthrough is more likely to occur with more frequent and intense conversations between collaborators from diverse backgrounds. xvi Co-creation also allows for the formation of a more intimate relationship between the technology originator and the customer, as a joint development project where both contribute their expertise. xvii</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" confidence="possible">Although the competition includes an online forum and possible interaction between the company and consumers, while there are many teams made up of collaborating individuals, the Netflix Prize is less about creating a product based on firm-customer collaboration than it is about the competitive ‘sourcing’ of a solution to a specific problem.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="185">Consequently, it is not just the frequency of interaction, but the quality of the relationship that companies form with and facilitate among their customers, which will determine how knowledge is created, shared and transferred.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="186">among determine how</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="187">Though it may be an effective form of purpose-driven innovation, crowdsourcing of this kind is often a heavily controlled process involving a relatively one-sided flow of information from customers to companies. Co-creativity, on the other hand, is more fully engaged, departing from the idea that people are vessels of knowledge that can simply be tapped into by a company in the form of downloadable information.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="188">Netflix’s existing algorithm’s predictive power by at least 10%.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx189">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62q7.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="190">Origins: the intellectual roots of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="191">12</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="192">An iterative process</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="193" confidence="possible">In the context of co-creation, knowledge creation and transfer have to be understood as an iterative process involving the construction and de-construction of experience. As such, co-creation processes go through various cycles of value development. An adaptive framework Co-creation can lead to future pathways of value from which both customer and firm can benefit. Rather than viewing it as a tool for the creation of ideas, co-creation should thus be seen as an adaptive framework that facilitates innovation in a ‘boundary-spanning’ way by connecting customers and other members of the organisation.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="194" confidence="possible">innovation / Improvement Product Tacit (in -u se) E x c i it l p knowledg k</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="195" confidence="possible">A developmental tool Co-creation can also help organisations re-develop themselves by fostering inventive communities internally and externally. As such, co-creation is a process that can facilitate change by intertwining organisational knowledge and learning processes with relationship building and the creation of new value and meaning.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="196">Product Tacit (in -u se) E x c i i l t p knowledg k n e ow le dg e Experience</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="197">Product</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="198">Tacit (in -u se) knowledg e</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="199">E x p l i c it k n ow le dg e</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="200">Experience</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="201">e</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="202">n ow le dg e</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="203">Experience</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="204">Knowledge flow between product and experience: Continuous collaborative innovation with consumers</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="205">Time</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx206">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62q7.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="207">Benefits: the impact of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="208">13</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="209">The benefits of co-creation cut both ways. While consumers benefit from greater personalisation and value as a result of co-creation processes, the motivation for companies is about building competitive advantage by turning just-in-time knowledge from customers into just-in-time learning for their organisation.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="210">Access to wider, richer experiences</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="211">rapid and numerous design iterations. Better, quicker, less risky innovations</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="212" confidence="possible">Online collaboration: more than just innovation outcomes From experience to advocacy In addition to more direct innovation outcomes, there are also numerous intangible benefits that can spring from customers’ involvement in co-creation processes. Studies have cited, among other things:</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="213">Proctor &amp; Gamble’s Connect + Develop programme ‘Connect + Develop’ is P&amp;G’s version of open innovation that encourages and enables partners and other stakeholders to contribute and assess new ideas. The programme was a response to what P&amp;G saw as a defunct innovation model: “By 2000, it was clear to us that our invent-it-ourselves model was not capable of sustaining high levels of top-line growth. The explosion of new technologies was putting ever more pressure on our innovation” xxii In a 2004 interview with Business Week, P&amp;G’s Chief Technology Officer declared: ‘we estimated when we started about three years ago, we had about 20% of our ideas, products, and technologies that came from totally outside P&amp;G. Today, we’ve got about 35%, and our target is to get to 50%. It’s also a tremendous productivity enhancer. This has actually occurred with a 20% reduction in the R&amp;D investment we make’ xxiii P&amp;G claim that the initiative has led to over 1,000 active agreements. xxiv</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214">&gt; Increased attitudinal loyalty in While the literature on co-creation processes of customer-supplier often fails to raise critical issues, co-production (‘constructive customer discussions of benefits are abundant. participation in the service creation In new concept development, and delivery process’) xviii collaboration increases the number of sources of new ideas in innovation. &gt; Higher perceived value of future It enables cross-fertilisation and idea co-creation, satisfaction with service generation through shared knowledge recovery, and intention to co-create and experiences. By giving R&amp;D value in the future as a result of personnel greater access to a richer stock customer participation in a self-service of experiences and stories, collaboration service recovery process. xix creates a greater potential for recognising possible technology applications. &gt; Greater satisfaction and commitment due to participation or co-operation Collaborative teams bring a greater body with a service provider. xx of knowledge to bear, enabling more &gt; Increased likelihood of positive word-of-mouth with higher levels of customer participation in Specific innovation benefits for service delivery. xxi companies that are credited to customer involvement in the literature (particularly when assisted by technologies such as the internet) have included: Research on the effect of customer involvement in innovation is a not &gt; Increased speed to market common. In addition, companies &gt; Lower cost; higher profitability often take the beneficial effect of &gt; Better product quality and greater collaborative innovation with consumers satisfaction for granted, thereby overlooking the &gt; Reduced risk broader impact that this process has on customer experience. Given that much co-creation with consumers occurs online, the impact of Virtual Customer Environment (VCE) participation is a good starting point. One study based on a sample of consumers participating in IBM and Microsoft VCEs showed that positive customer interaction experiences and attitudes generated in such settings are associated with both future participation and attitudes towards the host firm (based on perceived reputation, quality consciousness, customer friendliness, etc.).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx215">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62q7.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="216">Benefits: the impact of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="217">14</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="218">Evaluating the success of co-creation strategies calls for a multi-dimensional approach to impact assessment. Measures can focus either on macro, meso or micro levels of performance, e.g. number of service improvements vs the quality of the co-creation process vs the amount of ideas generated through co-creation.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="219" confidence="possible">Measuring impact: from subjective to objective Many KPIs focus on the success or failure of generated products. xxv We have already referred to benefits related to improved speed, volume and quality of co-created products and services. Earlier on in the innovation process, subjective measures include ‘perceived usefulness’ or ‘innovativeness. Measuring impact: co-creation KPIs Product-focused Measures and KPIs of Innovation/Co-creation Success Measures &amp; KPIs of innovation/co-creation success Objective Number of new patents Time to development Assessment of new ideas Number of new product ideas</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" confidence="possible">Example: In an experiment on mobile phone service innovation it was found that service innovations suggested by users were considered to be significantly more innovative than those generated by professional service developers. xxvi Further down the line a company’s co-creation outcomes may be assessed by the number of successful products that have benefited from consumer input as opposed to purely in-house NPD.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="221">Time to market for new products or improvements</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="222">Example: Two concept cars previously featured on Volvo’s virtual customer environment (VCE) have gone into production. The ‘Adventure’ concept car became the XC90, and the ‘Performance’ concept cars later became the S60R and V70R models. xxvii Co-created innovation can lead to spill-over effects such as spin-off products or more general cross- pollination of product ideas. Once we reach the in-use stage, success can be measured through customer satisfaction and loyalty (including word of mouth) as well as through financial indicators such as increased market share.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="223">Cost reductions New/improved product &gt; Revenue &gt; Pro tability &gt; Market share</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="224">Time to break-even for new product introductions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="225">Customer &gt; loyalty &gt; WOM</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="226">Technological acceptance: - Perceived usefulness - Perceived ease-of-use, etc.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="227">Customer satisfaction</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="228">Perceived innovativeness: originality/value/ realisability of product ideas Subjective Ideation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="229">Evaluation stages</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="230">Market/in-use</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx231">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62q7.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="232">Benefits: the impact of co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="233">15</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="234">Impacts on the organisation itself</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="235">Co-creation success can also be evaluated from organisational point of view. Prahalad and Ramaswamy claim that organisations in the co-creation age to become increasingly flexible, while negotiation and collaboration, along with cross-boundary knowledge transfer skills, will become essential.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" confidence="possible">There are general areas we can expect to be affected by co-creation: 1 Co-creation has a direct impact on traditional innovation practices and processes. 2 Co-creation can affect the quality and speed at which decisions are made in relation to the development and filtering of ideas. 3 Co-creation will enable creativity at individual and group level and potentially enable customer knowledge development and transfer across the organisation. 4 Co-creation will increasingly be used as a way of creating strategy collaboratively.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="237" confidence="possible">Since co-creation can be regarded as a new way of practising innovation within firms, especially when employees interact with external stakeholders, this will also have an effect on how innovation is practised and lived within a company. As implied previously, co-creation may also increase customer identification with products and the brand through active involvement, while sensitising managers towards supporting new ideas and a more participatory leadership style to help foster innovation and creativity at team level.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="238">In order to trigger change by innovation co-creation be disruptively as and as non-disruptively</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="239">an will have managers trained in</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="240">At an organisational level, customer involvement may ultimately increase overall flexibility and adaptiveness. By speeding up innovation processes themselves, co-creation has thus the potential to systematise and enable change through innovation. Finally, co-creation may also make companies more attractive for employees, as participating in direct value creation (independent of their actual work position) may trigger identification and attract future talent.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="241">needs to implemented as necessary</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="242">as possible.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx243">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62q7.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="244">Success: managing co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="245">16</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="246">Questions to consider</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="247">Co-creation, according to our definition, stands collaboration processes between an customers. Depending on the size and market positioning of the firm, the ways in which this collaboration may vary. Any company considering a needs to consider the following 6 questions:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="248" confidence="possible">1 Who will be involved? The ‘locus of co-creation control’ – i.e. who’s in the driving seat - differs for different product development or innovation regimes. Companies may want to involve existing customers, customers of competitors (latent customers) and non-users (latent users). Some have suggested that particular types of customers (e.g. early adopters) may be more suitable for certain types of co-creation objectives, such as breakthrough innovation. However, specific co-creation contexts and purposes are the only reliable gauge of who to involve. 2 What’s the purpose? Co-creation raises important questions about innovation focus. It may be used to develop a specific solution to a problem or to develop a specific product – we would call this purpose driven co-creation. On the other hand, co-creation may not be driven by any purpose at all and practised simply in order to produce new ideas that allow for an opening of entirely new opportunities. In addition, the objective may be to either continuously improve existing products or create radically new ones. Finally, a question of purpose and customer value may be what form of customer value should be created,</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="249" confidence="possible">e.g. standardised value (benefiting all customers), customised value (e.g. mass customisation of goods or services) or personalised value (e.g. as in co-produced services). 3 Where does it occur? One of the core questions of consumer involvement is not only for what purpose the consumer will be involved, but where in the innovation process participation should take place. As outlined previously, potential customer involvement in the new product development (NPD) process have generally included the following stages: (1) Idea generation and selection; (2) Design (3) Testing/ refinement (4) Support (5) Marketing/ commercialization. However, it seems that there are currently very few forms of customer involvement that can cover the whole range of phases in the new product development (NPD) process. xxviii As Dahlsten xxix has pointed out, NPD projects are typically directed by stage-gate models xxx in which different types of customer input are needed during different phases and stages of the innovation process.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="250">for creative organisation and its takes place co-creation strategy</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="251">Online customer involvement A 2006 article by Prandelli and colleagues xxxi has given some indications of where in the NPD process companies tend to involve customers the most. The study looked at online tools to support collaboration with customers at each stage of the innovation process, as used by a sample of companies from automobile, motorcycle, consumer electronics, food and toiletries industries (hereafter, ‘food’), and toiletries industries. Results showed that the use of collaborative internet tools was particularly widespread at the idea generation stage in the form of traditional ‘contact the firm’ options (90%) or feedback sessions/surveys (37%), but they were rare for the idea selection stage. Only 4% of companies in the sample allowed individual users to review other customers’ evaluations and none allowed for a direct interaction among those customers. At the product design stage, mass customisation of functional attributes was not uncommon (30%), but lacking at more innovative levels (one of the better-known exceptions to this is P&amp;G, which allows customers to send in their independently developed patented ideas and technologies).</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx252">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62q7.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="253">Success: managing co-creation</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="254">17</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="255">eliciting views more particularly</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="256">The XC90 project involved 24 participants, the majority (16) of which were involved at all stages. According to Dahlsten, the $50 compensation received for each meeting by the high-earning professional participants in the XC90 project were less of an incentive than the social value they derived from the sessions and the opportunity to be heard.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="257">Collaborating about the XC90. Meetings followed along the whenever the Volvo management innovation process: third team focus had something group emphasized to discuss. interior A Volvo XC90 and exterior design, involving the display of a full-scale plastic model in a hotel ballroom. A final meeting was held two years into the project, giving participants the opportunity to drive the final version of the XC90.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="258" confidence="possible">A good example of ongoing co-creation with the same customer group along all stages of the innovation process was the Volvo XC90 NPD project, reported by Fredrik Dahlsten, xxxiv which started with a trial meeting with a group of female customers (affluent professionals) in California, complementing traditional market research that was going on at the same time. The purpose of the first informal meeting was to extract expectations and opinions regarding SUVs in general to be used in the concept development phase. After a successful first meeting, a second meeting was set up half a year later, as a more formal focus group</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="259">fewer interactions and thus keep customers willing and happy to further engage in the co-creation process.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="260">6 How do you incentivise? Research suggests that intrinsically motivated participants are best suited for sustained interest and creativity, although stamina may also be affected by extrinsic incentives like monetary rewards. Future research should investigate aspects of participant selection, incentives and motivation further by focusing on dimensions like self-selection, co-creation objectives (e.g. product type), degrees of co-operativeness or competitiveness, customer perceptions and trust, as well as co-creation settings.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="261" confidence="possible">4 How much 5 For how long? involvement? Organisations may engage customers in one-off co-creation workshops, on At an organisational level, consumer an ad hoc project-by-project basis, in involvement for the purpose of co- regular intervals or even continuously. creation should be as non-disruptive Merely keeping a channel open for as necessary, while creating maximum customer feedback is not enough. benefits and value for both the As markets are constantly co-evolving, company and its customers. The extent frequent (and constructive) interaction to which innovation is open in turn has been suggested as a sensible flags issues about transparency, access, form of customer involvement. xxxii trust and risks occurring in collaborative The length of consumer involvement innovation with customers. Strong can be both a strategic and project- involvement (including consumer based question. As noted by Lundkvist access to information and corporate and Yakhlef, xxxiii significant motivation transparency) is necessary for may be needed to get customers meaningful open co-innovation. cognitively mobilized, but may not be Disclosure has generally become an able to secure their active/sustained important corporate practice to build participation over a longer period trust among consumers. On the of time. However, the quality of the other hand, access and transparency interaction may compensate for in the co-creation process has lead to delicate issues about intellectual property: who owns the ideas Four dimensions of participant motives generated when customers and</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="262">organisations co-create?</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="263">Extrinsic</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="264">Intrinsic</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="265">Self-orientation Material rewards, such as money, goods, etc. Interest, learning, enjoyment, etc.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="266">Other orientation Image, status, recognition ‘showing ideas’ Helping others, belonging to a group</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx267">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62q7.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="268">Future challenges</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="269">18</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="270">Whenever products are developed in outside of an organisation, potential problems &gt; Increased dependency on outside collaborators &gt; Cost of co-ordinating the co-creation process &gt; The need for new management skills (most notably the ‘boundary spanner’) &gt; Different personnel management styles &gt; Customers gaining access to confidential information and proprietary skills Co-created value also produces new of co-creation changes consumer expectations. may reduce customers’ pain threshold for By giving consumers greater control, then, about new challenges that have to be dealt with organisation, including a re-orientation of Management in association with R&amp;D and marketing. Either way, it’s unlikely that most businesses will ignore the co-creation trend in the future.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="271">collaboration with players may also include: xxxv (e.g. customers)</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="272">challenges, because experience Personalised products dissatisfaction, for example. co-creation brings throughout the Customer Relationship</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="273">be able to</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx274">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_019.image_19.png" thmb="62q7.page_019.image_19-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="275">Appendix</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="276">19</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="277">Concept</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="278">Description</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="279">Examples</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="280" confidence="possible">[see also Open Innovation]</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="281">Boeing 787: The development of the Boeing 787, ranging from concept to production, was done by Boeing and its global partners.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="282">xxxvii</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="283">‘U-Scan’; Ikea Self-service checkouts at supermarkets or self-assembly furniture</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="284">a</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="285">Wikipedia Articles on the world’s largest online encyclopedia, written entirely by internet users.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="286">Dell; Nike ID Dell computers allow customers to configure the specifications of the computers that they purchase</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="287">xxxx</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="288" confidence="possible">[See also Collaborative Innovation]</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="289">Collaborative innovation Gaining competitive advantage by expanding the borders of an organization through widespread involvement and interdependence between actors at all levels, daily based information exchange, integration of business processes and joint work and activities. For radical or discontinuous innovation, joint development and co-design are the most typical forms of networking. In the case of continuous innovation and improvement processes, the most common form of inter-company interaction is mutually-beneficial customer-supplier collaboration over an extended period of time. Consumer / customer The concept of consumer/customer involvement has been involvement used in two different ways: A) Psychological: a consumer’s perceived importance, risk, symbolic value or emotional appeal of a product or product category. xxxvi B) Behavioural: When firms engage consumers/customers in some way, leading to a benefit for the firm, customer or both (e.g. as resource in product innovation or co-producer of products). Co-production In co-production, the customer is an active participant in the production and delivery of a service, giving the participant a potential to customize his or her world. A broader perspective of co-production is found in the interpretive marketing literature, suggesting that a fundamental characteristic of the postmodern era is the reversal of production and consumption, requiring marketers to increasingly open up their processes and systems. xxxviii Mass Collaboration A kind of collaboration model based on collective actions, (‘Wikinomics’): which occur while large numbers of contributors or participants work independently but in collaboration on single modular project. Projects typically take place on the internet by means of web-based collaboration tools. xxxix Mass Customisation Mass customisation refers to firms applying technology and management methods to provide product variety and customisation through flexibility and quick responsiveness. While the goal of mass production is to produce an affordable standardized product, mass customisation produces enough variety in products and/or services so that nearly everyone finds exactly what he or she wants at a reasonable price. Open Innovation Open innovation occurs when a company commercializes its own ideas and innovations from other firms, and seeks ways to bring its in-house ideas to market by deploying pathways outside its businesses. External R&amp;D can create significant value; internal R&amp;D is needed to claim some portion of that value. xxxxi User Generated Content User generated content can be defined as content made (UGC) publicly available through technologies like the internet, reflecting a certain amount of creative input or effort that is created outside of professional practices or routines. xxxxii</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="290">Linux; Procter &amp; Gamble P&amp;G’s ‘Connect + Develop’ programme enables a two-way sharing of innovation between P&amp;G and external individuals or organisations. Youtube Youtube, the online video sharing service, allows users to upload their own and view content generated by other users.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="291">User Involvement</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="292">User involvement occurs when representatives of a target user group participate in the system [software, etc.] development process. xxxxiii</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx293">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_020.image_20.png" thmb="62q7.page_020.image_20-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="294">References</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="295">20</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="296">i Prahalad, C.K. , &amp; Ramaswamy, V. (2004). The future impacts on supply-chain performance. of competition: co-creating unique value with International Journal of Production Research, customers. Boston: Harvard Business School Press. 45(11), 2567-2594. Needham, A., &amp; Medeiros,</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="297">Swink, M. (2006). Building Collaborative Innovation Capability. Research Technology Management, 49(2), 37-47</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="298" confidence="possible">ii Thrift, N. (2006). Re-inventing invention: new tendencies in capitalist commodification. Economy &amp; Society, 35(2), 279-306. iii Prahalad, C., &amp; Ramaswamy, V. (2000). Co-opting customer competence. Harvard Business Review, 78 (1), p. 82 iv Ramaswamy, v. (2008). Co-creating value through customers’ experiences: the Nike case. Strategy &amp; Leadership, 36(5), 9-14. v Lusch, R. (2007). Marketing’s Evolving Identity: Defining Our Future. Journal of Public Policy &amp; Marketing, 26(2), 261-268. vi Prahalad &amp; Ramaswamy (2000) , op. cit., p. 83 vii Pine, J., &amp; Gilmore, J. (1999). The Experience Economy. Boston: Harvard Business School Press. viii Prahalad, C.K. , &amp; Ramaswamy, V. (2004), op.cit. ix Rowley, J., Kupiec-Teahan, B., &amp; Leeming, E. (2007). Customer community and co-creation: A case study. Marketing Intelligence &amp; Planning, 25(2), 136-146. x Moon, J. Y., &amp; Sproull, L. (2001). Turning love into money: How some firms may profit from voluntary electronic customer communities. Unpublished manuscript, Stern School of Business, http:// userinnovation.mit.edu/papers/Vol-Customers.pdf. xi Piller, F., Schubert, P., Koch, M., &amp; Möslein, K. (2005). Overcoming Mass Confusion: Collaborative Customer Co-Design in Online Communities. Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication, 10(4). xii Zwick, D., Bonsu, S. K., &amp; Darmody, A. (2008). Putting Consumers to Work: ‘Co-creation’ and new marketing govern-mentality. Journal of Consumer Culture, 8(2), 163-196. xiii Sources are: Gloor, P., &amp; Cooper, S. (2007). The New Principles of a Swarm Business. MIT Sloan Management Review, 48(3), 81-84. Nambisan, S., &amp; Nambisan, P. (2008). How to Profit From a Better ‘Virtual Customer Environment’ MIT Sloan Management Review, 49(3), 53-61. Sawhney, M., Verona, G., &amp; Prandelli, E. (2005). Collaborating to create: The Internet as a platform for customer engagement in product innovation. Journal of Interactive Marketing, 19(4), 4-17. Blazevic, V., &amp; Lievens, A. (2008). Managing innovation through customer coproduced knowledge in electronic services: An exploratory study. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 36(1), 138-151. Wikström, S. (1996). The customer as co-producer. European Journal of Marketing, 30(4), 6. Prahalad, C., &amp; Ramaswamy, V. (2004). Co-creation Experiences: the Next Practice in Value Creation. Journal of Interactive Marketing, 18(3), 5-14. Zwick, D., Bonsu, S. K., &amp; Darmody, A. (2008). Putting Consumers to Work: ‘Co-creation’ and new marketing govern-mentality. Journal of Consumer Culture, 8(2), 163-196. Chung, Y.M. (2009). Co-creation with the customer: a strategy for organisation learning</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="301" confidence="possible">A.C.M. (2008). The ‘Co-creation Revolution. Paper presented at INNOVATE 2008 - ESOMAR World Research Conference. Retrieved December 17, 2008, retrieved at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www" id="299">http://www</ext-link>. facegroup.co.uk/up_video/learn/AFN.AM%20 Esomar%20Paper%20Final.pdf xiv Maklan, S., Knox, S., &amp; Ryals, L. (2008). New trends in innovation and customer relationship management. International Journal of Market Research, 50(2), 221-240. xv Ind, N. &amp; Riondino, M. (2001) Branding on the web: a real revolution? Journal of Brand Management, 9, 1, pp. 8–20. xvi Dahlsten, F. (2004). Hollywood wives revisited: a study of customer involvement in the XC90 project at Volvo Cars. European Journal of Innovation Management, 7(2), 141-149. xvii Neale, M. and Corkindale, D.R. (1998), ‘Co-developing products: involving customers earlier and more deeply, Long Range Planning, Vol. 31 No. 3, pp. 418-25. xviii Auh, S., Bell, S., McLeod, C., &amp; Shih, E. (2007). Co-production and customer loyalty in financial services. Journal of Retailing, 83(3), 359-370. xix Dong, B., Evans, K., &amp; Zou, S. (2008). The effects of customer participation in co-created service recovery. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 36(1), 123-137. xx Bettencourt, L. (1997). Customer voluntary performance: Customers as partners in service delivery. Journal of Retailing, 73(3), 383-406. xxi File, K., Judd, B., &amp; Prince, R. (1992). Interactive Marketing: The Influence of Participation on Positive Word-of-Mouth and Referrals. Journal of Services Marketing, 6(4), 514. xxii “Connect and Develop: Inside Procter &amp; Gamble’s New Model for Innovation” Harvard Business Review, Vol. 84, No. 3, March 2006. Retrieved at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://hbswk.hbs.edu/archive/5258.html" id="300">http://hbswk.hbs.edu/archive/5258.html</ext-link> xxiii At P&amp;G, It’s ‘360-Degree Innovation’ Business Week, October 11, 2004, www.businessweek.com/ magazine/content/04_41/b3903463.htm xxiv See https://secure3.verticali.net/pg-connection- portal/ctx/noauth/0_0_1_4_83_4_3.do xxv Matthing, J., Sandén, B., &amp; Edvardsson, B. (2004). New service development learning from and with customers. International Journal of Service Industry Management, 15(5), 479-498. Kristensson, P., Gustafsson, A., &amp; Archer, T. (2004). Harnessing the Creative Potential among Users. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 21(1), 4-14. Sheth, J., Sisodia, R., &amp; Sharma, A. (2000). The Antecedents and Consequences of</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="303">xxvi Matthing et al (2004), op. cit. xxvii Nambisan, S., &amp; Nambisan, P. (2008). How to Profit From a Better ‘Virtual Customer Environment’ MIT Sloan Management Review, 49(3), 53-61. xxviii Dahlsten (2004), op. cit. xxix Dahlsten (2004), op. cit. xxx See Cooper, R.G. (1993). Winning at New Products: Accelerating the Process from Idea to Launch. Reading: Addison-Wesley. xxxi Prandelli, E., Verona, G., &amp; Raccagni, D. (2006). Diffusion of Web-Based Product Innovation. California Management Review, 48(4), 109-135. xxxii Ramaswamy, V. (2008), op.cit. xxxiii Lundkvist, A., &amp; Yakhlef, A. (2004). Customer involvement in new service development: a conversational approach. Managing Service Quality, 14(2/3), 249-257. xxxiv Dahlsten (2004), op. cit. xxxv Biemans, W. G. (1995). Internal and External Networks in Product Development: a Case for Integration, in Product Development: Meeting the Challenge of the Design-Marketing Interface. In Bruce, M. &amp; Biemans, W. G., 137-159, Wiley. xxxvi Laurant, G, &amp; Kapferer, J. N. (1985). Measuring Consumer Involvement Profiles. Journal of Marketing Research, 22(1), 41-53. xxxvii Lengnick-Hall, C. (1996). Customer contributions to quality: A different view of the customer-oriented firm. Academy of Management Review, 21(3), 791-824. xxxviii p. 14-15, Bendapudi, N., &amp; Leone, R. (2003). Psychological Implications of Customer Participation in Co-Production. Journal of Marketing, 67(1), 14-28. xxxix Ghazawneh, A. (2008). Managing Mass Collaboration: Toward a Process Framework. PhD Thesis, University of Lund, Sweden. Retrieved on 30 October, 2008. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://biblioteket.ehl.lu.se/" id="302">http://biblioteket.ehl.lu.se/</ext-link> olle/papers/0003116.pdf xxxx p. 22, Kotha, S. (1995). Mass Customisation – Implementing the Emerging Paradigm for Competitive Advantage. Strategic Management Journal, 16, 21-42 xxxxi Chesbrough, H (2003). ‘The era of open innovation. MIT Sloan Management Review, 44(3), 35-41. xxxxii p. 4, Wunsch-Vincent, S., &amp; Vickery, G. (2007). Participative Web: User-Generated Content. Report by the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, Directorate for Science, Technology and Industry. http:// www.oecd.org/dataoecd/57/14/38393115.pdf</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="304">xxxxiii Ives, B, &amp; Olson, M. H. (1984). User Involvement and MIS Success: A Review of Research. Management Science,(30(5), 586-603.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="305">and innovation. International Journal of Learning Customer-Centric Marketing. Journal of the and Intellectual Capital 2009 - Vol. 6, No.1/2 pp. 19 – Academy of Marketing Science, 28(1), 55-66. 30. Lusch, R., Vargo, S., &amp; Malter, A. (2006). Marketing as Service-Exchange: Taking a Leadership Role in Joshi, A., &amp; Sharma, S. (2004). Customer Global Marketing Management. Organisational Knowledge Development: Antecedents Dynamics, 35(3), 264-278. Elofson, G., &amp; Robinson, and Impact on New Product Performance. W. (2007). Collective customer collaboration Journal of Marketing, 68(4), 47-59.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx306">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_021.image_21.png" thmb="62q7.page_021.image_21-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="307">References</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="308">21</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="309">About the authors</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="310">the Patrick main Humphreys scientific supervisor (PhD), is of the Contact</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="311">Thorsten Roser (Dipl.-Psych.) is the founder and current director of the London Research and Consulting Group (LRCG) a network of knowledge entrepreneurs emanating from the LSE. Thorsten graduated in Psychology from the University of Heidelberg and is a qualified business psychologist specialising on knowledge, networks and innovation. As innovation consultant, he worked extensively with large and medium-sized enterprises, particularly in Germany. He is currently affiliated with various research groups at the Institute of Social Psychology at the LSE, including the Organisational Research Group (ORG), the Knowledge Organisations and Development Network (KODE), as well as the London Multimedia Lab for Audio Visual Composition (LML).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="315">Dr Nick Coates Research Director <email id="312">ncoates@promisecorp.com</email> Promise 75 Wells Street London W1T 3QH United Kingdom Tel: +44 (0) 207 290 0290 Fax: +44 (0) 207 290 0280 One Thomas Circle, NW 10th Floor Washington, DC 20005 Tel: +1 (202)772 5019/+1 (202)870 1234 Fax: +1 (202)955 5328 www.promisecorp.com Author contacts Thorsten Roser: <email id="313">t.roser@lse.ac.uk</email> Alain Samson: <email id="314">a.samson@lse.ac.uk</email> © 2009 Promise Corporation</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="316" confidence="possible">research undertaken by the LSE Enterprise team. He is the former director of the Institute of Social Psychology at the LSE. He is a Professor in Organisational Social Psychology and currently the Co-Director of the London Multimedia Lab for Audiovisual Composition and Communication (LML). Patrick has expertise in innovative and creative decision-making, decision support systems, and enhancement of resources for health, culture, development, and networking. He currently leads a RTD team for the European Union framework Project “InCaS: Intellectual Capital Statement, Europe”, and is also responsible for the LML’s joint initiative with ZenZone Media Lab, Beijing on “Spritivity Workshops”. He has been involved in initiatives research the Alain and to including He market (mainly Alain consultant by mouth, commercial social the theories is public quantitative best has Samson psychology areas research influence experiments for been media, known sector. with and of clients and consumer (PhD), involved methodologies a is academic market finance, for and His history and frequently in his and approach various is cynicism. the a contributions in research of word psychologist surveys) FMCG emerging strategic work. both sectors, informed of to and from In Creativity Worldwide the Group, dialogues Vitamin He and making Pearl involving and was countries. 2006 is IFIP sector alternative a a River sponsor founding LLP WG8.3 he and Creative organisational and between He was Delta” development and Ltd Decision is Innovation of conference and programme urban chair director partner Space, the coordinated Papertronic different workshop of Support models IFIP Guangzhou. of transformation of in in on Spritivity the many WG8.3. chair Decision individuals in by and Ludic “Live Ltd. the for field and He Psychology), School of both States He consumer Michigan holds has worked of academic and published of behavioural a Economics research. the PhD and in an UK. Switzerland, and from MA a articles BA commercial economics. Alain from the (Social from London the related has UC the University lived Berkeley. United to extensively and background Organisational Eidi leadership, LSE’s psychology the from US. creativity, Cruz-Valdivieso Multimedia the She LSE. community in currently and in Eidi the primarily clinical and holds Lab has areas Social works for (MSc), worked an and development of in Audiovisual MSc Psychology change, Mexico community at has in the a and Composition and Communication (LML). Her current research interest focuses on aspects of flow in relation to creativity and innovation, as well as on Cross-Organisational Assessment and Development of Intellectual Capital (CADIC). Further, she is providing</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="317">consultancy relating to the European Intellectual Capital Statement (InCaS) and is involved in extending consulting capabilities of the InCaS consortium to Latin America.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="318">About Promise Promise is a customer-centred consultancy. We work in the areas of insight, innovation and brand strategy, where we apply our unique mix of marketing, psychology, research &amp; branding expertise to generate deep and lasting solutions for our clients. We pioneered co-creation techniques through the 1990s. Since then, we’ve worked with 27 major corporations across 51 countries on a string of winning strategies and programmes that have driven revenues, profits, customer and staff engagement. Most recently we have worked with McDonalds, Kraft Foods, Visa, Etihad Airlines, Prudential, Astra Zeneca, the Dubai Government, HMRC and the Ministry of Justice.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx319">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62q7.page_022.image_22.png" thmb="62q7.page_022.image_22-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter"/>
  </article>
</pdfx>
