<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>63824c3fba61d0076977516e07b7f6cbd19b5337475067fdc479bed980d0ff66</job>
    <base_name>62re</base_name>
    <doi>10.1080/15710880701875043</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">CoDesign Vol. 4, No. 1, March 2008, 19–30</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Staging imaginative places for participatory prototyping</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">b</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Christina Brodersen a</name>
          <aff id="5">*</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Christian Dindler b</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Ole Sejer Iversen</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="14" page="1" column="1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email id="13">christina@ilab.dk</email></footnote>
      <region class="unknown" id="8">a InnovationLab, Finlandsgade 20, 8200 Aarhus N, Denmark; b Department of Information and Media Studies, University of Aarhus, Helsingforsgade 14, 8200 Aarhus N, Denmark (Received 2 November 2007; final version received 17 December 2007)</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="9" confidence="possible">When we stage participatory prototyping, we arrange constraints and possibilities and envision a place of co-creation for designers and users. We argue that the activity of participatory prototyping can benefit from unfolding in imaginative places that are radically distant from the places of current practice. Our work with participatory prototyping indicates that a radicalisation towards an imaginative place of co-creation provides participants with an extended space for imagining future practices. Departing from the Scandinavian participatory prototyping heritage, our research is an inquiry into staging the places of participatory prototyping. Staging imaginative places is carried out by a careful selection and coordination of anchoring elements that maintain references to current practice and elements of transcendence that afford the imaginative place. As such, we supplement the qualities of the prototype and the process of prototyping with a concern for the place in which prototyping unfolds. We present two cases of participatory prototyping sessions that outline our work with staging imaginative places for participatory prototyping. Keywords: participatory design; participatory prototyping; imaginative places</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="1" column="1">Transporting people into an imaginative realm and making it believable is the stuff movies are made of, but invoking a sense of suspended disbelief can also help us unlock creativity in participatory prototyping processes. We argue that the activity of participatory prototyping can benefit from unfolding in imaginative places that are radically distant from the places of current practice. Staging participatory prototyping is a challenge that focuses on creating a common ground within which the participants can engage each other in co-creation of possible futures. Our starting point is traditional participatory prototyping and the balance described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Ehn (1993)</xref> as tradition and transcendence in design; we initiate the co-creation of new IT-artifacts in the current use-practice. However, with this paper we present ways of opening the design space through staging imaginative places for prototyping activities where we maintain certain anchoring elements from current practice, but provide more elements of transcendence to create a shared imaginative place. The tools with which we develop anchoring elements and elements of transcendence may be narrative frames, roles, the physical space, props, etc. Relating to Ehn’s (1993) account<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> of the use of Berthol Brecht’s theatrical alienation effect (Verfremdungseffekt) to unite tradition and transcendence by presenting something well-known in a new light, the imaginative place moves focus away from practice without completely abandoning all known concepts and structures. In the following section, we will describe our participatory prototyping heritage as a foundation for staging imaginative places of prototyping activities. We will highlight the existing body of literature with which we share a focus in order to position our contribution. In section three, we outline our understanding of imaginative places and discuss the means with which we develop these places. In section four, we present current work with participatory prototyping to illustrate how we have staged imaginative places and how the prototyping activity unfolded.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="1">ISSN 1571-0882 print/ISSN 1745-3755 online Ó 2008 Taylor &amp; Francis</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17" page="1" column="1">DOI: 10.1080/15710880701875043 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.informaworld.com" id="16">http://www.informaworld.com</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="18" page="2" column="1">20</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="19" page="2" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="2" column="1">2. The participatory prototyping heritage</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="2" column="1">Methodologically, we belong to the Scandinavian participatory design tradition (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Bjerknes et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Ehn 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Greenbaum and Kyng 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Bødker et al. 2000</xref>) and consequently, we understand design as an open, innovative, user-involved, cross- disciplinary, and thus multi-perspective cooperative process aimed at creating tools and systems for a variety of use context. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Floyd (1984)</xref>, we distinguish between prototypes and prototyping; prototypes, as rooted in the industrial design tradition embody a ‘first of their kind’ or a physical manifestation of a future artifact. For example, in car industry, producers usually develop a full-scale prototype of new cars to test its driving abilities before the final product is produced. Prototyping, on the other hand, refers to the mutual learning process that takes place in a cooperative design setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Floyd 1984</xref>). In the process of constructing the prototype car, the developers discuss, explore, and try out various aspects of the new concept with the prototype and thus mediate communication between members of the design team. The value of prototyping in participatory design is well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Floyd 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Bødker and Grønbæk 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Greenbaum and Kyng 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Grønbæk 1991</xref>). In the traditional sense, we may consider prototyping a collaborative identification of possible futures, rooted in current practice but with the purpose of introducing change. We are not the first to propose ways of managing this balance: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Mogensen (1992)</xref> introduces the concept of provotyping as a means of moving our practice, our actions and our visions of the future while still approaching it with a respectful understanding of what has been. The provotyping approach points to the fact that designers can benefit from ‘provoking concrete, everyday practice, by exposing current problems, calling forth what usually is taken for granted’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Mogensen 1992</xref>: 1). In the provotyping approach, design departs from an identification of problems in current practice with the designer as a provocateur not only interested in the immediately identifiable aspects of practice. We share with Mogensen the idea of the designer as a proactive participant in participatory prototyping. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Brandt and Grunnet (2000)</xref> take the role of the designer as change agent a step further by introducing the use of drama and props in design for the purpose of providing means for collaboratively evoking new design possibilities. According to Brandt and Grunnet, drama can help designers to achieve a greater empathy for the users and the contexts of use: ‘With inspiration from how actors can build up psychological characters the designers can enter the world of the users with both body and mind’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Brandt and Grunnet 2000</xref>: 9). Moreover, Brandt and Grunnet introduce props in prototyping as both ‘things to think with’ and ‘things to act with’ in their effort to transcend current practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Brandt and Grunnet 2000</xref>: 1). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Buur et al. (2000)</xref> present video as a design material where they use improvised video scenarios as ‘a collaborative inquiry into ‘‘what might be’’’ and thus<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> create a shared narrative of a possible future to be negotiated and reified between the participants. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Buchenau and Suri (2000)</xref> present the concept of experience prototyping for ‘understanding existing experiences, exploring design ideas and in communicating design concepts’ through enactment, role-playing and hands-on experiences with design materials to answer questions such as ‘what would it feel like if . . .?’ Common to these uses of dramatisation and improvisations is that they emphasise that the foundations of transcendence is to be found in the detailed investigation of current practice. We share the goal of transcending practice through participatory prototyping; however, our use of dramatisation differs in being designed to deliberately move the participants far away from current practice through narratives, props and physical space. Thus, we emphasise an imaginative place that is radically different than current practice as a vehicle for transcendence. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="42" class="deo:Reference">In this sense, our approach more closely resembles the work of Djajadiningrat et al. (2000)</xref>, where the use of, for example, extreme characters as the starting point for design moves the design setting far away from any given current practice. However, we differ fundamentally from their work because they do not work collaboratively with users but focus on developing design techniques for designers exclusively.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="39" page="3" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="40" page="3" column="1">21</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" page="3" column="1">3. Staging imaginative places of participatory prototyping</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" page="3" column="1">In talking about the places of participatory prototyping, we wish to express a particular concern for how this activity unfolds in physical and socio-cultural settings. The idea of staging the places of design collaboration is far from foreign to the participatory design tradition. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Muller (2003)</xref>, several participatory design techniques and approaches express fundamental hybridity in that they unfold in circumstances that are ambiguous or uncertain, neither belonging to the everyday domain of the designers or the domain of the users. Based on a survey of participatory design practice, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Muller (2003)</xref> discusses a range of strategies for achieving hybridity such as Sitings, Workshops, and Dramas, that may be applied in creating a third space of participatory design. Using various workshop formats, using dramas to frame cooperation or letting the workshop take place on sites neither belonging to the users or the designers are examples of strategies for creating hybrid spaces for design cooperation. When we choose to emphasise the places of participatory prototyping, we do this to stress a particular focus on the context of action as performed by the participants. ‘Place’ and ‘space’ are contested concepts within the literature concerned with design (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Harrison and Dourish 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Perry 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Dourish 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Ciolfi and Bannon 2007</xref>) and discussed at length within philosophy and humanist geography (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Tuan 1977</xref>, de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Certeau 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Casey 1997</xref>). Our purpose here is not to account for the richness of this discourse or to dwell on the philosophical aspects of the concepts. Our interest concerns participatory prototyping and how this activity is fundamentally structured according to the material, social and cultural context in which it occurs. To this end, we adopt the perspective inspired by de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Certeau (1984)</xref>, namely that what we encounter and practice in the world are places that are instilled with meaning, culture and context of action. Places are thus understood as the ‘orders’ and stability by which we relate to the world. A common theme in our previous years of work with participatory prototyping has been a dedication to staging these places in order to address new design challenges. In many respects, we see our efforts as a continuation of the work on prototyping within the tradition of participatory design whose qualities remain attractive in our work. We will, however, argue that we can benefit from moving towards imaginative places of participatory prototyping to create a more open and exploratory design space. By imaginative places we mean places that are radically distant from the<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> places of current practice. This distance may be realised through different dimensions: places may be distant in time as participants imagine a place for the prototyping session that is extrapolated in time. Distance may also be staged through cultural and social structures by imagining a place where cultural expectations are radically different or where particular social structures apply. The distance is thus a matter of creating radically new horizons for action where new possibilities and constraints apply. As these places are practiced by participants and make up the horizon of action for prototyping activities, the scope of opportunity for what is envisioned and explored is widened. Echoing de Certeau’s (1984) basic notion of ‘space as practiced place’ (p. 117), this approach thus focuses on how the design space is widened as a result of participants engaging in prototyping in particular places. In talking about staging these places for the activity of prototyping, we refer to the process in which we as designers carefully arrange the activity. As such, we are not creating the place of the prototyping activity as the place of this activity is fundamentally tied to the participants’ actions. We do, however, stage this place as a place of particular opportunity and constraint through the use of narratives, artefacts, location, etc. These means embody particular types, modes and rules for action that come to structure the process of prototyping. Moreover, in applying these means, we aim towards particular qualities of this place that are closely related to the design task. For example, if the design task is to explore the potential of the body in educational practice (as in our first case), the staging may be realised using artifacts that particularly promote using bodily skills or narratives that frame the activities around a theme of sports in the prototyping session. These means fundamentally come to structure the place of prototyping and thus the design space that emerges from this activity. A concrete participatory design technique for staging imaginative places by way of narrative is presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Dindler and Iversen (2007)</xref>. For a more detailed discussion of the means by which this staging is achieved, we distinguish between anchoring elements and elements of transcendence. Both concepts are closely related to our focus on staging imaginative places for prototyping as a way of creating a more open and exploratory design space. By anchoring elements we refer to the particular means of staging that maintain reference to current practice. Certain artifacts or concepts used in a particular session may anchor the process in aspects of existing practice (e.g. physical locations, artifacts, etc.). By elements of transcendence we refer to the means that create the unfamiliar; means that create new aspects of the place of prototyping that transcend the familiar. Narratives provide a good example of this process of estrangement: as children play in the yard they may pretend by means of narratives that the old shed is a dragon’s lair and that the sticks in their hands are swords. Elements of transcendence fuel the process of creating distance from current practice and make participatory prototyping take place in imaginative places. From our two cases we elaborate on the intricate connections between anchoring elements and elements of transcendence and how these relate to the design task at hand. Moreover, our two cases exemplify our attempts in balancing these means of staging imaginative places of prototyping.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="56" page="4" column="1">22</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="57" page="4" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="60" page="4" column="1">4. Prototyping interactive school floors</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="4" column="1">Our case material derives from ongoing research into IT support for educational purposes ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Brodersen and Iversen 2007</xref>). The iSchool project is a research project within the Center for Interactive Spaces, ISIS Katrinebjerg; an interdisciplinary research centre bringing together architecture, engineering, and computer science with a research mission to create new concepts for future interactive spaces. The iSchool project is a collaboration between<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> academia and industry with the vision of developing software infrastructures, user interfaces and spatial concepts for new interactive school environments. To fulfil this mission, we engage in designing innovative technology to support schoolwork that goes beyond the PC in cooperation with pupils and teachers. One particular research focus of the iSchool project has been to explore the kinesthetic dimensions of learning and the potential of revitalising the body in education. One of the prototypes resulting from this work is a large interactive floor (4 6 3 m) – the ‘Wisdom Well’ – situated in an open square of a local school (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). The interactive floor was developed in collaboration with commercial partners, pedagogical experts, teachers and pupils in a participatory design project. The concept of the Wisdom Well and the software applications for the Wisdom Well are further described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Grønbæk et al. (2007a)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Grønbæk et al. (2007b)</xref> and in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Iversen et al. (2007)</xref>. In this section, we will describe two particular participatory prototyping sessions which took place in the Wisdom Well project. The prototyping sessions are selected as they both echo general concerns with respect to staging imaginative places. The two cases exemplify two different ways of working consciously with anchoring elements to current practice and with elements of transcendence. The first case, the ‘Olympics 2020 in Andorra’, illustrates this by introducing a narrative that works as an element of transcendence. Here, the prototype in itself, the physical surroundings and the purpose of the session all serve as anchoring elements to current practice. In the second case, the ‘Murder Case’ prototyping session, the staging is taken a step further through the narrative frame, the role of the participants and the temporal aspects of the prototyping session.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="63" page="5" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="64" page="5" column="1">23</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="5" column="1">4.1. Olympics 2020 in Andorra</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="5" column="1">Prior to the installation of the Wisdom Well, we hosted a prototyping session where researchers, designers, teachers and pedagogical experts (15 people in all) were invited to explore how interactive floor surfaces could support kinesthetic learning in school</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_005.image_01.png" thmb="62re.page_005.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="73" page="5" column="1">Figure 1.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">The Wisdom Well is a 4 6 3 m interactive floor aimed at supporting kinesthetic learning in school environments.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="6" column="1">24</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="76" page="6" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" page="6" column="1">environments. The workshop took place in teaching facilities at the University of Aarhus and was carried out in a three hour session in the spring of 2006. The session was framed under the title of ‘Olympics 2020 in Andorra’ (OL 2020), entailing that participants were to develop new disciplines for the 2020 Olympics in Andorra. The session consisted of two main parts: a warm-up session and a development session. During the warm-up session, participants competed in a range of disciplines, such 1 as Sony Eye Toy games and Twister (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>). Having completed the warm-up, participants where divided into four teams and assigned the task of exploring new disciplines that might be used for the 2020 Olympics. As the Olympics were to be held in Andorra (a very small state in Europe), space was limited and the participants had to create disciplines that would be usable on a 4 6 3 m surface. The progression of the prototyping session was relatively tight as activities, tasks and resources were well defined. After a slightly reluctant start to the warm-up session, participants began to engage in the OL 2020 narrative, and the physical activities increased significantly. The warm-up worked well as an invigorating social activity that set the stage for the proceeding work. The second session, in which participants constructed concepts for the 3 6 4 m surface also had a slightly hesitant start. All groups started by negotiating the premises of the work, both regarding the narrative and the other factors that would affect the work. In one of the groups, the participants discussed whether their future concept should be limited to a two-dimensional projection on the floor surface or whether they could work with a three-dimensional space. The groups, however, soon went on to more exploratory activities. The room for the session had been equipped with a variety of balls, sports equipment and other artifacts that gave very immediate openings for the process. Participants would switch between playing with these artifacts, negotiating the premises of the task and exploring new possibilities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>). After two hours of work, the groups had each developed one or more concepts for the floor surface. The concepts developed were hybrids in the sense that they addressed the coupling between kinesthetic disciplines and the educational focus. The OL 2020 workshop resulted in three concept proposals for the Wisdom Well. One of these concepts was particularly interesting according to the development of future applications for the Wisdom Well. ‘Bob the Blind Builder’ was a geometry learning game in which pupils would get hands-on experience with three-dimensional geometric</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_006.image_02.png" thmb="62re.page_006.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="81" page="6" column="1">Figure 2.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Participants in sports clothing during the warm-up session (left), e.g. with Sony Eye 1 Toy (right).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83" page="7" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84" page="7" column="1">25</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_007.image_03.png" thmb="62re.page_007.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="86" page="7" column="1">Figure 3.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Participants developing a game concept on the floor surface (left) and discussing the concept (right).</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" page="7" column="1">shapes. The idea was that a group of pupils should guide a classmate by building a system- generated three-dimensional figure on the Wisdom Well. The classmate was blindfolded, so in order to solve the building challenge the pupils needed to communicate and negotiate, improving their geometrical vocabulary. The building blocks were foam blocks in different shapes and colours that could be tracked by a not-yet-existing three- dimensional tracking system on the Wisdom Well. ‘Bob the Blind Builder’ combined kinesthetic learning (as the pupils would physically build the figures on the Wisdom Well) with geometric issues in a collaborative game setup. The concept has been further developed into a new prototype application for the Wisdom Well. A second concept, the ‘Kenyan Chess Game’, in which pupils would compete in pairs, brought about general discussion on competition as a vehicle for learning. As the existing palette of applications for the Wisdom Well all focused on collaboration and negotiation, the Kenyan Chess Game was a valuable input for discussing the aspect of competition and reconsidering our understanding of the learning activities on the Wisdom Well. Relating to participatory prototyping, the OL 2020 prototyping session was meticulously staged to address kinesthetic aspects. Participants were asked to wear sports clothing, sports drinking bottles were handed out, all chairs were removed, and the room was equipped with a variety of sports utilities. Moreover, the first part of the session (the warm-up) was specifically aimed at setting the stage for physical activity. The narrative of the 2020 Olympics had a dual purpose. Firstly, it too was aimed at staging the event as a physical endeavour. Secondly, the narrative framing promoted a certain imaginative freedom as new meanings, activities, and concepts were legitimised within this frame. In this sense, the narrative frame, along with the other efforts to frame the physical aspects of the session, marks a staging of an imaginative place in which activities unfold. In relation to existing practice, these efforts constitute a range of elements of transcendence that were intentionally instilled in the prototyping session. Working with elements of transcendence is, however, intrinsically relational; they make sense only in relation to a point of departure that marks a contrast to the existing elements. Thus, as a place of meaningful design action, the session retained a range of anchoring elements in existing practice. The constraint of the 4 6 3 m surface created using tape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>) was a clear reference to the existing interactive floor as the focus of the process. Furthermore, although the theme of the session was the Olympics and thus</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="90" page="8" column="1">26</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="91" page="8" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_008.image_04.png" thmb="62re.page_008.image_04-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="93" page="8" column="1">Figure 4.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">The prototyping session set-up (right) was inspired by Lars Von Trier’s motion picture ‘Dogville’ (left) in which the scenery is limited to tape on the floor.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" page="8" column="1">promoted activities within the sports and game genre, the obvious link to the actual interactive floor and the teaching background of several of the participants meant that the educational concern was present throughout the work. To retain the link to the educational theme, the groups were asked to relate the concepts they developed to a matrix of different learning styles and modes of physical activity. The relationship between the anchoring elements and the elements of transcendence are intentional constructs in that they reflect specifically the design task at hand. In the case of OL 2020, the elements of transcendence were intentionally directed towards several key issues. Firstly, the elements were directed towards the central material of the project in the form of the Wisdom Well floor surface. Secondly, the elements were directed towards the kinesthetic capabilities of future users. Thirdly, the elements were directed towards the overarching theme of educational practice. This third point was, to a large extent, implicit in that all participants were aware that this was a prototyping session specifically about the Wisdom Well in educational settings. These three points all mark key aspects of the design process. Although we have argued that this first case may be characterised as a staging of an imaginative place of prototyping activity we maintain that the imaginative aspects are fundamentally woven into the fabric of key anchoring elements in current practice and derives from intentionally addressing the design task. Practicing these places of participatory prototyping entails a constant interplay between the familiar and the radically unfamiliar.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="96" page="8" column="1">4.2. The Murder Case</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" page="8" column="1">Our second case takes staging a step further and provides an example with numerous elements of transcendence. This case also derives from the Wisdom Well installation. The Murder Case prototyping session was carried out at ‘Møllevangskolen’, which is a public school in the city of Aarhus, Denmark. Twelve pupils (both girls and boys) aged 11–14, their teacher (a 30-year-old male teacher), and five designers participated in the session. The location of the session was the department square next to the Wisdom Well at Møllevangskolen. Similar to the OL 2020 prototyping session, the intent of this session was to prototype concepts for the interactive floor surface. The session was structured around a murder case <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> narrative where pupils would take on the role of forensic detectives charged with the task of solving a murder case. Each pupil was provided with a T-shirt with a New York Police Department logo to emphasise their role in the narrative and to extend the gap between the school environment and participatory prototyping session. The department square of the school was set up as the crime scene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>) – the victim (a mannequin) lying still on the floor next to the Wisdom Well with clues surrounding the body. The clues were randomly chosen to provide an open-ended and highly complex point of departure for the pupil’s investigation. As a first element of transcendence in the prototyping session, we extrapolated the temporal aspect of the narrative: the murder was conducted in 2020, but the time of the investigation was in 2006. In other words, the pupils (and teachers) were encouraged to investigate a murder that had not yet been committed. Not only were the participants to solve a murder case, which was in itself an imaginative leap compared to their usual school practice, they also had to deal with contradictions and unfamiliar conceptions relating to their understanding of time and place. The Wisdom Well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>) was the wild card in solving the murder case; whenever pupils had forensic evidence that they needed to analyse, models of the crime situation they needed to visualise or in general were in need of assistance, the Wisdom Well was the place to go. The Wisdom Well did not have any implemented functionality, so the pupils would have to imagine how the Well should work. When they had described what they needed from the Well and how this should work, they would be provided with the answer to their question or another clue. A member of the design team acted as the Wisdom Well technician, who discussed the concepts for the Well and provided the pupils with answers to their requests. Another member of the design team acted as a reporter, who had legitimate access to asking the investigators questions about their work and ideas during the murder investigation. This provided us with valuable video documentation of the participants’ actions and especially a documentation of their prototyping activities on the Wisdom Well. After the pupils had been introduced to the framing of the session, they began to explore the clues from the crime scene. Among these where clues pointing to the website of the victim (which had been set up in advance), footprints that indicated where the murderer had left the building and a range of strange artifacts, the purpose of which the pupils needed the assistance of the Wisdom Well to figure out. As so many elements in the setup represented unfamiliar territory, the pupils needed assistance to get started and</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="98" page="9" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="9" column="1">27</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_009.image_05.png" thmb="62re.page_009.image_05-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="104" page="9" column="1">Figure 5.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Participants exploring the interactive floor surface of the Wisdom Well (left) as part of the murder case setup (right).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="106" page="10" column="1">28</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="10" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" page="10" column="1">on several occasions needed help from the teacher. As the session progressed, students did, however, begin to acknowledge the open-ended character and accept that action in this setting required them to make assumptions and produce creative solutions. As such, the imagination of the pupils grew as the session progressed. In particular, this was reflected in the use of the Wisdom Well; as pupils began to understand the idea of being able to use the Wisdom Well for creative solutions, their ideas became more refined and daring. The pupils would consult the Wisdom Well for a number of tasks. One group of girls used the 1 Wisdom Well as an over-sized, digital version of the Brio ‘Labyrinth Wooden Maze Game’, using their body weights to control an imaginary ball on the floor. Their game design was motivated by the occupation of the deceased who, according to them, had been a brilliant game designer. A group of boys turned to the Wisdom Well to find technical clues to solve the murder case. They imagined that the killer had left some footprints on the interactive floor and by means of some imagined tools for measuring distance and angles they were convinced that they could explain exactly what happened at the time of the murder. The conceptualisation of an application that could measure distance between points and angles was further discussed in subsequent co-creation sessions and an application is currently under development for the Wisdom Well. In general, the murder case session resulted in a number of concepts for how the Wisdom Well could be used for visualisations, for coordinating shared activities and for how other forms of digital and physical material would relate to the Well. The session was concluded with the pupils presenting their findings from the crime scene and their conclusions on the murder case. Following this and leaving the narrative of the murder case, all participants discussed the potential of the Wisdom Well in school activities. Relating to prototyping practice, the murder-case session shared several characteristics with OL 2020. Both revolved around a narrative frame that served as an element of transcendence, mediating the activities and actions of the participants. In both cases, the narrative frame provided a powerful tool for creating distance between the place of prototyping and current practice. In the murder case, we experimented with a radicalisation of the temporal regularity. A murder was committed in 2020, but was to be investigated in 2006, providing the imaginative place of the prototyping session with a high degree of complexity containing so many elements of transcendence that it tended towards a situation of flux. This ‘Alice-in-Wonderland’ imaginative place was only anchored by the physical setting of the school square and the relation between teacher and pupil, that was manifested in the relationship between the chief investigator and his detectives in the narrative frame. Whereas the physical setting in the OL 2020 session served as an element of transcendence, the physical setting of the murder case session was conversely an anchoring element. As argued above, the relationship between the anchoring elements and the elements of transcendence are intentional constructs in that they specifically reflect the design task at hand. The two cases mirror our research efforts exploring how prototyping can benefit from unfolding in imaginative places that are radically distant from the places of current practice. The staging of these imaginative places is done by consciously considering the placement of anchoring elements and elements of transcendences in the imaginative place.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="109" page="10" column="1">5. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" page="10" column="1">Our work in recent years has led us to reflect on the ways in which we are practicing participatory prototyping. The particular concern of this paper has been to reflect on the <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> changing places in which prototyping is practiced. From our work, we see a movement towards staging imaginative places to create an increased distance between the places of current practice and the places of prototyping. More than anything, this development has been motivated by the design task that we have been facing; a need for an open exploratory design space emerging from design cooperation. Our two cases from the iSchool project provide examples from which we have discussed staging imaginative places as a play between anchoring elements that maintain a hold in current practice and elements of transcendence that represent the unfamiliar and open up the horizon of opportunity. As shown from the cases, the elements of transcendence may be manifested as narratives, physical artifacts, tasks, activities, etc. The relation between anchoring elements and elements of transcendence closely reflects the design intention; in the OL 2020 session anchoring elements, which included the 4 6 3 m floor surface and the elements of transcendence, were centred on the kinesthetic aspects of interaction. The two cases exemplify a span in the continuum of imaginative places. In the murder case, the staging was characterised by a large number of elements of transcendence, bordering on a state of flux. However, the murder case was not completely bereft of anchoring elements; it was performed in the school and thus tied to this particular physical setting. Moreover, the teacher/pupil relation was maintained within the roles in the narrative. We see this as an important point with respect to staging and practicing imaginative places in participatory prototyping: without anchoring elements to current practice, the narrative and tasks would not relate to meaningful design action. The rationale and thus the potential of the approach that we have outlined is to extend the design space of opportunity emerging from participatory prototyping sessions. We share with the existing body of literature the goal of transcending practice through participatory prototyping. However, as suggested in this contribution, instead of looking for the foundations of transcendence in the detailed investigation of current practice, we start our development of transcendence in a staged imaginative place.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="111" page="11" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112" page="11" column="1">29</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="114" page="11" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">This work has been funded by Center for Interactive Spaces, ISIS Katrinebjerg, and we thank our colleagues there for their support. In particular, we thank Karen Johanne Kortbek, Kaspar Rosengreen Nielsen, and Louise Aagaard for their dedicated work in the Wisdom Well project. Finally, we are indebted to the pupils, teachers, and researchers who have participated with enthusiasm in the prototyping sessions.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="116" page="11" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" page="11" column="1">Bjerknes, G., Ehn, P., and Kyng, M. eds. 1987. Computers and democracy: A scandinavian challenge. Aldershot: Avebury.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="118" page="11" column="1">Brandt, E. and Grunnet, C., 2000. Evoking the future: drama and props in user centered design. In: Proceedings of the participatory design conference. New York: ACM Press, 11–20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="119" page="11" column="1">Brodersen, C. and Iversen, O.S., 2007. Dressing up for school work—supporting a collaborative environment with heterogeneous technologies. In: Proceedings of ECSCW, Limerick, Ireland. London: Springer Verlag, 251–270.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" page="11" column="1">Brown, B. and Perry, M. Of maps and guidebooks: designing geographical technologies. In: Proceedings of designing interactive systems 2002. London: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" page="11" column="1">Buchenau, M. and Fulton Suri, J., 2000. Experience prototyping. In: The proceeding of designing interactive systems. New York: ACM Press, 424–433.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" page="11" column="1">Buur, J., Binder, T., and Øritsland, T.A. Reflection on design practice: exploring video documentary of designers in action. In: Proceedings of the designing interactive systems, 17–19 August 2000. New York: ACM Press, 450–452.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" page="12" column="1">Bødker, S., Ehn, P., Sjo  ̈ gren, D., and Sundblad, Y., 2000. Co-operative design perspectives on 20 years with ‘The Scandinavian IT Design Model’. In: J. Gulliksen, A. Lantz, L. Oestreicher, and K. Severinson Eklundh, eds. Proceedings of NordiCHI 2000. Stockholm, Sweden, October 23– 25, 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="126" page="12" column="1">Bødker, S. and Grønbæk, K., 1991. Cooperative prototyping: users and designers in mutual activity. International journal of man–machine studies, 34, 453–478.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="127" page="12" column="1">Casey, E.S., 1997. The fate of place—A philosophical history. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="128" page="12" column="1">Ciolfi, L. and Bannon, L., 2007. Designing hybrid places: merging interaction design, ubiquitous technologies and geographies of the museum space. Journal of codesign, 3 (3), 159–180.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="129" page="12" column="1">de Certeau, M., 1984. The practice of everyday life. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="12" column="1">Dindler, C. and Iversen, 2007. Fictional inquiry—design collaboration in a shared narrative space. Journal of codesign, 3 (4), 213–234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="12" column="1">Djajadiningrat, J.P., Gaver, W.W., and Fres, J.W., 2000. Interaction relabelling and extreme characters: methods for exploring aesthetic interactions. In: Proceedings of designing interactive systems. New York: ACM Press, 66–71.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="12" column="1">Dourish, P., 2006. Re-space-ing place: ‘place’ and ‘space’ ten years on. In: Proceedings of CSCW. Canada: ACM Press, 299–308.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="12" column="1">Ehn, P., 1988. Work-oriented design of computer artifacts. Falko  ̈ ping, Sweden: Arbetslivscentrum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="12" column="1">Ehn, P., 1993. Scandinavian design: on participation and skill. In: D. Schuler and A. Namioka, eds. Participatory design—principles and practices. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="12" column="1">Floyd, C., 1984. A systematic look at prototyping. In: R. Budde, K. Kuhlenkamp, L. Mathiassen, and H. Zu  ̈ llighoven, eds. Approaches to prototyping. Heidelberg, West Germany: Springer Verlag, 1–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" page="12" column="1">Greenbaum, J. and Kyng, M. eds. 1991. Design at work—cooperative design of computer systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="12" column="1">Grønbæk, K., Prototyping and active user involvement in system development: towards a cooperative prototyping approach. PhD thesis, Department of Computer Science, University of Aarhus, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="12" column="1">Grønbæk, K., Iversen, O.S., Kortbek, K.J., Nielsen, K.R., and Aagaard, L., 2007a. Interactive floor support for kinesthetic interaction in children learning environments. In: Proceedings of INTERACT , Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 10–14 September. Berlin: Springer-Verlag, 361–375.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="12" column="1">Grønbæk, K., Iversen, O.S., Kortbek, K.J., Nielsen, K.R., and Aagaard, L., 2007b. iFloorGame—a platform for co-located collaborative games. In: Proceedings of the international conference on advances in computer entertainment, 13–15 June, Salzburg, Austria. New York: ACM Press, 64– 67.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="12" column="1">Harrison, S. and Dourish, P., 1996. Re-place-ing space: the roles of place and space in collaborative systems. In: ACM conference on computer-supported cooperative work, Boston. New York: ACM Press, 67–76.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="12" column="1">Iversen, O.S., Kortbek, K.J., Nielsen, K.R., and Aagaard, L., 2007. Stepstone—an interactive floor application for hearing impaired children with a cochlear implant. In: Proceedings of 6th international conference on interaction design and children, 6–8 June, Aalborg, Denmark. New York: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="12" column="1">Mogensen, P., 1992. Towards a provotyping approach in system development. Scandinavian Journal of Information Systems, 3, 31–53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="12" column="1">Muller, M.J., 2003. Participatory design: the third space in HCI. In: J. Jacko and A. Sears, eds. Handbook of HCI. Mahway, NJ: Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Tuan, Y.-F., 1977. Space and place. The perspective of experience. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="123" page="12" column="1">30</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="124" page="12" column="1">C. Brodersen et al.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx145">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62re.page_013.image_06.png" thmb="62re.page_013.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
