<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>2cf3d5ce8dcbe238848488173a358d8b15755cdd12ca8a5432b4bb18312b8d49</job>
    <base_name>62fe</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/mere.2008.3</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Articulating Software Requirements Comic Book Style</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Amanda M. Williams</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Thomas A. Alspaugh Informatics Department University of California</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Irvine</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">USA</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="7"> <email id="6">{amandamw,alspaugh}@ics.uci.edu</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8">It is almost a truism that system stakeholders do not fully understand and communicate what they want, often until a system is produced and they see it isn’t right. Such an out- come is wasteful, expensive, and unsatisfactory. Working with requirements in comic book style provides affordances, absent or weaker in other requirements forms, that may as- sist stakeholders in surfacing and expressing desires sooner and developers in understanding them and each other. Ap- propriate incorporation of comic book style artifacts into requirements work, in addition to making it more playful and enjoyable, can contribute to greater stakeholder satis- faction and more effective software development.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="9" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="1" column="1">The form in which information is presented affects how well it is understood and by whom, the ease of identifying problems and missing information, and the facility with which adjustments and corrections can be made [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="10" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. Scenarios, use cases, and other narrative requirements have been augmented with images, sound, and video clips in order to increase their effectiveness in achieving various goals such as identifying missing requirements. Comic book style offers a different set of affordances in comparison with either textual scenarios or scenarios enriched with media. In this paper we examine the articulation of requirements in comic book style, which we characterize (drawing from McCloud [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="11" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]) as follows:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">1. Textual content in comics is subordinated to and organized by the images. Text annotates the images, and is organized in the layout of the image frames. In contrast, an augmented scenario’s images or other media annotate the text, and are organized by the structure of the text. 2. Comics images are typically sketch-like, with limited and often focused detail and a sense of revisability.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">In contrast, a photograph or video presents an actual scene without the emphasis and detail elimination that is possible in a sketch or diagram, and the media elements used to augment scenarios have an air of relative actuality and finality. 3. Iconically-drawn comics characters enhance the reader’s identification with the characters and im- mersion in the narrative. McCloud argues that a comics reader perceives more-realistically represented characters as “another” and more-iconically represented characters as “yourself” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="14" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], identifying with iconically-drawn characters and being drawn into the narrative more deeply. 4. The frame-by-frame presentation of comics gives the reader an active role in perceiving the whole of what is being presented. McCloud expresses this in terms of the reader filling in “the space between the panels” by perceiving completely what is represented incom- pletely and discretely, to produce closure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="15" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. Closure makes the reader an active participant in the percep- tion of what is being narrated. McCloud lists six categories of panel transitions, such as temporal progres- sion in a single action (moment-to-moment), succes- sive actions of a single subject (action-to-action), and changing points of view (subject-to-subject).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" page="1" column="2">Antón and Potts (among others) have pointed out what is perhaps the central problem of requirements:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">Stakeholders seldom understand their requirements fully at the beginning of a project. They often lack a clear vision of what the system should do and change their minds during development. In general, stakeholders only become more sure about what they want when they see a system that does not exhibit the necessary features. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="18" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="2">A primary goal of requirements work is to get stakeholders to explore and articulate their requirements sooner, so that the eventual system is more likely to satisfy them. Another goal is to communicate those requirements among all <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> the people involved, so that there can be effective discussion and evaluation of them, identification of problems and gaps, negotiation and (ideally) agreement, and eventually a shared understanding among them. The participants in- clude stakeholders and developers, including, as interdisciplinary teams become more common, diverse developers such as interaction designers and ethnographers. This paper discusses how comics-style requirements address this problem and can help work towards these goals. We en- vision a selective use of comics in conjunction with other requirements forms and approaches, directed toward earlier stakeholder requirements exploration and articulation and communication among all participants. A number of researchers have augmented narratives with media. Maiden et al. add images, audio, and video to possible scenarios of expected use to provide a richer set of recognition cues that can help identification of the scenarios that are appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="22" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]. Textual scenarios are auto- matically generated as alternative courses through a set of events, then annotated with media. Haumer et al. add rich media to better capture usage of an existing system to support analysis and identification the goals it achieves, in order to more effectively define goals of a future system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="23" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>]. Storyboarding has been used in requirements and ap- pears in the literature most commonly as sequences of program screens (for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="24" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]), a form which has little in common with comics. Storyboards in the Hollywood sense of a sequence of drawings of scenes have been used, for example by Maiden and Robertson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="25" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>], and are more closely related to comics. However, requirements storyboards have not to our knowledge taken advantage of the range of technical choices (such as characters’ degree of iconicity, and the categories of panel transitions) or the introspective analysis that have been explored in comics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="26" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. In contrast, comics combine image and text more cohesively, display a more effective consciousness of the reader, play with tem- porality and spatiality to communicate things storyboarding does not, and in general use the possibilities of image+text. The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. Sections 2, 3, and 4 outline the contributions of scenarios to requirements, sketching to design, and images in general to ethnography. Section 5 discuss text and graphics working together. Section 6 focuses on comics as boundary objects. Finally, Section 7 summarizes the paper and future work.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21" page="1" column="2">2008 Third International Workshop on Multimedia and Enjoyable Requirements Engineering (MERE'08) 978-0-7695-3626-2/08 $25.00 © 2008 IEEE</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="2" column="1">2. The work that scenarios do for requirements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="2" column="1">Alexander and Maiden show the central role of scenarios in requirements in their informal definition of what a requirements engineer does: “I get people to tell the stories of what their systems are meant to do, so they build the right thing” [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="29" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. Scenarios make use of people’s natural ability to tell and understand stories. Audiences can often<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> infer context, causation, and motivations from even a simple scenario. No special training is needed to understand them, so all stakeholders and developers can participate through them and potentially come to agreement in terms of them. Scenarios provide concrete examples for more abstract requirements and models. They draw their audience into the story and get them thinking about the system, its social context of use, how it changes the world of its stakeholders, and what it should provide. As we will discuss later for comics in particular, scenarios can help stakeholders put themselves into the future world in which the planned system will operate so that the stakeholders consider whether the system will meet their needs. A scenario typically engages and involves stakeholders more effectively than a more-formal model or requirement, positioning them to raise insightful questions and explore alternatives. Missing requirements are particularly difficult to identify and address. Scenarios can help stakeholders identify missing requirements, but as many researchers have noted people are better at identifying errors of commission (“that behavior of the system is wrong”) than errors of omission (“the system should do this but doesn’t”). This is a difficult problem with any form of requirements; it has been addressed through scenarios by various approaches for generating possible scenarios for stakeholders to approve or re- ject (for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="31" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>] and earlier work leading up to it).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="33" page="2" column="2">3. The work that narrative sketching does for design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="2" column="2">Narratives of use also play a critical role in product and interaction designers’ processes of refining tentative designs into usable artifacts. While the terminology may be different, the goals are remarkably similar: to bring abstract design goals to life in ways that enable us to better communicate, to explore alternatives, question the utility, usability, and aesthetics of the design, find problems, and begin to agree on the nitty gritty details of implementation. In much of design practice, however, it is common to create these narratives in sketches. Designer Mark Baskinger articulates the importance of narrative sketching for communication around design practice: “Explicit goals for drawing and sketching are 1. to ex- ternalize and convey the process of thinking — to transform intangible ideas to tangible information for others; 2. to re- veal ideas/relationships, not results; and 3. to engage discussion around the subject/problem as an inclusive activity.” To this end, narrative sketching must offer “concrete touch points” for viewers and provide a sequence that can easily be followed, even by non-designers. For all their concrete detail, sketches are not final artifacts, but meant to be subject to revision [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="34" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>].<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Design sketching, then, exhibits a characteristic, and productive, tension: while images are produced with the goal of making design ideas concrete and particular, they must remain flexible and revisable. One way to address this tension would be to use cartoonish sketching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>), as opposed to more high-fidelity illustrations, to allow that flexibility. As demonstrated by Landay and Myers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="40" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>], when presented with the task of prototyping a software interface, designers who sketched free-hand tried many vari- ations while “those who used a drawing program tended to focus more on refining the initial design, without generating design variations.” Another tactic might be to draw many vivid versions of the design, each differing in particular details. These meth- ods of illustration are by no means incompatible. As comics artist Scott McCloud points out [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="41" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], “the ability of cartoons to focus our attention on an idea is, I think, an important part of their special power, both in comics and in drawing gen- erally.” Sketching is robust enough to accommodate flexibility and cartoonishness or particularity and realism quite selectively. The designer can then be very particular about the setting, but vague about the design of the device; or pre- cise in the device’s button placement, and vague about what the user looks like.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="36" page="2" column="2">2008 Third International Workshop on Multimedia and Enjoyable Requirements Engineering (MERE'08) 978-0-7695-3626-2/08 $25.00 © 2008 IEEE</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fe.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62fe.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="38" page="3" column="1">Figure 1. A quick, sketchy presentation of a temporal sequence. The text complements and gives context to the action, discussing broad themes of interaction while the pictures and dialogue show a particular instance. It could be an ethnographic narrative of an interaction that actually happened, or a projective scenario of something that might happen, perhaps in the next iteration of the system.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="3" column="1">4. Images in ethnographic engagement</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" page="3" column="1">In constructing scenarios, illustrated or not, we are nec- essarily telling stories about someone: the people who are stakeholders in the system. In this respect, requirements en- <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> gineers and designers share goals and concerns with ethnographers who play an increasing role in the design and development of technological systems. Broadly speaking, this discipline of “design ethnography” is concerned with “the broad patterns of everyday life that are important and rele- vant specifically for the conception, design, and development of new products and services” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="45" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>], yet for all its concern with “broad patterns” the way that design ethnographers bring home their findings is in the form of vivid stories; broad patterns of domestic life are exemplified in stories of sitting around a <xref ref-type="table" rid="Tin" id="46" class="deo:Reference">table in</xref> an Italian kitchen, being teased for drinking water out of a porcelain cup instead of a proper glass. Narratives such as these, that make broad patterns concrete, can be a first step towards the design of a product or system. Though much of the focus in visual ethnography has been on photographs and video [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="47" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>], design ethnography more recently has begun using design sketches as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="48" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. The uses of these images can elicit conversations with participants that would never have happened were they not presented with the researcher’s concrete representations of their needs and aspirations. The idea behind the use of sketches and illustration in ethnography is not simply to document, though there may be documentary aspects to such imagery. The image is part of the encounter between researcher and informant, understood as a part of the visual culture that surrounds them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="49" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. The technology used to make the image and the sorts of images created will have an effect on how users and/or informants receive the researcher and her images. An example<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> of this sort of interaction might involve a requirements engineer presenting sleek computer generated design mock- ups to a stakeholder for feedback. The stakeholder is quite likely to read these images as late-stage designs, having seen similar images primarily on finished software in everyday life, and this will color their feedback, making them more apt to suggest only minor changes. In these cases a sketchier, more cartoonish style can elicit more honest and helpfully critical feedback [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="52" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>].</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="51" page="3" column="2">2008 Third International Workshop on Multimedia and Enjoyable Requirements Engineering (MERE'08) 978-0-7695-3626-2/08 $25.00 © 2008 IEEE</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="54" page="4" column="1">5. Text and pictures working together</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="4" column="1">Articulating requirements work in the form of comics incorporates some of the strongest contributions of requirements engineering, design, and ethnography’s narrative tra- ditions. Good comics art can not only incorporate the text- driven narratives of RE scenarios and the image-driven narratives of product and interaction design, but also ethnography’s critical concern with the ways in which viewers in- terpret and answer narrative images. Because of this multi- faceted treatment of text, imagery, and reader engagement, we believe that comics-style narratives can powerfully communicate with stakeholders and project teams across a variety of disciplinary and technical backgrounds. Comics-style scenarios differ from current approaches in several ways. First, according to Baskinger images offer “faster access to the idea” than words do, yet words can provide much- needed context and nuance. Comics may combine words and pictures in a variety of ways; in some cases the picture may simply be illustrating what the words say, or the words simply describing what the pictures depict [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="55" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. Redundance may even be advantageous in a narrative that is meant to be shared and understood by people from very different backgrounds. Alternatively, if either the words or the pictures alone tell the plot story very clearly, then the other has lati- tude to show other aspects of the story — perhaps the user’s emotional state, a memory triggered by the situation, or a brief reference to the broader context of use. In this way, a rich narrative can be conveyed concisely, yet clearly. Second, comics-style illustrations shares with design illustrations a capacity for sketchiness. Far from being a weakness, sketchiness early in the design process, allows readers to more easily imagine revisions. Using drawn images, designers and developers have the flexibility to spec- ify details or render them vaguely, depending on the stage of the design or requirements engineering process, or what is to be elicited from stakeholders. Third, when comics-style narratives specifically render characters in a simple and iconic fashion, they invite readers to put themselves in the character’s place [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="56" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. A tech- nique common to comics, which could serve requirements engineering well, is to render scenery and objects in realistic fashion, while rendering characters simply and iconi-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> cally, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>. This could address the primary goal mentioned in the Introduction, by inducing stakeholders to be more effectively engaged in the scenarios and thus to explore their requirements sooner. Lastly, while words allow us to convey ideas in sequence, it is images that allow us to use space as well to convey ideas in different patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>). The space between comics panels, crucially, separates each depicted moment, demanding that our imagination fill in what happens between [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="62" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. While errors of omission are often difficult to find in traditional text scenarios, the format of comics art is quite explicit about showing the gaps and inviting people to make the imaginative leap to visualize what might be missing. We hypothesize that producing the closure across these gaps may surface concerns and goals that would oth- erwise not be expressed, and thus contribute to addressing the problem of missing requirements in a novel way.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fe.page_004.image_02.png" thmb="62fe.page_004.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="59" page="4" column="2">Figure 2. A more polished, realistic presentation done in PhotoShop and based on photographs. The drawings select and empha- size the important elements, eliding unimpor- tant detail. Here the panels illustrate things happening at or near the same time, but in different locations.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" page="4" column="2">6. Comics scenarios and boundary objects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" page="4" column="2">In advocating this particular approach to creating illustrated and engaging scenarios, we are borrowing techniques from design and ethnography. This is no accident. Increas- ingly, devices and software systems are being produced by interdisciplinary teams. While the issue of communicating <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> about requirements with stakeholders is crucial to good system design, it is just as important for the project teams to be able to communicate towards common goals despite different practices and disciplinary backgrounds. Comics have the advantage of being widely readable (like scenarios), not just to an entire project team but to stakeholders as well. But as we have illustrated in previous sections, different groups of people may produce and use narratives in different ways, as appropriate to their way of working. In a discussion of multi-group collaboration on a large project, Star and Griesemer note that “people coming together from different social worlds frequently have the ex- perience of addressing an object that has a different mean- ing for each of them.” These objects, which they call boundary objects, facilitate collaboration by being “both adapt- able to different viewpoints and robust enough to maintain identity across them” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="67" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. We suspect that comics-style narrative scenarios can be effective boundary objects. One example of how this might work would be the ways in which requirement engineers might use scenarios to talk about what they think will happen, while ethnographers might construct narratives with similar structure, but that describe or composite what does (or at least did) actually happen. In a well-designed system, the first sort of narrative might be heavily based on the second sort.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66" page="4" column="2">2008 Third International Workshop on Multimedia and Enjoyable Requirements Engineering (MERE'08) 978-0-7695-3626-2/08 $25.00 © 2008 IEEE</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="69" page="5" column="1">7. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" page="5" column="1">In this paper we have proposed the use of comics-style narrative to communicate scenarios in requirements engineering. Comics exhibit characteristics that may encour- age stakeholder engagement in requirements engineering, and foster a productive imagination around how scenarios might play out. They also exhibit an intersection of various narrative practices that can help members of interdisciplinary project teams communicate about their work. We have described some of the related ways in which the different disciplines of requirements, design, and design ethnography use textual and pictorial narratives in various ways to make abstract patterns and needs more vivid. While the approaches may be quite different, the goals are the same: to create good systems that meet the needs of all stakeholders. We have identified several items of future work. The first is a case study of the application of comics-style requirements to the requirements process of a system. While it seems clear to us that comics-style requirements can be created (indeed, the figures for this paper show several small examples), we need to explore and evaluate how they may be useful in requirements work. Second, McCloud’s expli- cation of the foundations of comics [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="70" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] gives a much more detailed space that specific comics reside in, from which we have selected only the four items listed in the introduction.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> It is quite possible that other dimensions we have not con- sidered here (for example, the degree to which the comics are abstracted towards the picture plane) may turn out to be significant. Of the items we selected, the six categories of panel transitions seem likely to repay further analysis in the context of requirements.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="73" page="5" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="74" page="5" column="2">[1] I. F. Alexander and N. Maiden, editors. Scenarios, Stories, Use Cases: Through the Systems Development Life-Cycle. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd., 2004.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="75" page="5" column="2">[2] T. A. Alspaugh, S. E. Sim, K. Winbladh, M. Diallo, H. Ziv, and D. J. Richardson. The importance of clarity in usable requirements specification formats. In 5th Int. Wkp. on Com- parative Evaluation in Reqts. Eng. (CERE’07), Oct. 2007.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="76" page="5" column="2">[3] S. J. Andriole. Storyboard Prototyping: A new approach to user requirements analysis. QED Inf. Sciences, 1989.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="77" page="5" column="2">[4] A. I. Antón and C. Potts. The use of goals to surface requirements for evolving systems. In 20th Int. Conf. on Software Engineering (ICSE ’98), pages 157–166, Apr. 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="78" page="5" column="2">[5] M. Baskinger. Pencils before pixels: a primer in hand- generated sketching. interactions, 15(2):28–36, 2008.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="5" column="2">[6] P. Haumer, K. Pohl, and K. Weidenhaupt. Requirements elicitation and validation with real world scenes. IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, 24(12):1036–1054, Dec. 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" page="5" column="2">[7] J. A. Landay and B. A. Myers. Sketching interfaces: To- ward more human interface design. Computer, 34(3):56–64, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="5" column="2">[8] N. Maiden and S. Robertson. Developing use cases and scenarios in the requirements process. In 27th Int. Conf. on Software Engineering (ICSE ’05), pages 561–570, May 2005.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="82" page="5" column="2">[9] S. McCloud. Understanding Comics: the invisible art. Harper, 1994.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" page="5" column="2">[10] T. H. Pang, N. A. M. Maiden, K. Zachos, and C. Ncube. Do rich media scenarios support requirements discovery? In 11th International Workshop on Requirements Engineering: Foundation for Software Quality (REFSQ’05), pages 152– 166, June 2005.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="84" page="5" column="2">[11] S. Pink. Doing Visual Ethnography: Images, Media and Representation in Research. Sage, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="85" page="5" column="2">[12] T. Salvador, G. Bell, and K. Anderson. Design ethnography. Design Management, 10(4):35–41, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="5" column="2">[13] S. L. Star and J. R. Griesemer. Institutional ecology, ‘trans- lations’ and boundary objects: Amateurs and professionals in Berkeley’s Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, 1907-39. So- cial Studies of Science, 19(3):387–420, 1989.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="5" column="2">[14] Y. Y. Wong. Rough and ready prototypes: lessons from graphic design. In SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI ’92), pages 83–84, 1992.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="5" column="2">[15] S. P. Wyche, P. M. Aoki, and R. E. Grinter. Re-placing faith: reconsidering the secular-religious use divide in the United States and Kenya. In 26th SIGCHI Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI ’08), pages 11–20, 2008.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="89" page="5" column="2">2008 Third International Workshop on Multimedia and Enjoyable Requirements Engineering (MERE'08) 978-0-7695-3626-2/08 $25.00 © 2008 IEEE</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
