<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>8ff53ed492db409e03bfd53f13d8129bc6ecc565de2038366f28989ff6454f66</job>
    <base_name>62rb</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/hicss.2004.1265487</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Toolkits for Open Innovation - The Case of Mobile Phone Games</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">) 1) 2) Frank Piller</name>
          <aff id="4">1</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Christoph Ihl</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Johann Füller</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Christof Stotko</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="9">Technische Universität München Dept. for General and Industrial Management Leopoldstrasse 139, 80804 München [piller, ihl, stotko]@wi.tum.de CEO Hyve AG Ligsalzstrasse 16 80339 München <email id="8">johann.fueller@hyve.de</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="11"><marker type="block"/> presented ‘toolkit for open innovation’ will be the foundation of a ‘value web’ in a unique manner: a value web in between consumers and users. The paper further derives economic benefits of the developed toolkit for mobile phone game creation theoretically and integrates them into a diversified business model. The toolkit as a distinct performance feature has the potential to establish a social environment for its most enthusiastic users and thereby to strengthen user relationships with the provider and increase overall business success.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction and Motivation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">User toolkits enable consumers to develop customized product applications without having dedicated technical knowledge. Applied in the field of handheld computing, toolkits are a very powerful instrument to meet the growing demand for customized mobile applications. In this paper, the theoretical principles and functionalities of user interaction toolkits are translated into a technical software concept for mobile phone games. The presented toolkit is a new internet based application allowing users to create a customized game on their desktop computer and to transfer it to handheld devices. In contrast to well known open source software development projects, no programming expertise is required. Thus, participation of innovative users is comparatively easy. In line with the open source concept, but as an extending feature to the toolkit approach, the presented solution is embedded in an online community. Thus, contributions by innovative users can be stored in a library leading to a continuously growing information pool of available components. Games and components can be passed on easily between customers, facilitating the adoption of other users’ contributions as well as collaborative development between users. The community feature of the toolkit does not only provide the common toolset of online communities allowing for user-to-user communication, e.g. chats and bulletin boards, or text based contributions, e.g. recommendations, product evaluations and voting tools, but it also enables users to exchange and jointly develop actual product prototypes. In this regard, the</region>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" page="1" column="1">Enterprises in all branches of industry are being forced to react to increasingly heterogeneous demand and to find ways for a closer reaction to customers’ needs. At the same time the internet with its multimedia richness, interactivity, global accessibility and low cost communication and information processing offers new promising ways to interact with a large number of formerly anonymous consumers. In unprecedented ways companies can get into dialog with a great number of potential and current customers and integrate them into value creation at great scale. But even if consumers know what they want, they are often not capable to express their ideas and requirements of a customized product in a way that their input can be utilized by the producer. What is missing is an approach that enables customers to contribute to product specification procedures in an easy and fast way. The toolkit approach, suggested by <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> von Hippel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="19" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>] , could fill in this gap. This paper applies the toolkit approach in the field of mobile phone games. The mobile phone industry is a perfect case to study user interaction toolkits. The industries’ members need to enhance call-services by data services to utilize the heavy investments in new generation networks. The next generation of handheld mobile devices will be equipped with Java technology enabling users to run a high number of different applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="20" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>] . Nevertheless, the ability to customize and create applications is reserved to experts with sophisticated programming skills - a hardly conquerable barrier for those of us not being “natural born programmers”. The user interaction toolkit introduced in this article helps to overcome this obstacle and to resolve the user limitations in realizing their ideas and visions. The basic principles and functionalities of toolkits are translated into a technical software concept to facilitate online customer interactions. As an internet based application running on a community platform for online gaming, the toolkit provides a user-friendly graphical interface tailored to the creation of new games on a desktop computer. The paper theoretically explores the feasible range of customer integration tasks that customers are capable and willing to handle. Furthermore, potential sources of benefits for users and suppliers based on the user interaction toolkit will be proposed. They will be deployed as a foundation for a diversified business model in the mobile gaming industry. The paper concludes with an outlook on future empirical work and on potential applications in other industries.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="2">1)</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="16" page="1" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="17" page="1" column="2">1</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18" page="2" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="22" page="2" column="1">2. Customer Integration for Co-Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="2" column="1">Customer integration into value creating activities has become widely appreciated by companies in many different branches of industry. Virtual customer integration over the internet is seen as an effective and cost efficient mechanism in the consumer goods field. Two prominent strategies are relevant for our concept: mass customization [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="23" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] and user innovation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="24" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>] . In the mass customization concept, goods and services are to meet individual customer’s needs produced with near mass production efficiency. This preposition means that individualized or personalized goods can be provided without the high surpluses connected traditionally with (craft) customization. User innovation is a concept that integrates consumers in early value chain stages of product innovation and development. Whereas in mass customization consumers create personalized product variants, here consumers are supposed to partly develop new products concepts by themselves or co-develop it with the innovating company by participating in the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> innovation process. By letting customers partly take over product development tasks, producers can benefit directly from the innovativeness, experience and profound knowledge of users. The economic ratio behind customer integration is the following: To specify a product according to individual customer wishes, need-related information and product design capability must be brought together – virtually or physically at a single locus. To the product designer, the identification of users needs is a necessary undertaking, which however, is constrained by some costs of acquiring the relevant information. Product designers will soon face the problem that customers locally hold a significant, but rather sticky portion of information required for product design. Von Hippel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="26" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>] defines “sticky information” as “the information that is costly to acquire, transfer, and use in a new location.” The degree of stickiness is defined as the incremental expenditure for transferring a certain unit of information to a specified locus in a form that is useable to the information seeker. When cost is low information stickiness is low, when cost is high stickiness is high. High information stickiness may be due to the attributes of information itself, such as the way information is encoded. Alternatively, it can be due to attributes of information seekers and providers. For example, a particular information seeker may be less able in acquiring information because of a lack of certain tools or complementary information. The customer integration approach suggests that customers have to be provided with sufficient “solution related information”. It has to be made “unsticky” by producers, in order to let customers express their needs and wishes in a usable format and fulfil product design task themselves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="27" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>] . The main part of the interaction with the customer takes place during the configuration and design of a customer specific product. Therefore, it seems appropriate to call the customer a co-designer. Customer co-design describes a process that allows customers to express their product requirements and carry out product realization processes by mapping the requirements into the physical product domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="28" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>] . The product design process should be repartitioned into subtasks. Subtasks that largely require sticky “need- related” information are assigned to customers so that costly information shifts can be reduced. Customers with superior capabilities for product design tasks are called “lead users” – customers that : (1) face needs that will be general in a marketplace – but face them months or years before the bulk of that marketplace encounters them and (2) are positioned to benefit significantly by obtaining a solution to those needs. In rare cases, customers even take over the role of being the product designer entirely, if the “need-information”<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> can be converted into a final solution or prototype directly at the locus of the customer. Customer co-design is the underlying principle and source of competitive advantage for both mass customization and user innovation strategies. However, co-design can also lead to a complex, risky and uncertain buying situation counterbalancing the benefits of customer integration from the customers’ perspective. The result is “mass confusion” (Pine in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="33" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>] ) instead of creative variety. Customers can be overwhelmed by the number of choices and the degrees of freedom during product co-design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="34" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] . Large assortments and choice are often negatively perceived by consumers. Instead of unleashing creativity, they seem monumental and frustrating. The burden of choice may simply lead to information overload, resulting from the limitations of the human capacity to process information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="35" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>] . As a result the co- design process may last too long, and customers may experience an increasing uncertainty or frustration in fulfilling co-design tasks. These uncertainties and the cognitive effort vary with the degree of customer integration and the underlying task complexity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="36" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] . At a low degree of customer integration, a larger customer segment is able to choose from a pre-defined set of variants to reveal preferences for a mass customizable product. At a high degree of customer integration, probably a smaller fraction of highly sophisticated customers, the “lead user” segment, is able to perform more innovative tasks which could actually lead to entire new product concepts. Uncertainties and cognitive effort can be interpreted as additional transaction costs which reduce the expected value for the customer from being integrated as a co- designer. The degree of customer integration and the corresponding co-design tasks has to meet not only producers’, but also consumers’ expectations to receive valuable outcome from the interaction. One can look at the relation between the customer and a supplier as a cooperation providing benefits for both sides, but demanding inputs from both sides, too. The expected value from interaction largely determines customers’ motivation to perform tasks within the process stage he is integrated. Task complexity as a major influence can erode consumers’ expected value and deter them from contributing to the joint value creation. The “costs” of complexity faced during the co-design process varies for each individual customer depending on the customer’s expertise with the product [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="37" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>] . Especially in consumer markets the “average” customer may often not have sufficient knowledge for the definition of a product specification, which corresponds to their needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="38" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] . Depending on the assigned role and the complexity of the delegated task, customers with<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> different levels of expertise and motivation have to be integrated. It is most important for customer integration to ensure that the customer’s expenditure is kept as low as possible, while the benefit she experiences has to be clearly perceptible. The use of dedicated tools to handle and reduce the co-design complexity is a major success factor.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="30" page="2" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="31" page="2" column="2">2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="3" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="41" page="3" column="2">3. Ways to Overcome the Confusion and Motivation Problem</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="42" page="3" column="2">3.1 User Interaction Toolkits</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" page="3" column="2">Interaction systems for customer integration are the primary instrument to reduce costs by shifting certain design tasks from the locus of the manufacturer to the locus of the customer, who can apply their need-related information directly without costly transfers to the producer. Known as configurators, choice boards, design systems, toolkits, or co-design-platforms, these systems provide customers with sufficient “manufacturing related information” and guide the user through the co-design process of expressing their needs and wishes in a usable format [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="43" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>] . In these systems different product variants and design options are represented, visualized, assessed and priced in a learning-by-doing process for the user. To address these interaction systems, the term “configurator” or “configuration system” is quoted rather often in literature. Often, configurators provide users with a mere arithmetic algorithm to combine modular components. They just allow customers to choose from different options (color, size, etc.) and to select their personally favored variant from a variety of possibilities. Hence, configurators are used to partly individualize products like cars and computers – a good example is Dell Computers. In such systems, the degree of creativity to develop new solutions besides the predefined configurations is rather limited. But interaction systems as “user interaction toolkit” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="44" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>] can do more than this. The toolkit approach recognizes that interaction systems are not limited to a technical software concept, in fact they do not even have to be based on software, and that their scope of application can be much broader. As opposed to configuratiors as low-end toolkits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="45" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] , high-end toolkits offer a theoretically unlimited solution space within the production capabilities of the manufacturer. They enable creative new solutions to old problems as well as the detection (and solution) of new problems. Thus their outcome can be new functions and even completely new products. The user actually creates (and not only chooses).<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> In order to fulfil requirements postulated by von Hippel and Katz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="50" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>] , an effective toolkit must provide the following characteristics: • User-friendly operation: the user finds his way intuitively. The tool is clearly structured. • Libraries: basic functionality, that allows for a simple and efficient creation of new products. Users fall back on ready-made routines and designs, so that they do not have to start always from scratch. • „Trial and Error“ functionality: the participants can improve their product by playing around with them through test runs on the computer. They learn to better evaluate the design while going through several iterations. • Solution Space: there exists a predefined solution space, in which the user can become creative, to ensure that the programme is executable. Co-designers are most likely willing to pay more for their own creation than for a standard solution, even the work is done by them. It is important to note that if the co-design process itself is perceived as entertaining due to the toolkit providing a positive flow experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="51" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>] , it can be considered as part of the product purchased. This would add to the value of the obtained customized product and increase the overall perceived value of customer interaction. Therefore, a positive design experience can increase motivation and positively stimulate the customers to make the effort. However, existence of a user interaction toolkit does not automatically solve the complexity and motivation problems associated with the co-design process. Empirical research shows that despite of good process logic customers often still feel uncomfortable with the co-design task and experience high risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="52" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] .</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="47" page="3" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="48" page="3" column="2">3</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49" page="4" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="54" page="4" column="1">3.2 Communities of Toolkit Users</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="4" column="1">In terms of market research knowledge generating processes within a community provide a wide range of customer information as a backbone for personalized recommendations. Personalization in general is about automatically filtering information for an individual customer by using sufficient information base of user customer profiles. While in traditional (electronic) shopping environments customers are skeptical about the benefit of revealing personal information and often fear misuse, they are usually more willing to share and accept such information in an online community. Trust in recommendations is usually higher when the recommendations stem from peers. If direct interaction among community members leads to actual relationships, the social environment created in the community could also strengthen customer <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> relationships with the company and increase customer loyalty and repurchases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="56" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] . Besides for marketing purposes, communities can also gather knowledge that serves as input for innovation and product development. Virtual communities are a perfect source where lead users can be identified. In virtual communities, these lead users can serve as trend scouts to catch future developments or as product testers. As shown in the literature, early examples of communities of lead users offer a large potential for new successful innovations due to the members strong interest and in depth knowledge communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="57" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="58" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. Following the general opinion that co-designing a customized product is almost exclusively connected to “individuality”, customer integration could be reduced to the interaction between a firm and one customer. However, people appreciate personal recommendations in transactions and search for confirmation from others. Valuable recommendations stem from people we trust. This holds most likely or even especially true for the case of co-design toolkits offering high variety and many degrees of freedom, given the possible lack of competence and motivation as barriers to co-design from the customer perspective described above. Customization is often motivated by the requirements or constraints of a group rather than that of a single person. Aesthetic design is often influenced by peers and the taste of a community rather than by the taste of a single person. It is in many cases not their own “individual taste” which customers are seeking but often a special design which is likely to appeal to peers. Breaking down the barriers among toolkit users could also open several possibilities for reducing the uncertainty associated with the co-design process. User communities may generate knowledge about possible customized solutions as well as about the design process and the use of the toolkit itself; as observed for computer games [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="59" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>] . Users may mutually support each other in finding a solution which fits best to their needs. Before we illustrate the case of a community based toolkit for mobile phone games with its potential for a diversified business model, we extend the line of thought to the open source software development to further identify possible success factors for the toolkit approach.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="61" page="4" column="2">3.3 Towards Open Innovation in Value Webs</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="4" column="2">Offering communities of users the possibility to interact and collaborate on a toolkit basis in order to co-create new products or solutions proved to be a very successful development strategy for open source software development. We will not repeat the numerous academic contributions on the economics of <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> open source software development, but concentrate on one very specific aspects of open source software: Open source software development corresponds to customer integration to the largest possible extent. In the special case of open source software, the final product with all its customized variants emerges merely from user-to-user interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="66" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>] . The value being created by the peer contributors is the common pool of source code that comprises the final software product with all its currently available customized variants. However, this value web would not be working and existing without the toolkit as interface between all peers. In the following, we will use the term “open innovation” to describe a concept of innovation building on (some of) the principles of open source development. Chesbrough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="67" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>] opposes this traditional innovation system with a “logic of open innovation”. Open innovation in his understanding draws on technologies from networks (value webs) of universities, start-ups, suppliers, and even competitors. However, open innovation in our understanding goes one important step further: Open innovation aims at transferring the ideas and approaches from open source software development to the domain of other product categories and services. The idea is to build and operate platforms where (communities of) customers and users create, develop, and discuss newly customized products and services. This concept could also help to bring the toolkit and the community approach together. Very often collaboration is not existent or considered by community operators. However, user community platforms around toolkits might especially encourage the support of co-design through collaborative interaction among users. The basic idea is that users interact indirectly to contribute to a continuously growing information pool dynamically accumulating customer contributions. But users’ contributions for initial set-up configurations can also be exchanged directly among other users. A customizable product and its solution space is complex because of usually many features and much more possible combinations of this features in product variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="68" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>] . Using the toolkit, users can produce digital prototypes of their customization and could add it to a pool of customized product variants. These sample prototypes can describe the solution space of a customizable product. Gathered in a searchable information pool they can serve other customers as guidance for their own co-design. Digital prototypes can be developed and diffused by customers themselves via a toolkit at virtually no cost. Analogous to the open source idea, users can build upon other user’s contributions or collaborate with other users.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> But why should users be willing to contribute to a common information pool? It bears the risk of underinvestment because each user faces the free rider problem or public externality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="70" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] . Lessons learned from open source show, that users are motivated to participate in programming efforts and to contribute to the open source code as a public good, because they can directly benefit from a customized product variant, but also due to factors of intrinsic motivation as well as peer recognition and reputation they can gain in the community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="71" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="72" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>] . Even if peer recognition and community reputation can not be converted to cash like in a professional setting of open source programmers, it can be enjoyed for the sake of an “ego boo”. If these social momentums can be induced in the toolkit community, the membership could be considered as part of the product purchased and consumed. This should increase the expected value customers and hence willingness-to-pay and/ or customers’ motivation to contribute to the common information pool. We believe that such “toolkits for open innovation” around PC and mobile phone games present another predestined source for user innovations and creative potential.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="63" page="4" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="64" page="4" column="2">4</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="5" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="74" page="5" column="2">4. Usertool Game Creator –Technical Case</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" page="5" column="2">4.1 Game Creation Process</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="5" column="2">The Usertool Game Creator combines approaches of mass customization and user driven innovation to help users to develop their most preferred mobile phone games. According to their needs and expertise, users can decide among a set of interactive tasks and features ranging from restricted selections for customization to nearly unrestricted innovative tasks. In a guided configuration and selection process, the user is provided with libraries of existing modules of game figures that he can choose from. The parameters of the chosen gaming mode can be customized to the desired level of the users’ gaming skills as well. In a creative process with many degrees of freedom, users can draw their own game figures to determine new characteristics in terms of shape, colour and movements. The Usertool Game Creator’s graphical user interface is easily accessible through the internet and splits the game creation process in four stages each integrated in a separate web page ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). The first stage allows users to select a game mode (e.g. Jump’n’Run, Puzzle and many others). Following this, the users can design individual components (heroes, enemies and goodies) for their personalized game. For this, consumers can use the ComponentCreator, a tool for image editing.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The next step would be the configuration of the game, which allows the user to select the desired components by browsing the libraries and to specify various game properties like name, keys, lives and speed. In the last stage of the creation process the server builds a jar file and an applet. The former can be transferred to a mobile device. The latter enables the user to immediately play the game, in order to improve the game’s configuration in a trial and error process before transferring it to a mobile device.<marker type="block"/> As Usertool Game Creator is designed for users without any programming skills, the creation process is kept simple. The user does not even have to write one line of code. This approach appeals to a broad range of users, but runs the risk of alienating game developers who prefer to write code. To avoid this loss of competence, the basic Java classes for each game mode are open source and can be improved or upgraded by skilled programmers using the java programming mode. The implementation of entire new game modes is also encouraged.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="78" page="5" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="79" page="5" column="2">5</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="80" page="6" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rb.page_006.image_01.png" thmb="62rb.page_006.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="83" page="6" column="1">Figure 1. Four Stages of the Usertool Game Creation Process</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="85" page="6" column="1">4.2 System Modules</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="6" column="1">The Component Creator The presentation and logic of the system is a mixture of client-side and server-side technology. The pages for mode selection and configuration are servlets, whereas the ComponentCreator is an applet. The latter is the most complex of these three modules and provides the user with a drawing board and many other features, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>. The drawing board is fixed in size to maintain the web layout. It shows a grid with each cell representing one pixel on a handheld display. The scale of the grid is adjustable by the user to allow for a component size on the handheld display ranging from 10x15 pixel to 40x60 pixel. To give the user an impression of the proportions, a preview box visualizes the appearance of the component on a handheld display. For drawing the components, the user is provided with a selection of standard instruments: pin, rubber, line, rectangle and oval. To specify the created component, the user can set a type (hero, enemy or goody), a name, a category and a move.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Besides creating and saving their own components, users can also search for and build upon existing components in the library. These two functions for saving and searching components in the library are implemented as servlets which are called by the applet. As applets and servlets are written in Java, it is possible to use Java objects to efficiently exchange data via http post. A component is saved as a PNG image and as serialized color array on the server’s hard disk, while the attributes of a component (name, category, user etc.) are stored in a MySQL database. The servlet receives all data from the applet, except for the PNG image. This image is created by the server with the Java Advanced Imaging (JAI) Module using the transferred color array as data source. The size of the PNG image may differ from the size of the color array, because blank or unused pixel rows and columns are cut out to minimize the consumed hard disk space. Both files are stored in a specified folder, using the unique component-id as filename.<marker type="block"/> User Community The Community is needed for the Usertool Game Creator to animate users to create value themselves. The basic idea is that all users contribute to a continuously growing library of components, games and even game modes to enhance the overall utility of the toolkit. The Usertool Game Creator is dynamically accumulating its content depending on the number of customer contributions. Using the toolkit is therefore not just a simple customer-supplier-interaction, because contributions are not left anonymous. The toolkit offers a broad range of features for a fruitful interaction of users<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> among each other. Every user has access to the games created by others to test, download and play them. The component library can be accessed at two different stages of the game creation process. Firstly, users can integrate existing components in their personal game by browsing the library with the configuration servlet. Secondly, users can load existing components in the Component Creator to get impressions for their own component or to modify them. Thus consumers can take up, enhance or just comment contributions by others analogous to the open source idea. To enhance the open source idea, users can not only build upon other user’s contributions but also jointly develop a game with other users in the graphical user interface mode as well as in the java programming mode. Besides the core library, the web page contains community features like a “best of”-list to rank games and users as well as a forum to discuss issues related to gaming and support for the basic product.<marker type="block"/> Game Configuration and Testing The game configuration is supported by a servlet, which allows the user to specify a name, the components taking part in the game, the keys used and many other attributes depending on game mode. The user has to bear in mind the necessity of creating a fair and playable game by setting sensible values for the number of enemies or goodies as well as the amount of lives and game speed. As personalization service at the beginning of a new creator session based on collaborative filtering, the users are offered components recently created by them or by customers they recently interacted with. Instead of passing this information as attribute/parameter, the servlet checks the timestamps in the component library to retrieve the information. The servlet also allows for browsing the component library and selecting components created by other users for their personalized games. After all configuration properties are submitted correctly, the system generates a config file and a jar file. The entities of the jar file are the basic Java classes depending on the game mode, the PNG images of components specified by the user, the config file as well as the jar’s manifest. The config file, a comma separated plaintext file, contains all the configuration properties set by the user and is parsed by the game at runtime. The jar’s manifest also has to be generated, because the game’s name as used by the mobile device is stored there. Furthermore, the game’s name and its creator are stored in the database. In order to give users a convenient impression of what they just created, the system also builds an applet, which can be tested immediately on the desktop computer. This proves to be an important feature, as the game configuration cannot be changed on a mobile<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> device. It also facilitates a trial and error process, so that the user can improve the configuration of the game before transferring it to the mobile device. The creation of this applet is similar to the building process of the jar file for the mobile device.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rb.page_006.image_02.png" thmb="62rb.page_006.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="89" page="6" column="2">Figure 2. The Component Creator with Drawing Board and Component Library</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="92" page="6" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="93" page="6" column="2">6</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94" page="7" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="98" page="7" column="2">5. Usertool Game Creator –Business Case</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="99" page="7" column="2">5.1 Towards a Diversified Business Model in Value Webs</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" page="7" column="2">A business model is (1) an architecture for products, services, and information flows, including a description of the various business actors and their roles, (2) a description of the potential benefits for business actors and their roles, and (3) a description of the sources of revenue. Timmers [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="100" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] characterizes the virtual community as a business model in electronic markets, stating that “the ultimate value of virtual communities [comes] from the members (customers or partners) who add their information”. The first communities of interest provided a structured platform for persistent communication and interaction. However, the strong social momentum could not be economically exploited by the community operator. Virtual communities can only be managed to that extend, that they are turned in a socioeconomic business model by adapting the technological architecture for interaction to the social structure of the community. The shift from communities as sociological phenomena to communities as socioeconomic business models is facilitated by the increasing role of technology in supporting interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="101" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>] . In the socioeconomic business model, libraries, search engines, recommendation systems and the proposed toolkits are services that could be used by communities to structure conversation, make it persistent and rich in content. This kind of technology supported interaction probably does not entirely meet the need for social relations, but it has the distinct advantage of scaling and of not requiring users to be highly motivated or to make a significant contribution. Two different economic interests in virtual communities can be distinguished. The virtual community as a stand-alone business model that finances itself through advertising revenues, membership fees and commerce revenues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="102" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] is an electronic environment solely for community activities. The virtual community as add-on in a diversified business model like content or commerce platforms is widely used in order to integrate customers for feedback and loyalty and can also provide additional revenues through advertising. Though the stand-online business model for communities for sure is no vein of<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> gold, transforming communities into other business models can work. Looking at the sub models of a business model, primarily content, brand, entertainment and commerce sites can integrate communities into their revenue model by gaining additional advertising or commerce revenues through the excess of traffic generated through a virtual community. But also immaterial compensations like consumer stickiness, consumer-created content and customer information as well as influencing customers can be attained through virtual communities. The customer relationship model as part of a business model shows the logic how to reach, serve and maintain customers. A business model needs to answer the question how these values can be turned into additional revenues or cost savings. The creation of economic value in this business model results from the content and knowledge the participants bring into the community [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="107" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] . The members of a community contribute to the creation of economic value with information, product reviews, and recommendations. The contributions of an average peer customer in a toolkit based community might not be comparable to the intellectual performance of open source developers, but due to the toolkit these contributions are certainly of greater sophistication than the average text based contributions in common online communities. This could imply that the “pride of ownership” is an important source of motivation that generates additional “traffic” in online communities. Strategic potential of toolkits as component of a business model has already been described. They have the potential to (further) exploit mature markets through mass customization and user driven innovation. To pursue the economic interest of selling self- or co-designed products, the toolkit and a user community appear to be promising add-on services in a diversified business model.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="104" page="7" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="105" page="7" column="2">7</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="106" page="8" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="109" page="8" column="1">5.2 Potential Benefits for Users and Suppliers</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" page="8" column="1">Mobile phone providers and producers of cell phones can derive five types of benefits from offering a toolkit for open innovation for the user-driven creation of mobile phone games. First, it allows fulfilling specific customer needs to a higher degree at basically the same marginal costs as providing standardized games, which are close to zero for digital goods like mobile phone games. This refers not only to the product itself, but also to social benefits of individualization (i.e., the demonstration of individuality) and psychological benefits of being the creator of the product (‘pride of authorship‘) [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="110" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] . Second, the toolkit for open innovation may not only be supportive to better meet customer needs, but also<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> may be an attractive product feature itself. Buyers of self-designed games might find the use of the toolkit entertaining. On the other hand more sophisticated users with more creativity or even programming skills might enjoy more complex development tasks. Furthermore, very active users who support the reciprocal exchange of gaming components very frequently and intensively can earn reputation for being a “good” community member or a even a talented game designer and programmer – this is in imported aspect to enhance the motivation for user contributions and the enjoyment of the user interaction toolkit itself. Third, toolkits for open innovation can serve as a powerful marketing tool. To conduct market research they can gather customer profiles that can be used to generate personalized recommendations or be exploited through complementary commerce. Toolkits can be used as customer relationship management tools as well to establish a virtual dialog with enthusiastic mobile phone users, increasing loyalty in terms of higher customer purchase, retention rates and an increased visit frequency. Forth, the presented toolkit approach can serve as a perfect source of information to generate innovations. A benefit in this manner is the identification of lead users. Even lead users with extensive java programming skills might be drawn to the toolkit community and identified through sophisticated contributions. Especially for mobile applications, programmers are needed desperately [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="112" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] . Very sophisticated user contributions might be a valuable source of ideas for the provider themselves. Contributions that probably extend and develop new gaming modes by programming in Java can result in innovative new product concepts for the mobile phone game provider. Fifth, the creative user contributions might not only be of interest to the provider, but can also be valuable for other users. User communities around toolkits can facilitate automatically filtered personalized recommendations of default configurations. From a large set of possibilities, customer specific recommendations are selected. By presenting only personalized default configurations and options being identified as relevant from a customer’s profile, the complexity and burden of choice can be reduced heavily during the configuration process and the co- design process can be shortened, streamlined and focused on providing real customer value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="113" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>] . Instead of starting to combine the core product from scratch with hundreds or millions of options, customers could start with a recommended configuration that fits her needs. User contributions can be gathered in an information pool containing self-customized prototypes together with trusted comments of other users. Deploying this<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> information pool as a “Participatory Electronic Product Catalogue (PEP)” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="118" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>] , it can be searched for inspirations for own creations (indirect information exchange). Users can benefit from existing contributions by using them as guideline for their own idea generation or even build upon other users’ contributions. The libraries of existing user contributions improve the utility derived by users from the toolkit, because users can narrow down the feasible solution space to specify their own needs and come to an own solution more quickly. Along with general product support, users might benefit from the community driven library of existing components to exploit the full benefit of high degrees of variety and freedom. Furthermore, user community platforms enable direct information exchange among users to support each other during the use of the co-design toolkit or even allow for collaborative co-design between several users, jointly developing a solution for one particular user or all members of the group.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="115" page="8" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="116" page="8" column="2">8</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="117" page="9" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="120" page="9" column="1">5.3 Sources of Revenue</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" page="9" column="1">Among the benefits mentioned above, there are some that do not have to remain immaterial, but actually have the potential to be a source of direct revenue. The downloaded mobile phone games as core products are probably to be the main source of revenue. Supposedly, they should offer the potential of customers’ higher willingness-to-pay compared to standard games. The game download could have a fixed priced per game or charged as a data service with a price per data volume. When looking at the classic concept of the community as a stand-alone business model without an underlying product, in which people get into contact with new and old friends on neutral ground, it can be shown that economic success is often lacking. However, subscriber fees, advertising, e- commerce as main revenue sources of these communities also apply to a product related communities for self-customized mobile phone games. Advertising revenues through banners or sponsoring account for the biggest share of revenues of most virtual communities. In the case of mobile phone games, important Telco players like network providers, mobile phone manufacturers or game industry players should be major sponsors, if not operators of the presented business. The introduction of membership fees in traditional virtual community often fails. In contrast to the real world where people pay to have a beer in a bar just to talk with some friends, users of online communities are not willing to pay just to have a nice chat in cyberspace. This problem does not only affect virtual communities, content sites that implement paid content <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> strategies also face this problem. To gain revenues through membership fees, operators must provide an added value to their constituents. Added value services around the core product of mobile phone games would be the basic toolkit with various levels of collaborative interactions with community members. With the basic toolkit being for free, increasing membership fees could apply to different interaction levels: i.e. (1) access to the library; (2) personalized default configurations; (3) direct communication with other users and (4) collaborative co-design. E-commerce revenues can be gained in two different ways. Virtual communities have the opportunity to sell merchandise like mobile phone cases and other accessories. On the other hand there is revenue sharing on sales made on commerce sites that are initialized (usually by banner click-through) by community sites. Revenue sharing could materialize with complementary products such as mobile phone contracts or devices.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="123" page="9" column="2">6. Conclusions and Outlook</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="9" column="2">This paper investigates the applicability of user- friendly toolkits to create customized Java based mobile phone games. The presented technical solution provides users with the opportunity to customize and develop game components via a graphical user interface. In contrast to well known open source software development, no programming expertise is required. In line with the open source concept, but as an extending feature to the toolkit approach, the presented solution is embedded in an online community. Thus, contributions by customers can be stored in a library leading to a continuously growing information pool of available components. Games and components can be passed on easily between customers, facilitating the adoption of other users’ contributions as well as collaborative development between users. The community enables users to exchange and jointly develop actual product prototypes. In this regard, the presented approach will be the foundation of a ‘value web’ in a unique manner: a value web in between consumers and users. Certainly, this analysis lacks empirical evidence yet. The potential benefits have been derived theoretically and integrated into a diversified business model. By the time this paper was written, the software development project was nearly finished and the toolkit one step away from being online. We are confident to run the system in a quasi experimental or real commercial setting that allows for unbiased empirical observations. Each benefit stated above has to be verified by empirical analysis. Beyond observations <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> how the system will be utilized by customers, personal data about the users’ motivation, experience and knowledge relevant for our research will be gathered in an online survey. Whether all or just a few potential benefits actually materialize depends after all on the consumer acceptance and behavior. In this empirical regard, we state the basic hypothesis: the basic requirement for toolkit success and acceptance by customers relies on a central issue that task complexity corresponds with consumers’ expertise and motivations. In general, toolkits have to be designed in a way that consequently takes this into account. Online communities seem to be the most powerful solution, to strengthen customers’ capabilities and enthusiasm.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="125" page="9" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="126" page="9" column="2">9</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="127" page="10" column="1">Proceedings of the 37th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences - 2004</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="129" page="10" column="1">7. References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="10" column="1">[1] Alba, J W.; J. W. Hutchinson (1987), “Dimensions of Consumer Expertise,” Journal of Consumer Research 13(March), 411-454.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="10" column="1">[2] Arrow, K.J. (1962), ‘Economic Welfare and the Allocation of Resources For Invention’ in Nelson, R. (ed.), The Rate and Direction of Inventive Activity: Economic and Social Factors, Princeton, N.J., p. 609-625.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="10" column="1">[3] Bauer, H.H., Grether, M., Leach, M. ‘Building Customer Relations over the Internet’, Industrial Marketing Management, Special Issue on Internet Based Business-to-Business Marketing, Jg. 31 (2002), Band , S. 155-163.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="10" column="1">[4] Bessen, James: Open Source Software: Free Provision of Complex Public Goods. Working Paper Version 5/01, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="10" column="1">[5] Bettman, J.R., E.J. Johnson,J.W. Payne (1990), ‘A Componential Analysis of Cognitive Effort in Choice’, Organizational Behavior &amp; Human Decision Processes, 45(1), 111-140.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="10" column="1">[6] Chesbrough, H (2003), ‘Open innovation: the new imperative for creating and profiting from technology’, Harvard Business School Press: Boston.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" page="10" column="1">[7] Du, X. and Tseng, M.M. (1999), ‘Characterizing Customer Value for Product Customization’ ,Proceedings of the 1999 ASME Design Engineering Technical Conference, Las Vegas.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="10" column="1">[8] Franke, N.; Piller, F. (2002), ‘Key Research Issues in User Interaction with Configuration Toolkits in a Mass Customization System’, International Journal of Technology Management (IJTM), 26, 578-599.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="10" column="1">[9] Franke, N.; Schreier, M. (2002), ‘Entrepreneurial Opportunities with Toolkits for User Innovation and Design’, The International Journal on New Media Management, Vol. 4, No. 4, pp. 225-234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="10" column="1">[10]Franke, N. and Shah, S. (2002), ‘How Communities Support Innovative Activities: An Exploration of Assistance and Sharing Among End-Users’, Research Policy (forthcoming).</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="10" column="1">[11] Hars, A. and Ou, S. (2002), ‘Working for free? Motivations for participating in open-source projects’, International Journal of Electronic Commerce 6, 25-39.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="10" column="1">[12] Hertel, G., Niedner, S.; Herrmann, S. (2003); ‘ Motivation of software developers in open source projects: An internet-based survey of contributors to the Linux kernel’, Research Policy, forthcoming.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="10" column="1">[13] Huffman, C.; Kahn, B. (1998) ‘Variety for Sale: Mass Customization or Mass Confusion’, Journal of Retailing, Vol. 74, pp. 491-513.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="10" column="1">[14] Jeppesen, L.B. (2002), ‘Making Consumer Knowledge Available and Useful - The Case of the Computer Games’, DRUID Working Paper No 01-10, 2nd version, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.druid.dk/wp/pdf_files/01-10.pdf" id="143">http://www.druid.dk/wp/pdf_files/01-10.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2003-05- 14).</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="10" column="2">[15] Kiely, D. (2001) ‘Wanted: Programmers for Handheld Devices’, Computer, May 2001, pp. 12-14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="10" column="2">[16] Lawton, G. (2002) ‘Moving Java into Mobile Phones’, Computer, June 2002, pp. 17-20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="10" column="2">[17] Lechner, U. and Hummel, J. (2002), ‘Business Models and System Architectures of Virtual Communities: From Sociological Phenomenon to Peer-to-Peer Architectures’, International Journal of Electronic Commerce, Spring 2002, Vol. 6, No. 3, pp. 41-53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="10" column="2">[18] Lüthje, C. (2002), ‘Characteristics of Innovating Users in a Consumer Goods Field’, Technovation, forthcoming.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="10" column="2">[19] Maes, P. (1994), ‘Agents that Reduce Work and Information Overload’, Communications of the ACM’, Vol. 37, No. 7, pp. 31-40, 146.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="10" column="2">[20] Novak, T.P., Hoffman, D.L.,; Yung, Y.F. (2000), ’Measuring the Customer Experience in Online Environments: A Structural Modeling Approach’, Marketing Science, Winter, 19(1), 22-44</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" page="10" column="2">[21] Piller, F. T. (2001), ‘Mass Customization’, 2nd ed., Gabler: Wiesbaden.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="10" column="2">[22] Schubert P. (2000), ‘The Participatory Electronic Product Catalog: Supporting Customer Collaboration in E-Commerce Applications’, In: Electronic Markets Journal, Vol. 10, No. 4.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="10" column="2">[23] Teresko, J. (1994), ‘Mass Customization or Mass Confusion’, Industry Week’, Vol. 243, No. 12 pp. 45-48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="10" column="2">[24] Timmers, P. (1998), ’Business Models for Electronic Markets’, Electronic Markets, Vol. 8, No. 2, pp. 3-8.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="10" column="2">[25] Von Hippel, E. (1998), ‘Economics of product development by users: the impact of „sticky“ local information’, Management Science, 44, 629-644.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="10" column="2">[26] Von Hippel, E. (2001),‘User Toolkits for Innovation’, The Journal of Product Innovation Management Vol. 18, pp. 247- 257.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="10" column="2">[27] Von Hippel, E. and Katz, R. (2002), ’Shifting Innovation to Users via Toolkits’, Management Science, Vol. 48, 821-833.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="158" page="10" column="2">0-7695-2056-1/04 $17.00 (C) 2004 IEEE</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="159" page="10" column="2">10</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
