<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>10720da669fdcb3ebeca34485483fc5c1de781bcc9c72811b4507cf7562ead33</job>
    <base_name>62jb</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/9783034611398.127</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Creating Interdisciplinary Hypotheses: How the Discipline of Design Benefits from Abductive Reasoning, Simplexity and Emergent Behavior</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">CHRISTOPH MERDES M</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible">MHMK Macromedia University for Media and Communication 80339 Munich, Germany <email id="3">christoph.merdes@mhmk.de</email> January 2012</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">Abstract</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6">Within the field of design, complexity emerges due to the nature of design as a practice, a science, a meta-science and a system. The cross-disciplinary behavior of design is in need for a methodology to deal with complexity and to reduce complexity. Complex systems can only be observed by modeling the attributes of the system and the context of the environment the systems are located. The following investigation shows an attempt of abductive reasoning, simplexity and emergence to investigate existing knowledge and build a hypothesis how models from different fields can be compared and synthesized to reduce complexity and encourage innovation.</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="3" column="1">Table of contents</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">1     Introduction ............................................................................................................... 1     2     Models as way to deal with complexity ................................................................... 8     3     Creating hypotheses through the synthesis of models ......................................... 12     4     Conclusion ................................................................................................................ 17    </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="9" page="4" column="1">List of figures</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">    </h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="4" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>: Molecule of H2O ............................................................................................... 3     <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>: Customer Journey Map .................................................................................... 12     <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>: Heatmap ........................................................................................................... 13     <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>: Actions as events in time and place ................................................................. 14 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>: Amount of actions ........................................................................................... 14 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>: Actions as colored tiles in place and time ....................................................... 15 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>: A heatmap in quantitative figures .................................................................... 15 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>: Connecting the hot spots on a heatmap ........................................................... 16                                        </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="20" page="5" column="1">1 Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="5" column="1">Frequently – if not always – acting in the field of design implies dealing with complexity. A designer as a practitioner of a multidisciplinary approach has to face different levels of involvement with his environment. Design as such can be seen as a practice, a science and a meta-science with its own "research methods, methodology [...], philosophy, philosophy of science, and related issues in the metanarrative thought which a research field takes shape" ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Friedman 2003</xref>). This was not always the case and design has often be referred to as art (Schneider 2005, 195, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Selle 1997</xref>, 8, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Mareis 2011</xref>, 26) or in the case of the Design Methods Movement as an attempt to locate design in the field of science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Archer 1965</xref>, 58, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Bayazit 2004</xref>, 19, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Dorst 2006</xref>, 4, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Mareis 2011</xref>, 46-49). Cross (2001, 55) states that "Following Schön and others, many researchers in the design world have realized that design practice does indeed have its own strong and appropriate intellectual culture, and that we must avoid swamping our design research with different cultures imported either from the sciences or the arts."<marker type="block"/> Today, one aspect of complexity in the field of design is based on the fact that a designer has to be aware of other cultures related to design but at the same time contributes to his own field of activity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Simon (1996)</xref> used the term "science of the artificial" to focus on the act of creation by men and to a scientific context. From his point of view, a science operating in the field of the artificial is the fundamental base for understanding and therefore creating knowledge in the field of how new and artificial things are made of and brought into reality. For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Schön (1991)</xref>, science in the field of design is about to investigate how practitioners generate knowledge while acting and how knowledge can be generated while observing how practitioners work. Distinguishing between a theoretical framework and a practical approach to knowledge generation is crucial to communicate the knowledge process in design.<marker type="block"/> The creation of the artificial – the designers practice – is in fact a hybrid. Creating artificiality implies to create something what is considered to be new or not existing prior to the act of creating. For the object of creation itself, resources and knowledge, manifested in material and immaterial nature are applied which are considered to exist. The process of creation shifts existing resources and knowledge to a not existing configuration or modification. The created object as well as the process of creation form a unity which is now existing or has been existing for a limited amount of time and 1<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> therefore can be analyzed in a scientific way to explicate the used and produced knowledge. To build upon the explicated knowledge, reproduction is commonly seen as a way to read knowledge and repeat the formerly not existing way of re-configuration and modification of existing material and immaterial resources. As soon as the artificiality becomes part of our environment, it can be seen as resource or knowledge to be introduced in the circle of creating artificiality of a non-existing type.<marker type="block"/> Dealing with complex systems as mixture of non-explicated, semi-explicated and explicated knowledge of material and immaterial nature implies a deeper understanding of how complexity is defined. In general, Weaver (1948) discovered two kinds of complexity: ordered complexity and disordered complexity. Drawing a distinction between them is not always possible. Disordered complexity can be of the nature of ordered complexity, but the way of observing the characteristics of a complex system can obfuscate the intrinsic nature of a system. Ordered complexity in turn can be of the nature of disordered complexity when you look at other dimensions or parts of a system. For example, the chemical formula of water can clearly be expressed in letters as H20. The molecule of water contains one atom of oxygen and two atoms of hydrogen. If you look deeper, an atom consists of a core and a cloud of electrons surrounding the core. But the velocity of electrons orbiting around the core is so fast, that formulas can only predict the region or orbital where an electron is located (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Mulliken 1967</xref>). It cannot be defined as a precise location.<marker type="block"/> Systems describing the atoms as letters and molecules as combination of letters can build up a hierarchical order of complexity. One single letter defines the smallest element in the system. Behind that single letter, disordered complexity in terms of un- locatable electrons start. You can now go further and state that the intrinsic nature of a system does not exist and the categorization of a system depends on the way we perceive and classify a system based on our findings. These findings again are based on our methods of observing. Lehmann (2005, 2) relates the fuzziness of describing a system and clarifies the elements and borders of a system to the nature of design. She argues that design itself is no other than a substitute for the nature of a system characterized by a "self- processing, self-distinguishing and self-indicating, self- referential form" – an evidence for the practice, the science and the meta-science in Friedmann's sense.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">2</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="7" column="1">For further course of action, complexity should be referred to Simon (1996, 183-184) as a system "...made up of a large number of parts that have many interactions". This view on ordered complexity allows communicating about systems with the help of a communication system. Disordered complexity can be described by a communication system through elements of ordered nature. As soon as disordered complexity is being translated into a communication system, the description – not the nature – of disordered complexity becomes of ordered complexity. With this description, we can define an atom, a molecule and even a complete DNA – a macromolecule consisting of thousands of molecules.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="39" page="7" column="1">O H H</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="40" page="7" column="1">Figure 1: Molecule of H2O.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Going back to Lehmann (and in context to Luhmann), observing a system includes an observer, which is also part of a system. Therefore, Simon's view on artificiality and Weavers categorization of complexity need to be observed by an observing system. A designer in this case is representing the observing system. As stated before, designers – and men in general – can never be considered without their environment in which they are living.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="7" column="1">Schönwandt (1999, 28) describes a model according to Uexküll (1973, 158) considering the different levels of involvement and interaction with the environment. He investigates the functionality of men within the scope of planning. Planning, on the one hand refers to conceptualize artificiality. On the other hand, planning has to deal with complexity in the sense of analyzing and understanding the environment. Uexküll illustrates four worlds that are interrelated to each other:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">3</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">• The world of memorizing (Merkwelt), which is based on the perception of our senses. • The world of thinking (Denkwelt), which performs impulses for steering living creatures. • The world of action (Wirkwelt), which deals with the impact on the environment. • The surrounding world (Mitwelt), which outlines the observations and manipulations within the environment.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="8" column="1">The four worlds, comparable to Maturana's and Varela's model of autopoiesis ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Maturana 1982</xref>), help to draw a distinction between the inner state of a human being and the outer world. Complexity exists in the inner as well as in the outer world. So far, as the investigation into complexity in design revealed, the nature of design is comparable with the nature of a system. As such, complexity in design deals with complexity of artificial, non-existing systems – and with the complexity of every existing system.<marker type="block"/> Dependent from the point of observation, to cope with complexity, and therefore being able to cope with life and the environment, human beings possess the ability to filter sensory impressions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Niekerk and Buhl 2004</xref>, 56). Going back to Uexküll, the characteristics of filtering affect the way of memorizing and thinking (a more comprehensive research related to this fields can be found in biology, neuroscience and perceptual psychology). Filtering implies the skill to abstract, simplify and leave out. In design, this is an essential requirement when dealing with multidisciplinary issues and complexity.<marker type="block"/> Abstraction, simplification and leaving out are, besides the representation of reality, characteristics of a model. Reality and modeling in this sense are related to the autopoietic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Maturana 1982</xref>) way of reification of the sensory impressions that are unique to each human being. A model can be seen as an artificial tool, created by men, to cope with and understand reality. Modeling is essential to science as a tool to represent findings from research activity as well as a tool for design to plan artificiality. Even artists model reality through their projection of thoughts and their use of techniques for representation. Cross (1999, 7) describes the characteristics of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">4</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">knowledge generation as rational and objective in the field of science, reflective and subjective in the field of art and imaginative and practical in the field of design. Every quality of knowledge generation in Cross' sense implies dealing with models. Whether the model is rational as a representation of a molecule, subjective as a sketch or imaginative as the prototype of a machine, it helps dealing with complexity.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="9" column="1">If modeling can be seen as a way to reduce complexity, as a matter of fact, different models made by different people can represent similar realities. Additionally, if similarities are discovered in different models, the models can be combined or clustered. As a third and more abstract way, this implies that different models can form a third model based on a theory for the benefit of synthesis. Pierce (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Burch 2001</xref>) described the last approach as abductive reasoning. For Pierce, abduction, deduction and induction form the logic of scientific exploration. Abduction creates a hypothesis, based on findings that are derived through deduction or induction. Through deduction, conclusion is drawn from the hypothesis. Induction can be compared to experiments to test the scientific validity of the hypothesis.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">The hypothesis for further investigation is based on the assumption that different fields of application will benefit from an abstracted way of modeling in terms of creating opportunities through examination and combination of existing models. Therefore, it has been necessary to show who is modeling (designer, scientists and artists), how models can be derived from reality (through abduction, deduction and induction) and what reality can be like (a complex environment, in which we memorize, think, act and build our own representation of reality based on our way of observing). In terms of complexity, models mediate between the ordered and disordered complexity. They represent a system of elements that enables people to understand reality and build upon the understanding. When dealing with models, the user of a model does not have the need to explore the subject the model is representing in a scientific way. Nevertheless, the user has to be aware that the model abstracts a complex entity. Nowadays, a variety of models exists and intersects with other fields of application. In many cases, the terminology of the models prevents a beneficial synthesis across the different fields. The thought is offered, that through a designerly approach – the multidisciplinary practice of analysis, synthesis, ideation, prototyping and implementation, new models can be derived from existing models and barriers of 5</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="10" column="1">terminology can be circumvented. One way of creating a hypothesis for a new design – abductive reasoning – has been illustrated as part of a scientific approach and even as a model for the scientific approach itself. Another way, creating simplexity, is a more terminological and illustrative way of combining and translating between complexity and simplicity. <marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Kluger (2008)</xref> therefore compares environmental conditions and examples from life to question the obvious nature and levels of complexity and simplicity: "A houseplant, with its micro hydraulics, fine-tuned metabolism and dense schematic of nucleic acids, may be more complex than a manufacturing plant. A modern army, with its thicket of bureaucracy and static encampments, may be simpler than a nimble guerrilla group." Goldsmith (1953, 439), coming from the field of geology, uses the term simplexity to measure structural complexity in crystallization processes. For him, simplexity shows structural simplicity and high entropy (the velocity and movement of atomic particles in space) at the same time. This kind of comparison is another way to shape a model. Through comparison, a common denominator or a set of common denominators has to be defined. The frame of a model constituted by comparison is specified by the amount of comparable sizes. On the other hand, if the frame is defined, existing models can be used to compare against the object of study. This implies that a model is comparable to other models by a reduced amount of comparable sizes in contrast to the situation the model depicts.<marker type="block"/> In the fifth of his ten laws of simplicity, Maeda (2006, 45) states that "simplicity and complexity need each other". His rather philosophical view on design, technology, business and life are observations and personal conclusions about the nature of complexity. For Maeda, a humanistic approach towards complexity is needed, which is constituted by design: "An alternative to the roughness of the "engineering approach" is the more sophisticated "designer approach" to easing the process of understanding. The best designers marry function with form to create intuitive experiences that we understand immediately – no lessons (or cursing) needed." (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Maeda 2006</xref>, 39). To point out that a model as such needs to be understood and adopted by people interacting with the model is essential for the process of developing a model.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">To put the concept of a model in the context of the investigation, the model as such is shown as an approach to cope with complexity. Design, in a systemic way, is 6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="11" column="1">considered as a complex entity in which humans dealing with design are in need for a more simplified complexity. Upon understanding a model, artificiality can be brought into existence and new models can be developed while reflecting the act of creating the artificial. Creating an artificial model – which does not yet exist – can be achieved by abductive reasoning, the comparative concept of simplexity and the adjustment of the model to human needs and preferences. <marker type="block"/> There is a fourth category, which needs to be addressed before the creation of models is explored. Abductive reasoning, simplexity and human centeredness can be planned in the sense of adopting a methodological approach to build a model. Emergence, on the opposite, is a way of changing the level of complexity by the system itself. For <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Johnson (2001)</xref>, "Emergence is the ability of low-level components to self-organize into a higher-level system of sophistication and intelligence. Known by many names – collective phenomenon, bottom-up behavior, self-organization, and decentralization". In analogy to the practical approach of design, the strength of emergence lies in the creation of the artificial by its own means. In design, the recombination of insights, the ideation and the reflection while creating prototypes embeds emergent behavior. Using conscious and unconscious states of mind, the designer is often confronted by the revelations and new meanings of his own creations. This does not represent the nature of emergence as a self-organizing intelligent system, but it shows the fuzzy transition of observation and self-creation. Goldstein (2003, 5) relates emergence to creativity and innovation in the field of design. For him, after John Gero (1992) "... an emergent property in a design is one which was not represented explicitly but shows itself through the discovery of a revised description, or structure." At this point, one can claim that a description or structure not even need to be revised, but to be intentionally created as a version that can be taken into consideration for further development of a design issue. To name one example, the technique of brainstorming within the scope of product development can create multiple approaches to an assignment. For further development of the product, one approach needs to be pursued in detail. Having the other approaches during the brainstorm in mind, the selected approach benefits from emergent behavior in the sense of re-shaping and re-evaluating. The need to create versions of ideas and to make them visible and tangible during the design process is a key to create sophisticated and sustainable design solutions. Such solutions profit from teamwork through the individual perceptions and communication of the individual approaches.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">7</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" page="12" column="1">One can argue that emergent behaviors can be observed – abductive and behaviors of simplexity can be induced. Equally, one can argue that abductive and behaviors of simplexity can be observed – emergent behaviors can be induced. Both views on facts are neither right nor wrong. Going back to the principle of the reflective practitioner from Schön, observing can be done at the same time as inducing suggestions or practicing design. To explore the approach of "inducing the non-existing artificiality" by means of creating a hypothesis of abstracted modeling, the research itself as shown has to be divided into theory, practice and the reflection about both sections. Up to now, coming from a scenario about complexity in design to a general definition of complexity, modeling as a way to understand and reduce complexity and design as a way to create new models based on divergent, abductive, emergent thinking, the scientific stage is set for translating these insights into practice.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">The complexity of systems definition and systems behavior is not nearly covered with the findings so far. Therefore, the research shown in this investigation is a simplified view on the scientific efforts in this field. Nevertheless, the following approach to translate findings into practice embeds the possibility to create artificial knowledge out of the synthesis of the generated knowledge so far. On a higher level, the nature of this investigation itself is a model of what is called reality and can be seen as a designerly approach to prepare for the act of practicing.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="68" page="12" column="1">2 Models as way to deal with complexity</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">To conduct design practice as the basis for reflection, the object of design has to be defined in detail. At a very basic level, to build a model has been considered as a method to cope with and simplify complexity. It has been stated that according to the different perceptions of human beings and the terminology of different fields of applications, a model can embed similar characteristics from a variety of fields. These characteristics are not often explicated in a cross-disciplinary terminology and design has been named as a meta-discipline to translate findings into a beneficial solution for practical applicability. Models do not have to be of physical, tangible nature. A model often exists as a construct in our mind. According to Stachowiak (1973, 131-133), a model consists of the following attributes: 8</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">• Illustration: a model is an illustration of a real or artificial original. A model can also be a model of another model. • Reduction: a model is reduced to the relevant attributes the creator of the model determines. • Pragmatism: a model does not always have a strict relation to an original. The purpose, the timespan and the subject define the application of the model.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" page="13" column="1">In the field of design, a model often serves as a mediator between theory and practice. The designer is able to interact and modify a model while creating and using it. Design theory in the sense of applying knowledge to a distinct field codifies this knowledge in terms of an instruction or blueprint. The instruction then has to be translated into reality. In many cases, a model in design determines a frame that needs to be adapted to a special situation. Framing in this sense means to define a set of attributes of a model that can be substituted with content according to the characteristics of the frame. <marker type="block"/> In design, a model is a unique representation of reality. In contrast to a scientific model, the subject matter of a model in design illustrates the subjective reality of the creator of the model. The distinctive feature of a design approach is to generalize the understanding and communicate the content as a representation of reality. In science, a model serves as a set of characteristics that are considered true as long as they are not proven wrong. Due to this approach, reality can be modeled according to the stated rules up to a certain level. Scientific models do not allow modifying these rules as long as the scientific community agrees to the validity of the modification. This is one of the reasons why the design methods movement failed in the attempt of the scientification of design. A design approach deals with the creation of the artificial where there are not always rules for the ideal solution. To take the chemical formula of H2O as an example again, the scientific representation of the molecule infers that certain chemical reactions can be performed with a predictable outcome. If the outcome is of the predicted nature, the model is proven. In design, a construction plan also represents a set of attributes, but is not able to synthesize the formula for the ideal outcome. Comparing these two models draws a distinction between planning in science and design. Planning in science, e.g. the construction of a molecule can be performed by scientific methods codified in scientific knowledge. Planning in design takes the scientific knowledge into account, but has to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">draw upon the knowledge to create artificiality. Design deals with complex and wicked problems that need a solution but cannot be solved in a way to state that the solution is correct or false (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Rittel and Webber 1973</xref>). Therefore, if a problem can be solved in a scientific way, artificiality as the creation of unproven solutions to the problem is not needed.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="14" column="1">Trying to solve problems can be compared to scientific research. The difference lies in the nature of the outcome. Problem solving can produce a universally valid result, but also a subjective solution to a problem. This implies that a solution not always solves a problem in the sense of providing the correct answer because the problem is or cannot be well defined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Jonas 1993</xref>). For design, dealing with wicked problems and complexity, a solution is an assumption of the modification of future environments and the impact on different systems. The approach of a solution to a wicked problem implies the need for the creation and use of models in design as objects of:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">• Communication to describe systems and behaviors in a simple, comprehensive way. • Analysis to visualize systems and behaviors • Modification for implementing changes. • Projection to illustrate future situations. • Framing to use a model as an outline or instruction to translate existing situations in distinct patterns. • Revelation to identify issues only visible by translation into a model. • Modeling by providing a starting point to create new models. To emphasize the hybrid nature of design between science and practice, simplicity and complexity, existing situations and artificiality, a model is sometimes referred to as method. A method on the one hand is a set of instructions that form a process to create an outcome. A method on the other hand is a model itself by framing the process of creating that outcome with a unique set of rules and instructions. For further investigation, both views on a method will be of importance to deal with complex systems and to question the way of dealing with these systems. A method will be considered as a guideline to a process that is manifested in a model and will produce a model. 10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="15" column="1">As an attempt do deal with complexity, two models from two different fields of application will be taken into consideration to illustrate the process of abduction and simplexity. The models will serve as an already existing body of knowledge and instruction of application for a hypothesis how a combination of these models will benefit from each other. To refer to the investigation about complexity and artificiality in systems, the approach of comparing two existing models and drawing a conclusion upon the synthesis is based on the assumption that each field of application can benefit from the other in terms of cross-disciplinary insights. Therefore, a customer journey map in the field of service design and the model of a heat map in the field of web design are compared. <marker type="block"/> Choosing these two models provides a first evidence of abductive reasoning. There is no distinct rule or guideline to compare models based on certain characteristics. A hypothesis needs to be drawn why a customer journey map and a heatmap might benefit from each other. In this case, the assumption that a colored layer of accumulated data might time-wise visualize the intensity of each action of a customer journey map was taken into consideration when regarding both models. On the contrary, a heatmap in the field of web design might also benefit from the visualization of the touchpoints and the structure of actions in time from the customer journey map.<marker type="block"/> Both assumptions are neither validated nor codified in knowledge. A preconceived notion exists that both models imply a structure that allows translating and comparing certain attributes of each model. The preconceived notion might result from previous applications of the models, acquired knowledge or the perception of the visualization of the models. It seems like a sudden inspiration that stimulates the act of comparison of both models by vaguely implying that there might be a beneficial outcome. To prove that outcome, both models need to be analyzed in detail to identify similarities and comparable characteristics.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">11</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="83" page="16" column="1">3 Creating hypotheses through the synthesis of models</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="16" column="1">According to Stickdorn and Schneider (2010, 158) "A customer journey map provides a vivid but structured visualization of a user's experience. The touchpoints where users interact with the service are often used in order to construct a journey - an engaging story based upon their experience." The main parts of the journey consists of:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">• Actions of the user. • Touchpoints of the user with the service to visualize the service interface, tangible service evidence and the interaction with the service provider. • Text, photos or illustrations to describe and visualize the actions. • A timeline to assign the actions to a certain point of time.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" page="16" column="1">The customer journey map therefore provides a holistic overview to identify problem areas and opportunities as the basis for future innovation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Stickdorn and Schneider 2010</xref>, 159). Insights from an analysis of a service can be allocated to the specific action in the customer journey map to improve the service.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_016.image_01.png" thmb="62jb.page_016.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="89" page="16" column="1">Figure 2: Customer Journey Map.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">"A heatmap is a tiling of a planar region, with each tile colored according to a color scale. [...] Color scales are usually chosen to suggest temperature or other perceptual dimensions." (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Wilkinson 2004</xref>). Heatmaps in the field of web design serve as a visualization of accumulated data of the duration of visitors on a website at a certain area of the website. A heatmap consists of: 12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">• Tiles that indicate the location of an action. Tiles consist of an array of pixels in the case of screen-based media. • Colors that indicate the intensity of an action. • Text, photos or illustrations to describe and visualize the basis for the accumulation of data. • Time or another unit that defines the color of the heatmap. In the case of web design, this might be the amount of clicks or the timespan the user focuses on an element on a website. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Weinstein (2008)</xref>, "For visualization, by far the most popular graphical representation has been the clustered heat map, which compacts large amounts of information into a small space to bring out coherent patterns in the data."</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_017.image_02.png" thmb="62jb.page_017.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="96" page="17" column="1">Figure 3: Heatmap. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Phaydon (2008)</xref>.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="17" column="1">To constitute a basis for the comparison of both models, a set of common denominators has to be defined. This might be able by comparing the elements or the content of a model with each other.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">This might look like the following: Actions are considered to be events in time and place.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_018.image_03.png" thmb="62jb.page_018.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="101" page="18" column="1">Figure 4: Actions as events in time and place.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">An indication of the amount of actions can be shown as a quantitative figure.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_018.image_04.png" thmb="62jb.page_018.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="104" page="18" column="1">Figure 5: Amount of actions.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">These figures can then be translated into colors, taking the range of colors from the visible spectrum of light from violet to red into account. 14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_019.image_05.png" thmb="62jb.page_019.image_05-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="107" page="19" column="1">Figure 6: Actions as colored tiles in place and time.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">This basic approach to compare two models indicates the ability to build a hypothesis upon existing knowledge by decomposing a model to its core components. The reconfiguration of the components was made possible by identifying a common denominator - the amount of actions as data, represented in figures or translated in colors. On the other hand, a heatmap also benefits from the value of a customer journey. The intensity of a heatmap can be represented as quantitative figures.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_019.image_06.png" thmb="62jb.page_019.image_06-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="111" page="19" column="1">Figure 7: A heatmap in quantitative figures. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Phaydon (2008)</xref>.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">The figures can then be arranged in numerical order and be prioritized. Out of the prioritization, a path can be drawn to connect the "hot spots" according to their magnitude.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62jb.page_020.image_07.png" thmb="62jb.page_020.image_07-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="116" page="20" column="1">Figure 8: Connecting the hot spots on a heatmap. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Phaydon (2008)</xref>.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">The path can serve as a customer journey in the field of web design. The area where people click or look at for the most time might set up the starting point of the journey. Subsequent actions of a user can be predicted out of the prioritization conducted in the last step. Again, a very basic approach composed a hypothesis about the behavior of a customer journey in another field of application.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" page="20" column="1">The benefit of translating the two models and their characteristics might result in the ability to show color-coded quantitative figures in a customer journey and a journey upon the data of a heatmap. This extension allows showing additional information in a comprehensible way due to the already existing and proven models. Further steps may be conducted in the general acceptance of the combination of the two models. It is clear, that this approach is shown on a very basic level. In-depth research needs to be done on the applicability, the terminology of the compared attributes or the origins of the knowledge in the different fields to draw conclusions on similar patterns of models early on.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">16</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="120" page="21" column="1">4 Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">In the context of the investigation, the comparison of the two models illustrates the attempt to deal with complexity. By taking existing knowledge and practice into account, a simplification in the form of a reduction to the core values is possible. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Shostack (1982)</xref> speaks in terms of a "molecular approach". The act of taking into account in a cross-disciplinary way is one of the strengths of design - as a science, a practice, a meta-science and even as a system. For Holston (2011, 181), "Much of creative thinking is about changing assumptions and using techniques that fall into the four categories of metaphor, changing perspective, random stimulus, and creating combinations."</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="21" column="1">Abductive reasoning, simplexity or emergent behavior show basic approaches how to think out of the box when dealing with different systems. With the help of a practical example, the comparison and synthesis of a customer journey map and a heat map, the quality of design as a connecting field becomes clear. Design not only delivers knowledge and examples from practice. It is more a mindset and an attitude to investigate the environment, find and create patterns and make these patterns useful, usable and adaptable to others. Only with the openness and willingness to examine different fields of application, design as a discipline will succeed by creating new values out of existing systems. <marker type="block"/> The challenge for the future lies in the basic requirements for the comparison. It is possible to compare every existing model with each other and develop methodologies for comparing attributes and ontologies to classify the findings. But is the effort worth it? Does a designer need a preconceived notion and knowledge which elements are worth a comparison and synthesis? Or does a design approach imply a set of methods to find comparable results? Is the comparison itself beneficial in terms innovation when comparing existing models and draw conclusions about the added value of a synthesis?<marker type="block"/> Many of these questions show the inner nature and therefore the difficulty of what is called design. As a permanently developing field, complex behavior and the attempt to model can be found in the discipline of design itself. Design as a model can be described up to a distinct level of ordered complexity, but a lot of areas and uncovered knowledge is still of disordered nature. Attempts like this investigation into design and 17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">complexity help to advance and define the field by practical research and the reflection upon the generated knowledge. Design might be a system, but it also shows the emergent behavior of a system to shape the nature of its own and other systems.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">18</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="128" page="23" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="129" page="23" column="1">Archer, Bruce. 1965. Systematic Method for Designers. London: Council of Industrial Design.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="23" column="1">Bayazit, Nigan. 2004. “Investigating Design: A Review of Forty Years of Design Research.” Design Issues 20 (1): 16-29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="23" column="1">Burch, Robert. 2001. “Charles Sanders Peirce.” Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/peirce." id="131">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/peirce.</ext-link> Accessed January 13, 2011.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="23" column="1">Cross, Nigel. 1999. “Design Research: A Disciplined Conversation.” Design Issues 15 (2): 5-10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="23" column="1">Cross, Nigel. 2001. Designerly ways of knowing: design discipline versus design science. Design Issues 17 (3): 49-55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="23" column="1">Dorst, Keest. 2006. “Design Problems and Design Paradoxes.” Design Issues 22 (3): 4- 17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" page="23" column="1">Friedman, Ken. 2003. Theory construction in design research: criteria: approaches, and methods. Design Studies 24 (6) (November): 507-522.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="23" column="1">Gero, John S. 1996. “Creativity, emergence and evolution in design.” Knowledge-Based Systems 9 (7): 435–448.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="23" column="1">Goldstein, Jeffrey. 2003. “Emergence, Creativity, and the Logic of Following and Negating.” The Innovation Journal: The Public Sector Innovation Journal 10 (3): 2-10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="23" column="1">Holston, David. 2011. The Strategic Designer. Tools and Techniques for Managing the Design Process. Cincinnatti, Ohio: HOW Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="23" column="1">Johnson, Steven B. 2001. Emergence: The Connected Lives of Ants, Brains, Cities. New York: Scribner.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="23" column="1">Jonas, Wolfgang. 1993. “Design as Problem-Solving?” Design Studies 14 (2): 157-170.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="23" column="1">Kluger, Jeffrey. 2008. Simplexity: Why Simple Things Become Complex (and How</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Complex Things Can Be Made Simple). New York: Hyperion Books.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="23" column="1">19</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="24" column="1">Lehmann, Maren. 2005. Rats in the Maze. In Design System Evolution. Proceedings of the 6th EAD Conference. Bremen.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="24" column="1">Maeda, John. 2006. The Laws of Simplicity. Design Technology Business Life. Cambridge: The MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="24" column="1">Mareis, Claudia. 2011. Design als Wissenskultur. Interferenzen zwischen Design- und Wissensdiskursen seit 1960. Bielefeld: Transcript Verlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="24" column="1">Maturana, Humberto R. 1982. Erkennen: Die Organisation und Verkörperung von Wirklichkeit. Braunschweig: Vieweg.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="24" column="1">Mulliken, Robert S. 1967. "Spectroscopy, Molecular Orbitals, and Chemical Bonding". Science 157 (3784): 13–24.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="24" column="1">Niekerk, Kees van Kooten, and Hans Buhl. 2004. The Significance of Complexity. Approaching a Complex World Through Science, Theology and the Humanities. Burlington: Ashgate Publishing Company.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Phaydon. 2008. “Wohin schauen Sie?”. Accessed January 26. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://initiativemittelstand.files.wordpress.com/2008/12/google-heatmap_blog.jpg." id="151">http://initiativemittelstand.files.wordpress.com/2008/12/google-heatmap_blog.jpg.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="24" column="1">Rittel, Horst W. J., and Melvin M. Webber. 1973. “Dilemmas in a general theory of planning.” Policy Sciences 4 (2): 155-169. Schneider, Beat. 2005. Design. Eine Einführung. Basel: Birkhäuser Verlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="24" column="1">Schön, Donald A. 1991. The Reflective Practitioner. How Professionals Think in Action. Aldershot, United Kingdom: Ashgate Publishing.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schönwandt, Walter. 1999. Grundriss einer Planungstheorie der «dritten Generation». Disp 35 (136/137): 25-35.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="24" column="1">Selle, Gert. 1997. Geschichte des Design in Deutschland. Frankfurt am Main: Campus Verlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="24" column="1">Shostack, G. Lynn. 1982. “How to Design a Service.” Ed. C. A. Congram and M. L.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="24" column="1">Friedman. European Journal of Marketing 16 (1): 49-63. <marker type="block"/> 20</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="25" column="1">Simon, Herbert A. 1996. The Sciences of the Artificial. 3rd ed. Cambridge, London: The MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="25" column="1">Stachowiak, Herbert. 1973. Allgemeine Modelltheorie. Wien: Springer.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="25" column="1">Stickdorn, Marc and Jakob Schneider. 2010. This is service design thinking. Amsterdam: BIS Publishers. Uexküll, Johann J. von. 1973. Theoretische Biologie. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp. Weaver, Warren. 1948. Science and Complexity. American Scientist 36: 536.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="25" column="1">Weinstein, John N. 2008. “A Postgenomic Visual Icon”. Science 319 (5871): 1772– 1773.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="25" column="1">Wilkinson, Leland. 2004. “Heatmaps” Workshop for Multiscale Structures in the Analysis of High-Dimensional Data, University of California, October 25-29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="25" column="1">Wilkinson, Leland and Michael Friendly. 2009. “The History oft he Cluster Heat Map”.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">The American Statistician. 63 (2): 179-184.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="25" column="1">21</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
