<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>cbf3e083373a3b2ea7967c5f8f0e286c7a132ab69f323f2595f643cdde4e91f9</job>
    <base_name>62bg</base_name>
    <doi>10.1145/1460355.1460359</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">ALESSIA RULLO University of Siena</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="3">17</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="4" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Systems Applications]: Interfaces and Presentation]: Applications]: and Society]:</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="5" confidence="possible">This article provides a methodological perspective on the notion of the aesthetics of interaction in ambient computing systems. Aesthetics of interaction is challenged by the design proposal for the soft qualities of interaction, which is used as a tool to complement existing design methodologies. The perspective presented is based on work conducted in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit at Siena Hospital in Italy, as a part of the EU PalCom project. The early outcomes provide a heuristic account which questions the design process by fostering the novel complexity of ambient technologies in delicate and fragile settings. Categories and Subject Descriptors: H.4.0 [Information General; H.5.2 [Information User Interfaces—User-centered design; theory and methods; evaluation/methodology; J.3 [Computer Life and Medical Sciences— Health; K.4.1 [Computer Public Policy Issues—Computer-related health issues General Terms: Design, Human Factors, Theory Additional Key Words and Phrases: Aesthetics of interaction, soft qualities, neonatal care, noninvasive and nonintrusive monitoring</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="6" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Reference Format:</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Rullo, A. 2008. The soft qualities of interaction. ACM Trans. Comput.-Hum. Interact. 15, 4, Article 17 (November 2008), 25 pages. DOI = 10.1145/1460355.1460359 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/" id="8">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/</ext-link> 1460355.1460359</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11" page="1" column="1">The life of a human technological system entails a complex whole of variables, which determine not just how we use such instruments (i.e., functionally), but also how we make sense of them and how their presence in our lives manifests itself. Recent research in the HCI and interaction design field would suggest that the design space should be reconceived to allow for the introduction not only of functional variables that affect and determine our interaction with systems and tools, but also of the emotional variables that can be triggered by the</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">This research was supported by the PalCom Project. Author’s address: A. Rullo, Communication Science Department, University of Siena, Via Roma, 56 53100 Siena, Italy; email: <email id="12">rullo@media.unisi.it</email>. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or direct commercial advantage and that copies show this notice on the first page or initial screen of a display along with the full citation. Copyrights for components of this work owned by others than ACM must be honored. Abstracting with credit is permitted. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, to redistribute to lists, or to use any component of this work in other works requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. Permissions may be requested from Publications Dept., ACM, Inc., 2 Penn Plaza, Suite 701, New York, NY 10121-0701 USA, fax +1 (212) 869-0481, or <email id="13">permissions@acm.org</email>. C 2008 ACM 1073-0516/2008/11-ART17 $5.00 DOI 10.1145/1460355.1460359 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/" id="14">http://doi.acm.org/</ext-link> 10.1145/1460355.1460359</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="16" page="1" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="17" page="2" column="1">17:2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18" page="2" column="1">•</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="19" page="2" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" page="2" column="1">aesthetic values of the designed solutions [Djajadiningrat et al. 2002, 2000; Norman 2004; Petersen 2004]. Design methodologies can be seen as similar to evolutionary objects, which constantly change to adapt to the emerging needs of designing human-technology interaction. The user’s needs form a complex of expectations, previous usage experiences, and emotional variables that should be integrated into the system design. It is indeed fundamental to embody the variations in usage expectations, and experiences that are established among individuals throughout their interactions with the tools and the environment. This work adopts the notion of aesthetics of interaction in order to investigate these issues. In many senses, the perspective of the aesthetics of interaction can be considered as a means of facilitating the way in which computation is manifested in a system’s design, and overcoming some of the traditional problems of ubiquitous, ambient, and pervasive computing which cause computation to become invisible, with subsequent loss of control on the part of the user [Petersen 2004; Tolmie et al. 2002; Weiser 1993, 1991; Weiser and Seely Brown 1996]. This idea of invisibility in use has been interpreted in many ways, with the objective of exploring how computation can manifest itself and, when necessary, become perceptible to the user. According to Weiser’s interpretation of the concept, “invisible” means that individuals can become so familiar with the use of certain technologies that they don’t have to think about the fact that they are interacting with them. Technologies are readily available, and people can focus on the task with which they are involved without concentrating on their interaction with the mediating device. In reality, this idea of invisibility did not result in concrete and useful outcomes regarding the way in which people may interact with these kinds of technologies, and this notion of invisibility has primarily been translated into an idea of proactive computing that makes decisions on behalf of the users [Rogers 2006]. This tendency is also reflected methodological approaches toward the design of ubiquitous and ambient systems. As Höök [2006] explains, in the contemporary practice of software development, less time-consuming design strategies are adopted. For instance, the “proactive” computing stance as- sumed in the research fields of ubiquitous computing, affective computing, and intelligent environments significantly reduces users to mere information, pro- cessing units that can be modeled and understood, thus permitting the system to act on their behalf [Höök 2006]. This approach can have successful results if the situation at hand occurs within a context that is limited enough to be modeled in the entirety of its details and consequences. However, due to the inherent complexity of the lives of human-technology systems, in the major- ity of cases this approach dramatically oversimplifies human interaction and affects, among other things, the inspection mechanism and the management of the system breakdown. Therefore, one of the primary issues in contemporary design practice is that of understanding the role of users in the design of human-technology systems which should continuously adapt to design contexts and to emerging design demands. According to this perspective, as Rogers clearly points out [2006], ubiquitous computing, or UbiComp, research should begin to target rethinking the <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> meaning of computational invisibility. To quote Rogers herself, the design of ubiquitous and ambient technologies should “shift from proactive computing to proactive people” [Rogers 2006, p. 406] and find new modalities to engage user experiences. This concept of design demand leads to further reflection on design methodologies and tools. In fact, in order to engage users in interaction with ubiquitous and ambient technologies, new strategies for participation in the design process should be considered, aiming at understanding how the role of the user can evolve during the design process, how the user can participate and express her needs, and which tools can be adopted in order to capture ever-more complex and multifaceted user requirements. This methodological demand raises additional issues as to how to interpret and design for specific qualities of computational material that influence user interactions and engagement. In the domain of ubiquitous and ambient applications, computational technology appears as a new type of design material with its expressional necessities. Computational materials present an inherent complexity, since computation occurs according to simultaneous and abstract processes which function on a logical level, and it is difficult for inexpert users to determine what is happening and on what level. In addition, computation is immaterial; in fact, many computational processes and resource management tasks occur outside of the user’s perceptual range, and are thus unnoticeable [PalCom Deliverable 2008]. Specific features characterize the expressional level of computation, for instance, the temporal dimension and therefore the possibility of expression throughout time [Halln as  ̈ and Redström 2002]. These characteristics delineate certain qualities that can affect and shape use [Landin 2005] by defining the expressional level of interaction. Aesthetics of interaction can, according to this perspective, be intended as one of the components of the idea of computational expressiveness. Petersen [2004] proposes that the aesthetics of interaction can be adopted as a design strategy to make computation remarkable:<marker type="block"/> According to this view, aesthetics represents the modality by which interaction can be playful and engaging, allowing exploration of novel ways in which computation can become visible and noticeable, opening the design space for the users’ emergent behaviors. Stemming from this position and in keeping with Rogers’s proposal of designing UbiComp technologies to engage user experiences, in this work, aesthetics is considered an immanent quality of our experience with interactive systems that emerges as an interactive process and that may influence our attitude toward the situation or activity at hand. Thus, the notion of the aesthetics of interaction is herein defined as a process of appropriation and engagement with technologies based on interpretation of the experiential and subjective variables that interplay throughout<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> the interaction. The possibilities for interaction can manifest themselves by balancing the different qualities that affect ambient computing systems. This work therefore aims at addressing the role of the aesthetics of interaction in ambient computing systems, with the ultimate objective of understanding how it can reflect on design methodologies so as to achieve a twofold intent: (1) reflecting on the significance of user participation in the design process; and (2) trying to find new strategies to allow emergence and to codify existing needs as well as the novel demands of a specific design context in an appropriate design format. These considerations gain a particular significance when examining application domains that present a particular, systematic fragility; the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit is a specific example.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21" page="2" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="22" page="3" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23" page="3" column="1">•</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24" page="3" column="1">17:3</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="26" page="3" column="1">Aesthetic interaction is not about conveying meaning and direction through uniform models; it is about triggering imagination, it is thought provoking and encourages people to think differently about interactive systems, what they do and how they might be used differently to serve differentiated goals [Petersen et al. 2004, p. 271].</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="28" page="3" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="29" page="4" column="1">17:4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="30" page="4" column="1">•</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="31" page="4" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_004.image_01.png" thmb="62bg.page_004.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="33" page="4" column="1">Fig. 1. The Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Siena Hospital, Italy.</caption>
      </region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="4" column="1">2. THE NEONATAL INTENSIVE CARE UNIT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="4" column="1">The Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) presents a particular, systematic fragility; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>. The premature birth or occurrence of problems after childbirth is a dramatic event, often unexpected, that amplifies the sense of separation normally associated with the delivery experience. Care of premature newborns is a composite process, involving the use of complex machineries and collaboration among different persons with varying skills and backgrounds, different objectives, and different expectations (i.e., neonatal doctors, nurses, therapists, and families) [Marti and Rullo 2006; Grönvall et al. 2005]. Admissions to the NICU generally happen under emergency situations related to problems occurring during delivery, or during the pregnancy if the infant’s or mother’s health status becomes critical. Premature newborns usually require complex medications, umbilical tubes, and intubations. In particular, the incubator appears to be the main ap- paratus that medical staff can configure to adapt temperature, oxygen, and humidity, depending on the baby’s condition. The system is characterized by a high level of reconfigurability, since each incubator should be conceived as an ad hoc entity which is tailored to the baby’s conditions and that changes dynamically over time. The Neonatal Intensive Care Unit environment should be able to support the coexistence of these diverse necessities and afford an easy reconfiguration as these necessities change. The work practice is based on continuously combining and integrating data ar- riving from different sources. According to this perspective, what is crucial is the way in which people make sense of what it is going on and how a continuous<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> process of understanding is supported and correlations are created. This aspect is fundamental for the medical personnel, as it permits prompt intervention on the baby’s behalf when necessary, but also for families, in order to assist them in psychologically enduring such a delicate situation and to allow them to play an active role in the childcare, offering as much as possible their presence and affective support [Westrup 2005]. Ambient computing solutions designed for this setting could raise several issues that would affect both the functional and subjective experience of work in this environment and influence the life of the overall system.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="38" page="4" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="39" page="5" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="40" page="5" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="5" column="1">17:5</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="5" column="1">3. THE METHODOLOGICAL PERSPECTIVE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="5" column="1">Aesthetics within healthcare settings has proven to be key, capable of influenc- ing medical treatment and the overall care of patients. Recent progress made in the treatment of neonatal pathologies has significantly increased life expectancy after a premature birth or a birth with com- plications. However, the greatest successes in the medical field have led to a serious paradox: While the possibility of survival for these children is continually increasing, it is not yet possible to stabilize their environmental and relational conditions [Symington and Pinelli 2003; Sizun and Westrup 2004]. The aesthetic characteristics of the environment can facilitate autoregulative behaviors in the newborn. A variety of interventions can be adopted in order to control environmental stressors known to cause physiological and behavioral disorganization in newborns, for example, light and sound, scheduling of care- giving, integration of parents, specific supportive behavioral techniques such as non-nutritive sucking, opportunities for grasping, swaddling, general motor containment, and kangaroo care [Als 1982; Als et al. 1986]. Assuming, therefore, that aesthetics has an important function in this application domain, how can the aesthetic elements be extracted and subsequently rendered applicable to the design? How do they relate to other variables of the design process? Indeed, any attempt to concretely incorporate the aesthetic concerns of a design into a sharable approach has scarcely been investigated, and aesthetics has been traditionally delegated to specific design sensibilities. One exception to this rule is exhibited in the work of Djajadiningrat et al. [2000]. These scholars suggest that the aesthetics of interaction must consider the richness of appearance, the actions and the role of a design, thus moving be- yond the mere idea of usability. This perspective demands new methods for the comprehension of design possibilities. Moreover, as Djajadiningrat et al. [2000] discuss, it is important that the latent needs of existing practices become manifest to designers, so that they may later be incorporated into the requirements and design solutions.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="5" column="1">3.1 The Soft Approach to Design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="5" column="1">The assumption of the proposed work is that when designing for ambient computing applications, the design space should be opened in order to consider more variables, not only functional ones but also emotional, experiential, and aesthetic. <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> In this sense, the nature of the requirements to be considered should be extended to include what in traditional architecture has been called “soft qual- ities” in the Design Primario movement [Branzi 1986] or “Quality Without a Name” as proposed by Alexander [1979, 1977]. In both of these cases the design demand is that of externalizing those features that define aesthetics and that create the sense of wholeness that may characterize our relationship with certain environments. As Alexander [1979] also points out, defining these qualities is quite complicated, since they are generated by those variables of the design that somehow escape the consideration of designers interested in purely functional aspects. According to Alexander, one of the distinguishing aspects of the quality without a name is that of enabling those conditions for which one town or one building is “lived” and perceived as “alive”: Things which are living may be lifeless; nonliving things may be alive. . . . Beethoven’s last quartets are alive; so are the wave[s] at the ocean shore; so is a candle flame; a tiger may be alive, because more in tune with its own inner forces, than a man [Alexander 1979, p. 29]. But life cannot be created on purpose; rather, it is the result of a process of appropriation. This process can also be supported by the precise physical con- figurations of the space, by the specific design choice, which Alexander calls the pattern language. The life of a space can also evolve from the occurrence of patterns of events that allows each place to develop a precise character and have its own life.<marker type="block"/> Compare for instance, two ways of including water in a building. Suppose, on the one hand, that there is a concrete reflecting pool outside your room—with no purpose except to reflect the sky. And suppose, on the other hand, that there is a stream outside your room with small rowing boat on it, where you can go, to row, to lie on the water, struggle against the stream . . . [Alexander, 1979, p. 65]. Of course, the row boat makes the most difference to the structure, since it alters the entire experience of the building. Similarly, the life of our house or our town is not given directly by its geometry, ornament, or plan, but by the qualities of the events and situations we encounter there. This implies that the qualities put into place are not only fixed properties of the physical object, but are subjective values built throughout interaction. In a more recent book, Branzi [2004] provides an additional interpretation of the application of soft qualities in the design of products and everyday objects. This is the idea of “blistering.”<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> surrounds a delicate part of it, and separates it from an excess of contacts and consumptions [Branzi, 2004, trasl.]. In Branzi’s view, the concept of blistering refers to a specific quality of soft design. The possibility of enabling different simultaneous levels of visibility can create a protective environment and allow novel interactions based on a new interpretative basis. 1 In this work, the soft qualities of interactions offer an additional dimension to the design space and they act in two different ways. On the one hand, they are analytical tools that attempt to isolate specific elements of the interaction, which are related more to the way in which people construct meaning (the expressional level of interaction) than to the way in which people do things (the functional level of interaction). On the other hand, soft qualities are inspirational instruments that enlighten the design space with a focus on these latent values of the interaction, which often escape design techniques [Rullo 2008]. In this light, these qualities may complement design methodologies by allowing interpretion of the experiential values that emerge in the interaction and effecting the expressional level at which computation can be manifested. Indeed, it is the author’s conviction that the role of these aspects is indispens- able to the design of ambient computing systems, in which interaction does not take place only according to the one-on-one relationship between human and device; it is also distributed within the setting and throughout settings, per- vading everyday objects, and enabling new relationships which arise from the environmental and relational conditions enabled. From this perspective, it can also be useful to refer to the use, in the interaction design field, of the notion of “place,” intended as an entity which embodies the experiences and aspira- tions of people. This approach looks at the way in which the physical world is constantly lived, modified, and experienced by people, and investigates those design strategies that can allow a “nonplace” to become a space [Coyne and Stewart 2007] that people can appropriate through interactions. This notion of place is adopted as a key variable in understanding the dynamic relationship between human behavior and the surroundings as they are shaped at personal, social, cultural, and physical levels [Ciolfi and Bannon 2007, 2005; Ciolfi 2004]. In keeping with these positions, this work aims at capturing these experiential aspects of human activities, focusing on the qualities that permit people to appropriate, interpret, and create meaning throughout interactions. The concrete enablers of this methodological proposal are the soft qualities of interaction, the soft set of requirements, and the soft prototype as analytical and operative tools that are used to actualize the notion of the aesthetics of interaction in the design practice. The case study presented in this work will exemplify the use of these methodological tools by presenting a design experience taken from the PalCom project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ist-palcom.org/)." id="58">http://www.ist-palcom.org/).</ext-link> The PalCom project explored the challenges of the ambient computing system and proposed a conceptual framework and an open architecture for palpable computing [B uscher  ̈ et al. 2007; Ingstrup and Hansen<marker type="block"/> 1 For a complete review of the “Blister” collection by Andrea Branzi [2004], see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www" id="60">http://www</ext-link>. designgallerymilano.it/blister.html.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> Participatory design sessions with the neonatal team, Siena Hospital (Italy): data sessions, future laboratories, and “bricolage” workshops.<marker type="block"/> 2005]. This case will present the design of palpable technologies for the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit and will illustrate how the methodological tools herein proposed are used to complement the design process, by focusing on particular aspects of the interaction.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="47" page="5" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="48" page="6" column="1">17:6</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49" page="6" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50" page="6" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="53" page="6" column="1">Blisters are that kind of packaging for medicines—pills and lozenges, that preserve their content within the plastic and that must be broken to let each single pill come out before it is swallowed. . . . But blisters are not simply a kind of packaging, I think they are something philosophical; a general protective cover that defends us from the products and the products from us . . . The blister is thus a reciprocal technology, an important environmental presence, a way of looking at the world through an opacity that</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="54" page="6" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="7" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="7" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="57" page="7" column="1">17:7</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="62" page="7" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="63" page="8" column="1">17:8</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="8" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="8" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_008.image_02.png" thmb="62bg.page_008.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="67" page="8" column="1">Fig. 2.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="8" column="1">4. THE FIRST DESIGN PHASE: DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" page="8" column="1">The context of the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit requires a specific design strategy to capture the complexity of the human activity taking place there and to evaluate the feasibility and reliability of the envisaged solutions [Rullo et al. 2006]. Thus, a participatory approach and a high-level strategy for the evaluation have been adopted. Different techniques have been experimented with throughout the design process, which were directly inspired by the participatory design traditions [Schuler and Namioka 1993]; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>. User workshops and activity modeling, data sessions and “bricolage” workshops [Shapiro 1996] have been conducted with the neonatal team. Diaries [Gaver et al. 1999] and ques- tionnaires have been distributed and collected, interviews have been carried out with parents and experts; as well as future laboratories workshops [B uscher  ̈ et al. 2004]. Different usage scenarios have been developed interpreting the user requirements that emerged during fieldwork activities. The outcomes of these activities clarified the basic features of existing technologies (i.e., their physical characteristics), the functional requirements, and some drawbacks. For example, the existing devices are often connected with wires and tubes that can provoke abrasions or irritations if in contact with the baby’s skin. From these activities, many interesting elements emerged to inform the design process. The incubator was reconsidered in order to support the creation of an environment that fully embraces the child, with abilities to sustain its body and to reproduce the kind of stimulation and environmental conditions the child had received in the mother’s uterus, supporting portability of the environment through use of an ad hoc net of sensors, and providing the least intrusive monitoring possible. Furthermore, the medical personnel suggested the possibility of detecting the pressure points of a newborn body from beneath the mattress on which the baby lays. Redesigning the existing mattress with</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="73" page="8" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="74" page="9" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="75" page="9" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="76" page="9" column="1">17:9</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="TI">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="77" page="9" column="1">Table I. Initial Set of Functional Requirements</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">GENERAL Opening system Description: The performance of treatments on the babies, such as intubations and the placing of sensors, currently requires that the incubator be opened, which dramatically effects the micro-environmental conditions inside. It should be possible in- tervene on the baby both without opening the incubator and in such a way that the medical staff is provided with a sufficient degree of comfort in accomplishing their operations. Acoustic pollution - Description: The overall environment (the ward as such) has External noise acoustic pollution that can have a damaging effect and is perceived as harmful for the newborn in the incubator. There is a wish to prevent these noises from reaching the newborn. This is also applicable when the child is undergoing an intervention, (e.g., in today’s case, when the lid of the incubator is open). Acoustic pollution - Description: The modern-day incubator also generates noise Internal noise that disturbs and affects the child in a negative way. To provide just one example of the various types of these noises, current models are powered by an engine that is placed within the incubator, which produces a very high level of sound. The new incubator should seek to limit or completely remove such noises. Internal temperature Description: The child should be kept in a temperature- control controlled environment as much as possible. This temperature should be set and maintained by the staff, even during all kinds of interventions. Today the incubator is opened during some interventions, thus directly changing the protective environment that is normally maintained inside the incubator THE COVER Light control Description: A prematurely born child is extremely sensitive to light and for this reason it is requested that the amount of light inside the incubator be controlled and kept constant, regardless of the brightness of the external light sources. Visibility Description: The staff should be able to visually monitor the child without difficulty or obstruction, even if the light inside the incubator is dimmed. THE BED Soft mattress Description: The mattress on which the baby lies is currently made of a hard plastic material; it is not comfortable and not adaptable to the baby’s body. A soft, more adjustable mattress is requested that supports the interventions and the needs of the child. Tilting mattress Description: To assist the child’s respiration it is necessary that the bed can tilt the child and maintain a position in which the head is higher than the feet and vice versa, until such a time that the child is remanipulated. Fixed body Description: The medical staff would like to be able to keep the position/Prevent big body child in particular positions for some interventions or to keep movements the child in a position that supports its current needs. Flexible body Description: The child, even in a fixed position, should be able movement/Allow small to make small movements. The mattress should support this body movements necessity even if in a predefined position.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="79" page="9" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="80" page="10" column="1">17:10</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="10" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="82" page="10" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_010.image_03.png" thmb="62bg.page_010.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="84" page="10" column="1">Fig. 3. The first 3D model of the incubator prototype.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" page="10" column="1">ambient/palpable technologies appeared a promising solution for detecting the pressure points of the newborn’s body, with the added benefit of combining this data with other parameters of the incubator system. This would be done in order to avoid pressure sores and frequent postural problems, to survey the newborn’s spontaneous respiratory movements, and, in combination with a Webcam, to investigate the infant’s micromovements. These early findings were elaborated into an envisioning process, directly involving the neonatal team and the newborns’ families through interviews. The outcome of this activity led to the definition of the first incubator concept, namely the “water lily.” Indeed, the water lily represents a soft and protective environment composed of a layered structure of petals and smart materials. The list presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="TI" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Table I</xref> illustrates the functional requirements expressed by the users that are exemplified in this early concept with a specific reference to the newborn’s micro-environment and to the mattress features [Rullo 2007]. Taking this list of requirements as a starting point, the main features of the incubator prototype were discussed with the medical staff. On this basis, it was possible to sketch out the initial physical model of the incubator; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>. The incubator in this prototyped version is seen as a portable environment that is conceived as an assembly of devices and functions to be configured on the basis of the baby’s conditions. Within the micro-environment of the incubator, the baby lies on a mattress containing body-pressure sensors that detect the weighted areas of the baby’s body on the mattress surface; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>. In order to avoid pressure sores and similar problems, a fine-grained modular system allows the medical staff to manipulate and change the position of the baby’s body without opening the incubator, thus preserving the micro-environmental conditions inside. This manipulation is allowed by a pin-art type of system whose elements can be moved up and down directly or remotely [Rullo 2007; Rullo et al. 2006]. Different user workshops with the medical personnel at the neonatal ward focused on the evaluation of the first model of an incubator prototype and its associated functionalities. A preliminary assessment of the mattress concept was performed by building a physical mock-up of the mattress, which nurses and physicians used by simulating on a baby doll ordinary operations during future laboratory sessions. One of the main topics of discussion related to the interaction modalities embodied in the mattress design. The main outcomes can be summarized as follows.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> — Manipulation of the Baby Through the Mattress. Medical personnel deemed it very useful to have a trace of the pressure points of the baby’s body on the mattress, in order to simultaneously monitor the baby’s movements and anticipate pressure on high-risk areas, or just to avoid pressure sores. However, the modality of manipulation of the baby through the bed pins must be reconsidered, since the baby should be handled only for therapeutic purposes. The pin-art-like system does not allow exploring the possibility to have direct contact with the baby, nor does it provide the child with the appropriate sensorial stimulation. — Physical Design: The Design for Separation. The mattress itself is still similar to the original model, that is, a layer of hard, plastic material which has been augmented with new functionalities (pressure-point detection and automatic manipulation), but it’s not able to contain the baby’s body. The mediation that the incubator structure provides is still perceived as a separation between the child and the external world.<marker type="block"/> In short, the technological innovation introduced by the first design phase provided new functionalities, but didn’t represent a real added value for the people acting in this setting. These design solutions have also been subjected to an expert evaluation; the prototype and scenarios have been assessed by Professor Westrup, the founder of the NIDCAP approach to the care of premature newborns. NIDCAP stands for the Newborn Individualized Developmental Care and Assessment Program [Westrup 2005], an approach that uses a range of medical and nursing interventions that aim to decrease the stress of preterm neonates in NICUs and to support the creation of care communities around each baby [Symington and Pinelli 2003]. Professors Westrup was asked to evaluate the prototype, both from the NIDCAP’s perspective and while also trying to represent the needs of the newborns, whom obviously could not be directly involved in the design process. Professor Westrup severely criticized this first prototype. In fact, in this design solution he didn’t recognize any manifestation of those environmental qualities that are fundamental to the care of the child (i.e., support of direct contact between child and caregivers in order to enable care actions toward the child and to minimize separation between the newborn and the external environment). In fact, even if the prototype is able to support the child’s well being from a functional perspective (i.e., through maintenance of environmental<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> conditions inside the dome, the filtering of light and sound, and facilitation of medical staff intervention), from an interactive perspective, this prototype is still no better than its predecessor. It still embodies the traditional concept of the incubator space, which does not allow the kind of direct contact between child and care-givers that is necessary in the early development of the child.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="89" page="10" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="90" page="11" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="91" page="11" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92" page="11" column="1">17:11</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_011.image_04.png" thmb="62bg.page_011.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="94" page="11" column="1">Fig. 4. Mattress, the first mock-up, the map of pressure sensors, the pins system, and a future laboratory session.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="97" page="11" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="98" page="12" column="1">17:12</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="99" page="12" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100" page="12" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="102" page="12" column="1">5. SOFT QUALITIES OF INTERACTION AND SOFT REQUIREMENTS: THE SECOND DESIGN PHASE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="12" column="1">The methodological perspective of this work is intended to complement the design process undertaken in the PalCom project. As demonstrated throughout the evaluations undergone in user workshops, discussions of future laboratories at the hospital, and in interviews with the expert, this first incubator prototype was effective in responding to the precise necessities of newborns and of caregivers. In contrast, and particularly in reference to the mattress evaluation mock-up (i.e., the pin-art-like system), the prototype was not able to interpret the more delicate variables present within the setting of the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, such as: (1) the necessity of physical contact between child and care-givers; (2) support for different levels of understanding of the baby’s conditions by diverse individuals of the care community; and (3) the shift of perspective that is necessary to psychologically support the different emotional needs of the people involved. In this regard the central questions are as follows. Can the design of ambient computing systems respond to such a complex whole of variables? What is the role of the aesthetics of interaction?</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="12" column="1">5.1 Map of Remarkable Experiences</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" page="12" column="1">With the aim of outlining the problem, an initial user workshop was conducted with representatives of staff members of the Neonatal Ward at Siena Hospital. This was intended as an explorative workshop aimed at understanding to what extent a deeper comprehension of the aesthetic aspects of the daily experience at the NICU could provide useful information for the mattress redesign. The strategic approach of this part of the work was that of distinguishing certain remarkable experiences at the NICU and, by use of in-depth interviews, trying to determine which elements (functional and aesthetical) were put into place. The user workshop involved three members of the medical staff: two neonatal doctors and one physiotherapist. They were asked to describe experiences related to the following topics: conflicts, participation, surprise, stimulating experiences, upsetting experiences, moving moments, provocation, and reactions. The rationale at the basis of the workshop was that of exploring the whole spec- trum of emotions, from negative to positive experiences, that were felt in this environment, with the aim of understanding the key dynamics that affected these staff members’ attitudes toward their work as these emotions occurred. The data from this preliminary activity is reported in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>. This map exemplifies an attempt to represent various facets of what can be ascribed to the aesthetic experience in this setting, by means of a description<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> of the subjective values associated with the experience. Because the group in question is limited to a very small number of participants, the map of outcomes of the activity is not meant to be exhaustive, nor was the aim to exemplify all of the aspects involved. Rather this figure gives an initial understanding of the subject being analyzed and of the methodological problems with which the group was faced. Indeed, collecting information on these aspects means asking the users to report on dynamics of which they are often not aware. What initially emerges from these data is that the work in the NICU has a very strong impact on the emotional and psychological life of the subjects, affecting their motivations, their involvement, their level of satisfaction, and their frustration. Despite this, the contact between mother and baby, whenever it occurs, represents the main stimulation and focal point of the aesthetic manifestation in this setting. This exchange is at the core of all interactions, from which all the different courses of action can be carried out. In other words, the physical relationship between family and child is the motivating factor behind the organization of various actions that are taken in the NICU environment. The data presented in the “remarkable experiences” map has been compared with the data coming from previous observations at NICU and with the interviews with the families of the newborns. On this basis it was possible to distinguish three levels of analysis: the micro- environment, the macro-environment, and the interactions (see Tables II, III, and IV). These levels have been further elaborated eliciting the soft qualities of interaction.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="107" page="12" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="108" page="13" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109" page="13" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="13" column="1">17:13</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_013.image_05.png" thmb="62bg.page_013.image_05-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="112" page="13" column="1">Fig. 5. Map of remarkable experiences at the NICU.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="114" page="13" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="115" page="14" column="1">17:14</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="116" page="14" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="117" page="14" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx118">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_014.image_06.png" thmb="62bg.page_014.image_06-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="TII">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="119" page="14" column="1">Table II. Micro-Environment: Interferences, Overlapping, Separation and Interpenetration Micro-Environment The interferences are generated at this level by the co- presence of varied and complex environmental stimuli (e.g., the quality of light, noise level, temperature, and air quality). Manifestations of the interference phenomena that occur at the micro-environmental level can be simplified by the creation of overlapping and sepa- rate/interpenetrating phenomena. Overlapping occurs any time that the light, sound, and temperature conditions of the incubator are filtered with the intention of sustaining the baby, which is the pre- dominant strategy that is used to protect the baby from the outside environment. Examples include the use of sheets that cover the transparent glass of the incubator to filter the light inside or the blanket in which the baby is wrapped, which is used to maintain its body temperature. Separation is another consequence resulting from the necessity to preserve the micro- environment of the baby (e.g., the baby is kept separate by the incubator glass; the micro- environment of the baby is separated by the macro-environment of the ward). Separation is the given rule of interaction within this setting, which is enabled by the environment. It is interesting to note that the interpenetration between the external and internal environment of the incubator counters the separation that is typical of interactions within this setting. The fact that the design for separation can actually be surpassed by the exchange between mother and child is also interesting; this factor generates the strongest aesthetic phenomena in this setting.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="120" page="14" column="1">5.2 Soft Qualities of Interaction at the NICU</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="14" column="1">In order to better illustrate the soft qualities of interaction at play at the NICU, two different strategies have been adopted in this work: (1) a comparison between various settings with the aim of finding reoccurring and dissimilar situations, which can be intended as an inspirational activity; and (2) what can be called “aesthetical isolation,” an analytical process by which the soft qualities of interaction in this setting are isolated from the functional aspects. In this article it will not be possible to discuss at length the details of the soft qualities of interaction occurring at the NICU; however, a synopsis will be provided (see Tables II, III, IV). For a complete discussion of these topics, see Rullo [2007]. The occurrence of these interaction qualities is grounded on the diversity of needs and expectations of the different individuals, and is enabled by the nature of the environment and by the behavioral possibilities of the system.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="122" page="14" column="1">5.3 The Soft Set of Requirements</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="14" column="1">Of course, the first incubator prototype cannot be intended as a finished work, but merely as a first attempt to embody some of the design issues; it should be considered in light of subsequent iterative design cycles. Nonetheless, it was decided to begin a parallel and complementary design phase that places a greater focus on some of the soft aspects of the interaction. This is in order to better externalize the latent needs of this application domain and to draw on the richness of the activity outcomes and analysis of the inspiration provided by soft qualities of interaction. <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> This methodological proposal adopts the notion of the soft qualities of interaction as an inspirational/analytical instrument to design for the aesthetics of interaction in ambient computing systems, by better focusing on the latent interaction dynamics taking place. In greater detail, the soft qualities of interaction have been used to re-elaborate and visualize the design concept for the incubator micro-environment, with a focus on the baby’s mattress. In fact, this has emerged through evaluation with the expert, the members of the medical staff at Siena Hospital, and the newborns’ families. It was decided that the mattress artifact should be redesigned as a dynamic layer that protects the child, keeps the baby’s body in place, facilitates the transportation of the newborn, allows detection of the pressure points of the baby’s body, and can enable a more direct and intimate contact between newborns and care-givers. According to this summary, different graphical representations of the vision of the mattress prototype (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>) have been developed that are inspired by the soft qualities of interaction. These various representations are the result of a design workshop involving interaction with graphic designers. This work has been devoted to the transformation of the abstract notion of quality into a design representation that is sharable with the other design-team members, including the stakeholders. The three proposals present explicit design solutions that trigger specific interaction values on the basis of our experience of using these everyday objects or natural elements (i.e., bag, lily flower, and<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> leaf). Their role is that of transforming the soft qualities in “tangible” ways and embodying these qualities in appropriate design metaphors. They are based on our previous experience in order to exemplify the embedded interaction values and to open the design space to emergent usage. Based on this rationale, the natural metaphor of the leaf has been selected to represent in its description some of the soft qualities of interaction, namely: (1) The conditions of access and the separation/interpenetration dynamics are supported, in the idea of the leaf, by the co-existence of a rigid structure (i.e., the leaf ’s stem) and more flexible part (i.e., the leaf itself); this also enhances the novel conception of the newborn’s micro-environment, to be dynamically closed or opened according to necessity. (2) The possibility of manipulating the leaf ’s surface suggests different solutions to manage the interferences and overlapping effects at the micro-environmental level. (3) The transparency of a leaf ’s surface addresses the possibility of having a different layer of visibility in order to reveal or mask the baby’s status, depending on the situation, and to support the varying perceptions of the caregivers, whether parents, nurses, or neonatal doctors. The different graphical representations were then evaluated with the stakeholders at the hospital as well. In this way, specific features of the other proposals have been considered and transformed into specific requirements. These iterative evaluation cycles, both internal to the design team and with the stakeholders at the hospital, aimed at allowing an understanding of how physical aspects of the representation (shape, size, material) could trigger specific interaction values.<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> This engendered a new dialog between the physical, “tangible” dimension of those leaf metaphor and those interactions that would define the usage dimension, stemming from the soft qualities analyzed in this setting. This effort elicited the concrete soft set of requirements. Indeed, some of the soft requirements embody specific soft qualities that were determined during this inspirational and analytical phase, while the others reformulate pre-existing functional requirements. The latter have been enriched in light of the soft qualities of interaction [Rullo 2007].<marker type="block"/> Soft Set of Requirements — Filtering: Different Level of Opacity. Opacity will become a design quality of this environment, acting in two different ways: firstly by creating a light insulation for the child, and then by supporting a smoother and softer view of the child for the families. Soft Quality: interferences; background/foreground effects. — Open/Closed Environment. The incubator environment shall be able to be freely opened or closed to allow direct contact or protection, according to different needs and situations. Soft Quality: background/foreground effects; separation/interpenetration; access. — Perceivable Output. The incubator environment shall make even small traces of the child’s life visible. These will represent an indication of the child’s well being for medical personnel, but will also be a sign that is comprehensible for the parents. Soft Quality: background/foreground effects; different visibilities. — Granularity. The introduction of technology shall be visible at different levels, thus permitting an aggregated view of various data as well as an in-depth view of a particular value, with the primary objective of supporting inspection, revealing functional connections, and integrating information.<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> Soft Quality: background/foreground effects; varying visibilities; interference. Reformulated Functional Requirements — Postural Stabilization/Embracement. The incubator environment shall be considered as a delicate layer which embraces the child, sustains the baby’s body, and preserves the environmental conditions. Soft Quality: overlapping; access. — Layering. The incubator environment shall manage different layers of interaction. The multilayered property of this environment shall allow the end-user configurability and simultaneous courses of action. Soft Quality: layering; access. — Rigid Structure/Foldable Material. The incubator environment shall balance a rigid structure that creates a safe environment during interventions, with a soft and foldable material that can be easily transported and configured. Soft Quality: separation/interpenetration. The soft set of requirements describes features of the mattress prototype that have been informed by the soft qualities of interaction. These features can be defined at two different levels. On the one hand, they define the physical, “tangible” characteristics of the prototype, such as the shape, material, and the functioning system. On the other hand the nature of these requirements defines new interaction modalities by the specific use of sensors and smart material, which are supported by the overall infrastructure of palpable computing. These features also define new ways to render computation visible for the users, “blis- tering” the information when necessary, or revealing it when the conditions change. The proposed soft set of requirements is not considered exhaustive as such; on the contrary, these should complement and reformulate the functional requirements of a setting or a system, based on specific technological innovations and user needs. The result of this activity has been shared in a design workshop among the design-team members and supported by the creation of a soft prototype to test soft requirements with the users at the hospital.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="124" page="14" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="125" page="15" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="126" page="15" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="127" page="15" column="1">17:15</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx128">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_015.image_07.png" thmb="62bg.page_015.image_07-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="TIII">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="129" page="15" column="1">Table III. Macro-Environment: Layering, Foreground/Background Effects, Different Levels of Visibility Micro-Environment The NICU setting enables different levels of visibility of the status of the babies and of the different equipment, depending on the compe- tence of the various individuals involved, the emotional attitude supported in the interaction, and the physical and behavioral design of the system. The background/foreground effect is recurrent in our continuous, everyday experience, but the nature of this setting leads to a particular manifestation of this effect. Within this setting, what remains in the background and what dominates the scene represents a dynamic process that changes as the condition of each baby changes. This effect concerns the intangible conditions of the environment previously discussed: Light, sound, and temperature determine the aesthetic effects that are engendered by shaping the perception of the events taking place in the space. The status of the child, the visual displays, visual feedback, and noise in the ward create a space of redundancy, in which priority is given to the way in which information can emerge from the background and be perceived by the various personnel, both professional and nonprofessional. Each incubator system, intended as the combination of incubator and medical equipment, would enable diverse foregrounds and backgrounds that would be perceived in various ways by the personnel. This process is present in every exchange, but it acquires a particular importance when occurring in an emergency situation, in which everything should be orchestrated in order to optimize the efficacy of the intervention taking place on the child. The coexistence of these different layers reflects on the various levels of interaction present in the ward and the courses of action possible throughout the care of the child. Indeed, this type of layering represents a key quality of design.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="132" page="15" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="133" page="16" column="1">17:16</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="134" page="16" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="135" page="16" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx136">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_016.image_08.png" thmb="62bg.page_016.image_08-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="TIV">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="137" page="16" column="1">Table IV. Relationship: Access, Separation and Interpenetration Relationships The neonatal ward is perceived as an isolated world that is difficult to enter. Separation occurs at different levels: between the incubator and the external environment, between mother and child, and between the different figures (neonatal doctors, nurses, therapists, and families) who act individually in the care process. It is possible to discern a sort of continuum in the passage from separation to interpenetration in different layers of the environment (micro and macro) and in the presence of the various individuals in the ward, primarily between mother and child. Interpenetration is made possible by the nature of the access enabled by the design of the spaces and by the tools that are available. The nature of access may profoundly affect the subsequent interaction with this environment. The incubator in its current conception presents numerous barriers for both the medical staff and the parents, who cannot easily enter the baby’s micro-environment without completely removing the glass that covers the device. This aspect of incubator design not only prevents physical contact between the parents and newborns, but also influences the way in which the incubator can be reconfigured according to emergency situations or for routine procedures. Points of prospect are quite rare at the NICU and nonprofessionals typically feel disoriented by the amount of data and information that must be continually processed, which can result in errors and contradictory behavior. More importantly, the access design demon- strates how the different interaction units (mother-child, child-nurse, child-nurse-neonatal doctor, child-therapists, mothers-child-therapist, mother-child-nurse, mother-child-neonatal- doctor) emerge and can be created around the incubator space.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="139" page="16" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="140" page="17" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="141" page="17" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="142" page="17" column="1">17:17</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_017.image_09.png" thmb="62bg.page_017.image_09-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="144" page="17" column="1">Fig. 6. The different graphical representations of the vision on mattress prototype.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="147" page="17" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="148" page="18" column="1">17:18</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149" page="18" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="150" page="18" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="152" page="18" column="1">6. TOWARD A MATTRESS PROTOTYPE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154" page="18" column="1">The function of the soft prototype of mattress is strategic; indeed, it allows direct exploration of the soft qualities of the mattress by isolating the soft requirements in its design and providing a good balance between the supported functionalities and certain aspects of its look and feel. The specific characteristics of the mattress soft prototype move toward the ideal of embodying the soft requirements in intermediate solutions, to be tested and evaluated with users. In the soft prototype of the mattress, three elements play a critical role in the successful embodiment of soft requirements in such a way that they can be rendered sharable with users: the softness of the adopted material (i.e., a soft rubber foam), the thickness, and the metamorphic possibilities (realized using a matrix of copper threads inside the rubber foam; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="TV" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Table V</xref>). An evaluation undertaken with various users revealed that these elements supported the way</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="155" page="18" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="156" page="19" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="157" page="19" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="158" page="19" column="1">17:19</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx159">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_10.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_10-thumb.png"/>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_11.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="TV">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="160" page="19" column="1">Table V. Mattress First Mock-Up and Mattress Soft Prototype (a comparative analysis based on the results of the evaluation conducted with the neonatal team) Mattress First Prototype Mattress Soft Prototype Functional Soft Requirements Requirements Granularity Opening system Rigid structure/foldable Environmental pollution material Internal temperature Embracement control Open/closed environment Light control Filtering Visibility Soft mattress Tilting mattress Fixed body position/ Prevent big body movements Flexible body movement/ Allow small body movements</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="161" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Prototypes Features Prototype Features</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx162">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_12.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_12-thumb.png"/>
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_13.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_13-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Body pressure sensors that Shape memory material detect the weighted areas Material that preserves the of the baby’s body on the environmental conditions mattress surface. Use of specific sensors Fine-grained modular Integration/assembly of system/pin-art type of sys- different data tem Visibility of data and the Remote manipulation system’s status/placement Map of pressure-loaded of sensors areas Integration/assembly of different data</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="164" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Supported Interaction Supported Interaction</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx165">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_14.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_14-thumb.png"/>
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_019.image_15.png" thmb="62bg.page_019.image_15-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="166" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Supported soft qualities of Interaction</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="167" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Manipulation of the baby Direct contact between through the mattress child and caregivers Remote/Automated Dynamic management of a manipulation of the baby closed/open environment The mattress mediation is Intuitive perception of the perceived as a separation mattress output between the child and the Trace of the baby life external ward Maintenance of environmental conditions inside the incubator Facilitation of the medical staff intervention through bed-pins manipulation</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="168" page="19" column="1">separation/interpenetration background/foreground effects, different visibilities, interferences, access, overlapping</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="169" page="19" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="170" page="20" column="1">17:20</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="171" page="20" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="172" page="20" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_020.image_16.png" thmb="62bg.page_020.image_16-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="174" page="20" column="1">Fig. 7. Experimenting the mattress soft prototype: user workshops at the NICU, Siena Hospital, Italy.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_020.image_17.png" thmb="62bg.page_020.image_17-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="176" page="20" column="1">Fig. 8. The mattress prototype: early trials at the Neonatal Ward, Siena Hospital (November through December 2007).</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" page="20" column="1">in which the medical staff could experiment, with the qualities of the mattress, the possibility of embracing the child and the possibility of configuring the space. Furthermore, the way in which the “foldable” requirement has been represented proves sustainable the ways parents could differently “open” the child’s micro-environment, passing from mediated to direct contact. Another important aspect is related to the envisioned use of sensors in this prototype. In fact, the presence of sensors on the mattress base is made visible to different individuals acting in this setting, which provides interaction cues for both the medical personnel and parents. In this way, the medical staff can be made aware of the functioning of the sensors and of their correct placement with respect to the baby’s postural regulation, whereas the parents can use the visualization of the sensors as an indication of life in the baby, and can inform themselves about the baby conditions by making sense of this information.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="178" page="20" column="1">6.1 Noninvasive and Nonintrusive Environmental Monitoring System</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="186" page="20" column="1">These outcomes led to a further elaboration of the mattress prototype, intended to be evaluated by staff members and families; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="179" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>. The first implementation of the mattress prototype has been conducted in collaboration between the University of Siena and the Bioengineering Department of the Milan Polytechnic Institute (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="180" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>). Indeed, the specialized and reconfigurable properties of the mattress have been acquired through specific use of sensors and smart material, creating a micro-environment around the child that is able to provide a noninvasive and nonintrusive monitoring. A special material has been selected for implementation of the prototype. The mattress prototype has been developed in polyurethane gel with embedded<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="block"/> sensors intended for the recording of temperature, movements, and interface pressures at specific anatomical points. The gel has antidecubitus properties, as it distributes interface pressures throughout a wider surface with respect to standard foams and with isotropic behavior, in this way relieving contact points on the body (for a complete description of the gel features, see www.technogel.it). The gel structure also provides a soft supporting surface that is easily foldable in order to embrace the child, thus covering and protecting the baby’s body while providing postural stabilization and making the perception of the newborn more delicate for the parents. The gel also has a high thermal inertia and thus favors maintenance of body temperature. The pressure and temperature sensors are embedded in a distribution matrix so that they cover the entire area under the body. These permit the measurement and monitoring of pressure, temperature, respiration (indirect measurement from the rhythmic pressure variation over time) and physical movements. The signals are collected through a dedicated DAQ, and a UBS that is connected to and powered by a PC that contains the visualization and setting software. If the PC is a notebook or a PDA, newborn portability is assured with continuous monitoring. 2 A range of preliminary trials have been conducted with the neonatal team at Siena Hospital. These trials provided some indications for the next phase of prototyping. Among other things, the head physician of the neonatal ward suggested that the mattress base be made of modular units with a specific distribution of sensors, in order to be differently composed according to the monitoring necessities of the newborn.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="182" page="20" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="183" page="21" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="184" page="21" column="1">•</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="185" page="21" column="1">17:21</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="187" page="21" column="1">6.2 Future Work</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="188" page="21" column="1">Introducing new technologies in a Neonatal Intensive Care Unit is a long and quite complicated task, and it is therefore necessary to perform a number of different clinical trials before testing the designed solutions with users in a setting that is as realistic as possible. The mattress prototype made of a gel structure augmented with sensors will be further tested with the neonatal team and the families of premature babies at the NICU of Siena Hospital. The study will experiment with use of the mattress prototype in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit; among other objectives it will seek to evaluate how this prototype can engender novel diagnostic possibilities and support the care community (i.e., the neonatal team and the families) by offering novel opportunities for interaction and emergent usage.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="189" page="21" column="1">7. DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="190" page="21" column="1">Design methodology, as Landin [2005] clearly suggests, is one way of elaborating knowledge about the expressional qualities of computational technologies. This can be achieved in two ways: by following an approach by design [Landin 2005; Djajadiningrat et al. 2000] that explores the aesthetics of the intended use [Halln as  ̈ 2004] in design solutions; and by an aesthetical analysis of actual use,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="191" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">2 The mattress prototype is one of the components of the system that reconceives the incubator setup through the notion of palpable assemblies (for a complete discussion, see Rullo [2007] and Gronvall et al. [2007]).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="192" page="21" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="193" page="22" column="1">17:22</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="194" page="22" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="195" page="22" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F9">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bg.page_022.image_18.png" thmb="62bg.page_022.image_18-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="197" page="22" column="1">Fig. 9. The soft approach to design.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="205" page="22" column="1">that poses the delicate issue of transforming analytical knowledge into design knowledge [Landin 2005]. The soft approach presented herein is an attempt to combine an analytical and a design perspective in order to integrate the aesthetics of interaction in the design of ambient computing systems; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9" id="198" class="deo:Reference">Figure 9</xref>. This approach aims at developing new strategies to codify and represent those delicate and fragile situations in which computation should enter the life of complex socio-technical systems. The operative tools by which aesthetics can emerge and can be designed for are described by the soft approach: the analysis and inspiration through the soft qualities of interaction, the elicitation of the soft requirements, and the creation of a soft prototype. From this perspective, aesthetics cannot be intended as a driving force for the design of complex systems where computation is made available in a distributed, networked, embedded way and the soft approach does not represent any consolidated framework; it represents an early reflection on the operative role of the aesthetics of interaction, aiming at raising questions rather than providing conclusions. An initial consideration relates to the role of users throughout the design process. As discussed in the case reported herein, despite their strong participation in all phases of the design process, users are not always able to make explicit the latent, but fundamental, needs that affect their experience in a setting (e.g., as a doctor, parent, or a nurse). This implies that a perspective that is exclusively focused on user involvement does not allow for a complete comprehension and therefore for an effective representation of all of those variables playing a role. Complementary design strategies should be identified to effectively collect people’s composite needs and to transform them into accurate design requirements, in this way experimenting with new modalities for user participation and expression. In this sense, consideration of the soft variables of interaction can revise the design process by introducing an additional point of view on the design space, both in analytical and in design terms. Specifically, this can be achieved<marker type="page" number="23"/><marker type="block"/> by making explicit certain latent aspects of the interaction which are also fundamental to the explanation of the complex dynamics of this setting, by externalizing the knowledge gained throughout the design process, and by using prototypes and different representations to share and evaluate the qualities, requirements, and design solutions. These aspects could lead to concrete advantages, one of which is external to the design process. In particular, making latent variables explicit can anticipate problems occurring in the interaction with the designed system and can help with the process of acceptance when introducing new technological equipment in delicate settings such as the one in consideration. The other advantage is internal to the design process. The work reported in this research mainly demon- strates how the manner by which design process information passes from one phase to another is in reality a decisive factors. Systematic use of different kinds of representation (i.e., the qualities representations, the soft prototype) sustained the design process in order to allow identifying, sharing, and eval- uating the role of soft qualities as they were progressively shaped into design solutions. Of course, further examination of this approach in other application domains will reinforce these early outcomes. In this methodological proposal, the possibility of continuously finding new balance points between two coexisting dimensions (manipulating functional and soft aspects) allows designers to explore the novel implications of their work and users to experience a new awareness of their daily practices. This enhanced awareness allows to give voice to the emotional, psychological, and experiential aspects involved in an interaction that can express specific socio- technical fragility. In this perspective, the mattress prototype, in its evaluation phase, has the potential to modify environmental conditions at the NICU in order to adapt to the baby’s needs and to mediate the relationship between the infant and the different care-givers, including families. In fact, the protocols usually adopted for the care of the premature newborn strongly address the need to re-establish a direct contact between mother and baby by promoting as much as possible the direct care of the mother. The initial results of the preliminary evaluation suggest that the mattress developed through the soft approach could sustain this novel meaning of mediation, which reflects directly on the possibilities for creating contacts, establishing relationships, and supporting collaborations in the care community.<marker type="block"/> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS A sincere acknowledgment goes to V. Barsotti for her important contribution in the leaf design proposal, to the bio-engineering team of the Milan Polytechnic Institute, to the neonatal team of the “Le Scotte” Hospital, and to all my colleagues in the PalCom project. A special thanks goes to the editors and re- viewers of this special issue for their essential input and continuous support.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="200" page="22" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="201" page="23" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="202" page="23" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="203" page="23" column="1">17:23</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="206" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">A LEXANDER , C. 1979. The Timeless Way of Building. Oxford Books, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">A LS , H., L AWHON , G., B ROWN , E., G IBES , R., D UFFY , F. H., M CANULTY , G., AND B LICKMAN , J. G. 1986. Individualized behavioral and environmental care for te very low birth weight preterm infant</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">at high risk for bronchopulmonary dysplasia: Neonatal intensive care unit and developmental outcome. Pediatrics 78, 4, 1123–1132.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">A LS , H. 1982. Toward a synactive theory of development: Promise for the assessment and support of infant individuality. Infant Mental Health J. 3, 4, 229–243.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">B RANZI , A. 2004. Blister. Design Gallery Milano. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.designgallerymilano.it/blister.html." id="215">http://www.designgallerymilano.it/blister.html.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">B RANZI , A. 1986. The Hot House. The MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">B USCHER  ̈ , M., C HRISTENSEN , M., H ANSEN , K. M., M OGENSEN , P., AND S HAPIRO , D. 2007. Bottom-Up, top- down? Connecting software architecture design with use. In Configuring User-Designer Relations: Interdisciplinary Perspectives, M. Hartswood et al., Eds. Springer.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">B USCHER  ̈ , M., M OGENSEN , P., A GGER E RIKSEN , M., AND K RISTENSEN , F. J. 2004. Ways of grounding imagination. In Proceedings of the Participatory Design Conference (PDC). Toronto, Canada, 193–203.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">C IOFLI , L. 2004. Understanding spaces as places: Extending interaction design paradigms. Cog- nition Technol. Work 6, 1.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">C IOFLI , L. AND B ANNON , L. J. 2007. Designing hybrid places: Merging interaction design, ubiquitous technologies and geographies of the museum space. Co-Design (Sept.).</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">C IOFLI , L. AND B ANNON , L. J. 2005. Space, place and the design of technologically enhanced physical environments. In Space, Spatiality and Technology, P. Turner and E. Davenport, Eds. Springer, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">C OYNE , R. AND J AMES , S. 2007. Orienting the future: Design strategies for non-place. In Design for the 21st Century, T. Inns, Ed. Gower Ashgate, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">D JAJADININGRAT , J. P., O VERBEEKE , C. J., AND W ENSVEEN , S. A. G. 2002. But how, Donald, tell us how? In Proceedings of the Symposium for Designing Interactive Systems (DIS) (London). ACM Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">D JAJADININGRAT , J. P., G AVER , W. W., AND F RENS , J. W. 2000. Interaction relabelling and extreme characters: Methods for exploring aesthetic interactions. In Proceedings of the Symposium for Designing Interactive Systems (DIS). ACM Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">G AVER , W., D UNNE , A., AND P ACENTI , E. 1999. Cultural probes. Interact. 6, 1, 21–29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">G R ONVALL  ̈ , E., P ICCINI , L., P OLLINI , A., R ULLO , A., AND A NDREONI , G. 2007. Assemblies of heteroge- neous technologies at the neonatal intensive care unit. In Proceedings of the European Conference on Ambient Intelligence (AmI). Darmstadt, Germany.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">G R ONVALL  ̈ , E., M ARTI , P., P OLLINI , A., R ULLO , A., AND B ERTELESEN , O. 2005. Palpable time for hetero- geneous care communities. In Proceedings of the Critical Computing Conference, O. Bertelesen</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">et al., Eds. ISBN 1-59593-203-8. H ALLN Ä S , L. 2004. Interaction design aesthetics—A position paper. In Aesthetic Approaches to Human-Computer Interaction, O. Bertelsen et al., Eds., in Proceedings of the NordiCHI Workshop. DAIMI PB-572, Department of Computer Science, University of Arhus.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">H ALLN Ä S , L. AND R EDSTR OM  ̈ , J. 2002. From use to presence: On the expressions and aesthetics of everyday computational things. ACM Trans. Comput.-Hum. Interact. SI New Usability 9, 2.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">H O  ̈ OK  ̈ , K. 2006. Designing familiar open surfaces. In Proceedings of the ACM International 4th Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction: Changing roles (NordCHI) (Oslo, Norway). ACM Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">I NGSTRUP , M. AND H ANSEN , K. M. 2005. Palpable assemblies: Dynamic service composition for ubiquitous computing. In Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering. Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">L ANDIN , H. 2005. Fragile and magical materiality of computational technology as design material. In Proceedings of the Critical Computing Conference, O. Bertelsen et al., Eds. 117–120. ISBN 1- 59593-203-8.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">M ARTI , P. AND R ULLO , A. 2006. Progettare in ambienti ‘fragili’: Il valore della partecipazione. In La Parola e la Cura. Ch’ange Ed. Torino.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">N ORMAN , D. A. 2004. Emotional Design: Why We Love (or Hate) Everyday Things. Basic Books, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">P ALCOM P ROJECT . 2008. PalCom project homepage. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ist-palcom.org/." id="236">http://www.ist-palcom.org/.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">P ALCOM D ELIVERABLE . 2008. PalCom delivery 37 (2.1.2): Palpability: Revised conceptual framework for palpable computing, Section I. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ist-palcom.org/publications/deliverables/" id="238">http://www.ist-palcom.org/publications/deliverables/</ext-link> Deliverable-37-%5B2.1.2%5D-palpability-revised-SectionI.pdf.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">P ETERSEN , M. G. 2004. Remarkable computing: The challenge of designing for the home. In Ex- tended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems at the ACM International Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction. Vienna.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">P ETERSEN , M. G., I VERSEN , O. S., K ROGH , P. G., AND L UDVIGSEN , M. 2004. Aesthetic interaction: A pragmatist’s aesthetics of interactive systems. In Proceedings of the Conference on Designing Interactive Systems: Processes, Practices, Methods, and Techniques. Cambridge, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">R OGERS , Y. 2006. Moving on from Wieser’s vision of calm technologies: Engaging UbiComp experiences. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp), P. Dourish and A. Friday, Eds. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol. 4206. Springer, 404–421.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">R ULLO , A. 2008. Opening the design space: The soft set of requirements. In Proceedings of the Symposium on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS). Cape Town, South Africa.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">R ULLO , A. 2007. Aesthetics of use: A methodological perspective on ambient computing. Ph.D. thesis, University of Florence, Italy.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">R ULLO , A., M ARTI , P., G R ONVALL  ̈ , E., AND P OLLINI , A. 2006. End-User comoposition and re-use of technologies in the neonatal intensive care unit. In Proceedings of the Conference on Pervasive Healthcare. Innsbruck, Austria.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">S HAPIRO , D., M OGENSEN , P., AND B USCHER  ̈ , M. 1996. Bricolage as software culture and practice. In Proceedings of the COSTA4 Workshop on Software Cultures. Technical University of Vienna.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">S CHULER , D. AND N AMIOKA , A., E DS . 1993. Participatory Design: Principles and Practices. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale, NJ.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="252" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">S IZUN , J. AND W ESTRUP , B. 2004. Early developmental care for preterm neonates: A call for more research. Arch. Dis. Child Fetal Neonatal 89, 5 (Sept.), F384–F388.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="253" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">S YMINGTON , A. AND P INELLI , J. 2003. Developmental care for promoting development and prevent- ing morbidity in preterm infants (Cochrane review). Cochrane Database Syst. Rev. 4: CD001814. www.technogel.it.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="254" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">T OLMIE , P., P YCOCK , J., D IGGINS , T., M AC L EAN , A., AND K ARSENTY , A. 2002. Unremarkable computing. In Proceedings of the ACM International Symposium on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Minneapolis, MN, L. Terveen, Ed. 399–406.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="255" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">W EISER , M. 1993. Some computer science problems in ubiquitous computing. Commun. ACM (Jul.), reprinted as “Ubiquitous Computing,” Nikkei Electronics, 137–143.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="256" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">W EISER , M. 1991. The computer for the twenty-first century. Sci. Amer. (Sept.), 94–110.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="258" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">W EISER , M. AND S EELY B ROWN , J. 1996. The coming age of calm technology. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ubiq" id="257">http://www.ubiq</ext-link>. com/hypertext/weiser/acmfuture2endnote.htm.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="259" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">W ESTRUP , B. 2005. Newborn individualized developmental care and assessment program (NIDCAP): Family-Centered developmentally supportive care. NeoRev. 6, 3 (Mar.).</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="260" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Received March 2007; revised January 2008; accepted January 2008</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="209" page="23" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="210" page="24" column="1">17:24</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="211" page="24" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="212" page="24" column="1">A. Rullo</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="240" page="24" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="241" page="25" column="1">The Soft Qualities of Interaction</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="242" page="25" column="1">•</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="243" page="25" column="1">17:25</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="261" page="25" column="1">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, Vol. 15, No. 4, Article 17, Publication date: November 2008.</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
