<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>b00f220ffc56cc35fe90dcc2d784d94fe64484aad6a75cca309330ebed1c2303</job>
    <base_name>62kx</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2470654.2481286</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Extracting Usability and User Experience Information from Online User Reviews</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Steffen Hedegaard</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">Department of Computer Science, University of Copenhagen Njalsgade 128, 2300 Copenhagen S, Denmark <email id="5">steffenh@diku.dk</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7">Internet review sites allow consumers to write detailed reviews of products potentially containing information related to user experience (UX) and usability. Using 5198 sentences from 3492 online reviews of software and video games, we investigate the content of online reviews with the aims of (i) charting the distribution of information in reviews among different dimensions of usability and UX, and (ii) extracting an associated vocabulary for each dimension using techniques from natural language processing and machine learning. We (a) find that 13%–49% of sentences in our online reviews pool contain usability or UX information; (b) chart the distribution of four sets of dimensions of usability and UX across reviews from two product categories; (c) extract a catalogue of important word stems for a number of dimensions. Our results suggest that a greater understanding of users’ preoccu- pation with different dimensions of usability and UX may be inferred from the large volume of self-reported experiences online, and that research focused on identifying pertinent dimensions of usability and UX may benefit further from empirical studies of user-generated experience reports.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Author Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="18">Jakob Grue Simonsen</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" page="1" column="1">User experience; usability; natural language processing; end user reviews; machine learning.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Classification Keywords</h2>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">General Terms</h2>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="1" column="1">H.5.2 Information Interfaces and Presentation (e.g., HCI): User Interfaces–Evaluation/Methodology</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Experimentation; Human Factors; Measurement.</region>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="15" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">Related work</h2>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="1">Investigation of a product for usability or user experience (henceforth UUX for short) problems typically requires expensive experimentation. In contrast, informal, but</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="17" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. CHI 2013 , April 27–May 2, 2013, Paris, France.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="20" page="1" column="2">Department of Computer Science, University of Copenhagen Njalsgade 128, 2300 Copenhagen S, Denmark <email id="19">simonsen@diku.dk</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" page="1" column="2">structured electronic word-of-mouth communication between end users affords a potential, cheap source of information concerning UUX. Customer reviews on commercial sites such as amazon.com, or dedicated review sites such as epinions.com, contain reviews that are not just summary assessments or recommendations, but also self-reports of the end users experiences, in their own words, in the wild. The aim of this paper is to quantify the amount of UUX information and dimensions in online reviews from the specific domains of software and video games. We also implement and test a machine-learning-based classifier that tags sentences in reviews according to whether they contain usability or UX-related information and according to the dimensions of usability or UX they pertain to. The primary aim of the classifier is to automatically extract the pertinent vocabulary of end users associated with the various dimensions of UUX. A secondary aim is to investigate the feasibility of using such a classifier to automatically catalogue UUX information found in databases of thousands of reviews, too large for qualified human analysis. We hope to aid the understanding of which dimensions of product use motivate laymen reviewers, and in the future potentially use this understanding when re-designing a product. The scope of the present work is to provide a tool to UUX researchers; future work will ex- plore the automatic identification and extraction of specific actionable outcomes for practioners. In order to process information from many different reviews, our approach focuses on extraction of information from individual sentences, rather than entire texts. This is somewhat at odds with approaches in focusing on obtaining a holistic understanding of interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="21" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>], but as a review may in- corporate both good and bad experiences relating to many different dimensions of UUX, we believe that a sentence- based bottom-up approach will yield more precise information about the “typical” vocabulary associated to specific dimensions of UUX.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" page="1" column="2">User experience has been studied by soliciting user narratives [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="24" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="25" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="26" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>] where information is manually extracted from user-generated texts. The volume of texts studied has been substantial (500 texts in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="27" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]), but still small enough for dedicated researchers to process manually, and the users have been specifically asked to write the texts, unlike the typ-<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ical online review. Similarly, studies in asynchronous usability testing and reporting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="33" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="34" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>] have studied user-generated problem reports that are only later reviewed by experts or researchers. Outside UUX, classification and information extraction from user-generated text is a vibrant research area, both for full texts, and at sentence or short message level, e.g. tweets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="35" class="deo:Reference">39</xref>]. Some pertinent examples: Gamon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="36" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] perform sentence-level sentiment analysis on car reviews using several methods from machine learning, but only classify sentences into positive/negative/other. Kim et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="37" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] perform sentence- based classification of pros and cons for mp3 and restaurant reviews in order to extract plausible reasons for the review- ers’ recommendations or non-recommendations, but they do not extract vocabulary or classify according to a diverse number of dimensions. Pang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="38" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>] classify movie reviews as positive/negative at document level. The primary differences between our work and studies on sentiment analysis as above are twofold: Firstly, we focus on a substantial number of distinct UUX dimensions, some of which may be objec- tive (e.g. a count of false positives from AV software) with no negative or positive opinion, and others which may be described in neutral terms (e.g. aesthetics) where a reviewer can use neutral terms without showing any sentiment. Secondly, unlike most studies in sentiment analysis, the outcome of the classification is primarily a means to an end, namely charting the UUX content of reviews and the vocabulary used by reviewers to describe UUX-related phenomena.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="29" page="1" column="2">Copyright 2013 ACM 978-1-4503-1899-0/13/04... $ 15.00.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="30" page="1" column="2">2089</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="31" page="2" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="2" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="40" page="2" column="1">REVIEWS ON THE INTERNET AND UUX</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="2" column="1">For the purpose of this paper a review is a piece of text de- tailing pros and cons of a product and possibly an assessment of it and recommendations for potential buyers, written by a user of the product who has been in possession of said product and used it for some time. It may be written either by a professional reviewer or an ordinary end user. We concentrate on reviews assumed to be written by ordinary end users on dedicated web sites, for example epinions.com or amazon.com. An example of an online review is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>. Consider the following sentence from a review of the game Gears of War for the Xbox 360: “You’ll be a little creeped out while playing this game almost all the time.” The above sentence clearly contains information that is hedonic in nature: Being scared due to the horror elements in the game, and there is a–much less clear–element of the satisfaction usability aspect: the sentence communicates a positive experience by the user. From a communication perspective, user reviews may be viewed as word of mouth communication: informal communication between private parties concerning evaluation of goods and services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="42" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]; reviews from review sites, online fora, and blogs are clearly examples of such informal communication, and are accordingly called eWoM (electronic word of mouth) in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="43" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. Anderson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="44" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>] found that either<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> very satisfied or very dissatisfied customers were more likely to engage in (non-electronic) word of mouth and the word of mouth satisfaction was best described by a bimodal (U- shaped) model. This was confirmed for online reviews by Hu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="48" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>] who found that 53% of products on Amazon had a bimodal score distribution (with peaks at very low scores and very high scores). Due to the bimodal distribution, the average score for these products may be misguiding. In addition, the information extracted from online reviews may not be in- dicative of the experience of the average user, but may rather represent those experiences that add or deduct so much from certain users’ experience that they are motivated to write a review. For (non-electronic) word of mouth communication, extremely dissatisfied customers also engage more in word of mouth than very satisfied customers, though in a sizeable case of their data the differences were not significant[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="49" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]; it seems plausible that the same phenomena occur for online user reviews. There is evidence that potential buyers put more emphasis on reviews with low satisfaction than those with high satisfaction as they have a bigger impact on product sales than that of positive reviews and word of mouth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="50" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="51" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>].</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kx.page_002.image_01.png" thmb="62kx.page_002.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="47" page="2" column="2">Figure 1. Example of the first part of a review from epinions.com 12. September 2012.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">Usability and UX in reviews</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" page="2" column="2">Usability is a way to measure a products ability to help a user solve a given task adequately. It is dependent on the product, task, user and circumstances [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="54" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>], and has been the object of intense academic scrutiny. UX is a younger, emerging field that studies users’ experience with products and the design of<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> such product with the purpose of generating certain experiences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="59" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="60" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. In usability, traditional studies focus on short term product use (median 30 minutes duration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="61" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]) and conducted in lab settings; few studies stretch across longer time periods and then only weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="62" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]. In contrast, most UX research concerns open use situations (61%) and controlled task (33%) experiments, only 20% of papers contain studies based on user-initiated use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="63" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. No UX research covers longer time periods of months or years which is the expected life span of most products but instead covers at most only a few weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="64" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. In contrast to traditional studies, reviews describe a users opinion and experiences after more protracted use. And in contrast to user narratives solicited for product improvement or research purposes (cf. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="65" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="66" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="67" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>]) online reviews are in a different genre: Authors must follow certain conventions of the review genre, for instance give recommendations on whether or not to buy it. In addition, and unlike narratives written for UX studies, customer reviews on Internet sites appear to be written because the reviewer is motivated by his or her own use of the product, usually in conjunction with some small reward (tangible if the review site offers “credit” for reviews, intangible in the form of community recognition because of the perceived help afforded by a review, or both). There are important caveats when assessing the potential use- fulness of online reviews: It is not clear whether online reviews are written by users typical of the user base; in addition, very few details about reviewers (e.g. gender, age, pref- erences) are available, in contrast to standard usability studies. Furthermore, some reviews may be fake. Finally, the bimodal distribution of satisfaction present in word of mouth communication leads us to conjecture that in terms of satisfaction, the average user is underrepresented among reviewers, and that reviews may not always yield a representative description of the typical experiences among the user base. However, satisfaction extremes are well represented, it should thus be possible to extract information about situations where the product under review performs both bad and good.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="56" page="2" column="2">2090</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="57" page="3" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="58" page="3" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="69" page="3" column="1">DIMENSIONS OF USABILITY AND USER EXPERIENCE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" page="3" column="1">Usability and User Experience are central terms in human- computer interaction. Their precise definition, and their sub- division into dimensions such as Efficiency, Learnability, Hedonic quality, and so forth is still debated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="70" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>], in the case of UX hotly so [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="71" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="72" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="73" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>], and there seems to be no universal consensus about whether UX is an aspect of usability or vice versa. We are particularly interested in the way researchers have subdivided UUX into various dimensions that pertain to specific aspects, viewpoints, or phenomena within UUX. We briefly review existing research below.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Dimensions of usability</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="109" page="3" column="1">The ISO 9241 standard [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="76" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] defines usability in terms of the three dimensions effectiveness, efficiency and satisfaction:<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Usability: The extent to which a product can be used by specified users to achieve specified goals with effectiveness, efficiency and satisfaction in a specified context of use. A more fine-grained description of usability is obtained by the following five dimensions which, with some variation in the naming of the aspects, are often used for measuring and describing usability in models and literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="78" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="79" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>]: (i) Ef- fectiveness/Errors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="80" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="81" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="82" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="83" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="84" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="85" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>], (ii) Efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="86" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="87" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="88" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="89" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="90" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="91" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>], (iii) Satisfaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="92" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="93" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="94" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="95" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="96" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="97" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>], (iv) Learnability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="98" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="99" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="100" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="101" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="102" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>], (v) Memorability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="103" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="104" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="105" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="106" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>]. The definitions of the above five dimensions vary somewhat in the literature, and some studies use only a subset of the above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="107" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]. In addition, some studies use a precise and limited definition of measures, and others such as the ISO definition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="108" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] take a broad view of the measures.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="110" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Dimensions of user experience</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" page="3" column="2">Unlike usability, there seems to be much less consensus on the definition of the notion of user experience and its seg- mentation into meaningful aspects. The ISO 9241-210[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="111" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>] definition states: User experience: A person’s perceptions and responses that result from the use and/or anticipated use of a product, system or service. We may interpret the above as being covered by the Satisfaction dimension of the ISO 9241-11 definition of usability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="112" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>], but the literature contains many more nuanced interpre- tations: For example, Bevan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="113" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] describes four dimensions, called satisfaction measures, and Ketola and Roto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="114" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>] describe a study at Nokia among relevant senior staff who were asked which UX data they found useful, which Bevan later grouped into dimensions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="115" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. McNamara et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="116" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>] split the need for evaluation into the three (overlapping) components of functionality, usability and experience. Similarly, Hassenzahl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="117" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>] divides UX analysis into the three partially overlapping approaches beyond the instrumental, emotion and affect, and the experiental, but in later work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="118" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>] shifts focus to the subjective side of product use and relates it to Self Determina- tion Theory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="119" class="deo:Reference">35</xref>] and Flow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="120" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. Bargas-Avila and Hornbæk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="121" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] systematically collect a sample of 51 publications from 2005-2009 reporting empirical studies on UX and describe a number of (non-mutually exclusive) dimensions together with the percentage of studies from their sample that pertain to the identified dimensions.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="123" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Dimensions selected for this paper</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="3" column="2">Based on the literature above, we elected to use the 5 standard dimensions of usability, and chose the sets of dimensions from 3 of the studies of UX that had both precise definitions of the dimensions and clear demarcations of the differences between them (with two exceptions in FREQUENT , see below). A summary is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>; we briefly describe the dimensions below.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="126" page="3" column="2">2091</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="127" page="4" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="128" page="4" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx129">
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="4">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> CLASSICUA ([12, 36])</td>
                    <td class="table"> BEVAN ([3])</td>
                    <td class="table"> KETOLA ([23, 4])</td>
                    <td class="table"> FREQUENT ([2])</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Memorability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Likeability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Anticipation</td>
                    <td class="table"> Affect and Emotion</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Learnability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Pleasure</td>
                    <td class="table"> Overall Usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enjoyment, Fun</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Efficiency</td>
                    <td class="table"> Comfort</td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> Aesthetics, Appeal</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Errors/effectiveness</td>
                    <td class="table"> Trust</td>
                    <td class="table"> Detailed usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Engagement, Flow</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> User differences</td>
                    <td class="table"> Motivation</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Support</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enchantment</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Impact</td>
                    <td class="table"> Frustration Hedonic</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="136" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">CLASSICUA ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="130" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="131" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>]) BEVAN ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="132" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]) KETOLA ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="133" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="134" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]) FREQUENT ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="135" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]) Dimension Dimension Dimension Dimension Memorability Likeability Anticipation Affect and Emotion Learnability Pleasure Overall Usability Enjoyment, Fun Efficiency Comfort Hedonic Aesthetics, Appeal Errors/effectiveness Trust Detailed usability Engagement, Flow Satisfaction User differences Motivation Support Enchantment Impact Frustration Hedonic</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="137" page="4" column="1">Table 1. Dimensions of UUX used for the studies in this paper. . CLAS -</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">SICUA is short for “classic usability”, BEVAN and KETOLA are named after the authors of the pertinent studies, and FREQUENT is short for “frequently mentioned dimensions”.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" page="4" column="1">The dimensions of CLASSICUA [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="139" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="140" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>] are: Errors/effectiveness: The number of (non-fatal) errors made by users on their way to completing a task or the quality of task outcome. Efficiency: The speed or other measure of cost associated with performing the task for users at a given experience level. Satisfaction: A subjective rating of satisfaction with product use or liking of the product or features. Learnability: The amount of time it takes to learn to use the system, how difficult it is for a first time user or development over time. Memorability: How well users retain information gained about or through the system. The dimensions of BEVAN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="141" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] are: Likability: The extent to which the users are satisfied with their perceived achievement of pragmatic goals, including acceptable perceived results of use and consequences of use (note the close simi- larity with Satisfaction from CLASSICUA ). Pleasure: The extent to which the users are satisfied with their perceived achievement of hedonic goals of stimulation, identification, evocation and associated emotional responses. Comfort: The extent to which the users are satisfied with physical comfort. Trust: the extent to which the users are satisfied that the product will behave as intended. The dimensions of KETOLA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="142" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="143" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>] are: Anticipation: What did users expect, what is the anticipated use? Overall usability: Was the user successful in taking the product into use or upgrading from a previous product. Hedonic: Fulfill- ment of inner needs such as pleasure, enjoyment, or things preventing this such as frustration. Detailed usability: Going into details on which functions are used, ordinary usability problems and performance satisfaction/problems. User differences: Differences between users such as previous product experience, how they access features and differences between the actual buyers and target user group. Support: Aspects with the human- or software-support available and how it affects user satisfaction, possible product returns, or user wish lists. Impact of use: If and how the new device change the usage patterns of the users. The dimensions of FREQUENT are: Affect and Emotion: Affect and emotion induced by using the product, including other aspects such as Enjoyment, fun and Frustration. This dimension fully encompasses Enjoyment, fun and Frustration, and would be considered encompassed by the Hedonic dimension. Enjoyment, Fun: How entertained is the user while using the product? This is also an affect and emotion,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and hedonic, dimension. Aesthetics, Appeal: Appreciation of beauty or good taste. Typically associated with graphics or sound. Engagement, Flow: How engaged is the user in using the product forgetting everything else? Also includes challenge versus skill balancing needed for achieving flow state. Motivation: What motivates the user in using the product (task/inner motivation etc.)? Enchantment: Being “both caught up and carried away” in the experience forgetting everything else, and causing a disorientation associated with a pleasurable sense of fullness and liveliness that charges atten- tion and concentration. Frustration: Frustration or hardship induced by using the product. This is also a negative hedonic dimension. Hedonic: Defined the same way as in KETOLA . We discarded the two dimensions Generic UX and Other as reported by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="145" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] as no clear definition was available.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="147" page="4" column="2">PRE-STUDY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="148" page="4" column="2">To see whether randomly sampled reviews contain sufficient UUX-related information to warrant further study, we performed a pre-study among usability experts who were given a sample of Internet reviews and a free-form exercise asking them to mark sentences containing information about usability or UX.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="149" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">Participants</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="150" page="4" column="2">9 usability experts were contacted, all of whom are active researchers in usability (7 from academia, 2 from industry). Of these, 8 gave affirmative answers and were enrolled as participants. All participants were compensated with two bottles of wine.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="151" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">Procedure</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="158" page="4" column="2">24 reviews were sampled on January 5 2012 from 12:00 – 14:00 from the website epinions.com, collecting the 6 most recent reviews of each of the four categories “Digital Cameras”, “Headphones”, “Software” and “Video games”. 3 reviews were discarded, all from the software category (1 was a review of an iPhone game (games were covered explicitly in another category), and 2 were reviews of printed children’s books). Each review was randomly assigned to 2 distinct participants. Each participant was asked to read and comment on six different reviews in total. The participants received only written instructions asking them to free-form annotate text in the reviews that they found interesting concerning (a) their own perception of usability, and (b) user experience. Participants were neither given definitions of usability or user experience, but encouraged to use their own perception of these terms. Each participant was asked to use at most 2 hours in total on all six reviews, including time to read and to annotate. We collected the annotated texts and post-processed them in two ways: Raw containment of UUX: Each review was manually split into sentences and was marked with the identity of a participant if the participant had marked part of or the entire sentence as relevant. Due to the level of annotation performed by most experts, no distinction was done between dimensions or UX and usability based on the experts comments. <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Presence of UUX dimension: For each review, the first au- thor coded all sentences annotated by at least one participant using the dimensions from <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="156" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>; the same sentence could be annotated with more than one dimension. Examples of dimension assignments can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="157" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref></region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="153" page="4" column="2">2092</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="154" page="5" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="155" page="5" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx159">
            <content>
              <h1 class="table"> Content Dimensions present</h1>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="5">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> If you like multiplayer strategy games, buy this with confidence.</td>
                    <td class="table"> satisfaction,</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> user differences</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Those expectations were met. Mostly, anyway.</td>
                    <td class="table"> anticipation,</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> satisfaction</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> ... making the game enjoyable for beginners as well as veterans.</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> user</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> flow,</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> hedonic</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Multiplayer is excellent, but the single player campaign isn’t.</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> satisfaction</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Most of the inter-mission story telling happen in this mode,</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> satisfaction,</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> which tend to be awkward and clumsy.</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> frustration</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> Most of the missions are enjoyable, and each one has optional</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"> enjoyment,</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table.strange">
                    <td class="table.strange"> goals which add replay value.</td>
                    <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="160" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Content Dimensions present If you like multiplayer strategy games, buy this with confidence. satisfaction, user differences Those expectations were met. Mostly, anyway. anticipation, satisfaction ... making the game enjoyable for beginners as well as veterans. user differences, flow, enjoyment, hedonic Multiplayer is excellent, but the single player campaign isn’t. satisfaction Most of the inter-mission story telling happen in this mode, satisfaction, which tend to be awkward and clumsy. frustration Most of the missions are enjoyable, and each one has optional enjoyment, hedonic, goals which add replay value. engagement/flow</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="161" page="5" column="1">Table 2. Examples of annotation from the video game Starcraft 2.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="162" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Results</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" page="5" column="1">Raw containment of UUX: Calculation of inter-rater agreement for raw containment of usability or UX indicated that participants were somewhat in agreement on which sentences did, or did not, contain any relevant information at all, but that no hard conclusions should be drawn based on the data (Krippendorff’s α = .783) 1 . In total, 13 % of all sentences were marked as relevant to usability or UX by both participants assigned to each review, 36 % as relevant by one, but not both assigned to each review, and 51% of all sentences were unmarked (i.e., deemed as irrelevant by participants). There was great diversity in the understanding of UUX and annotation volume per participant. One participant specifically noted that he had given up marking user experience data as it “virtually encompassed everything”, and only a single participant consistently annotated UX and usability information as two distinct categories. We observed some discrepan- cies in annotations; for example, one participant had marked the sentence “The product works extremely well” as relevant for UUX in a review, but later in the review failed to mark the similar sentence “It also works well when listening to music while using power tools . . .” as relevant. Presence of usability or UX dimension: The results are sum- marized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="163" class="deo:Reference">table 3</xref>. For the classic usability measure as seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="164" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>, almost all sentences in the dimension errors/effectiveness were describing quality of task outcome (e.g., music quality for headphones), but a few classic error counts were also present (e.g., notes correctly transcribed by a sheet music scanning feature of a program, and false positives in anti virus software). Only rarely (N = 4) did reviews attach any numbers to measures of efficiency and effectiveness, and even then they were not considered as exact measures, but merely rough estimates such as “...and the whole process only takes about 5 min- utes...” Detailed inspection of the reviews revealed that some dimensions only occurred in specific product categories: The 1 No hard conclusions should be based on data with .667 ≤ α &lt; .8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="165" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> dimension physical comfort was exclusively encountered in camera and headphones reviews, and the dimension pleasure mainly for video games. The dimensions of motivation and enchantment, both popular dimensions in empirical user experience research being represented in 8% and 6% of papers respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="167" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], were not encountered at all in the pre-study.<marker type="block"/> In summary, 13% + 36% = 49% of all sentences were marked as relevant by at least one of the two participants annotating each review. Some confirmation bias may be present as participants were specifically asked to look for information relevant to usability or user experience, but based on the results we concluded that the volume of text in a review relevant to usability or UX, and the dispersion of text across UUX dimensions were both substantial enough to warrant a larger- scale annotation experiment.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx169">
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="3" page="5">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> CLASSICUA</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> BEVAN</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> KETOLA</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> FREQUENT</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Occ.</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Occ.</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Occ.</td>
                    <td class="table"> Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> Occ.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Memorability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.04%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Likeability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 4.70%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Anticipation</td>
                    <td class="table"> 3.57%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Affect and Emotion</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.24%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Learnability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 3.77%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Pleasure</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.56%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Overall usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.16%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enjoyment, Fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.40%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Efficiency</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.44%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Comfort</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.04%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.65%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Aesthetics, Appeal</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.48%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Errors/Effectiveness</td>
                    <td class="table"> 3.61%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Trust</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.12%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Detailed usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 21.07%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Engagement, Flow</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.68%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                    <td class="table"> 4.70%</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> User differences</td>
                    <td class="table"> 2.17%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Motivation</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Support</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.64%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enchantment</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Impact</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.32%</td>
                    <td class="table"> Frustration</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.20%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.65%</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="170" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">CLASSICUA BEVAN KETOLA FREQUENT Dimension Occ. Dimension Occ. Dimension Occ. Dimension Occ. Memorability 0.04% Likeability 4.70% Anticipation 3.57% Affect and Emotion 0.24% Learnability 3.77% Pleasure 0.56% Overall usability 0.16% Enjoyment, Fun 0.40% Efficiency 1.44% Comfort 1.04% Hedonic 1.65% Aesthetics, Appeal 0.48% Errors/Effectiveness 3.61% Trust 1.12% Detailed usability 21.07% Engagement, Flow 0.68% Satisfaction 4.70% User differences 2.17% Motivation 0.00% Support 0.64% Enchantment 0.00% Impact 0.32% Frustration 0.20% Hedonic 1.65%</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="171" page="5" column="2">Table 3. Occurrences of dimensions found in sentences annotated by participants as a percentage of the total number of sentences in all reviews.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="173" page="5" column="2">FIRST STUDY: ANNOTATION OF REVIEWS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="183" page="5" column="2">Based on the promising results of the pre-study, we opted to harvest a larger sample of reviews and annotate them. We de- cided to keep the per-sentence annotation of the pre-study and concentrate on only 2 product categories as it would allow us to annotate more sentences in each product category while retaining the ability to make comparisons across categories. Procedure We collected reviews from the two product categories Software (520 reviews) and Video games (2972 reviews across various PC and console platforms) on the epinions.com website on July 5th, 2012. All public available reviews in the two categories were collected. We split each review into sentences using a routine from the Python NLTK [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="174" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] which came pre-trained on the British National Corpus. We then drew sentences randomly from the pool of all sentences above and performed manual annotation on each drawn sentence. In total 4587 sentences (of a pool of 132609) were annotated from the Video games and 611 (of a pool of 18646) from the Soft-<marker type="block"/> The annotation was conducted by one of the authors and two graduate student annotators: The graduate students were given a short, written introduction description of all dimensions and participated in a co-annotation workshop for four<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> hours with one of the authors acting as instructor and senior annotator. This was followed by four hours of individual annotation where the student annotators could freely con- sult the senior annotator for questions. Inter-rater agreement was computed at the end of the individual annotation with Krippendorff’s α for all dimensions in the [0.9 − 1.0] range. Each graduate student annotator then continued individually for 22-25 hours over the course of two weeks, and the senior annotator for 10 hours during one week. All annotations were performed in a custom-built tool built by a research programmer not otherwise involved in the study. A total of 6655 sentences were annotated with 1315 sentences annotated by the senior annotator 2922 sentences by annotator 2, and 2418 sentences annotated by annotator 1, ev- ery tenth sentence annotated by an annotator was randomly chosen from sentences already annotated by another in order to compute inter-rater agreement; all dimensions annotated showed a high degree of agreement (Krippendorff’s α lowest score α = .842; 22 of 25 dimensions had α &gt; .90) 2 . Some examples of sentences from reviews and their annotations: • “Once again, the way sound distorts during the slow- motion sequences adds a nice touch to the experience.”. This sentence mainly describes Aesthetics and subsequently the effect on Engagement while playing the game, yet also expresses Satisfaction with the effect. As this example illustrates, several dimensions are often encountered together with Satisfaction. • “The sound is what you’d expect from a Nintendo title, and can become quite annoying after extended plays.” This sentence describes displeasure, relevant to the dimension Pleasure; this is also a measure of Satisfaction with the sound.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx176">
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> ware.</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="4" page="5">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"></th>
                  <th class="table"> Min.</th>
                  <th class="table"> Max.</th>
                  <th class="table"> Median</th>
                  <th class="table"> M</th>
                  <th class="table"> SD</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Software:</td>
                  <td class="table"> 26</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11686</td>
                  <td class="table"> 471</td>
                  <td class="table"> 780.6</td>
                  <td class="table"> 952.2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Video Games:</td>
                  <td class="table"> 30</td>
                  <td class="table"> 23989</td>
                  <td class="table"> 721</td>
                  <td class="table"> 880.8</td>
                  <td class="table"> 774.4</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="177" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">ware. Min. Max. Median M SD Software: 26 11686 471 780.6 952.2 Video Games: 30 23989 721 880.8 774.4</region>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="178" page="5" column="2">Table 4. Word count statistics for reviews.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="180" page="5" column="2">2093</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="181" page="6" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="182" page="6" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="184" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Results</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="188" page="6" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5" id="185" class="deo:Reference">Table 5</xref> shows the fraction of sentences in each product category annotated by the various UUX dimensions. The table confirms the observation from the pre-study that some dimensions are hardly used at all: In CLASSICUA , Memorability does not occur at all in the software category, and only in 0.37% of sentences among video games. Likewise, Efficiency occurs very rarely (4.45% in the software category, 1.12% in video games). Among the dimensions from BEVAN , Comfort and Trust are again absent, but Likeability is promi- nent, as expected from the pre-study. The dimension Pleasure is more prevalent among video game reviews than reviews of software. In KETOLA , Impact is almost completely absent, and Support rare, but more prevalent among software products, possibly reflecting that this dimension is more valued among users of software products than video games. Conversely, the dimension Hedonic is present in 7.77% of all sentences sampled in the video games category, more than twice as often as in the software category. 2 Data with α &gt; .8 are generally considered reliable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="186" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> It is striking that there are quite few sentences annotated by dimensions in the FREQUENT classification (9.25% for software, 29.72% for video games) compared to the CLASSICUA , BEVAN and KETOLA categories (where more than 40% of all sentences contain usability or UX information). This phenomenon is due to the FREQUENT classification’s lack of a “catch-all” category such as CLASSICUA ’s Satisfaction, BE VAN ’s Likability and KETOLA ’s Detailed usability. In summary, the results support two clear conclusions: First, The product domain of the review (in our case, software, resp. video games) influences the amount of sentences that pertain to specific dimensions of UUX (e.g., the dimension engage- ment, flow is much more prevalent in reviews of video games than in reviews of other software). Second, the four sets of dimensions of UUX we consider differ very much in the balance of dimensions: Clearly, FREQUENT , the model containing the most categories, has the most even distribution of sentences across the various dimensions, whereas the other sets of dimensions seem to have greatly skewed distributions towards the “catch-all” categories described above.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="189" page="6" column="2">SECOND STUDY: AUTOMATIC CLASSIFICATION OF SEN- TENCES IN UUX DIMENSIONS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="203" page="6" column="2">Based on the results of the first study, we wish to investigate the vocabulary employed by users when conveying information relevant to the dimensions of UUX. One straightforward way of extracting such a vocabulary is to construct a machine learning classifier that discriminates between dimensions based on words or other features of the text that are automatically computed during the training of the classifier. An added benefit is that the constructed classifier, if precise, may be used for automatically tagging a sentence with the UUX dimensions it pertains to. This tagging task may be viewed as a set of binary classification tasks: For each dimension, and for each sentence, does the sentence pertain to that dimension, or not. Such a tagger may be used to either aid future researchers in manual annotation, or in lessening the amount of sentences to be studied (i.e., sentences receiving no tags by an automatic classifier can be ignored at little risk). Procedure For each UUX dimension a binary classifier using a bag-of- words feature set was trained and evaluated in a sequence of steps as follows: Preprocessing step: Each sentence was tok- enized, words from the NLTK stop word list [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="190" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] removed and the remaining words stemmed using the Snowball stem- mer. Data split step: The total dataset is split into a five-fold stratified cross-validation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="191" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>] 3 scheme. Training step: For each cross-validation split, the training set is used for creating feature vectors with TFxIDF weighting and χ 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="192" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>] ranking is subsequently used to discard the 10% worst discriminating features. A linear kernel Support Vector Machine (SVM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="193" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>] is then trained using the feature set. Classification and validation step: For each cross-validation split, classification of the evaluation set using each SVM classifier is performed, and the classification results for all the cross-validation splits are aggregated, and standard performance measures (see Table 3 Stratified cross validation maintains the same class balance in the training and evaluation sets as found in the total data set.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 6) calculated. Extraction of important words for each dimension: For each dimension, we extracted the most informative words by selecting the word stems having the largest distance in descending order to the separating hyperplane afforded by the SVM. Aside from the classic bag of words approach as described above, we also experimented with the following feature sets commonly used in text classification tasks: binary bag of words, word di-grams and tri-grams, a combination of tri- agrams and a feature set consisting of all possible Wordnet synsets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="202" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>], and Wordnet synsets with automatic part of speech (POS) tagging. All of the alternative feature sets had slightly worse average performance than an ordinary bag of words approach, hence were discarded. To avoid drawing erroneous conclusions from unreliable data, we elected to only consider the extracted word stems from the dimensions where the classifier performed better than random chance. This was tested against a baseline classifier that always assigns to the majority class with significance at p &lt; .05 (using the non-parametric McNemar’s test with Yates’ correction, as we have categorical data and cannot assume a specific prior distribution).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="195" page="6" column="2">2094</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="196" page="7" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="197" page="7" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx198">
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> CLASSICUA BEVAN KETOLA FREQUENT</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="5" page="7">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                  <th class="table"> Software</th>
                  <th class="table"> Video Games</th>
                  <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                  <th class="table"> Software</th>
                  <th class="table"> Video Games</th>
                  <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                  <th class="table"> Software</th>
                  <th class="table"> Video Games</th>
                  <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                  <th class="table"> Software</th>
                  <th class="table"> Video Games</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Memorability</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.37%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Likability</td>
                  <td class="table"> 31.34%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 34.57%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Anticipation</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.23%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.78%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Affect and Emotion</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.91%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8.63%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Learnability</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7.36%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.54%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Pleasure</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.23%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6.08%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Overall Usability</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.37%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.71%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Enjoyment, Fun</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.37%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6.81%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Efficiency</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.45%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.12%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Comfort</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.17%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.42%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7.77%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Aesthetics, Appeal</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.60%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11.70%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Errors/effectiveness</td>
                  <td class="table"> 17.64%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8.61%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Trust</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.17%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Detailed usability</td>
                  <td class="table"> 44.52%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 41.34%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Engagement, Flow</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.71%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 12.24%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                  <td class="table"> 31.34%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 34.57%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                  <td class="table"> 32.02%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 37.23%</td>
                  <td class="table"> User differences</td>
                  <td class="table"> 12.33%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8.61%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Motivation</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.86%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.42%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                  <td class="table"> 46.58%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 41.83%</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Support</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.74%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.52%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Enchantment</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.86%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Impact</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.00%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.26%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Frustration</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.20%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.37%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                  <td class="table"> 53.60%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 50.83%</td>
                  <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.42%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7.77%</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                  <td class="table"> 9.25%</td>
                  <td class="table"> 29.72%</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="199" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">CLASSICUA BEVAN KETOLA FREQUENT Dimension Software Video Games Dimension Software Video Games Dimension Software Video Games Dimension Software Video Games Memorability 0.00% 0.37% Likability 31.34% 34.57% Anticipation 2.23% 3.78% Affect and Emotion 2.91% 8.63% Learnability 7.36% 3.54% Pleasure 2.23% 6.08% Overall Usability 1.37% 0.71% Enjoyment, Fun 1.37% 6.81% Efficiency 4.45% 1.12% Comfort 0.00% 0.17% Hedonic 3.42% 7.77% Aesthetics, Appeal 3.60% 11.70% Errors/effectiveness 17.64% 8.61% Trust 0.00% 0.17% Detailed usability 44.52% 41.34% Engagement, Flow 1.71% 12.24% Satisfaction 31.34% 34.57% Any Dimension 32.02% 37.23% User differences 12.33% 8.61% Motivation 0.86% 1.42% Any Dimension 46.58% 41.83% Support 2.74% 0.52% Enchantment 0.00% 0.86% Impact 0.00% 0.26% Frustration 1.20% 1.37% Any Dimension 53.60% 50.83% Hedonic 3.42% 7.77% Any Dimension 9.25% 29.72%</region>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="201" page="7" column="1">Table 5. Distribution of dimensions in sentences within Software and Video Games reviews. The “Any dimension” rows indicate the percentage of sentences annotated with at least one dimension. Each sentence can be annotated with more than one dimension, hence “Any dimension” is not the sum of the other numbers in the same column. Differences between the Software and Video Games categories were tested for significance using the non-parametric two-tailed Wilcoxon rank-sum test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="200" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>] and significance at p &lt; .05 is indicated in boldface.</caption>
        </region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="204" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Results: Quality of the classifier</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="207" page="7" column="1">To evaluate the quality of the classifier, we use the classic information retrieval metrics precision, recall, and F1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="205" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>]. Precision is the fraction of sentences correctly classified as relevant for a dimension among all sentences classified as relevant for it; recall is the fraction of sentences actually relevant for a dimension that are also correctly classified as relevant for it; F1 is the harmonic mean of precision and recall (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6" id="206" class="deo:Reference">Table 6</xref>). The results for the various dimensions are shown in</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx208">
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="6" page="7">
                <thead class="table">
                  <tr class="table">
                    <th class="table"></th>
                    <th class="table"> Precision</th>
                    <th class="table"> Recall</th>
                    <th class="table"> F1</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> P</td>
                    <td class="table"> = |R |C d ∩C d | d | R</td>
                    <td class="table"> = |R |R d ∩C d | d |</td>
                    <td class="table"> 2 P P +R ·R</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="209" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Precision Recall F1 P = |R d ∩C d | R = |R d ∩C d | 2 P ·R |C d | |R d | P +R</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="210" page="7" column="1">Table 6. Definitions of precision, recall and F1. R d is the set of sentences</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="211" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">relevant for dimension d, C d is the set of sentences that the classifier tags as relevant for d.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="217" page="7" column="1"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7" id="212" class="deo:Reference">Table 7</xref>, Significant results are marked in bold. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7" id="213" class="deo:Reference">Table 7</xref> shows that for the dimensions that are barely represented in the data, the classifier all sentences are classified as not relevant for the dimension. This is the case for Memorability, Efficiency, Comfort, Trust, Overall usability, Support,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Impact, Motivation and Enchantment that all have precision and recall at zero flat. For the more commonly occurring dimensions, the classifier performs better than the baseline of assigning all sentences to the majority class, but it is clearly quite conservative: Precision values are generally high, but recall values low (e.g., for Learnability, Anticipation, User differences, Engagement, Flow and Hedonic). In short, for these dimensions, the sentences tagged as being relevant to a dimension will be relevant with high probability, but the classifier will miss many relevant sentences. For dimensions that commonly occur in the data, the classifier works well, as should be expected: precision, recall and F1 are all high for Satisfaction and Likeability and–again with the exception of recall–for Enjoyment, Fun and Affect and Emotion, Frustration, and Hedonic. Differences in both data domain and classification tasks pre- clude us from directly comparing to other studies, but for all but the very sparsely represented dimensions, the performance of the classifier is on par with studies conducting sentence-based classification: Gamon et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="215" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] performed sentence level sentiment analysis on car reviews with precision for the negative class from 0.85 to 0.55 with recall from 0.1 to 0.25. Similarly, Kim et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="216" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] classified sentences with regard to pros and cons content, achieving P = 0.59, R = 0.62, F 1 = 0.61 and P = 0.54, R = 0.52, F 1 = 0.53 respectively on a well-balanced dataset of hotel reviews.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="218" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Results: Vocabulary of reviews</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="229" page="7" column="2"> <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8" id="219" class="deo:Reference">Table 8</xref> holds the 30 most important word stems for each dimension where the difference in precision, recall and F 1 between the classifier and the baseline was significant. As an example of top word stems associated with a dimension not included in the table are “sooth”, “cute”, “reliev”, “handhold” and “exist”, all associated with the dimension trust. For the dimension Frustration with word stems “frustrat”, “incompatibilit”, “hardest”, “perpetu”, “insult” what seems like less relevant words also made it to the top 30, for instance “babysit”. This is due to reviews containing text such as “And that is of course an AI partner controlled friend, there is noth- ing that can ruin a good RPG then a partner that is supposed to be helping you but instead makes you feel like your babysit- ting a 5 year old with mental problems, on top of battling blood thirsty monsters.” This particular sentence also illustrates the intricacies of our task: Clearly, the use of “babysit” is figurative, not literal, hence signals frustration.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Other spurious word stems in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8" id="228" class="deo:Reference">Table 8</xref> (e.g., “sc”, “thus”, “gps”) can be attributed to two phenomena: (i) the word stems in the dimension have low discriminatory power, whence the classifier was barely able to distinguish relevant/irrelevant sentences, and (ii) a word stem may be considered important if it by chance occurs in the training corpus of the classifier in a small number of sentences, all of which are relevant to the dimension. Dimensions such as Hedonic, Pleasure and Affect and emotion which fully or partially encompas other dimensions tend to share most of the top places of the included subcategories. For example, nine of the ten most important word stems from the dimension Enjoyment and Fun were found among the top 15 important word stems in the encompassing dimension Ef- fect and Emotion which also rated other word stems such as “scari” and “frustrate” related to emotion, but not enjoyment highly. The notable exception to this phenomenon is the dimension Detailed usability that encompasses all measures of classic usability as well as mention of specific usability problems; this dimension has many highly ranked word stems relating to Satisfaction, but fewer highly ranked words stems also occurring among the other classic usability dimensions.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="221" page="7" column="2">2095</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="222" page="8" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="223" page="8" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx224">
            <content>
              <h1 class="table"> CLASSICUA BEVAN KETOLA FREQUENT</h1>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="7" page="8">
                <thead class="table">
                  <tr class="table">
                    <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                    <th class="table"> P</th>
                    <th class="table"> R</th>
                    <th class="table"> F1</th>
                    <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                    <th class="table"> P</th>
                    <th class="table"> R</th>
                    <th class="table"> F1</th>
                    <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                    <th class="table"> P</th>
                    <th class="table"> R</th>
                    <th class="table"> F1</th>
                    <th class="table"> Dimension</th>
                    <th class="table"> P</th>
                    <th class="table"> R</th>
                    <th class="table"> F1</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Memorability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Likeability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.69</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.47</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.56</td>
                    <td class="table"> Anticipation</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.61</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.06</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.11</td>
                    <td class="table"> Affect and Emotion</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.81</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.42</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.56</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Learnability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.93</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.08</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.15</td>
                    <td class="table"> Pleasure</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.77</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.44</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.56</td>
                    <td class="table"> Overall Usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enjoyment, Fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.92</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.58</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.71</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Efficiency</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Comfort</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.80</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.41</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.54</td>
                    <td class="table"> Aesthetics, Appeal</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.82</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.47</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.59</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Errors/effectiveness</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.73</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.05</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.09</td>
                    <td class="table"> Trust</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Detailed usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.67</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.54</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.60</td>
                    <td class="table"> Engagement, Flow</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.72</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.16</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.26</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.69</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.47</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.56</td>
                    <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.73</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.70</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.71</td>
                    <td class="table"> User differences</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.68</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.04</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.07</td>
                    <td class="table"> Motivation</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.80</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.51</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.62</td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Support</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enchantment</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Impact</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> Frustration</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1.00</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.36</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.53</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.72</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.54</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.62</td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.80</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.41</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.54</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"></td>
                    <td class="table"> Any Dimension</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.80</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.51</td>
                    <td class="table"> 0.62</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="225" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">CLASSICUA BEVAN KETOLA FREQUENT Dimension P R F1 Dimension P R F1 Dimension P R F1 Dimension P R F1 Memorability 0.00 0.00 0.00 Likeability 0.69 0.47 0.56 Anticipation 0.61 0.06 0.11 Affect and Emotion 0.81 0.42 0.56 Learnability 0.93 0.08 0.15 Pleasure 0.77 0.44 0.56 Overall Usability 0.00 0.00 0.00 Enjoyment, Fun 0.92 0.58 0.71 Efficiency 0.00 0.00 0.00 Comfort 0.00 0.00 0.00 Hedonic 0.80 0.41 0.54 Aesthetics, Appeal 0.82 0.47 0.59 Errors/effectiveness 0.73 0.05 0.09 Trust 0.00 0.00 0.00 Detailed usability 0.67 0.54 0.60 Engagement, Flow 0.72 0.16 0.26 Satisfaction 0.69 0.47 0.56 Any Dimension 0.73 0.70 0.71 User differences 0.68 0.04 0.07 Motivation 0.00 0.00 0.00 Any Dimension 0.80 0.51 0.62 Support 0.00 0.00 0.00 Enchantment 0.00 0.00 0.00 Impact 0.00 0.00 0.00 Frustration 1.00 0.36 0.53 Any Dimension 0.72 0.54 0.62 Hedonic 0.80 0.41 0.54 Any Dimension 0.80 0.51 0.62</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="227" page="8" column="1">Table 7. Automatic classification of dimensions. Results are checked for significance against a baseline classifier that assigns to the majority class. Significance is calculated using the non-parametric McNemar’s test with Yates’ correction for continuity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="226" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. Significant results (p &lt; .05) are marked in boldface.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="230" page="8" column="1">DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="232" page="8" column="1">We have unearthed a significant difference between software and video game reviews in terms of which UUX dimension they frequently mention. With the exception of satisfaction software reviews emphasize classic usability measures more than video game reviews, which in term put more emphasis on dimensions such as Hedonic, Affect and emotion, Pleasure and Enjoyment and fun. The notable exception to this difference is Frustration for which the difference between software and video games were not significant. The automatic classifier works well on commonly occurring dimensions, but tends to be too conservative even for these dimensions. There are ways of improving such classifiers, but our experiments suggest that simple off-the-shelf machine learning solutions are insufficient. When sifting through large amounts of material, it is easy to miss infrequent, but potentially important information, for instance the presence of information pertaining to Enchantment or Trust, and the classifier clearly is unable to assist a human expert in this regard. However, for some of the commonly occurring categories, the classifier may assist by removing sentences irrelevant for the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> dimensions, at the cost of some potentially relevant sentences being removed. The set of word stems extracted shows that some dimensions (e.g., Enjoyment, Fun) have associated vocabularies containing words closely related to the words used to describe the dimensions in the literature (e.g., word stems that are syn- onymous or antonymous to enjoyment and fun, describing respectively positive and negative experiences), but other dimensions such as Errors/effectiveness instead have vocabularies related to specific problems and errors such as “lag”, “glitch”, “imprecise” and “bug”. This illustrates the varied vocabulary used by reviewers when describing specific dimensions of interaction, and that the vocabulary is more varied for some dimensions than others. Our results strongly suggest that more complex information about how users express their feelings and experiences with situations and problems related to UUX can be extracted from reviews and other narratives. The results also suggest that the task of mapping the users’ utterances to specific dimensions of UUX is only partially possible to do in an automatic fashion and that some of these dimensions are associated to a complex vocabulary. When using sets of dimensions of UUX for practical purposes–for example for gauging which dimensions of a product are perceived to be important by users–then sets with many complementary dimensions such as FREQUENT appear to be more fine-grained and informative than other such sets. It may be possible for the UUX community to settle on a small, possibly domain-dependent set of dimensions, sim- ply by performing empirical investigations such as ours, or in more traditional settings such as usability tests.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="233" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Limitations</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="241" page="8" column="2">While our results shed light on the general UUX concerns of end users, the anatomy of the reviews we considered, possibly Internet reviews in general, does not seem to contain much detailed information about specific situations of use, or of measurements. No reviewer writes “The number of mouse click to navigate from the start screen to the functionality I want is 7, and that this is annoying”. While it is conceivable that a professional software reviewer, or an end user taking a conscious interest in usability, would write such a sentence, we did not encounter these. Thus, it seems highly unlikely that mining Internet reviews can supplant traditional usability testing or UX studies. <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Finally, the sentence-based annotation has acted as a conve- nient proxy: If a user spends 10% of the sentences in a review discussing matters related to Enchantment, it is likely evident that enchantment is a major part of his view of the product; but there may be other measures that more precisely reflect how much the user is occupied with different dimensions of UUX.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="235" page="8" column="2">2096</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="236" page="9" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="237" page="9" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx238">
            <content>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="8" page="9">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Learnability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Errors/effectiveness</td>
                    <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                    <td class="table"> Hedonic</td>
                    <td class="table"> Detailed usability</td>
                    <td class="table"> Pleasure</td>
                    <td class="table"> Affect and emotion</td>
                    <td class="table"> Enjoyment, Enjoyment, Fun Fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> Aesthetics, Aesthetics, Appeal Appeal</td>
                    <td class="table"> Engagement, Engagement, Flow Flow</td>
                    <td class="table"> Frustration Frustration</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> intuit</td>
                    <td class="table"> glitch</td>
                    <td class="table"> great</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> realli</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> graphic graphic</td>
                    <td class="table"> challeng challeng</td>
                    <td class="table"> frustrat frustrat</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> easier</td>
                    <td class="table"> issu</td>
                    <td class="table"> love</td>
                    <td class="table"> enjoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> great</td>
                    <td class="table"> enjoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> enjoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> enjoy enjoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> sound sound</td>
                    <td class="table"> addict addict</td>
                    <td class="table"> incompatibilit incompatibilit</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> learn</td>
                    <td class="table"> lag</td>
                    <td class="table"> realli</td>
                    <td class="table"> frustrat</td>
                    <td class="table"> best</td>
                    <td class="table"> bore</td>
                    <td class="table"> bore</td>
                    <td class="table"> bore bore</td>
                    <td class="table"> music music</td>
                    <td class="table"> replay replay</td>
                    <td class="table"> hardest hardest</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> figur</td>
                    <td class="table"> camera</td>
                    <td class="table"> worth</td>
                    <td class="table"> annoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> nice</td>
                    <td class="table"> love</td>
                    <td class="table"> frustrat</td>
                    <td class="table"> entertain entertain</td>
                    <td class="table"> realist realist</td>
                    <td class="table"> difficulti difficulti</td>
                    <td class="table"> perpetu perpetu</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> easiest</td>
                    <td class="table"> imprecis</td>
                    <td class="table"> nice</td>
                    <td class="table"> bore</td>
                    <td class="table"> worth</td>
                    <td class="table"> entertain</td>
                    <td class="table"> annoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> funni funni</td>
                    <td class="table"> voic voic</td>
                    <td class="table"> hour hour</td>
                    <td class="table"> insult insult</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> eas</td>
                    <td class="table"> bump</td>
                    <td class="table"> best</td>
                    <td class="table"> funni</td>
                    <td class="table"> problem</td>
                    <td class="table"> annoy</td>
                    <td class="table"> entertain</td>
                    <td class="table"> love love</td>
                    <td class="table"> soundtrack soundtrack</td>
                    <td class="table"> difficult difficult</td>
                    <td class="table"> injuri injuri</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> straightforward</td>
                    <td class="table"> bug</td>
                    <td class="table"> graphic</td>
                    <td class="table"> love</td>
                    <td class="table"> love</td>
                    <td class="table"> felt</td>
                    <td class="table"> love</td>
                    <td class="table"> amus amus</td>
                    <td class="table"> effect effect</td>
                    <td class="table"> depth depth</td>
                    <td class="table"> dissadvantag dissadvantag</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> easi</td>
                    <td class="table"> configur</td>
                    <td class="table"> sound</td>
                    <td class="table"> entertain</td>
                    <td class="table"> overal</td>
                    <td class="table"> sooth</td>
                    <td class="table"> amus</td>
                    <td class="table"> humor humor</td>
                    <td class="table"> beauti beauti</td>
                    <td class="table"> harder harder</td>
                    <td class="table"> nerv nerv</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> sc</td>
                    <td class="table"> suspect</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> humor</td>
                    <td class="table"> graphic</td>
                    <td class="table"> lighter</td>
                    <td class="table"> laugh</td>
                    <td class="table"> laugh laugh</td>
                    <td class="table"> anim anim</td>
                    <td class="table"> moment moment</td>
                    <td class="table"> fuel fuel</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> foreword</td>
                    <td class="table"> error</td>
                    <td class="table"> overal</td>
                    <td class="table"> hate</td>
                    <td class="table"> easi</td>
                    <td class="table"> workout</td>
                    <td class="table"> scari</td>
                    <td class="table"> excit excit</td>
                    <td class="table"> look look</td>
                    <td class="table"> complex complex</td>
                    <td class="table"> afterward afterward</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> practic</td>
                    <td class="table"> flaw</td>
                    <td class="table"> problem</td>
                    <td class="table"> sooth</td>
                    <td class="table"> recommend</td>
                    <td class="table"> grin</td>
                    <td class="table"> excit</td>
                    <td class="table"> sooth sooth</td>
                    <td class="table"> environ environ</td>
                    <td class="table"> nonstop nonstop</td>
                    <td class="table"> grin grin</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> simpl</td>
                    <td class="table"> crowd</td>
                    <td class="table"> recommend</td>
                    <td class="table"> felt</td>
                    <td class="table"> issu</td>
                    <td class="table"> frustrat</td>
                    <td class="table"> addict</td>
                    <td class="table"> grin grin</td>
                    <td class="table"> vivid vivid</td>
                    <td class="table"> tough tough</td>
                    <td class="table"> needless needless</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> angl</td>
                    <td class="table"> dodg</td>
                    <td class="table"> disappoint</td>
                    <td class="table"> hum</td>
                    <td class="table"> pretti</td>
                    <td class="table"> humor</td>
                    <td class="table"> humor</td>
                    <td class="table"> lighter lighter</td>
                    <td class="table"> audio audio</td>
                    <td class="table"> easi easi</td>
                    <td class="table"> la la</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> menus</td>
                    <td class="table"> biowar</td>
                    <td class="table"> definit</td>
                    <td class="table"> lighter</td>
                    <td class="table"> bad</td>
                    <td class="table"> chore</td>
                    <td class="table"> sooth</td>
                    <td class="table"> kinda kinda</td>
                    <td class="table"> atmospher atmospher</td>
                    <td class="table"> valu valu</td>
                    <td class="table"> unfair unfair</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> steam</td>
                    <td class="table"> ai</td>
                    <td class="table"> favorit</td>
                    <td class="table"> cute</td>
                    <td class="table"> disappoint</td>
                    <td class="table"> incompatibilit</td>
                    <td class="table"> felt</td>
                    <td class="table"> fell fell</td>
                    <td class="table"> color color</td>
                    <td class="table"> deep deep</td>
                    <td class="table"> plain plain</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> sacr</td>
                    <td class="table"> troubl</td>
                    <td class="table"> good</td>
                    <td class="table"> grin</td>
                    <td class="table"> fun</td>
                    <td class="table"> fell</td>
                    <td class="table"> fell</td>
                    <td class="table"> hilari hilari</td>
                    <td class="table"> visual visual</td>
                    <td class="table"> therefor therefor</td>
                    <td class="table"> flat flat</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> plasmid</td>
                    <td class="table"> semblanc</td>
                    <td class="table"> bad</td>
                    <td class="table"> excit</td>
                    <td class="table"> sound</td>
                    <td class="table"> rooftop</td>
                    <td class="table"> grin</td>
                    <td class="table"> workout workout</td>
                    <td class="table"> sceneri sceneri</td>
                    <td class="table"> keep keep</td>
                    <td class="table"> grow grow</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> experiment</td>
                    <td class="table"> mater</td>
                    <td class="table"> price</td>
                    <td class="table"> catchi</td>
                    <td class="table"> good</td>
                    <td class="table"> nevertheless</td>
                    <td class="table"> lighter</td>
                    <td class="table"> nevertheless nevertheless</td>
                    <td class="table"> sprite sprite</td>
                    <td class="table"> imposs imposs</td>
                    <td class="table"> fusion fusion</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> password</td>
                    <td class="table"> inconsist</td>
                    <td class="table"> interest</td>
                    <td class="table"> addict</td>
                    <td class="table"> learn</td>
                    <td class="table"> laugh</td>
                    <td class="table"> chore</td>
                    <td class="table"> zero zero</td>
                    <td class="table"> impress impress</td>
                    <td class="table"> engag engag</td>
                    <td class="table"> cheat cheat</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> straight</td>
                    <td class="table"> suffer</td>
                    <td class="table"> cool</td>
                    <td class="table"> workout</td>
                    <td class="table"> favorit</td>
                    <td class="table"> afterward</td>
                    <td class="table"> truli</td>
                    <td class="table"> intrigu intrigu</td>
                    <td class="table"> render render</td>
                    <td class="table"> tire tire</td>
                    <td class="table"> melodramat melodramat</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> thus</td>
                    <td class="table"> data</td>
                    <td class="table"> fan</td>
                    <td class="table"> chore</td>
                    <td class="table"> definit</td>
                    <td class="table"> told</td>
                    <td class="table"> engag</td>
                    <td class="table"> rooftop rooftop</td>
                    <td class="table"> model model</td>
                    <td class="table"> hard hard</td>
                    <td class="table"> habit habit</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> minut</td>
                    <td class="table"> confus</td>
                    <td class="table"> improv</td>
                    <td class="table"> tens</td>
                    <td class="table"> better</td>
                    <td class="table"> intrigu</td>
                    <td class="table"> tens</td>
                    <td class="table"> shatter shatter</td>
                    <td class="table"> cute cute</td>
                    <td class="table"> intens intens</td>
                    <td class="table"> gasp gasp</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> master</td>
                    <td class="table"> technic</td>
                    <td class="table"> fantast</td>
                    <td class="table"> incompatibilit</td>
                    <td class="table"> feel</td>
                    <td class="table"> nostalgia</td>
                    <td class="table"> kinda</td>
                    <td class="table"> told told</td>
                    <td class="table"> detail detail</td>
                    <td class="table"> sc sc</td>
                    <td class="table"> heck heck</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> smooth</td>
                    <td class="table"> prompt</td>
                    <td class="table"> better</td>
                    <td class="table"> fell</td>
                    <td class="table"> price</td>
                    <td class="table"> shatter</td>
                    <td class="table"> incompatibilit</td>
                    <td class="table"> scare scare</td>
                    <td class="table"> appeal appeal</td>
                    <td class="table"> painstak painstak</td>
                    <td class="table"> annoy annoy</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> nunchuk</td>
                    <td class="table"> resolut</td>
                    <td class="table"> perfect</td>
                    <td class="table"> afterward</td>
                    <td class="table"> improv</td>
                    <td class="table"> regardless</td>
                    <td class="table"> hilari</td>
                    <td class="table"> younger younger</td>
                    <td class="table"> realism realism</td>
                    <td class="table"> lenient lenient</td>
                    <td class="table"> babysit babysit</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> incred</td>
                    <td class="table"> respons</td>
                    <td class="table"> unfortun</td>
                    <td class="table"> nostalgia</td>
                    <td class="table"> interest</td>
                    <td class="table"> perpetu</td>
                    <td class="table"> workout</td>
                    <td class="table"> im im</td>
                    <td class="table"> pixel pixel</td>
                    <td class="table"> hardest hardest</td>
                    <td class="table"> insan insan</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> sensor</td>
                    <td class="table"> load</td>
                    <td class="table"> lack</td>
                    <td class="table"> nevertheless</td>
                    <td class="table"> cool</td>
                    <td class="table"> moneybag</td>
                    <td class="table"> creatur</td>
                    <td class="table"> cute cute</td>
                    <td class="table"> bright bright</td>
                    <td class="table"> gripper gripper</td>
                    <td class="table"> vito vito</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> gps</td>
                    <td class="table"> primit</td>
                    <td class="table"> pretti</td>
                    <td class="table"> stagger</td>
                    <td class="table"> would</td>
                    <td class="table"> everytim</td>
                    <td class="table"> cute</td>
                    <td class="table"> queue queue</td>
                    <td class="table"> stun stun</td>
                    <td class="table"> becom becom</td>
                    <td class="table"> slog slog</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> casual</td>
                    <td class="table"> precis</td>
                    <td class="table"> feel</td>
                    <td class="table"> intrigu</td>
                    <td class="table"> perfect</td>
                    <td class="table"> adict</td>
                    <td class="table"> nostalgia</td>
                    <td class="table"> tedious tedious</td>
                    <td class="table"> creepi creepi</td>
                    <td class="table"> interest interest</td>
                    <td class="table"> scaletta scaletta</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> applet</td>
                    <td class="table"> delay</td>
                    <td class="table"> qualiti</td>
                    <td class="table"> regret</td>
                    <td class="table"> qualiti</td>
                    <td class="table"> countless</td>
                    <td class="table"> nevertheless</td>
                    <td class="table"> jeremi jeremi</td>
                    <td class="table"> hear hear</td>
                    <td class="table"> most most</td>
                    <td class="table"> flavor flavor</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="239" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Learnability Errors/effectiveness Satisfaction Hedonic Detailed usability Pleasure Affect and emotion Enjoyment, Fun Aesthetics, Appeal Engagement, Flow Frustration intuit glitch great fun realli fun fun fun graphic challeng frustrat easier issu love enjoy great enjoy enjoy enjoy sound addict incompatibilit learn lag realli frustrat best bore bore bore music replay hardest figur camera worth annoy nice love frustrat entertain realist difficulti perpetu easiest imprecis nice bore worth entertain annoy funni voic hour insult eas bump best funni problem annoy entertain love soundtrack difficult injuri straightforward bug graphic love love felt love amus effect depth dissadvantag easi configur sound entertain overal sooth amus humor beauti harder nerv sc suspect fun humor graphic lighter laugh laugh anim moment fuel foreword error overal hate easi workout scari excit look complex afterward practic flaw problem sooth recommend grin excit sooth environ nonstop grin simpl crowd recommend felt issu frustrat addict grin vivid tough needless angl dodg disappoint hum pretti humor humor lighter audio easi la menus biowar definit lighter bad chore sooth kinda atmospher valu unfair steam ai favorit cute disappoint incompatibilit felt fell color deep plain sacr troubl good grin fun fell fell hilari visual therefor flat plasmid semblanc bad excit sound rooftop grin workout sceneri keep grow experiment mater price catchi good nevertheless lighter nevertheless sprite imposs fusion password inconsist interest addict learn laugh chore zero impress engag cheat straight suffer cool workout favorit afterward truli intrigu render tire melodramat thus data fan chore definit told engag rooftop model hard habit minut confus improv tens better intrigu tens shatter cute intens gasp master technic fantast incompatibilit feel nostalgia kinda told detail sc heck smooth prompt better fell price shatter incompatibilit scare appeal painstak annoy nunchuk resolut perfect afterward improv regardless hilari younger realism lenient babysit incred respons unfortun nostalgia interest perpetu workout im pixel hardest insan sensor load lack nevertheless cool moneybag creatur cute bright gripper vito gps primit pretti stagger would everytim cute queue stun becom slog casual precis feel intrigu perfect adict nostalgia tedious creepi interest scaletta applet delay qualiti regret qualiti countless nevertheless jeremi hear most flavor</region>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="240" page="9" column="1">Table 8. Informative word stems for each dimension in the video games and software corpora. Most informative word stems are at the top. Only dimensions for which the classifier achieved significant results are listed.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="242" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Future work</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="243" page="9" column="1">The data we considered were limited to two specific domains (software and video games), and the volume of data, while respectable, was insufficient to establish a vocabulary for all usability dimensions. Future studies must extend our work to more domains, and must consider a very large volume of data (a rough estimate based on our work: several tens of thousands of sentences). In addition, the idea of extracting vocabularies and associating features of texts or other utterances to dimensions of UUX can be applied to other domains, including spoken words at traditional lab-based usability studies. It seems worth to investigate the difference across product domains of the distribution of sentences among UUX dimensions found in this study. Likewise, it is interesting to link the presence of sentences pertaining to the UUX dimensions to attributes of the reviews that can be inferred otherwise, for example negative vs. positive reviews, or the helpfulness of reviews as voted upon by other users. Filtering and grouping of dimensions may be examined in greater detail in follow-up studies also investigating actionable outcomes. Finally, a better-performing classifier, or human annotation of a larger amount of complete reviews instead of isolated sentences may allow for analyzing the distribution of the dimensions we consider, on a per-review basis.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="244" page="9" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" page="9" column="1">1. Anderson, E. Customer satisfaction and word of mouth. Journal of Service Research 1, 1 (1998), 5–17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" page="9" column="2">2. Bargas-Avila, J. A., and Hornbæk, K. Old wine in new bottles or novel challenges: a critical analysis of empirical studies of user experience. In Proceedings of the 2011 annual conference on Human factors in computing systems, CHI ’11, The ACM Press (2011), 2689–2698.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" page="9" column="2">3. Bevan, N. Classifying and selecting ux and usability measures. In International Workshop on Meaningful Measures: Valid Useful User Experience Measurement (2008), 13–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" page="9" column="2">4. Bevan, N. What is the difference between the purpose of usability and user experience evaluation methods. In Proceedings of the Workshop UXEM’09 (Interact 09) (2009).</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" page="9" column="2">5. Bird, S., Klein, E., and Loper, E. Natural Language Processing with Python. O’Reilly Media, 2009.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" page="9" column="2">6. Bruun, A., and Stage, J. The effect of task assignments and instruction types on remote asynchronous usability testing. In CHI, J. A. Konstan, E. H. Chi, and K. Höök, Eds., ACM (2012), 2117–2126.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" page="9" column="2">7. Castillo, J., Hartson, H., and Hix, D. Remote usability evaluation: Can users report their own critical incidents. In Proceedings of CHI ’98, The ACM Press (1998), 253–254.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="252" page="9" column="2">8. Chevalier, J., and Mayzlin, D. The effect of word of mouth on sales: Online book reviews. Tech. rep., National Bureau of Economic Research, 2003.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="253" page="9" column="2">9. Constantine, L. L., and Lockwood, L. A. D. Software for use: a practical guide to the models and methods of usage-centered design. ACM Press/Addison-Wesley Publishing Co., 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="254" page="9" column="2">10. Cortes, C., and Vapnik, V. Support-vector networks. Machine Learning 20 (1995), 273–297.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="258" page="10" column="1">11. Csikszentmihalyi, M. Flow: The psychology of optimal experience. Harper Perennial, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="259" page="10" column="1">12. Folmer, E., Van Gurp, J., and Bosch, J. A framework for capturing the relationship between usability and software architecture. Software Process: Improvement and Practice 8, 2 (2003), 67–87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="260" page="10" column="1">13. Gamon, M., Aue, A., Corston-Oliver, S., and Ringger, E. Pulse: Mining customer opinions from free text. In Advances in Intelligent Data Analysis VI, vol. 3646 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Springer Berlin / Heidelberg, 2005, 121–132.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="261" page="10" column="1">14. Hassenzahl, M. User experience (ux): towards an experiential perspective on product quality. In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference of the Association Francophone d’Interaction Homme-Machine, IHM ’08, The ACM Press (New York, NY, USA, 2008), 11–15.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="262" page="10" column="1">15. Hassenzahl, M., Diefenbach, S., and Göritz, A. Needs, affect, and interactive products. Human-Computer Interaction 25, 3 (2010), 235–260.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="263" page="10" column="1">16. Hassenzahl, M., and Tractinsky, N. User experience–a research agenda. Behaviour &amp; Information Technology 25, 2 (2006), 91–97.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="264" page="10" column="1">17. Hennig-Thurau, T., Gwinner, K., Walsh, G., and Gremler, D. Electronic word-of-mouth via consumer-opinion platforms: What motivates consumers to articulate themselves on the internet? Journal of interactive marketing 18, 1 (2004), 38–52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="265" page="10" column="1">18. Hollander, M., and Wolfe, D. Nonparametric Statistical Methods, 2nd ed. Wiley, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="266" page="10" column="1">19. Hornbæk, K. Current practice in measuring usability: Challenges to usability studies and research. Int. J. Hum.-Comput. Stud. 64 (February 2006), 79–102.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="267" page="10" column="1">20. Hu, N., Pavlou, P. A., and Zhang, J. Can online reviews reveal a product’s true quality? empirical findings and analytical modeling of online word-of-mouth communication. In Proceedings of the 7th ACM conference on Electronic commerce, EC ’06, The ACM Press (2006), 324–330.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="268" page="10" column="1">21. ISO 9241-11. Ergonomic requirements for office work with visual display terminals (vdts)–part 11: Guidance on usability. International Organization for Standardization, 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="269" page="10" column="1">22. ISO 9241-210. Human-centred design process for interactive systems. International Standards Organisation, 2010.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="270" page="10" column="1">23. Ketola, P., and Roto, V. Exploring user experience measurement needs. In 5th COST294-MAUSE Open Workshop on Valid Useful User Experience Measurement (2008).</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="271" page="10" column="1">24. Kim, S.-M., and Hovy, E. Automatic identification of pro and con reasons in online reviews. In Proceedings of the COLING/ACL on Main conference poster sessions, COLING-ACL ’06, Association for Computational Linguistics (2006), 483–490.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="272" page="10" column="2">25. Korhonen, H., Arrasvuori, J., and Väänänen-Vainio-Mattila, K. Let users tell the story. In Proceedings of AMC CHI 2010 Extended Abstracts, The ACM Press (2010), 4051–4056.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="273" page="10" column="2">26. Krippendorff, K. Content analysis: an introduction to its methodology. Sage, 2004.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="274" page="10" column="2">27. Lutz, R. Changing brand attitudes through modification of cognitive structure. Journal of Consumer Research (1975), 49–59.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="275" page="10" column="2">28. Manning, C. D., Raghavan, P., and Schütze, H. Introduction to Information Retrieval. Cambridge University Press, 2008.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="276" page="10" column="2">29. McNamara, N., and Kirakowski, J. Functionality, usability, and user experience: three areas of concern. Interactions 13, 6 (2006), 26–28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="277" page="10" column="2">30. Miller, G. Wordnet: a lexical database for English. Communications of the ACM 38, 11 (1995), 39–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="278" page="10" column="2">31. Nielsen, J. Usability Engineering. Academic Press Inc, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="279" page="10" column="2">32. Olsson, T., and Salo, M. Narratives of satisfying and unsatisfying experiences of current mobile augmented reality applications. In Proceedings of ACM CHI 2012, The ACM Press (2012), 2779–2788.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="280" page="10" column="2">33. Pang, B., Lee, L., and Vaithyanathan, S. Thumbs up? sentiment classification using machine learning techniques. In Proceedings of the ACL-02 conference on Empirical methods in natural language processing Volume 10, EMNLP ’02, Association for Computational Linguistics (2002), 79–86.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="281" page="10" column="2">34. Preece, J., Rogers, Y., Sharp, H., and Carey, T. Human Computer Interaction, 1st ed. Addison-Wesley, Wokinham, England, 1994.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="282" page="10" column="2">35. Ryan, R., and Deci, E. Self-determination theory and the facilitation of intrinsic motivation, social development, and well-being. American psychologist 55, 1 (2000), 68.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="283" page="10" column="2">36. Seffah, A., Donyaee, M., Kline, R., and Padda, H. Usability measurement and metrics: A consolidated model. Software Quality Journal 14 (2006), 159–178.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="284" page="10" column="2">37. Shackel, B. Usability-context, framework, definition, design and evaluation. Cambridge University Press, 1991, 21–37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="285" page="10" column="2">38. Shneiderman, B., Plaisant, C., Cohen, M., and Jacobs, S. Designing the User Interface: Strategies for Effective Human-Computer Interaction, 3rd ed. Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="286" page="10" column="2">39. Sriram, B., Fuhry, D., Demir, E., Ferhatosmanoglu, H., and Demirbas, M. Short text classification in Twitter to improve information filtering. In Proceedings of the 33rd international ACM SIGIR conference on Research and development in information retrieval, SIGIR ’10, The ACM Press (2010), 841–842.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="255" page="9" column="2">2097</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="256" page="10" column="1">Session: Evaluation Methods 2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="257" page="10" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="287" page="10" column="2">2098</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
