<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>68b40fc29771793a7f65ec6db219b9909e7e65228560d11ee9396a15c3231016</job>
    <base_name>62rx</base_name>
    <doi>10.2752/175470710X12735884220817</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">The Design Journal VOLUME 13, ISSUE 2 REPRINTS AVAILABLE PHOTOCOPYING © BERG 2010 PP 137–155 DIRECTLY FROM THE PERMITTED BY PRINTED IN THE UK PUBLISHERS LICENSE ONLY</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2" confidence="possible">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Paul Atkinson</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Sheffield Hallam University, UK</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">There is a developing awareness of the interconnected nature of design, its connections with other disciplines and the convergence of different design disciplines as boundaries are increasingly contested and transgressed. Yet, to my mind, the most significant boundary currently not only being crossed but being dismantled is the boundary between professional and amateur, or more pertinently, between ‘designer’ and ‘user’. Recent design methodology has stressed the importance of taking a user-centred approach, but has not envisioned a position where designer and user are essentially one and the same. This change in perspective has the potential to transform design education, design practice and the consumption of design.</abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="6">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">As design practice became more specialized and the technology involved became more esoteric, amateur creative involvement in many disciplines became unattainable. Yet, emerging technologies today in fact offer the potential to reduce dependence on professional design, and afford access to advanced production techniques. Describing a recent exhibition in which visitors to the gallery had the opportunity to not only create designs for products on screen, but have them actually manufactured and displayed as a part of the show, this paper describes the choices made by designers and craft makers developing such systems, and explores the tensions between professional and amateur creative activity. An exploration is also made of the issues raised for design education and the potential impact of systems that remove distinctions not only between different design disciplines but also between designer and user. KEYWORDS: professional design, amateur design, generative software, direct digital manufacture</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="2" column="1">Introduction – Disappearing Boundaries</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="9" page="2" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="2" column="1">+ It some seems time to now me that enabled technological users at all developments levels to attain have quality for standards in the work they produce that were unthink- able only a few years ago. Whether it is in the activities of furniture making, interior decoration, the production of printed documents or the taking and printing of high-quality photographs, machinery and materials are available to the general public that often are not far removed from (and occasionally identical to) those used by professional practitioners. Consequently, these technological developments are moving design towards a Post-Professional era – a critical situation where the boundaries between professional and amateur design practice become so warped as to be all but indefinable and indeterminate. These boundaries, which appear almost imaginary to me now, have long been an area of personal interest, and the more I think about them and the more I explore them, the more confused and the more slippery they appear to become. In wishing to explore this dichotomy between professional and amateur design activity from a historical perspective, I proposed and edited a special issue of the Journal of Design History covering the phenomenon of the Do-It-Yourself (DIY) movement, which was further developed into the curation of a touring exhibition (Atkinson, <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 2006b). The articles in the special issue spanned in total a period of some three centuries, and explored an eclectic range of issues including 18 th - and 19 th -century women’s home crafts, the promotion of DIY through 1920s and 1930s women’s magazines, the Cold War nuclear fallout shelter as a focus of American DIY activity, the development and consumption of the Mirror sailing dinghy and the subversive production of punk fanzines. Together, these sections showed how, historically, all forms of DIY enabled the consumer to rail against the prescribed design edicts or social mores of the time, providing an accurate yardstick by which the popular aesthetics of design can be measured (Atkinson, 2006a). The rationale for this exploration arose from</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="11" page="3" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">a perceived need to generate a discourse around the inter- face between ‘design’ taken as a function of the activity of ‘professional’ designers and being part of an established cycle of the design, production and consumption of goods; and ‘Do It Yourself’ taken as its antithesis – a more democratic design process of self-driven, self-directed amateur design and production activity carried out more closely to the end user of the goods created. (Atkinson, 2006a).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" page="3" column="1">As the introductory article to the special issue explained, ‘Hist- orically, productive and creative activities of this kind have allowed consumers to engage actively with design and the design process at a number of levels, and to express a more individual aesthetic unbounded by the strictures of mass-production’ (Atkinson, 2006a). A strong element of interest here was that despite at times strong opposition from the professions themselves,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">DIY activity acted as a democratizing agency . . . giving people independence and self-reliance, freedom from professional help, encouraging the wider dissemination and adoption of modernist design principles, providing an opportunity to create more personal meaning in their own environments or self- identity, and opening up previously gendered or class-bound activities to all. (Atkinson, 2006a)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="16" page="3" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="3" column="1">And of particular relevance to the notion of boundaries between professional and amateur design practice, DIY was shown to ‘enhance people’s notion of themselves as an agent of design rather than merely a passive consumer’ (Atkinson, 2006a). An opportunity to further explore ideas around the impact of the professionalization of design came with the co-editing of a second special issue of the Journal of Design History titled ‘Ghosts of the Profession’ with Gerry Beegan, an Associate Professor at Mason Gross School of the Arts, Rutgers University in New Jersey. This special issue contained articles covering the dilettante design <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> activities of the Russian Mir Iskusstva group, the production of self- build homes in the UK, the influence of vernacular building practices in Italian modernist architecture and the open creative production of freelance amateur web designers. In the introductory article to the issue, ‘Professionalism, Amateurism and the Boundaries of Design’, we argued that given the porous nature of the boundaries between professional and amateur; these terms are impossible to define. We stated that:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18" page="4" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">professional and amateur practices are always connected, even when the relationship is one of repudiation. Professional practice defines itself by its distance from the unschooled practitioner yet, as the essays in this collection show, the vernacular is an inescapable part of modern design. At the same time, the professional is often a categorization that amateur designers reject, as a limitation to their creativity or originality.’ (Beegan and Atkinson, 2008)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" page="4" column="1">The rise of the design professions in the 19 th century was ‘associ- ated with modernity, rationality and scientific progress and embedded within institutions of control, training and regulation such as universities and professional associations’ (Beegan and Atkinson, 2008). We also noted the undemocratic nature of the extant situation, in that ‘Professionalization acts as a system of exclusion by setting up criteria that intentionally, or unintentionally, bar individuals and groups on the basis of money, class, ethnicity and gender’ (Beegan and Atkinson, 2008). In spite of this, we noted, ‘professional attitudes to [amateur design] activities have continued to oscillate between fear and admiration’ (Beegan and Atkinson, 2008). Both of these special issues raised the question of the value of the professionalization of design to design itself, although they were obviously not the first writings to do so. For example, other negative aspects of the professional/amateur dichotomy were described earlier by Philip Pacey, who wrote a thoughtful article for the Journal of Design History in the 1990s calling for design history to take non-professional design into consideration in the construction of historical narratives. Concerned that the increasing tendency to see design as an activity carried out only within a professional framework was marginalizing any form of amateur design activity to the extent that it might cease to exist, Pacey suggested that design history ‘should investigate what happens to non-professional designing when a design profession comes into being’ (Pacey, 1992). He noted that:</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="22" page="4" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">the emergence of a profession can perhaps be thought of as, to some extent, the removal, from the public sphere and from a common wealth, of certain categories of skill and knowledge. (Pacey, 1992)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24" page="5" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" page="5" column="1">Pointing to examples of lost proficiency among the populace of industrialized nations compared to the traditional transference of skills between generations in less industrialized societies, Pacey asked the question ‘has the professionalization of design deskilled or disempowered us?’ (Pacey, 1992). His examples ranged from the abilities of people such as the Inuits to hand knowledge down of how to survive in a harsh environment, the communities of Bihar collectively learning to develop bamboo piping, and the abilities of craftsmen in localized communities to develop products far more suitable for the particular requirements of their customers than those created by a global production and distribution system. Seeing DIY as an active consumer movement, Pacey highlights the rights of lay persons to propose improvements to existing products, to see the world as it might be rather than as it is proscribed – rights that publications such as Stewart Brand’s Whole Earth Catalog promoted but which the design professions would have them denied. Of course, as in Pacey’s examples, the driving forces for innova- tive and creative DIY approaches to problem solving often arise from hardship and necessity (something many of us know little about) rather than a desire to subvert the established order. There are numerous examples arising in newspaper articles from time to time of improvisations by underresourced people, of young farm children in remote rural areas able to repair and maintain tractors and other machinery – skills seen as quite remarkable in an age where we routinely pay for mechanics to get their hands dirty on our behalf. One remarkable example received wide publicity recently with the publication of a book about the life of William Kamkwamba, a boy from Malawi who, forced to leave school because of a lack of funds, found a DIY guide to making a wind generator, and set about making his own with discarded tractor parts, drainpipes and an old bicycle. His book, The Boy who Harnessed the Wind, is lauded by environmentalists as an example of how one person with an inspired idea can change the world for the better. It is an example taken to heart by the Barefoot College in India, which trains uneducated poor people to become water and solar engineers, architects and teachers (Vidal, 2009). Concerns about the ability of people to be self-reliant in the face of potentially diminishing resources are not limited to the developing world, but are also to be found much closer to home. The Royal Society of Arts in the UK have a range of projects underway under the heading of ‘Design and Society’, one of which is concerned with design as resourcefulness and self-reliance:</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="26" page="5" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">The RSA’s central mission is to foster good citizenship by closing the gap between our everyday behaviour and the future to which we aspire. To close this gap, contemporary society needs to be more resourceful: its citizens more engaged, self-reliant and collective in their striving. Yet a combination of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28" page="6" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">professionalization, bureaucracy and consumerism threatens to reduce our resources of common competence and as citizens we often appear to be less resourceful than ever. (Campbell, 2009)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" page="6" column="1">The emphasis here is not only around removing the barriers between professional and amateur design practice, but also improving the ability of amateur designers to be able to act as professional designers do:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">If it is true, as Design &amp; Society argues, that designers are especially resourceful, then in a new climate of austerity, in which less might be done to us or for us, or available to buy, it is expedient to make everyone more like a designer in their readiness to improvise. (Campbell, 2009)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="6" column="1">In other words, it is better to give people the ability to design rather than design for them. The project also suggests that the design professional might benefit from paying close attention to the driving forces for amateur design activity and the insights of users. Similarly, in the Netherlands, Premsela, the government-funded Dutch forum for design and fashion, are conducting a multiyear programme in the areas of amateurism called the ‘People’s Republic of Design’, with the intention of making design a more open-source activity. Their reasoning is that:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">More than half of Dutch people design things themselves in their free time. Conversely, a significant portion of people working professionally have no design training. Design and fashion are visible parts of popular culture and are situated between art, entertainment and folklore. The rise of the ‘amateur’ thus comes as no surprise. It was always there; it’s merely becoming more visible. DIY design is now such an everyday practice that producers and marketing agencies are developing all sorts of ways to facilitate it. Premsela believes alertness to changes in the surrounding world is essential for the proper evolution of design and fashion. With the People’s Republic of Design programme, Premsela seeks to help design and fashion develop into open cultural fields. (Premsela.org, 2009)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="34" page="6" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" page="6" column="1">What is clear from these explorations and examples, then, is that despite the aims of much professional design to disenfranchise the amateur user from productive creative practice, design has always been, and will remain an activity engaged in by all at one level or another, and there is in fact little benefit to be gained from erecting obstructive fences to participation by non-professionals in creative practice. Rather, as Pacey proposed:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="7" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">design history should not merely chronicle the separation of designing from making and the subsequent history of the design profession, but that it should place this in relation to a broader picture which encompasses the non-professional designing which preceded and has co-existed with professional design. By looking at its conventional boundaries in this way, design history can reveal not only what the professionalizing of design removed from the public sphere, but also what the design profession could give (over and above the dubious benefits of ‘designer’ commodities) to people at large. (Pacey, 1992) Pacey’s view was that: A future along these lines need not be a future without professional designers; it should rather be a future in which professional designers cease to defend designing as their exclusive preserve, and choose instead to enable, educate, and empower their fellow-humans to design and participate in the designing of the world they inhabit. (Pacey, 1992)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="7" column="1">These sentiments, around what the design profession could give to people at large, inform the rest of this article.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="7" column="1">The Role of Technology in Transgressing Boundaries</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="40" page="7" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="7" column="1">As reported in both ‘Do It Yourself: Democracy and Design’ and ‘Pro fessionalism, Amateurism and the Boundaries of Design’ (Atkinson, 2006a; Beegan and Atkinson, 2008), when the exclusion- ary boundaries raised by professional design are crossed, the profession understandably raises concerns. In the case of DIY, technological developments enabled the commercialization of previously restricted materials and products such as ready- mixed paints, mass-produced wallpaper and hardboard, and the production of a range of power tools, most notably the electric drill. These effectively de-skilled many processes and gave the user the ability to produce ‘professional’ results, causing professional tradesmen to complain to DIY magazines about their livelihood being threatened and even approach Parliament in an attempt to have laws introduced to prevent amateur DIY practices (ostensibly on the grounds of safety) (Atkinson, 2006a). Similarly, since desktop publishing software opened up graphic design to the public in the mid-1980s, professional graphic designers have regularly voiced concerns that the status of their discipline is being undermined. Given the expanding nature of the production and dissemination of such work in web-based material, often produced by highly skilled yet untrained creative practitioners who have no interest in the notion of ‘professional’ status, the situation is getting worse. Following the publication of Ellen Lupton’s book D.I.Y.: Design it Yourself (Lupton 2006), in which she aims to provide amateur designers with a set <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> of core design principles, the designer and design historian Steven Heller argued:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="8" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">By making our work so easy to do, we are devaluing our profession. I like democracy as much as the next person, but because of new technologies, the definition of ‘amateur’ in fields like graphic design, photography, film and music, among others, is being redefined. With everything so democratic, we can lose the elite status that gives us credibility. Lupton countered by asserting: Perhaps our credibility shouldn’t come from design’s elite status, but rather from its universal relevance to daily life. Not everyone is a design ‘professional,’ a person dedicated to solving complex problems and carrying out large, capital- intensive projects. But everyone can design elements of their own life, from their personal business cards or letterheads to their own flyers and wedding invitations. (Online debate, cited in Beegan and Atkinson, 2008)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="45" page="8" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="8" column="1">The really interesting aspect of this particular debate, which has been raging in the area of two-dimensional design for some time now, is that the very same situation is starting to occur in three-dimensional (3D) design with the introduction of direct digital manufacturing. The main technologies used in direct digital manufacture have been developed from rapid prototyping. This is a technique that uses a piece of computer software to divide a 3D CAD model of an object into a series of very thin layers – typically 1/10 th mm or less. These layers are then ‘printed’ on highly specialized machines in a variety of ways: either by using a ultraviolet laser to cure a thin layer of liquid photopolymer resin (Stereolithography) the cutting of a single layer of paper or vinyl (Laminated Object Manufacturing); the localized melting and placing of plastic (Fused Deposition Modelling); the use of a powerful laser to fuse powdered metals (Selective Laser Sintering); or the quickest and easiest method based on inkjet printing technology – 3D printing, in which a bonding agent is printed onto a powdered substrate. In all cases, the machine then prints the next layer on top of the last until a final 3D form appears. The cost of the different processes varies greatly, and so the required strength and characteristics of the model produced deter- mines which of the available techniques is used. All of the techniques though, are ‘additive’ manufacturing processes, in which largely only the material required for the product itself is used. This makes for a strong sustainability argument when compared to traditional ‘subtractive’ processes that start with larger solid blocks and machine away large quantities of unwanted material. Compared to injection moulding processes, which require huge investment in the <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> creation of tooling, there is no requirement to produce thousands of pieces to justify the economic outlay, and no requirement for each piece produced to be identical. This fact alone, as will be shown, is key to the impact of such technologies. These techniques, which allow the remote creation of one-off objects from computer-generated models, have been around for a number of years, having first been developed in the mid- 1980s. Initially, such systems were incredibly expensive, and only relatively recently have they become cost-effective enough to use outside of large-scale industry. At the present time, the costs of professional systems mean that these are still largely ‘controlled’ by the establishment – employed either within industry or provided as required by a specialist bureau service. Starting to appear at prototype stages, though, are a number of domestic desktop versions of 3D printers, and it is only a matter of time before anyone can have such a device connected to their PC in their own home. Domestic 3D printers range from ‘official’ machines produced by companies such as Desktop Factory (part of 3D Systems), which fuses plastic powder using a halogen light source, to perhaps more interesting and more subversive machines promoted by open- source projects such as <email id="49">‘Fab@Home’</email> or ‘MakerBot’. MakerBot Industries (2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://makerbot.com/)" id="50">http://makerbot.com/)</ext-link> advertise a kit for sale for the ‘CupCake’ CNC (computer numerical controlled) rapid prototyping machine, enabling users to produce high-quality components in ABS (acrylonitrile butadiene stryene) plastic, whereas <email id="51">Fab@Home</email> (2009, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://fabathome.org/)" id="52">http://fabathome.org/)</ext-link> provides the hardware designs and software free of charge, enabling anybody to build and use their own desktop rapid prototyper or ‘fabber’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). Their Model-1 fabber, which can be built out of wood or acrylic sheet, has internal syringes to allow self-curing liquid materials to be squeezed into a variety of forms. Examples on the website of pieces created by users range from items made in silicon or epoxy resins, to pieces made of icing, chocolate and even squeezy cheese! Even simple working circuitry has been printed using normal and conductive silicon. Some of the parts produced are poorly finished rough pieces, but it is early days, and even though basic in design, fabbers have produced fully functional plastic components such as a bicycle chainring. One of the most interesting of these projects is also perhaps the logical extension of this development as well as one that recalls commonly held concerns of the lack of man’s control over technology. In 2004, Adrian Bowyer of the University of Bath wrote a paper in which he described the basis of the Bath Replicating Rapid Prototyper project. The ‘RepRap’ (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://reprap.org" id="54">http://reprap.org</ext-link>) is a self-replicating rapid prototyping machine. A machine capable of reproducing itself. And its free. The RepRap team has made the design for the machine available so that anyone can make one, and use that machine to make another which can be given to a friend, who can use it to make another machine and so on and<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> so on (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>). The project was driven by an altruistic intent to ‘allow the revolutionary ownership, by the proletariat, of the means of production’ in a process he calls ‘Darwinian Marxism’ (Bowyer, 2004). In this way, Bowyer hopes, manufacturing capability can be achieved by even the smallest communities in the developing world.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> All of these machines currently produce simple pieces in a small number of materials. But more developed machines, universal fabricators, capable of far more, are not far behind. Machines that can print in different materials simultaneously, including ceramics, wax and metals as well as plastics; machines that can print conductive materials to create complex embedded electrical circuits easily; and even machines that can print electronic componentry such as transistors. None of this is science fiction. The processes have been proved experimentally. It is happening now. The potentially huge impact of these and other projects, is that they are examples of ‘disruptive technology’ – technologies that threaten the existing paradigms of production and consumption. These developments challenge the established order of things. So, when (and not if) the now familiar occurrence of the lay user producing amateur pieces of graphic design on an inkjet printer is replaced with users producing their own amateur pieces of product design on 3D printers, and the realization of this crisis hits home, the outcry from the design profession will, I am sure, be loud. The advantage designers have (or should have) is that they have been here before, but that this time, they can see it coming. If design takes steps now to become more closely involved with such technologies, it might have a chance to influence the ways in which such technologies finally appear and are used in the mass marketplace.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47" page="9" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="48" page="9" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="10" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="59" page="10" column="1">Figure 1 The Model 1 fabber from <email id="57">Fab@Home</email>. Image: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://fabathome.org" id="58">http://fabathome.org</ext-link></caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_010.image_01.png" thmb="62rx.page_010.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx62">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_010.image_02.png" thmb="62rx.page_010.image_02-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="63" page="10" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="65" page="10" column="1">Figure 2 Adrian Bowyer and Vik Olliver with a ‘parent’ and ‘child’ version of the RepRap self-replicating rapid prototyping machine. Image: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://reprap.org" id="64">http://reprap.org</ext-link></caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="66" page="11" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="68" page="11" column="1">Post Industrial Manufacturing</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="69" page="11" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="11" column="1">This is why, as a counterpoint to exploring these issues of boundaries from a theoretical, contextual or historical perspective, my practice- based research has been addressing the very same subject as a consequence of the pragmatic application of emerging technologies to design. For the past seven years, I have been leading a research group in the area of Post Industrial Manufacturing, in particular exploring the potential impact of randomly generative 3D modelling software coupled with direct digital manufacture. In collaboration with a computer programmer, an industrial designer and a designer– maker, I have been assessing ways in which such technologies might be created, adapted and employed by both professional designers and amateur users. One limitation of the systems described so far is that there is still an element of training required to create successful 3D CAD models in the specialist software required. Another is that the systems only allow the production of pieces exactly as they are created by the designers. Personally, I am far more interested in the input of trained designers being in the setting up of systems to produce objects that can be creatively manipulated by untrained users to create and produce uniquely designed objects. A recent manifestation of this interest was presented at an exhibition I curated in May 2008 at Hub, the National Centre for Craft and Design in Lincolnshire, UK, which showcased the work of Justin Marshall (Automake), and Lionel Theodore Dean (FutureFactories) <marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/>  (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>). The purpose of the exhibition was to examine the relationship between traditional forms of production and consumption and those proposed by the Automake and FutureFactories projects. As one of the display boards in the exhibition showed, Mass Production can be seen as a process of professional design, factory production of a standardized product and consumption by a passive consumer. Craft Design on the other hand can be seen as a process of designing and making by the craftperson in limited quantities in a workshop, and selection of a variable product by a knowing consumer. Post Industrial Manufacturing sits somewhere else. It is a process in which the design decisions are made jointly by the designer and consumer in a process of co-creation. The products are then created interactively through the medium of the computer and rapid prototyping process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>).<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> This process raises a whole series of questions. In the catalogue for this exhibition, I wrote:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71" page="12" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="75" page="12" column="1">Figure 3 Poster for the Automake and FutureFactories exhibition. Courtesy of Hub, The National Centre for Craft and Design.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="76" page="12" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx77">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_012.image_03.png" thmb="62rx.page_012.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="78" page="13" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_013.image_04.png" thmb="62rx.page_013.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="80" page="13" column="1">Figure 4 The Automake Process. Courtesy of Justin Marshall</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Should we strive to make manufactured products identical? Should the designer or craftsperson control every aspect of the appearance of the artefacts they produce? Should we place different values on designs created in their thousands and objects created individually? Should the involvement of the consumer in the creation of a product detract from or add to its value? Automake and FutureFactories are examples of Post Industrial Manufacturing Systems. They are systems that transcend the limitations and expectations of established industrial design and production processes. In their conception, they liberate the designer from ultimate responsibility for the manufactured form. In their execution, they liberate the consumer from the singular manifestation of design concepts. Post Industrial Manufacturing Systems have the potential to change the meaning of design. (Atkinson, 2008).</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="83" page="13" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" page="13" column="1">In the projects I coordinated, both Dean and Marshall worked alongside CAD specialist Dr Ertu Unver to develop software systems that can allow users to view various designed forms on screen. In the FutureFactories project, these forms are continually randomly mutating in real time ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>). This is achieved by the designer specifying an initial form and putting in place constraints within which various elements of the form can change, each element within its<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> own time frame and specified envelope. In this way, each time the form is viewed, the form itself is completely random and cannot be revisited. The user cannot affect the form itself or the mutation in any way, but can decide at which moment they want to ‘freeze’ the constantly changing form to create a unique, one-off item. Once frozen, the relevant files are created by the computer and exported to a rapid prototyping machine to be manufactured. In the Automake project, a series of individual building block units having the ability to be connected together in various ways are assembled together randomly by the computer within a variety of 3D mesh forms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>). These mesh forms can be selected and then manipulated, twisted and scaled by the end user to create unique shapes, and the particular building block units to be used to fill the resulting shape envelopes can also be selected. When the process is complete and the mesh envelope has been filled with a unique 3D model, the resulting file can be sent directly to a rapid prototyping machine for building in the same way as FutureFactories products. An alternative process is also used, which takes advantage of a ‘gravity engine’ within the software. Each building block is assigned physical properties of bounce, and are then let free to fill an open mesh form that has been manipulated to a desired shape by the user. Thousands of virtual building blocks then pour into the mesh envelope and bounce around before coming to a standstill in a completely random fashion. The process continues until the mesh form is filled and a unique product has been created (Atkinson et al, 2008).<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> One of the most rewarding aspects of the Automake and FutureFactories exhibition was the ability for visitors to fully engage in the process of creative production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>). A computer and printer were set up, and the Automake system could be tried first hand. The results were printed out as colour photographs and mounted on the gallery wall, constantly expanding the exhibition. Additionally, an industrial sponsor of the show actually manufactured a selection of items created by visitors each week, and these too were put on display. Visitors returned to the show regularly and brought with them their friends and relatives to view their artistic output, expressing huge levels of pride in their achievements, stating that before this, they had never done anything creative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>). It is in the nature of generative systems that at least some of the control over the end result is relinquished as systems run autonomously. The nature of these products is such that the basic<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> starting points are conceived by designers who specify the original forms and the rules of mutation or manipulation involved, but relinquish the appearance of the final product either to the computer or the user and in fact may never see the final product created. In this scenario, who has designed the product? Where do the boundaries of design start and finish? As the user has made an aesthetic decision over the final form to be manufactured, should their input<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> be considered part of the design process or not? Questions of authenticity, authorship and creative control are all raised here. Similarly, the nature of the objects produced is in question. Are they ‘designs’ in a traditional sense (as they have at least the potential to be mass produced), or are they craft (as they are one-off, unique pieces, albeit not made by hand). These problems of boundaries question the nature of design itself, and their impact will also be felt in the field of design education. The training of 3D designers will have to adapt to cope with these new paradigms of production and consumption, as traditional manufacturing processes will only be one of a number of available options. Rather than training designers to attempt to achieve ‘perfection’ as it were; to achieve the multiple replication of an idealized form, educators may have to enable designers to develop systems where the end result is to some extent unknown. It is a break between design input and realization of a design that education currently fails to address. It has to be acknowledged that we are already in an new age of open source systems, shared product development and free distribution. The old rules no longer apply. The effect of not taking this fact on board was succintly summed up by Tadeo Toulis:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="86" page="14" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="87" page="14" column="1">Figure 5 ‘Holy Ghost’ chair, 2006. Courtesy of Lionel Dean</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_014.image_05.png" thmb="62rx.page_014.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="88" page="14" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="91" page="15" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="92" page="15" column="1">Figure 6 A selection of RPed bangles. Courtesy of Justin Marshall</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_015.image_06.png" thmb="62rx.page_015.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="93" page="15" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="97" page="16" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="98" page="16" column="1">Figure 7 View of the Automake and FutureFactories exhibition showing the works of Dean and Marshall. The system that could be tried by visitors is projected on the back wall. Photograph: Phil Cosker</caption>
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_016.image_07.png" thmb="62rx.page_016.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="100" page="16" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rx.page_016.image_08.png" thmb="62rx.page_016.image_08-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="102" page="16" column="1">Figure 8 Visitors to the Automake and FutureFactories exhibition with their creations. Courtesy of Justin Marshall</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="17" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Failure to appreciate DIY/Hack Culture is to risk having professional design become as irrelevant to the contemporary landscape as record labels and network television are in the age of iTunes and YouTube (Toulis, 2008).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="106" page="17" column="1">Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="107" page="17" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" page="17" column="1">As we have seen, the boundaries between professional and amateur design, seemingly so solid, have in fact been constantly contested, transgressed and rejected. They have been seen as exclusive, obstructive and restrictive by those involved in amateur practices of DIY, and opposed from within by creative practitioners operating at a ‘professional’ level, who have seen such labels as a limitation on their freedom of activities. As well as being contested by amateurs and professionals alike, the boundaries between professional and amateur design are also being highlighted as a potential problem in sustainability terms, and a restriction on society reaching its full potential by official, government-funded bodies. It is clear from the research done and the work already produced that Post Industrial Manufacturing deals with a new kind of designing that has the potential to create a different role for the designer; where design decisions are made jointly or collectively by the designer, the computer software and the user. The most significant outcome of the research to date from my perspective is not the development of the generative systems themselves, but the creation of processes and procedures that enable individuals to engage in a form of design and production that questions their familiar relationship with consumer products (Atkinson et al, 2008). <marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> As far as the issues of boundaries go, though, the work produced in the ‘Automake’ and ‘FutureFactories’ projects by the designers, and more importantly by the amateur users of the systems, seriously questions the role of the boundaries between professional and amateur and designer and user. How we address this issue will have significant bearing on the future of the whole design, production and consumption process. Whatever moves we make to tackle this crisis, the fact remains that it is not so much a crisis for design, merely a crisis for the design profession.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109" page="18" column="1">Paul Atkinson</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="111" page="18" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" page="18" column="1">Journal Design The</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="18" column="1">Atkinson, P. (2006a). ‘Do it yourself: Democracy and design’. Journal of Design History, 19(1), 1–10. Atkinson, P. (2006b). Do It Yourself: Democracy and Design [exhibition]. Design centre north, Barnsley: 5 May–17 June 2006 and Museum of Domestic Architecture and Design, Middlesex, 25 July–10 September 2006 (a photographic record is available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.paulatkinsondesign.co.uk/)." id="113">http://www.paulatkinsondesign.co.uk/).</ext-link> Atkinson, P. (ed.) (2008). Automake and FutureFactories [exhibition catalogue]. Sleaford: Hub, National Centre for Craft and Design, p. 15. Atkinson, P., Unver, E., Marshall, J. and Dean, L. T. (2008). ‘Post industrial manufacturing systems: The undisciplined nature of generative design’. Proceedings of ‘Undisciplined!’ Design Research Society 2008 Conference, Sheffield, 16–19 July 2008 [online]. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www3.shu.ac.uk/Conferences/DRS/" id="114">http://www3.shu.ac.uk/Conferences/DRS/</ext-link> [accessed 20 November 2009]. Beegan, G. and Atkinson, P. (2008). ‘Professionalism, amateurism and the boundaries of design’. Journal of Design History, 21(4), 305–313. Bowyer, A. (2004). Wealth without Money: The Background to the Bath Replicating Rapid Prototyper Project [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://reprap.org/bin/view/Main/BackgroundPage" id="115">http://reprap.org/bin/view/Main/BackgroundPage</ext-link> [accessed 23 November 2009]. Campbell, E. (2009). You Know More Than You Think You Do: Design as Resourcefulness &amp; Self-reliance. RSA Design &amp; Society project pamphlet. [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.thersa.org/projects/" id="116">http://www.thersa.org/projects/</ext-link> design [accessed 23 November 2009]. <email id="117">Fab@Home</email> (2009). <email id="118">Fab@Home</email> [online]. Available at http:// fabathome.org/ [accessed 20 November 2009] Lupton, E. (2006). D.I.Y.: Design It Yourself. New York: Princeton Architectural Press. MakerBot Industries (2009). MakerBot Industries [online]. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://makerbot.com/" id="119">http://makerbot.com/</ext-link> [accessed 20 November 2009]. Pacey, P. (1992). ‘“Anyone designing anything?” Non-Professional Designers and the History of Design’. Journal of Design History, 5(3), 217–225.<marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> Premsela.org (2009). People’s Republic of Design [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.premsela.org/project/-/project-60/en" id="122">http://www.premsela.org/project/-/project-60/en</ext-link> [accessed 23 November 2009]. Toulis, T. (2008). ‘Ugly: How unorthodox thinking will save design’. Core 77, October 2008 [online]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.core77" id="123">http://www.core77</ext-link>. com/blog/featured_items/ugly_how_unorthodox_thinking_will_ save_design_by_tad_toulis_11563.asp [accessed 23 November 2009]. Vidal, J. (2009). ‘Tilting at windmills: The boy who harnessed the wind’. The Guardian, Saturday 3 October 2009 [online]. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2009/oct/03/" id="124">http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2009/oct/03/</ext-link> malawian-teenager-builds-wind-turbine [accessed 30 October 2009].</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="121" page="19" column="1">Boundaries? What Boundaries? The Crisis of Design in a Post-Professional Era</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="126" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Biography</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" page="19" column="1">Dr Paul Atkinson is a Reader in Design at Sheffield Hallam University. His background is diverse, having been a practising engineer then industrial designer before entering education to teach product design and design history. His research intersts in design practice are based around emerging technologies in rapid prototyping and direct digital manufacture, and in design history are based around the design development and consumption of computing technology.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="128" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Address for Correspondence</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="131" page="19" column="1">Dr Paul Atkinson, Reader in Design, Faculty of Arts, Computing, Engineering and Sciences, Sheffield Hallam University, City Campus, Howard Street, Sheffield SW1 1WB, UK. Tel: +44 (0) 114 225 6208 Email: <email id="129">p.atkinson@shu.ac.uk</email> Website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://paulatkinsondesign.wordpress.com/" id="130">http://paulatkinsondesign.wordpress.com/</ext-link></region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="132" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" page="19" column="1">My thanks go to Adrian Bowyer, Phil Cosker, Lionel Dean, Hod Lipson and Justin Marshall for their permission to use the images in this article.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="134" page="19" column="1">Journal Design The</region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
