<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>944d75f784c7c5a5812441d39b90e4d1ff7d37db7a0127ed4aef492bda73a3bb</job>
    <base_name>62o2</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0020-7373(91)90030-b</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">bat. J. Man-Machine Studies (1991) 34, 453-478</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Cooperative prototyping: users and designers in mutual activity</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">SUSANNE BP)DKER AND I(kl GRBNBEK</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Computer Science Department, Aarhus University, Ny Munkegade, 8ooO Aarhus C, Denmark (Received April 1990 and accepted in revised form August 1990)</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5" confidence="possible">In most development projects, descriptions and prototypes are developed by system designers on their own utilizing users as suppliers of information on the use domain. In contrast, we are proposing a cooperative prototyping approach where users are involved actively and creatively in design and evaluation of early prototypes. This paper illustrates the approach by describing the design of computer support for casework in a technical department of a Danish municipality. Prototyping is viewed as an ongoing learning process, and we analyse situations where openings for learning occur in the prototyping activity. The situations seem to fall into four categories: (1) Situations where the future work situation with a new computer application is simulated to some extent to investigate the future work activity; (2) situations where the prototype is manipulated and used as a basis for idea exploration; (3) situations focusing on the designers’ learning about the users’ work practice; (4) situations where the prototyping tool or the design session as such becomes the focus. Lessons learned from the analysis of these situations are discussed. In particular we discuss a tension between the need for careful preparation of prototyping sessions and the need to establish conditions for user and designer creativity. Our conclusion is that users and designers should prepare to learn from breakdowns and focus shifts in cooperative prototyping sessions rather than trying to avoid them.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction: background and motivation The ideas behind cooperative, collaborative, participatory, or participative design, are not new. In fact, a conference entitled Systems Design For, With and By the Users, held in Italy in 1982 was dedicated to the topic “Participative design” (Briefs, Ciborra &amp; Schneider, 1983). Similar ideas have, however, received new and more widespread attention in recent years. A conference held in Seattle, USA, 1990 (Namioka &amp; Schuler, 1990) was dedicated to the topic “Participatory design”. One aim of this conference was to explore the possibilities of conveying the so-called “Scandinavian model” of user involvement in system design to North-American settings. Also within the CHI and CSCW communities, ideas about participatory design have been of growing concern, notable in contributions such as (Bodker, Ehn, Knudsen, Kyng &amp; Madsen, 1988; Blomberg &amp; Henderson, 1990; Grudin, 1990; Johnson, 1990). This paper documents research within this particular field of CSCW which is more and more commonly denoted “Cooperative design”. We have our roots in a Scandinavian tradition of system development, and in a three year period we have been engaged in a research program Computer Support for Cooperative Design and Communication. Within this program we have undertaken several field studies of <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> cooperative design, in particular prototyping. From such field studies we have discussed how, in current system design, descriptions and prototypes are developed by system designers utilizing users only as sources of information concerning the use domain (Gronbaek, 1989; Bodker &amp; Gronbazk, 1991). However, we see prototyping with active user involvement as a way of overcoming problems that current approaches have in developing computer applications that fit the actual needs of the users. Such prototyping using wood and paper mock-ups, was successfully applied in the UTOPIA project (Bodker, Ehn, Knudsen, Kyng &amp; Sundblad, 1987; Bodker, 1991). In several subsequent smaller projects this approach was applied using computer-based prototyping (Bodker &amp; Gronbiek 1989; Trigg, Bodker &amp; Gronbzk, in press and this paper). Experiences from these projects led to proposals for a so-called cooperative prototyping technique (Bodker &amp; Gronbak, 1989; Gronbaek, 1990). Cooperative prototyping is meant to combine the use of computer-based tools for exploratory prototyping (Floyd, 1984) with approaches to design that allow users to participate in the modification of wood and paper mock-ups as described in Bddker et al. (1987). The cooperative prototyping approach aims to establish a design process where both users and designers are participating actively and creatively based on their differing qualifications. Analysis and design activities are more closely coupled by rapid development of one or more prototypes early in the development process. The initial prototypes help make the participants’ visions concrete. This requires them to relate to core work tasks, i.e. users’ current skills must be confronted with new technical possibilities. These alternative, possible prototypes can then be modified, thrown away, or built anew in an iterative process that increases the participants’ understanding of technological possibilities related to the users’ work tasks. The activities may serve one or both of the following goals: (1) Idea generation and exploration; and (2) work-like evaluation of the prototypes. When serving the first goal, the focus is on the cooperative use of the prototyping tool and existing building blocks to create a prototype or extend an existing one. When serving the second goal, the designers must somehow let the users experience a fluent work-like situation with a future computer application. This can be done in a simulated future work situation or, even better, in a real use situation if a fairly robust prototype has been prepared. The users first get introduced to its use and then an evaluation based on work-like use of the prototype is undertaken. Breakdowns (Winograd &amp; Flores, 1986; Bodker, 1991) in this use caused by faulty design, lead to immediate modifications of the prototype. Breakdowns due to other causes are handled in other ways; for example, lack of training is handled by further training and by setting up training programs for future users. Ideally, cooperative prototyping should be performed by a small group of designers and users with access to flexible computer-based tools for rapid prototype development and modification. The (possibly simulated) functionality provided, should make it possible to envision future work tasks (Bodker et al., 1987; Beidker &amp; Gronbaek, 1989; Gronbrek, 1990). In the project described in this paper, the primary prototyping tool used was HyperCard for the Apple Macint0sh.t This paper discusses experiences from a project that was set up to further<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> investigate cooperative prototyping in realistic settings, in this case so-called casework in a Danish municipal office. Primarily, the project aimed to develop ways for users and designers to experience future use situations. The outcome of the project was not as anticipated, since it turned out that setting up ways for the users to experience future use was much more difficult than in our previous cases. However, the prototyping sessions did stimulate creative cooperation between users and designers, which will be discussed below. Our process was well documented by means of notes, audio and video tape. In this paper we will focus primarily on prototyping sessions where the users and designers work with a fairly advanced prototype. These sessions were video taped, and the recordings analysed (see also Trigg, Bodker &amp; Grcbnbak, 1990) where we applied interaction analysis techniques. Since our primary interest is in developing tools and techniques for cooperative prototyping, we have set up a framework to analyse the various situations and roles that users, designers, prototyping tools, prototypes and sample data get, in and between prototyping sessions. This yields a much more detailed analysis than we have achieved in our previous work.<marker type="block"/> 2. This section briefly describes the cooperative approach to prototyping used in the project. The design project was undertaken together with architects, engineers and draftspeople in a technical department of a Danish municipality.<marker type="block"/> A technical department has responsibility for tasks such as long-term urban planning, environmental inspection and advice, and so on. Besides these tasks, a number of smaller requests from citizens are treated on a day-to-day basis. The architects, engineers and draftspeople call their tasks cases and we use the term “casework” to describe their work. Thus, we call the architects, engineers and draftspeople, “caseworkers”. There is one caseworker in charge of a case. He or she handles external contacts and brings in a number of people with specific skills. The department currently possesses three different kinds of computer equipment. They use terminal connections to a common mainframe running shared databases for a number of municipalities. PC’s are used for small budget and environmental inspection calculations and Xerox Viewpoint? workstations are used for advanced text and picture processing. The different kinds of computer equipment are badly integrated and the caseworkers feel that better computer support could improve their work.<marker type="block"/> Together with the caseworkers from the technical department we went through a process, designed to take their practice as the starting point and involve them cooperatively in system design to influence technology development in their work environment. Elements of this process included studies of the workplace, brainstorming on problems and ideas, and cooperative prototyping activities. For a<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> of such techniques refer to (Greenbaum &amp; Kyng, 1991) which strongly inspired US when setting up the project. Using a previous contact in the technical department we presented a project proposal aimed at trying out our cooperative approach to system design. The benefit for the department was that it would receive an analysis of the possibilities for integrated computer support for casework. The caseworkers agreed to participate in order to gain insight into possibilities for improving their work, although they did not at the time have money to start an actual development project. We started by improving our understanding of the work tasks. In this round we interviewed most employees from the urban planning and environmental offices and sent summaries of our impressions to all interviewed participants. We arranged the workshops according to the results of the interviews. The caseworkers chose among themselves five representatives to participate. We denote these caseworkers A, B, C, D and E in the following analysis. Caseworkers A, C and E are from the urban planning office, and B and D are from the environmental office. We used the future workshop idea (Jungk &amp; Miillert, 1987) as a frame for the two first workshops. The first day dealt with the critique and vision phases.7 The participants were each asked to focus specifically on a central work task from their daily work in the presentations. Before the second workshop we tried to focus the discussions by suggesting some specific problem areas. The caseworkers chose one of these, and in the second workshop we continued with the realization phase: The visions were made more specific with respect to the selected problem realizable in a prototype. Following this, two initial prototypes* were set up, one for each of the groups: environmental caseworkers and urban planning caseworkers. The idea of making two prototypes was to focus on the specific needs of each group, as well as to get mutual inspiration from two rather different prototypes. The initial prototype for the environmental caseworkers was partly made by a group of students who had also attended the workshops. The environmental prototype was first tried out by B and D in two consecutive half-day sessions. The urban planning prototypes were similarly tried out by A, C and E in one half-day session. The prototypes were augmented cooperatively in the workshops and again revised by the designers between sessions. Following this, the prototypes were revised again and built together into one. This prototype was given to each caseworker to try out for one hour. They were to start out from the work tasks that they had chosen as representative earlier in the processs. These tasks thus framed the evaluation, and we call them frame tusk.s throughout the paper. The researchers/designers were present in the sessions. In each session, one of the designers had the role as primary designer, i.e. he or she sat close to the caseworker(s) and the machine, taking responsibility for the interaction with both caseworker(s) and prototype. The secondary designer sat in the background observing, taking notes and intervening in the design activity when appropriate. Inspired by (Suchman &amp; Trigg, 1991) the five sessions from the final</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="7" page="1" column="1">453</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="8" page="1" column="1">0020-7373/91/030453 + 26$03.00/O</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="9" page="1" column="1">@ 1991 Academic Press Limited</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="10" page="2" column="1">454</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="11" page="2" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GR0NBRK</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="13" page="2" column="1">t All trade marks are acknowledged.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx14">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62o2.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="15" page="3" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOT’YPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="16" page="3" column="1">455</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="18" page="3" column="1">The project: designing computer support for casework</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="20" page="3" column="1">2.1. CASEWORK</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="22" page="3" column="1">2.2. THE DESIGN PROCESS</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="24" page="3" column="1">t All trade marks are acknowledged.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx25">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62o2.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="26" page="4" column="1">456</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="27" page="4" column="1">S. B0DKER AND K. GRBNBRK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">t</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="30" page="4" column="1">Refer to Greenbaum and Kyng (1991) for a discussion on the use of the technique in a system design setting. *The prototypes were built by means of HyperCard, Reports, a word-processor and a spreadsheet application that could be linked together using HyperCard.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx31">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62o2.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="5" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="33" page="5" column="1">457</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx34">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62o2.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="35" page="6" column="1">458</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="6" column="1">S. B0DKER AND K. GR0NBkK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" page="6" column="1">prototyping workshop were all video-taped to make it possible to analyse the problems and prospects of the prototyping approach. Results from the design process were documented in a report that was given to the caseworkers in the technical department, and it was approved that the caseworkers could get access to the prototypes if they wanted. <marker type="block"/> As in the following analysis we use the terms breakdown (Winograd &amp; Flores, 1986) and focus shift frequently, they deserve an introduction in the context of prototyping. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="39" class="deo:Reference">In Bodker and Gronbaek (1989)</xref> we described cooperative prototyping as sessions in which users primarily experienced the future use situation and secondarily participated in modifying the prototypes when breakdowns required it. We distinguished between two levels of breakdowns present in the situation: those related to the use process, and those related to the in-session modification of the prototype. Breakdowns in the use process occur when work is interrupted by something, e.g. that the tool behaves differently from what was anticipated. In these situations the tool as such becomes the object of our actions. Breakdowns in relation to the modification of the prototype occur when the fluent conduction of the design situation is interrupted, e.g. because the user loses interest in what is happening. By focus shifts we mean breakdowns as well as changes of focus that are more deliberate than those caused by breakdowns. For instance, a designer or a user may have prepared to raise some issues in the session. Openings, e.g. pauses, in the session may allow for a participant to deliberately shift focus. The participating caseworkers each had their frame task to work on in the sessions. These tasks were representative of the work done by the caseworkers, and we aimed to create prototypes which would simulate support for these selected work tasks. From the outset we aimed to have the prototypes tried out in a work-like situation lasting for an hour, following an introduction to and a demonstration of the prototype. We did not set up evaluation in the real work setting, because we knew that our example material was far too limited for that. We found that while the structure of the protype was sufficient to support parts of the work tasks, the sample data was too limited to keep the illusion of a work-like situation going for a longer period. In retrospect, viewing what went on in the prototyping sessions as a real work process is of little value: Only one or two of the caseworkers started out on “their” frame task. Rather the evaluation can be characterized as a step-wise hands-on evaluation of the prototype using the frame task as a guide for the evaluation. The sessions appeared as a mixture of caseworkers expressing expectations and trying out single features, and designers guiding the caseworkers through the structure of the prototype. There was an on-going vivid discussion between the designers and the caseworkers participating in the session. The activities ranged from guided tours of prototypes, where the caseworker asked questions and came up with proposals, but touched the keyboard and mouse only when asked, to situations focused on the design of computer-based materials-forms, reports, plans, check-lists, etc.-used in the work processes.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> The caseworkers in general never engaged in long-lasting fluent simulated use situations. Thus, our analysis shows few of the breakdowns in simulated use suggested by Btiker (1991). One example is that we used an asterisk “*” as a hypertext link icon attached to a word, but to follow the link, the word marked with the “*” needed to be selected. Often the caseworkers selected the “*“, and got an error message, confusing them. Other breakdowns occurred, as mentioned above, when the users lost patience with the designers’ attempts to fix something in the prototype. This issue will be discussed later. Although the project activities dispered slightly from our expectations, our material shows a richness of openings for learning that can be analysed in terms of breakdowns and focus shifts. But restricting ourselves to the kinds of breakdowns mentioned previously is far too simple to help us explain the rich variety of learning openings. Rather we look for different kinds of potentials for focus shifts and breakdowns in prototyping situations than described in our earlier works. Focus shifts and breakdowns reveal the unpredictability of prototyping sessions that cannot be avoided. In most cases they are not just “failure” indicators, but rather they lead to new insight and trigger new ideas to be explored. We will give a number of such examples from our prototyping sessions.<marker type="block"/> 4. Our analysis of the prototyping situation is inspired by the application of activity theory to situations that range from empirical studies of physicians work (EngestCm, Engestriim &amp; Saarelma, 1988; Engestram &amp; Engestrijm, unpublished data), to Bisgaard, Mogensen, <email id="46">N@rby</email> and Thomsen’s (1989) application of the framework to system development. The key idea is that the design activity is a learning activity. The future work activity of the users, here the caseworkers, is its main object. Prototyping is a part of this, where, in our case, the detailed conduct of the work tasks-to-be are in focus.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="38" page="6" column="1">3. Breakdowns and focus shifts</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx41">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62o2.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="7" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="43" page="7" column="1">459</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="45" page="7" column="1">The theoretical framework</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="48" page="7" column="1">I and Instruments designers’ (prototyping understanding tools, of users the activity, etc.1</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="49" page="7" column="1">The material, the current work activity</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="50" page="7" column="1">The design group (designers and users)</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="51" page="7" column="1">1 The outcome, the changed work activity of the users</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">2. The design activity. Designers and users act together with the mutual purpose of changing the work practice of the users by introducing a computer application. The instruments of this change include prototypes and prototyping, programming and programming facilities, and so on, as well as the participants’ mutual language, and their pre-understanding of the use and design activity.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx53">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62o2.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="54" page="8" column="1">460</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="8" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GRBNB/EK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" page="8" column="1">Some of the fundamental concepts from activity theory are necessary to qualify our understanding: Human work activity is the basic component of the theory. A human being takes part in a number of activities when working: getting food and clothes, making an urban plan, etc. Activity is bound to a purpose and it gives meaning to each concrete action, through which any activity is conducted. These actions are conducted consciously by individual human beings. Each action is implemented through a series of operations. Each operation corresponds to the concrete material (physical or social) conditions for conduction of the actions, and it is triggered by meeting with specific concrete material conditions. Operations are carried out by a human being in a specific situation, without conscious thought, to perform the actions which he or she is consciously aware of. This framework is elaborated on by Bddker (1991). At the same time we can look at the activity, action and operational aspects of any human undertaking, by asking why it takes place, what goes on, and how it is carried out (Bzrentsen, unpublished data). In Engestrom and Engestriim (unpublished data) patients’ sessions with doctors are confrontations of two activities in quest for a mutual goal: to diagnose a certain illness based on the symptoms of the patient. The doctor in his or her diagnosis uses instruments such as X-rays, lab tests, the understanding of different diseases, and maybe even medical literature. The patient has access to the symptoms, the pain, and so on, but he or she may also interpret these in terms of folklore medicine, etc. We find many similarities between this situation and our prototyping sessions. The common goal of the prototyping situation is to develop a computer application to function in work. The designers use instruments such as the prototyping tool, interview techniques, etc. They have an understanding of numerous technical issues relevant to the process and product, and some understanding of the work practice. The caseworkers, on the other hand have access to the instruments and materials that they employ in their current work situation. They have an understanding of this, plus ideas for how they want things done differently. We see this framework as one application of the general understanding illustrated by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>. We have found it fruitful to look at the actions that the different actors involved take as part of their mutual activity [in some cases there is a very subtle difference between a cluster of such actions and a separation into several activities, as described by Engestrom and Engestrom (unpublished data, figure 3)]. In general we find issues of sharing or not sharing instruments as well as an understanding of the intentions of actions to be important for our analysis. For example, when a caseworker is deeply involved in some details of his or her work tasks, and the designer is looking impatiently at the clock, we interpret the caseworker to be focused on the work situation and the designer on the prototyping session. We will identify situations based on the intentions and foci by which they are characterized. We see roles as a cluster of actions that share an actor as well as focus/intention. Sometimes, such a cluster could rightfully be seen as a separate activity, similar to what is done in the doctors’ case. When observing change processes in organizational settings, Engestrom (1987) bases his analysis on contradictions within the activity and between this activity and surrounding activities, since they constitute the basis for change: he looks at contradictions in how tools, objects and subjects are seen. He suggests studying the contradictions found between the tools currently used and the object created for</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx58">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62o2.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="59" page="9" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="60" page="9" column="1">461</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="61" page="9" column="1">Designers</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="62" page="9" column="1">Users</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="63" page="9" column="1">Subject</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="64" page="9" column="1">instruments Instruments A___A I Subject Object(s) Object(s) (Shared material)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">FIGURE 3. Activity theory description of design situations. In our case, several caseworkers, as well as several designers, can appear on the scene. In some situations, the designers, for example, take action together, in some they do not. Actions have intentions and contribute to the goal of the activity. Operations always take place under certain material conditions, and both, as well as the activity as such, are mediated by instruments.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" page="9" column="1">example, or between the norms that are part of praxis and the division of work. We use the idea of contradictions to understand changes in the design situation. The types of contradictions that are relevant for our above trianglebeside from those already mentioned, where for example the designer feels both part of a collective subject, and a need to act as an individual-are contradictions for one of the groups, between the instrument applied and the object on which one is focusing. In the doctor’s case, this could be situations where the symptoms of a patient do not fit the models of diseases the doctor has in mind. In our analysis we will look both for such contradictions, and for situations where a shift of focus occurs. In a breakdown situation, the object or focus of a certain actor changes (Winograd &amp; Flores, 1986; Bodker, 1991). In our case, a breakdown often happens to one party, resulting in a change of this actor’s focus, e.g. when the designer is changing the prototype. Something happens, causing the designer to focus on the syntax of the programming language. This shift causes a later contradiction when the focus has become different for the two parties (e.g. the caseworker believes that they are still designing screen images, while the designer is fighting to correct the syntax). Breakdowns are openings for learning, and in our unhampered daily activity, we can see some breakdowns causing a focus shift by which a daily activity becomes the object of our learning activity (Engestriim, 1987; Bisgaard et al. 1989). Learning can take place in deliberate learning actions as well, where for example one of the actors teaches some other actor about his or her work practice. In the same way, the design activity can become the object of our activity. <marker type="block"/> In this section we apply the framework on a variety of situation types and focus shifts experienced in the project. We illuminate examples of openings for learning that occur in cooperative prototyping sessions. We claim that these types of openings are worth paying attention to in cooperative design in general. The</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="67" page="9" column="1">5. Prototyping sessions: situations and focus shifts</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62o2.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="70" page="10" column="1">462</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71" page="10" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GRONBRK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">examples are grouped under headings that point to more general types of situations, but do not span all possible cooperative design situations.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86" page="10" column="1">5.1. FOCUS ON SIMULATING FUTURE WORK ACTIONS This section focuses on situations in which the primary focus is on the prototypes as a medium for establishing work-like evaluation sessions by means of simulation. We discuss the conditions for, and problems in, setting up prototyping sessions where users pretend to be in a future work situation. <marker type="block"/> 51.1. Fluent play of work-like actions Our goal in cooperative prototyping is to evaluate prototypes in simulated work situations. Bodker and Gronbaek (1989) describe working with dental assistants to evaluate a prototype patient record system. But the current project differs from this earlier case with respect to the success of establishing fluent work-like evaluation. The caseworker sessions, produced only short passages that resemble a fluent simulation of future work. In one such situation, the urban planning caseworkers (A, C and E) were trying to navigate in the hypermedia structure, combining maps and physical data on a certain area under consideration for buildings renovation, Caseworker A clicked with the mouse on compass arrows and buttons attached to scanned maps (Figures 4-6). The quality of the scanned maps was too poor for actual use, but he had no problem in pretending that he was navigating real digitalized maps linked to textual information. Later when the caseworker had left the maps he wanted to quickly pick up the most detailed map again. This was, however, not possible to do directly; he had to follow the links from the overview map and go several levels down. This breakdown led to a proposal for a facility to by-pass the map hierarchy. This facility was built into the next version of the prototype. It proved to be useful in situations where caseworkers were<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> resuming work on cases for which they could remember labels of detail maps. The hierarchical navigation was useful when they had to find a detailed map for the first time. The illusion of a fluent work-like situation only lasted for a short period of time; therefore discourses caused by breakdowns in the simulated use in such situations were few. One explanation of the difference between experiences from the two projects could be that the prototypes used in the dental assistants sessions were simpler than the ones developed in this project. But we see a more important difference in the characteristics of the work task and the need for sample data to get a work-like evaluation going. In the dental patient record system, little initial sample data was needed to get started on a work task. Also, registering patient data is a considerable part of a dental assistant’s work. This implied that an important work task with the prototype was data entry, which meant that the dental assistants bootstrapped the prototype with sample data when evaluating it. In the dental assistant project, the material conditions to make a work-like evaluation take place, were more easily brought about than in the case of the municipal caseworkers: Most casework in the technical department was concerned with the use of existing information that had to be gathered from paper files and computer databases. Entering new data into these files is a minor part of daily work. To let a caseworker get started on, for instance, modifying a local area plan required having access to nearly all of the long-term plans in the hypertext structure that we had built. These long-term plans consisted of several hundred pages of text. 51.2. Point-whe play of work-like actions When one of the caseworkers, A, went through his frame task with the prototype at the second prototyping workshop, it was clear that he was not in a fluent simulated<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> work situation. Rather, we saw a performance of a sequence of actions, that the caseworker associated with the frame task. The caseworker used an important instrument in the prototyping situations, namely his understanding of how the information he worked on was organized in the real work situation. This understanding encompassed both structure and content of a large body of text. While looking for information in the prototype, a fluent work situation broke down because sample data was missing. But the caseworker performed an advanced play, where he used terms from his work domain only when referring to the prototype. For instance he said “I need to look at the ‘preconditions section’ of the municipality plan” when he pushed a link icon? and jumped to the place in the structure where he expected to find that section. He was also able to abstract from some kinds of breakdowns that happened in performance of such actions. This can be seen from A’s reactions in a situation where the designers had entered sample data in wrong places of the structure. He said “let’s just pretend that it was swapped. . . “. Caseworker A maintained a focus on the frame task throughout the whole session. When he tried to perform an action that was not supported in the prototype, he continued on his own initiative a discussion of what he wanted to do with the prototype using concepts belonging to the work domain (these issues are discussed further in a later section). For instance he said at one point: “At this place I would like to be able to bring up a list of tasks that I have to do when treating a case (on a local area plan) . . . and I would like to be able to mark the task I have already done”. Only in a few places breakdowns in actions were turning the</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="75" page="10" column="1">over xXxXx</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="76" page="10" column="1">FIGURE 4. Sketch of top level map for simulation of map navigation.</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62o2.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="77" page="11" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="78" page="11" column="1">443</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="79" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">FIGURE 5. Scanned map for simulation of map navigation.</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx81">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62o2.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="82" page="12" column="1">464</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83" page="12" column="1">S. BQDKER AND K. GRBNBz‘EK</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="84" page="12" column="1">Berkridse:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="85" page="12" column="1">FIGURE6. Scanned detailed map and data fields for simulation of map and database navigation</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">t “Link icon” is the hypertext term (Conklin, 1987) for the button to push when the user wants to follow a link to a destination node in the network.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx88">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62o2.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="89" page="13" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="90" page="13" column="1">465</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" page="13" column="1">focus to the prototype as an object detached from the frame task. These are cases where he needed instructions for how to continue. For instance he at some point wanted to follow a hypertext link backwards, and asked “which button should I push?” and when he got the answer he pushed the button and replied: “Oh, it is this arrow I have to push”. <marker type="block"/> 5.1.3. Discussion The sessions with A show that a fluent work like performance of the work task was difficult to set up at this early stage in the project, mainly due to lack of sample data. However, evaluation activities based on the frame task helped maintain a focus on the work task in a prototyping session. The close focus on work tasks brought up important issues such as the deficiencies of the hierarchical map navigation. The fact that the overall activity was design and not use, did not seem to disturb A. To some extent he used his paper-based materials when the materials were not available on the computer. There is no doubt that he knew he was in a learning situation, and not all the material conditions were as they should be, but the setting allowed him to try out certain future actions anyway. Thus we consider the future work situations with computer support much closer than is found in traditional evaluation. For instance Baecker and Buxton (1987) and Monk (1987) propose controlled experiments to collect data on specific features of prototypes. They take the prototype and its individual facilities as the starting point, not the work task which it is going to support. Our general conclusion from the two examples is that it is important to simulate aspects of the future use situation to some extent. The main purpose of this is to try out the future material conditions set up by the computer application. It is less important though to make this simulation work-like in all respects. Actually, we have seen demonstrated that a play-like situation may be useful.<marker type="block"/> Some situations from the prototyping sessions resemble brainstorming carried out by caseworkers and designers using the computer and prototype as instruments.? The prototype and computer are used to explore technological possibilities and for experimenting with design possibilities. In all such situations the caseworkers are articulating their work tasks rather than doing them.<marker type="block"/> The session with one of the caseworkers, B, quickly turned from a work-like evaluation to idea generation and augmentation of the prototype. The frame task was an environmental case: checking hidden oil tanks and drinking water conditions on a site. To get started on the task, B found the data of a fictitious site with a key-word search on the database. She examined the sample data already there and said “how do I find the site map ?” We explained that we had not prepared, i.e. scanned, a site map for this task. Instead she explained how she would examine the site map, and she entered some fictitious notes reflecting the examination of the site t Jordan, Keller, Tucker Jc Vogel (1989) introduced the term “software storming” for a mixture of<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> map and related data. In the middle of her formulation of a request for the name of the owner of the site, she said: “In general we would like to be able to subtract a ‘list of requests’ on house owners-nowadays we have to remember the requests ourselves”. B on her own initiative also took the mouse and attempted to use the existing key-word search function to search for house-owners who have had a demand given to them by the environmental office. Now the focus shifted from the frame task to a discussion of how a reminder facility could be designed. A first attempt on designing the facility was made by the primary designer who picked up the mouse, entered “Design mode” in the tool,? reorganized existing fields/buttons, and added two new fields “Deadline for fulfilling request” and “Description of request” to the current screen image. B tried to reformulate the request and used the fields. Then it was proposed that for a following session we prepare a report to generate the list of reminders on requests with deadlines in the current month. We also noted that the reminder facility might be useful in general for the tasks that the other environmental caseworker, D, was performing. But, B did not know at what level D made his request, thus we decided to discuss this issue with D in another session. We turned the focus back to the initial frame task. Later in the same session B needed information from the Building File, a file currently kept on paper. B pushed the button that brought her to the current representation of the Building File in the prototype. B examined the data on the screen and realized that there was no representation of the change applications/permissions that had been made for a building. B explained that each applications/permissions case consisted of a folder with letters and architectural drawings sent in by the various house owners. According to B it would be of no use to enter this extensive material into the computer, but it would be nice to have a list of all the cases on a building and for each case a brief abstract describing the case and telling where to find the material in the paper files. We started to design that facility. The primary designer entered “Design Mode”, and used some existing application-oriented objects. One of these objects was a scrollable item list field that could be used as an index of abstracts for the applications/permissions cases. An instance of this object was placed on the screen. B suggested a prototypical headline for an applications/permissions case. We added an “abstract” screen carrying this headline and linked that to the item on the list. Now the abstract could be brought up by a single click on the item in a list on the overview screen. B tried that operation and seemed satisfied with the solution. The example described here shows that B, the caseworker, got a number of ideas when confronting the frame task with a sketchy prototype that was supposed to support her work. The focus shifts in the session were not caused by breakdowns in the simulated use situation, but rather by ideas that came to B when she had to imagine the prototype being part of her future workplace. This way, the prototype was used to create visions concerning the future computer application and changed t We had customized our HyperCard environment with a “Status” menu that allowed us to make quick switches between “Design mode” and “Use mode”. In “Use mode” the environment was restricted to consist of only menus and windows that were familiar to the caseworkers. In “Design mode” two windows and some menus that among other things made a number of application oriented and general objects available for reuse/specialization in the session. Unfortunately HyperCard did not allow us to remove all the system menus, such as “File”, “Edit”, and “Go” that were not familiar to the caseworkers. But in “Use mode” the complexity of the screen-layout was reduced considerably.<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> work practice. Some of the proposals and ideas might have come across in a paper-based design session, but it seems as if the confrontation with the prototype triggered a more extensive idea generation, One explanation could be that the prototype was viewed as an object to be developed in conjunction with investigation of the frame task and not viewed as something complete that was brought into the office.<marker type="block"/> 5.2.2. Going beyond the current prototype In the first urban planning workshop with the caseworkers (A, C, E) we were designing computer support for urban and area planning. We considered A’s frame task on local area planning for an area where the building of a small airport was proposed. The initial prototype was made to try out how to organize the information in database fields on a series of screen images. A general issue was raised by A: when working with a local area plan it was often necessary to look up certain issues in the long-term plans. These were kept as textual/graphical descriptions in paper folders. In general the caseworkers found it hard to trace particular issues throughout these folders. Moreover, it was necessary to keep track of changes made between major revisions of the long-term plans. Such changes often had implications for a number of paragraphs, tables and figures throughout the plans. It would be useful for the caseworkers to be reminded of such add-ons when retrieving information, This general issue coined a discussion on how to represent large text and graphics documents in combination with a conventional database design. For the designers it seemed obvious that some kind of hypertext system was needed and one of the designers went to the blackboard and showed how sections and regions within sections of the long-term plan could be linked together as hypertext. At the same time, the other designer had opened a Guide hypertext document on the workstation.? A brief demo of Guide was given and one of the caseworkers tried to follow some links in the document. This example shows that it was possible for the caseworkers to relate already articulated problems concerning the material conditions and instruments of the work activity to the use of a prototype, and to be creative with respect to changing the situation. The conclusion of this session was that the designers, for the next session, should design a hypertext structure representing the long-term plan. In the second prototyping workshop the caseworkers were provided with this hypertext structure representing the long-term plan and they worked rather painlessly with hypertext facilities without much further introduction.<marker type="block"/> 5.2.3. Discussion The situations described in this section can be seen as examples of what Ehn (1988, pp. 451-453) calls creative transcendence of tradition. The caseworkers were able to go beyond their traditional skills when confronted with new technological possibilities such as prototypes and example applications. Moreover, the situations show that the caseworkers often take the initiative to transcend their own skills in such prototyping sessions. t Guide is a hypertext system running on the Apple Macintosh. We acknowledge all trade marks.<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> In the prototype modification situations the prototype had the role of an instrument to facilitate a concrete discussion of visions. Both caseworkers and designers were pointing at objects in the prototype and various facilities were discussed. Instead of using terms from the application domain there was a higher frequency of computer-oriented terms such as “screen image”, “fields”, “buttons” and “arrows”. This distance to the frame task was reduced a bit when reusing parts of the prototype already familiar to the caseworkers, but rarely were the parts to be reused referred to with a name familiar to the caseworkers. For instance B could recognize how to use the scrollable item list field when she saw it, but she did not have a name for it, because it did not correspond to something familiar to her. When hypertext was introduced the caseworkers easily adapted to the idea of browsing through text, using buttons, instead of key-word search facilities that were otherwise more common in the computer systems they were familiar with. The designers’ introduction of hypertext represented a more advanced form of text representation than what the caseworkers themselves knew about, or would have imagined to be implementable, on the computer. At the same time, however, there was a clear need to impose a structure on the current texts to support efficient traversal and to remind of crossing dependencies.<marker type="block"/> In several situations the focus is on the caseworkers current work practice. These are situations where caseworkers and designers use prototypes as instruments to trigger a further investigation of the current work practice. In these situations the caseworkers were articulating their work tasks rather than performing them.<marker type="block"/> C, B and D did not simulate the future use of the prototype very much. Rather the frame task was talked through while the prototype was examined. The role of the prototype became that of an object that was brought in to illustrate how certain parts of the frame task could be supported with a computer. The prototype never became an instrument for work actions. An example of such situations was seen in sessions with D who did environmental inspection of companies in the municipality. D’s frame task for the session was “collecting information before an inspection visit at a company”. The sessions started out with the designer giving a brief guided tour in the relevant part of the prototype. Then the initiative was given to D by the designer asking: “Show what you would start out with when you collect information for an inspection visit?“. D then took over and said “First I’m checking whether the company has a ‘Chapter 5 approval’ and then I check whether I have made an earlier inspection visit at the company. . . -1 guess I’ll enter this ‘Chapter 5 approval’ file”. D clicked the mouse on the corresponding item in the table of contents menu of the prototype. When the screen image came up D sat thinking for a while and said: “This is only an overview of approvals given-how do I find the detailed information? There ought to be information about heating technology, chimney size and the like!” The designer thought for a short while and said: “But this information is kept in the file of ‘inspection visit reports’-have a look !” The designer grabbed the mouse and jumped to the file of ‘inspection visit reports’. D said: “Oh here they are. . . but this<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> information is really needed in both places, because we have approvals on companies we haven’t formally inspected yet!“. This way we recognized a need for making links between “Chapter 5 approval” documents and “inspection visit reports”, and it was discussed how this could be done after the session. From this breakdown the session shifted to talking through the frame task as D could recall it, detached from his performance of the work. During this talk-through we experienced other focus shifts that moved us into other kinds of situations. On the one hand we moved into situations where we modified and augmented the prototype. On the other hand we also experienced the need for getting more information on D’s current frame task. This led to an interview-like situation with very little focus on future work; the kind of situation discussed in a following section. In these talk-through situations the caseworker primarily demonstrated his own current role when going through a typical work task-the frame task, by thinking aloud. This kind of thinking aloud is slightly different from the way it is practised in human-interface studies by for example Mack, Lewis and Carroll (1987). In those studies the designers define a new task that the users are going to learn and the designers want to study how they learn the task, e.g. by using a word processor. In our prototyping sessions the caseworkers were going through a task they were already familiar with, even though they were detached from their normal performance of the task. The designers on the other hand were listening to understand the work task, to ask questions, and to introduce relevant parts of the prototype. Focus shifts or breakdowns typically occurred when contradictions in the caseworkers and the designers understanding of the frame task occurred. Some of these contradictions related to the prototype as described above, but they occurred as well when the caseworker progressed in the detailed talk-through of the frame task. With the frame task it is possible to go through the work actions and articulate and investigate not only questions of what has been done, or should be done, but also questions of how and why.<marker type="block"/> 5.3.2. Caseworkers teach designers about their work practice In some situations the focus shifted from design towards more analysis-like situations, because of contradictions between the participants’ understanding of the frame task. An example of such a situation occurred in the session with D when he was examining the “inspection visit reports”. He realized that space was only allocated for making one query per visit. D explained that he typically made a number of queries on particular aspects such as chimney size or heating. The current forms used did not support this use and D made notes on the margin. This showed a misconception in the designers understanding of the queries. The focus of the session shifted to a situation where the caseworker was teaching the designers about his work. The designers were listening and occasionally questioning the caseworker about the different ways in which queries were used. In Trigg, Bodker and Gronbak (1990) a more detailed video analysis of the session with caseworker E is used. Among other things studied, was how a confrontation with a prototype inspired E to tell short anecdotes from her work. These anecdotes illustrated her daily work more generally than the frame task. This</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="93" page="13" column="1">5.2. FOCUS ON IDEA EXPLORATION</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="95" page="13" column="1">5.21. Augmenting the current prototype</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="97" page="13" column="1">rapid prototyping and brainstorming techniques.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx98">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62o2.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="14" column="1">466</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100" page="14" column="1">SB0DKER</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="101" page="14" column="1">AND K. GRQ)NB/EK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx103">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62o2.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="104" page="15" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="105" page="15" column="1">467</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="109" page="15" column="1">Compared with HyperCard it is better to illustrate hypertext, because it resembles a word-processor extended by linking facilities. It mainly supports replacement links and pop-up notes as discussed in Conklin (1987) and Bannon and Grenbaek (1989).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx110">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62o2.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="111" page="16" column="1">S. BODKER AND K. GR0NBA5K</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112" page="16" column="1">468</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="114" page="16" column="1">5.3. FOCUS ON CURRENT WORK PRACTICE</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="116" page="16" column="1">5.3.1. Talking through the frame tasks</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx118">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62o2.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="119" page="17" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="120" page="17" column="1">469</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx123">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62o2.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="124" page="18" column="1">470</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="125" page="18" column="1">S. B0DKER AND K. GRQNBRK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">was a similar but more indirect way of teaching the designers about her work practice.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" page="18" column="1">53.3. Discussion In the above situations the frame task and the prototype were used in different ways to help the caseworkers articulate problems with their current work practice. The situations were different with respect to the role of the prototype and the frame task. In the first one, the prototype was used to provoke articulation of work actions closely related to the frame task. In the second, the caseworkers taught the designers about their work. In these situations the designers got a pupil’s role. The prototype received the role of an instrument to trigger the caseworkers’ teaching and story-telling about their current work practice. These examples also show situations where it could have been useful to supplement the prototyping technique with other means to better document the caseworkers’ articulation of their work. For instance, the anecdotes could easily be overheard by the designers, and making basic investigations of current work practice in front of the prototype can cause premature changes to the prototype. <marker type="block"/> We often experienced breakdowns in the session, such as breakdowns that moved all participants’ foci towards the conducting of the session, the prototype, or the prototyping tool. These focus shifts are of little use as openings for learning with respect to the actual system to be designed. But with respect to improving the designers’ understanding of how to prepare prototypes and improve prototyping tools they can be quite useful. We give examples of this kind of focus shifts. In several situations we also see focus shifts when the designers are concerned about getting the session moving. These shifts are necessary to keep within time limits, but they can, as we shall see, easily disturb the prototyping activity.<marker type="block"/> 54.1. Lacking tool support In situations where the prototype was augmented, breakdowns occurred due to a mismatch between the designers ability to make modifications and the caseworkers needs. An example of such a situation happened with respect to use of prepared objects in the prototype. We had prepared a number of general objects such as general search buttons that could be parametrized, and fields with special hypertext supporting features. These objects were intended to be used in already existing screen images,? but a breakdown occurred when we wanted to start from scratch with the design of a new screen image. We needed a blank HyperCard screen that inherited properties similar to already existing screens. However, the tool was set up in such a way that it was not possible to get a blank screen, preserving for instance the browsing capabilities that all the screens in the application were supposed to have. One would either get a blank screen with no functionality, or a screen with contents similar to the current screen in use. This breakdown taught us to be better prepared for following sessions by providing blank screen images that preserved operational properties for each screen type we could expect to reuse for design from scratch. + “Cards” in HyperCard.<marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> Breakdowns due to regular programming bugs and misplaced sample data occurred as well. Some of these were simple bugs in details that caused little trouble. Either the fixing was simple or the bug could be ignored when continuing the session while still focusing on the users’ frame task. In a session with one of the architects we had swapped two pieces of sample data in the hypertext structure, but after realizing that it was not his fault he said on his own initiative: “let’s just pretend they are swapped’. Other bugs though were more serious. For instance breakdowns happened (see also Bodker &amp; Gronbazk, 1989) when we were evaluating a report design made before the session. The report generator would not select the data requested in the query. After three attempts, the report generator created a system bug that required reinstallation of the program in order to get started again. Meanwhile, the caseworker, who at the beginning was interested and active, became more and more passive as the designer moved into areas of the prototype that the caseworker did not understand. In that situation we were forced to shift focus and jump to another part of the prototype and continue evaluation there. The focus shifts described here give the prototype the role of an instrument that does not function well; neither as support for casework nor as a medium for the design activity. The designer becomes a repair person, a programmer, who uses only computer specific instruments to solve problems outside the scope of the caseworkers understanding. The caseworkers become passive observers who watch a professional completing a compilated task. These kind of breakdowns are not very productive with respect to improved understanding of computer support for casework. in this project the prototype was not aimed at becoming part of a final working system; hence lixing the programming bugs had little impact on the final system implementation. Thus these kinds of breakdowns should ideally be kept to minimum in cooperative prototyping sessions. Careful preparation and good understanding of what can be done in sessions to get around such breakdowns without spoiling the purpose of the session is needed on the designer’s side of the table. This issue is developed further in section 6.<marker type="block"/> 54.3. Conducting the session In several situations we saw focus shifts towards the conduction of the session. Frequently the designer who had the secondary role in the session realized that the session activities did not serve their purpose and started intervening into the situation. In one example, the caseworker A was deeply involved in typing some piece of information into a text node of the hypertext structure, whereas the designers got impatient and finally interrupted the caseworker. The caseworker was concerned with correctness of spelling and language. In contrast, the secondary designer was concerned about time frames and the evaluation of such: this was a pity as the caseworker spent the whole time typing away on details, instead of entering into some of the more “interesting” aspects of the prototype. In other situations the designers “pulled” the caseworker away from his or her focus, either because they wanted to get through the agenda for the session or simply because they were eager to explore some particular features of the prototype. In these situations the designer often intervened and encouraged the caseworker to<marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> “have a look at this”, “try this . . ” or “try to write something here”. This kind of designer intervention was not planned from the outset but often happened in situations where there was a break, a moment of silence, in which one of the designers lost his or her patience.<marker type="block"/> 5.4.4. Discussion We have seen various types of situations where the design situation as such has become the focus for the participants. When focus moved away from the frame task towards the sessions as an object, this usually did not lead to learning about the caseworker’s work or the computer system under design. However, we learned how to plan and conduct sessions. In one of the situations a breakdown occurred in the activity of the designers: the prototyping tool stopped working. This breakdown caused the designers to move away from the common activity, leaving the caseworker in a state of irresolution. In the other situation, one of the designers was reminded of his role as conductor of a session with limited time resources. This caused the designer to try to pull the caseworker out of the actions that were then being carried out, and so arresting the fluent acting. One lesson learned from these focus shifts, was that taking time limits seriously, is useful for evaluating future work-like situations in a theatre and movie-like fashion, where a scene indicates that some activity begins and quick scene shifts give the illusion that some long lasting activity has taken place. Activity then continues in a following scene assuming that time has passed and things are changed. We are actually facing a more general problem of how to reduce the complexity of real work tasks without losing the important points that lead to good design. Up until now we have not had concrete experiences with this issue, but find it important to consider when setting up simulated work situations.<marker type="block"/> We have discussed several types of situations that we have observed in cooperative prototyping sessions. These situations have helped shed some light on the different learning actions going on in cooperative prototyping. Learning with respect to the activity, the actions and the operations of the users, both with respect to the limitations of the current work practice, and to the possible changes when a computer application is introduced. But there is of course more to cooperative prototyping than what goes on in front of a prototype in sessions together with users. Before sessions, preparation and planning is needed; between sessions clean up and reconstruction of the prototype is needed; after a series of sessions results need to be collected and documented in order to propagate them to continuing development activities. In this section we briefly discuss lessons from the analysis with respect to setting up sessions, and the activities that go on before and between sessions. Each session needs to be prepared according to the current stage of the design process. Issues concerning preparation of protoyping sessions were discussed at a general level in Gronbaek (1989), where the consideration of the following questions for preparation is suggested: What is the purpose of the session? How stable should the prototype be in advance. 3 To what extent should in-session<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="block"/> modifications be made? What setting should be chosen? How should the outcome be documented or evaluated? The analysis in this paper has improved our understanding of the richness of cooperative prototyping sessions. We have seen that prototyping sessions are somehow unpredictable due to inherent properties of creative activities. Although sessions were prepared to be rooted in a certain frame task, the focus shifted due either to breakdowns or more or less deliberate “pulling” of the focus by participants. We have analysed a number of such situations and focus shifts. From these analyses we conclude that users and designers should view focus shifts as openings of learning in the prototyping sessions rather than trying to avoid them. Of course it is not all kinds of focus shifts that are particularly fruitful openings for learning, as pointed out. We have pointed to a tension between careful preparation of sessions and the inherent unpredictable character of the prototyping sessions. Being aware of such a tension, a contribution from our analysis is an improved understanding of the variety of situations that may occur in prototyping sessions. This understanding can be utilized in preparation of sessions--not to put a tighter steering on the session, but to prepare to handle better the most common and important types of situations and focus shifts. We briefly discuss a few examples of focus shifts to prepare for.<marker type="block"/> A first example is from the situations discussed in section 5.1. We saw that extensive sample data was equally important as the prototype in order to establish fluent work-like evaluation. We find it important to pay attention to sample data early in a prototyping process. Since the long-term municipal plans in this case did not exist in computer-readable form, our only realistic possibility here was to scan parts of the material into the prototype. This would help in situations where the caseworkers were navigating in existing information. But it would not help much in situations where the caseworkers needed to modify the material. Another lesson could be to be less ambitious in cases where it is hard to provide sample data, and only aim at a pointwise fluent performance of actions, as described in section 5.1. A second example is when ideas move the focus towards technological solutions beyond the current prototype, as described in section 5.2. We experienced a quite successful example of such a focus shift where we jumped out of the prototyping tool and experimented with the Guide hypertext system.? Guide happened to be installed on the computer that we were using in the prototyping session. We were not prepared for such a focus shift, but in this situation it worked quite well. We got a shared hypertext example before we actually built tailored facilities aimed at the particular work of the caseworkers. In this case this happened by coincidence. More generally we would support preparing enough to go beyond the current prototype. Such preparation requires some good guessing on behalf of the designers, for it is of course impossible for them to keep all sorts of example applications and be familiar with those. Thus, during preparation of sessions it is necessary to think of a repertoire of good example applications to have in stock for the next sessions. This corresponds to an attempt to anticipate the potential direction of development of the group in the following sessions. Such anticipation is generally hard and cannot t All trade marks are acknowledged.<marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="block"/> be directed by general guide-lines. But based on the understanding of the work practice studied in the actual project, it may not be equally hard for designers to make good guesses with respect to potential example applications in stock. There are other ways of being prepared for such situations. We see less fancy prototyping means such as mock-ups, see for example Kyng (1989); Bodker (1991) as a handy support. What we are thinking of is using anything from simple paper screen images to more advanced slide- or video-based simulations to support design. Vertelney (1989) describes the use of a range of tools from simple drawings in flip-books to advanced video-based animations for storyboard prototyping. Earlier projects (Btidker er al., 1987) have shown that often mock-up simulations are more easily set up for illustration than are computer-based prototypes. A disadvantage of mock-ups, however, is that it is harder for users to experience dynamic aspects of the future system than it is with a computer-based prototype simulation. A third example of a type of situation/focus shift that we could have handled differently in the project, is the situation where caseworkers teach their work practice as described in section 5.3. In this we realized that the designers needed to learn more about casework. The action changed from design to analysis. In one of the sessions, however, we kept sitting by the prototype mixing the caseworkers teaching of his work practice with interview-like inquiries. This took place without proper tools and techniques to undertake and document such activities. In order to be better prepared the designers could set up the sessions in a room equipped with pens and white cardboard or a flip-over. From our experience with future workshops, it seems to be a good idea to have simple means like white cardboard to write on, because it can easily be carried away as documentation. To designers, a computer-based tool might be appropriate, but to our experience users generally are more comfortable when using simpler means such as paper and pens to illustrate aspects of their work. Moreover, the designers should be prepared to move temporarily away from the prototype even though that is not always the best solution. A fourth example of a situation type that the designers could be prepared for is when, as described in section 5.4, the focus shifts towards conducting the session. In that kind of situation it is typically one of the designers that starts acting to get the process going. It is important that the designers on beforehand share an understanding of what they do when for instance time limits seem to be violated in the session, or when either one of the users or one of the designers jumps to a level of detail that seems to be irrelevant for the session. Having discussed such issues previous to sessions may help smooth possible adjustments in the sessions. It is difficult to give general guide-lines for what to do in the situations. But for the preparation there are important issues to consider: The number of participants and their roles are important to discuss. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="152" class="deo:Reference">In the project described by Bodker and Gronbaek (1989)</xref> a single designer was working together with two to four dental assistants in the sessions. In the current project we always arranged sessions with two designers and a varying number of caseworkers. From these experiences we conclude that it is clearly an advantage to have two (or more) designers participating in the sessions. Documenting the process and maintaining the session when states of irresolution occurred became much easier when, in the current project, the<marker type="page" number="23"/><marker type="block"/> secondary designer took responsibility for some of these tasks. The primary designer could concentrate on the interaction with the caseworker(s), and the prototyping tool when modifications to the prototype were needed. The conclusion with respect to the number of users is less clear. When the focus is on establishing work-like situations the nature of the frame task to some degree directs the number of participants. However, it may be an advantage to have several users participating when the focus is on idea exploration and current work practice. The confrontation between the users’ different understanding of the current work and the direction of development of the prototype can uncover issues that the designer would not realize from having contact with the users individually. A disadvantage of having more than one user participate in the session may be that some participants are too dominant and thus suppress important contributions from their participants. In the current project we observed that the draftspeople were generally more active when they were not together with architects or engineers in the sessions. In section 5.4 we also pointed to the possibility of making deliberate focus shifts like scene shifts in a movie to progress through the frame task in a condensed form due to time limits. The use of so-called storyboard prototyping as suggested by Vertelney (1989) and Andriole (1989) seem to provide good and flexible means for this.7 Storyboards can be used to identify individual scenarios to be tried out with a prototype. Shifts to other scenarios can be discussed with direct reference to the storyboard. The storyboard techniques are inspired both from scripting and storyboard techniques used in setting up movies and dance shows. The technique seems intriguing with respect to getting a representation of the use of scenarios to be considered in the evaluation. But a very strict planning of the scenarios may violate the idea of open-endedness (Trigg, Bodker &amp; Gronbaek, 1990) which is an important feature of cooperative prototyping. A final example of situations for which it is hard to be extensively prepared for are situations where the focus moves towards the prototyping tool (see section 5.4). This happens in situations where we reach the limits of the prototyping tool or when regular bugs are found. Bugs cannot be totally avoided and no prototyping tools are without constraints. It can, however, be discussed beforehand what the designers should do when such focus shifts are about to happen. For instance questions such as: “When is it worth fixing a bug in-session. 7 When and how should unsuccessful programming attempts be stopped?” could be considered. Focus shifts that have previously been experienced may lead to more general ideas of how to prepare subsequent sessions. For instance we experienced several breakdowns because we could not pick a blank screen with certain inherited properties. We prepared the next session by making it possible to pick a blank screen for all the different categories in the prototype. Another issue is to be able to anticipate certain types of breakdowns. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="157" class="deo:Reference">In Bodker and Gronbiek (1989)</xref>, we discuss when to stop an in-session modification, when the situation has become meaningless to the users, and too complicated for the designers to get out of within a reasonable amount of time. In this case study, we have seen situations where the designers support each other in getting out of the situation, and situations where they do not. The roles of the t Both Andriole (1989) and Vertelney (1989) use the term storyboard prototyping. But Andriole (1989)<marker type="page" number="24"/><marker type="block"/> designers should clearly be discussed in advance. Often it is the secondary designer who can feel when the user is loosing her or his patience. Clearly the decision about when to stop must be held up against the importance of the change, but generally the designers can avoid serious breakdowns in the sessions as such by understanding the extent to which in-session modifications make sense. Limitations in the current prototyping tool may also trigger consideration of different tools. Gronbrek (1990) discusses a variety of tools to support cooperative prototyping. The above examples do not claim to span the space of all possible situations and focus shifts, but they illustrate how focus shifts in prototyping sessions can be viewed as openings of learning. Taking such openings seriously they can make us improve our understanding of the cooperative design process in general. With respect to specific projects this understanding can improve our ways of setting up following cooperative prototyping sessions.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="128" page="18" column="1">5.4. FOCUS ON THE PROTOTYPING TOOL OR THE SESSION</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx131">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62o2.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="132" page="19" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="133" page="19" column="1">471</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="134" page="19" column="1">5 4.2. Bugs in prototypes or sample data</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx137">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_019.image_19.png" thmb="62o2.page_019.image_19-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="138" page="20" column="1">472</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="139" page="20" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GR0NBAZK</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx143">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_020.image_20.png" thmb="62o2.page_020.image_20-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="144" page="21" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="145" page="21" column="1">473</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="147" page="21" column="1">6.1. EXAMPLES OF LESSONS LEARNED WITH RESPECT TO PREPARATION</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx149">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_021.image_21.png" thmb="62o2.page_021.image_21-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="150" page="22" column="1">474</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="151" page="22" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GRBNB&amp;K</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx154">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_022.image_22.png" thmb="62o2.page_022.image_22-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="155" page="23" column="1">475</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="156" page="23" column="1">COOPERATIVE PROTOTYPING</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="159" page="23" column="1">is, unlike Vertelney (1989), only sketching the actual screen images of the human-computer interface in his storyboards and not the scenarios of use as Vertelney (1989) proposes.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx160">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_023.image_23.png" thmb="62o2.page_023.image_23-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="161" page="24" column="1">S. B0DKER AND K. GRBNBz4ZK</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="162" page="24" column="1">476</outsider>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="164" page="24" column="1">7. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" page="24" column="1">As pointed out in the introduction there is more to prototyping than rapid development of prototypes and demonstration of their features. To benefit from prototyping it needs to be carried out cooperatively by users and designers (Gronbaek, 1989). This kind of cooperation is a confrontation between two groups of subjects that from the outset possess different kinds of instruments and work on different kinds of objects aiming at different purposes. However, we claim that the purpose of designing computer support is that new objects tailored to the users’ needs, have to be temporarily shared between the two groups, or two skills. This implies that we as designers need to develop our instruments in a direction that make us able to deal with the objects of design as objects for a shared purpose. This is not easy, but techniques to perform cooperative system design experimentally is, from our point-of-view, the best attempt. This is similar to the observation that the best way to improve the understanding of the usability of design proposals is to have prototypes tried in use. The project that we have set up and analysed can be seen as a contribution to make the development of designer instruments go in a cooperative direction. In particular we have discussed a tension between needs for careful preparation of prototyping sessions and establishing good conditions for user and designer creativity. The message with this respect is that we need to be open to learn from focus shift in sessions and not try to avoid them. Compared with our previous work, the present study has illustrated a variety of situations where prototypes can be related closely to frame tasks. These are situations where point-wise performance of work actions take place, where ideas are explored, and where designers learn about the users work practice, etc. This is the case although work-like evaluation in early prototyping may be hard to get to in some settings. To maintain the idea of work-like evaluation the meaning of “work-like” needs to be modified somewhat. We find it inspiring to think of the prototyping activities as plays, where the participants act out some situations, but skip others. The timing of which situations to act out, and which to skip or condense in time seems to be of major importance for the development of this idea. In future research we will try out the emerging storyboard prototyping techniques.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx166">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_024.image_24.png" thmb="62o2.page_024.image_24-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="167" page="25" column="1">COOPERATIVEPROTOTYPING</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="168" page="25" column="1">477</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">This work was supported by the Danish Natural Science Research Council, FIIJ grant no. 5.17.5.1.30. The municipal</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="170" page="25" column="1">caseworkers, students and colleagues at Aarhus University are kindly acknowledged for their help with the project. Randy Trigg has played an important</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">role in the later phases of our analysis, and Jonathan Grudin has helped out with language and other comments in the final, critical state. Finally we thank the anonymous referees for their constructive comments.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="172" page="25" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="25" column="1">ANDRIOLE, S. J. (1989). Storyboard Prototyping-A New Approach to User Requirements Analysis. Wellesley, MA: QED Information Sciences, Inc.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="25" column="1">BAECKER, R. &amp; BUXTON, W. (1987). Empirical evaluation of user interfaces. In R. M. Baecker &amp; W. A. S. Buxton, Eds. Readings in Human-Computer Interaction: A MultidtXplinary Approach, pp. 131-134. Los Altos, CA: Morgan Kaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="25" column="1">BANNON, L. &amp; GRP)NB/EK, K. (1989). Hypermedia: support for a more natural information organization. In H. Clausen, Ed. In Proceedings of the Seventh Nordic Conference for Information and Documentation, Lyngby, Denmark, Dansk Teknisk Litteraturselskab.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="25" column="1">BISGAARD, O., MOGENSEN, P., NBRBY, M. &amp; THOMSEN, M. (1989). Systemudvikling som hzrevirksomhed, konflikter som basks for organisationel udvikling (Systems development as a learning activity, conflicts as the origin of organizational development), DAIMI IR-88. Arhus: Aarhus University.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="25" column="1">BLOMBERG, J. &amp; HENDERSON, D. A. (1990). Reflections on participatory design: lessons from the Trillium experience. In J. C. Chew &amp; J. Whiteside, Eds. Conference Proceedings Empowering People CHI ‘90 pp. 353-359. New York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="25" column="1">BQDKER, S. &amp; GRBNBEK, K. (1989). Cooperative prototyping experiments-users and designers envision a dental case record system. In J. Bowers &amp; S. Benford, Eds. Proceedings of the first EC-CSCW ‘89, UK, Computer Sciences Company.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">BBDKER, S. &amp; GRBNB~K, K. (1991). Design in action: From prototyping by demonstration to cooperative prototyping. In J. GREENBAUM &amp; M. KYNG, Eds. Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems, Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">BBDKER, S. (1991). Through the interface-a Human Activity Approach to User Interface Design. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="25" column="1">BBDKER, S., EHN, P., KAMMERSGAARD,J. KYNG, M. &amp; SUNDBLAD, Y. (1987). A Utopian experience. In G. Bjerknes, P. Ehn &amp; M. Kyng, Eds. Computers and Democracy: A Scandinavian Challenge, pp. 251-278. Aldershot, UK: Avebury.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="25" column="1">BBDKER, S., EHN, P., KNUDSEN, J. L., KYNG, M. &amp; MADSEN, K. H. (1988). Computer support for cooperative design. In Proceedings of Conference on CSCW, Portland, Oregon, September 1988, pp. 377-394. New York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">BRIEFS, U., CIBORRA, C. &amp; SCHNEIDER, L. (Eds.) (1983). System Design for, with, and by the Users. Amsterdam: North-Holland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="25" column="1">CONKLIN, J. (1987). Hypertext: an introduction and survey. IEEE Computer, 20, 17-41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="25" column="1">EHN, P. (1988). Work-Oriented Design of Computer Artifacts. Falkoping: Arbetslivscentrum/- Almqvist &amp; Wiksell International.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">ENGESTRGM, Y. (1987). Learning by Expanding. Helsinki: Orienta-Konsultit.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="25" column="1">ENGESTR~M, Y., ENGESTR~M, R. &amp; SAARELMA, 0. (1988). Computerized medical records, Production pressure and compartimentalization in the work activity of health center physicians. In Proceedings of Conference on CSCW, Portland, Oregon, September 1988, pp. 65-84. New York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="25" column="1">FLOYD, C. (1984). A systematic look at prototyping. In R. Budde, K. Kuhlenkamp, L. Mathiassen, 8~ H. Ztillighoven, Eds. Approaches to Prototyping, pp. 1-18. Berlin: Springer Verlag.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="25" column="1">GREENBAUM, J. &amp; KYNG, M. (Eds.) (1991). Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="25" column="1">GRUDIN, J. (1990). Obstacles to participatory design in large product development organizations. In A. Namioka &amp; D. Schuler, Eds. Proceedings of the Participatory Design <marker type="page" number="26"/><marker type="block"/> Conference PDC’90, Seattle, WA, March 31-April 1. Palo Alto, CA: Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility, Workplace Project. GRBNBZK, K. (1989). Rapid prototyping with fourth generation systems--an empirical study. OFFICE: Technology and People, 5, 105-125.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">GRONBZK, K. (1990). Supporting active user involvement in prototyping. Scandinavian</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="26" column="1">JOHNSON,J. (Moderator). (1990). Panel on participatory design of computer systems, In J. C. CHEW &amp; J. WHITESIDE, Eds. Conference Proceedings, Empowering People CHI’9O pp. 141-144. New York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="26" column="1">JORDAN, P. W., KELLER, K. S., TUCKER, T. W. &amp; VOGEL, D. (1989). Software storming: combining rapid prototyping and knowledge engineering. IEEE COMPUTER 22,</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="26" column="1">JUNGK, R. &amp; M~~LLERT, N. (1987). Future Workshops: How to Create Desirable Futures. London, UK: Institute for Social Inventions.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="26" column="1">KYNG, M. (1989). Designing for a dollar a day. Ofice, Technology and People, 4, 157-170.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">MACK, R. L., LEWIS, C. H. &amp; CARROLL, J. M. (1987). Learning to use word processors: Problems and prospects. In R. M. BAECKER &amp; W. A. S. BUXTON, Eds. Readings in Human-Computer Interaction: A Multidiscriplinary Approach. Los Altos, CA: Morgan Kaufmann.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">MONK, A. (1987). HOW and when to collect behavioural data. In R. M. BAECKER &amp; W. A. S. BUXTON, Eds. Readings in Human-Computer Interaction: A multidisciplinary Approach, pp. 138-142 Los Altos, CA: Morgan Kaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="26" column="1">NAMIOKA, A. &amp; SCHULER, D. (Eds.) (1990). In Proceedings of the Participatory Design</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Conference PDC’ 90, Seattle, WA, March Jl-April 1. Palo Alto, CA: Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility, Workplace Project.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="26" column="1">SUCHMAN, L. &amp; TRIGG, R. (1991) Understanding practice: video as a medium for reflection and design. In J. Greenbaum &amp; M. Kyng, Eds. Design at Work: Cooperative Design of Computer Systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Earlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="26" column="1">TRIGG, R. H., B~DKER, S. &amp; GR~)NBIEK, K. (1990) A video-based analysis of the</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="26" column="1">cooperative prototyping process. In R. HELLMAN, M. RUOHONEN, &amp; P. S~RGAARD, Eds. Preceedings of the 13th IRIS conference, Report on Computer Science &amp; Mathemat- ics no. 108, Abo Akademi University, Finland, pp. 453-474. VERTELNEY, L. (1989). Using video to prototype user interfaces. SIGCHI Bulletin, 21,</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="26" column="1">WINOGRAD, T. &amp; FLORES, F. (1986). Understanding for Design. Norwood, NJ: Ablex.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx191">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_025.image_25.png" thmb="62o2.page_025.image_25-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="192" page="26" column="1">S. BBDKER AND K. GRBNBRK</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="193" page="26" column="1">478</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx208">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62o2.page_026.image_26.png" thmb="62o2.page_026.image_26-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
