<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>d52c41e3cbb0e986c79b50bb18044913990873e01c95071df04f3ef8b26ed71b</job>
    <base_name>62qv</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/desi_a_00002</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Understanding Design Interventions in Democratic Innovation: a Toolkit Approach.</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Natasha Carolan</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Dr. Leon Cruickshank</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible">Lancaster University</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">The relationship between society and design is in a period of transition. We are observing a move from the ‘object’ to ‘service’, and from problem solving, to problem finding, to design strategy. In this paper we explore how a ‘toolkit approach’ allows us to both contribute to democratic innovation activity but also build a deeper understanding of the potential contribution design can have in this emerging area. This work was conducted in the prototyping stages of the Homesense initiative, a project run by Tinker London and Électricité de France. Homesense aims to facilitate user led innovation in smart home development through provision of toolkits and expert support. Through engagement with the Homesense project we identify areas and mechanisms for intervention in Democratic Innovation (DI) and discuss methodologies for future potential for a wider professional design engagement in DI.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="6" page="1" column="1">Overview</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="1" column="1">We are currently observing a shift from ‘consumer cultures’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="7" class="deo:Reference">Postman, 1985</xref>) to participatory cultures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="8" class="deo:Reference">Fischer, 2002</xref>, von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="10" class="deo:Reference">Brown, 2010</xref>). Such developments have obvious implications for the design and creative industries. As a shift this creates the conditions necessary for ‘social production for mass collaboration, for civic and political life, and for education.’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Fischer, 2009</xref>) Importantly, it is such developments that now enable and support the establishment of Democratic Innovation (DI).<marker type="block"/> Middle grounds between the ‘experts’ and ‘citizens’ or the ‘producers’ and ‘consumers’ are emerging. Here <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Tapscott &amp; Williams (2006)</xref> point to ‘prosumers’ those who are comfortable with the technologies they work with, lead-users (von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 2005</xref>), professional amateurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Brown, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Leadbeater &amp; Miller, 2008</xref>) and social production and mass collaboration. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Benkler, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Leadbeater, 2008</xref>).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">This paper has been prompted by a conviction that beyond user centred or participatory design, prosumers or lead users there is a lack of understanding of democratic modes of innovation, design and production. Here we demonstrate an approach using toolkits that helps to define potential contributions design can make in this space while contributing productively to DI processes.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="2" column="1">Democratic Innovation and Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" page="2" column="1">Definitions of innovation ultimately rest on the successful implementation of ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Fagerberg, 2005</xref>). There is an increasing emphasis on looking outside technological and R&amp;D labs as the drivers of innovation. ‘...innovation is being democratized... users of firms and services are increasingly able to innovate for themselves.’ (von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 2005</xref>). Other theorists in this space include, Bilgram, Brem, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Voigt (2008)</xref> and Bogers, Afuah &amp; Bastian (2010). Discussion is also seen through ‘Open Innovation’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Chesbrough (2003)</xref> ‘Open source’, ‘culture jamming’ and ‘mass collaboration’. Democratization of innovation may apply to products and software and increasingly societal issues, legislation and policy. Business, social and production models have developed around such democratic approaches.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">To consider the potential of professional design intervention in DI it is important to consider the relationship between innovation and design. While some in design question the distinction between innovation and design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Poynor, 2008</xref>), a more balanced view is adopted by George <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Cox (2005)</xref> in his report highly influential report on the creative industries in the UK stating that ‘design is what links creativity and innovation’. In fact there is little discussion of design in academic studies of innovation the relationships involved are emerging and chaotic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Cruickshank, 2010</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="2" column="1">Design also has a complex history of citizen engagement, the ‘practice of collective creativity in design has been around for nearly 40 years, going under the name of participatory design’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Sanders &amp; Stappers, 2008</xref>). This can be traced to 1970‘s Scandinavia and the Collective Resource Approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Bodker, 1996</xref>). Nigel Cross at a Design Participation Conference held in 1971 in Manchester called for ‘new approaches to design...’ citing citizen participation as a possible approach. Participatory approaches are employed by the design profession and wider industry in areas where user needs perspectives and requirements are considered valuable, if not always actually applied in reality.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Participatory design, collaborative design, co-design and meta-design are cited as possible approaches as these fulfill democratic ideals of citizen participation. The seminal work ‘Democratising Innovation’ by Eric von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Hippel (2005)</xref> presents lead user innovation and toolkit design as the core of democratizing innovation. Beyond this research in entrepreneurship, innovation communities, measurement and policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Baldwin, Heinerth &amp; von Hippel, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Shah &amp; Tripsas, 2007</xref>) adds to the debate. There are a number of examples of contrasting types of DI. These include but are not limited to; - Crowd-sourcing, as found with organizations such as Innocentive, Hypios and Local motors - Social innovation models such as OpenIdeo, Participle and Project H. - Social product design models as found with Quirky. - Democratic design production facilities such as FabLabs.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="3" column="1">Looking at one example in more detail, Quirky.com a product design model that describes itself as ‘social product design’ recently obtained $6 Million in venture capital funding. Using a ‘representative democracy’ typology citizens with a product idea can submit to a pool from which a voting process is used to decide which ideas are brought through to realization. Here a panel of professional designers co-ordinate voting and suggestions made by all participants.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="3" column="1">Understanding the Potential for Design Intervention: Homesense Case Study</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="3" column="1">This paper posits that within such DI approaches there is potential for a significant professional design intervention. We developed an approach that starts to draw out these potentials while preserving the freedom and cooperative spirit that defined DI.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Homesense is a research collaboration between Tinker London and Électricité de France R&amp;D (EDF R&amp;D) who, aim to facilitate citizen led design of smart homes by bringing the open collaboration methods of online communities to physical infrastructures in the home. This project is a response to perceived failings in smart home development to date which have been seen to predominantly adopt top down approaches. The Homesense Project suggests; ‘smart homes aren’t made by the people</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="4" column="1">who will actually live in them, but by designers in R&amp;D departments who have specific ideas about how they should be lived in.’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Homesense, 2009</xref>). The Homesense Project believes that better smart home scenarios will emerge if users are able to adapt products to their ‘specific needs, social contexts and lifestyles’. The Homesense project will document and facilitate these user-led activities and it is anticipated that ‘learning from them will in turn drive better product development &amp; innovation for relevant audiences of the Homesense Project.’ Running from October to December 2010 the project enlisted six European households with differing experience and motivations to participate in the project. Households and experts were self electing, recruited through press releases, word of mouth and social networking and finally selected by Tinker London according to proximity to an appropriate household/expert. Experts received training from Tinker London and EDF R&amp;D before being introduced to their respective households. A supporting blog space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Homesense, 2010</xref>) was provided alongside the toolkit to enable communication and documentation of concepts by households.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="4" column="1">Toolkit Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Working within the Homesense project the authors of this paper were engaged in the research, development and design of a prototype toolkit for the Homesense project, this allowed for the formulation of an initiative to undertake research spanning wider areas of consideration not only looking at toolkit design as a promoter of DI activities but also enabling the identification of mechanisms for design intervention in DI as a whole. A multistage action research approach was adopted in order to fully potential and areas for intervention. A toolkit was designed to target a number of the areas indicated as areas of potential for intervention in DI. (The components involved in this toolkit are part of the developing Tinker kit available from Tinker.it.) In designing the toolkit principles outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Thomke &amp; von Hippel (2002)</xref> indicated that toolkits should; ‘... enable people to complete a series of design cycles followed by learning by doing’</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">‘tool kits must be user-friendly. They should not require customers to learn an entirely new design language’ ‘they must contain libraries of useful components and modules that have been pretested and debugged’ ‘tool kits must contain information about the capabilities and limitations of the production process that will be used to manufacture the product.’</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">These principles combined with findings from research resulted in a toolkit with the following components. 1) Packaging design: to enable identification of components and reduce barriers to participation. 2) Worksheets: a worksheet designed to avoid alienating the user in their initial interaction with the kit, enable design cycles, learning by doing and access to pre-existing libraries of code. 3) 'Chocolate box' map: an insert attached to the top inner lid that directly maps the components allowing for easy identification of the relevant components.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx50">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qv.page_005.image_01.png" thmb="62qv.page_005.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">[Image: Prototype Kit 2010]</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">4) A supporting booklet: with three sections: 4.1) Actions, Sense and Core. Representations of components explaining their relevance, capability and function. 4.2) 'Tech Tales' Here designers employed narrative (modified fairy tales) to build on understanding that citizens already possess enabling citizen design and ideation processes. 4.3) Ideas. Examples of what other citizens have designed using similar kits.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" page="6" column="1">Validation and Responses</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" page="6" column="1">Four individuals aged between 16 and 28 were recruited using a random sampling method to test the toolkit. The authors conducted a two stage testing process, firstly of providing the toolkit without the supporting materials and observing how the user engaged and developed. Secondly the designed toolkit was presented and users were provided with a short expert introduction to the toolkit and a home-orientated scenario. A think aloud protocol (Ericsson &amp; Simon: 1993: Hannu &amp; Pallab: 2000) was adopted to provide qualitative insight into the user experience. In doing so the researchers were able to observe and evaluate how the user interacted with the Homesense kit. Scenario testing was followed by user questionnaires. <marker type="block"/> The initial response to the designed kit changed from one of unsureness to curiosity. Users of the kit indicated that they were (TUser 1) ‘less afraid of the kit’, (TUser 2) ‘able to ask questions about the bits using the map’ able to ‘remember what the person said’, (TUser 3) ‘more likely to play with the kit now and see what I can make’. Testing indicated that the toolkit, supporting materials and expert support was effective in terms of performance, accuracy, recall, emotional response, ease of understanding. It also performed in its ability to: guide to external resources, facilitate expert-user interaction, facilitate ideation process, reduce anxiety and perceived barriers to participation and an ability to enable longevity of participation.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="7" column="1">Toolkits as a Research Approach</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="7" column="1">Beyond designing and validating a successful toolkit our intention was to use the process of the toolkit design, testing and implementation as something akin to a cultural probe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Gaver, Dunne, Pacenti (1999)</xref> with an important difference. Rather than constructing a (hopefully) enjoyable to use data gathering method we wanted to create something that had real utility for the participants, that did not place them as a test subject but rather entered into the democratic innovation ‘ecology’. While this approach is still in development we believe this may prove to have significant practical and philosophical benefits centred around the desirability of active interaction and engagement of, and with all stakeholders in the DI ecosystem. Through this active engagement a number of key points were identified as having the potential for design intervention in DI.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">1) Motivation to participate: Those who declined to apply to participate in the Homesense project revealed that presentation of a technical toolkit actually represented a barrier to non-technical households, non-applicants labeled a first technically focused toolkit as ‘scary’, and ‘too difficult for me’.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="7" column="1">This was mirrored in participant observation of the household and workshop research groups, this revealed anxiety with initial presentation with the toolkit. A coded analysis of documented scripts of the household observation revealed that within the household study participants were alienated in early stages if they encountered significant difficulty which then acted as a barrier to their continued participation. (User 1) is quoted ‘what am I meant to do with this?’, ‘I don’t understand electronics’, ‘what if I do it wrong, will I damage anything?’. Here potential for design intervention was identified in designing to reduce barriers to initial participation and incentivising participation. <marker type="block"/> 2) Interacting with Experts: Pilot household observation with the toolkit revealed areas of tension in communication between experts and citizens. Experts stated ‘basic terminology is difficult to impart’ and householders said (User 1) ‘I don’t know how to talk about what I want to do’. Both Understanding and retention of information imparted by experts was significantly less than required for</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">ongoing participation. Here there is potential for design intervention centered around facilitating and enabling bidirectional communication.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="8" column="1">3) Facilitation and Co-Ordination: Designers and producers tend to know more than users about solution possibilities while users have expert ‘local’ knowledge. From both a pilot household study and observation of introductory workshops questions emerged as to the ability of citizens to express their own needs related to smart home concepts as well as their ability to work with the experts and the kit supplied in an effective manner. Potential for design intervention indicates facilitation of expression of needs, communication between citizen and expert and co-ordination of local knowledge and solution possibilities.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" page="8" column="1">Advantages of a Toolkit approach and future developments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="8" column="1">As this research has begun to demonstrate toolkit provision is a possible intervention in DI without transforming this into more ‘controlled’ types of design engagement (e.g. user centred or participatory design). Providing toolkits has advantages for DI through a process by which the user innovates using tools provided by the manufacturer or body who are expert in the solution space. Users inform and enrich this process by bringing along their own knowledge and needs (von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Hippel, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Piller 2004</xref>). This information is ‘sticky’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Nelson 1982</xref>; Pavitt 1987) and difficult to extract from users by other means. The success in toolkit provision is evident in the semiconductor field. ‘In 2000, more than $15 billion worth of custom integrated circuits were sold that had been designed with the aid of toolkits—often by circuit users—and produced in the “silicon foundries” of custom semiconductor manufacturers such as LSI’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Thomke and von Hippel 2002</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Extending this principle we anticipate we can create more product orientated toolkits. Not for making products but using ‘proto-components’ as part of a physical toolkit approach, giving similar utility benefits to the communication based toolkit described above. This builds on concepts such as underdesign (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Sanders, 2006</xref>) where the user must modify the proto-design product to finish it. For example in ‘Do Create’, Droog and KesselsKramer present an unfinished line of products. Consumers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">are required to ‘finish’ the design and thereby participate in the design process to complete the product and use it. These playful concepts encourage a level of integration of the user in the design process which in turn (we hope) will give richer, more insightful research results.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="9" column="1">In terms of research a toolkit approach has significant potential advantages, not only in having a real world impact at its core but also in harnessing the enthusiasm and energy found in genuinely citizen- led Innovation. This energy and level of engagement quickly dissipates when participants perceive that they are test subjects or serving someone else’s agenda.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="74" page="9" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" page="9" column="1">Designing and promoting design interventions in Democratic Innovation is timely and will become ever more prominent as such approaches proliferate. This is valuable not only for the citizen but also for society, business models and socially important agendas. The idea of DI is received with trepidation by some in the design industry where there is concern that through DI the role and position of designers might be undermined. However, we argue that in reality DI offers significant opportunity for increased professional design engagement (employment) for product, service and graphic designers. <marker type="block"/> This is a timely contribution to debates around the future of the design profession and future interaction (and employment) with a wider base of creative practitioners through processes such as Democratic Innovation. Equally we have started to demonstrate that design itself can he harnessed through a ‘design probe’ approach to toolkit creation to both contribute to DI and act as a research methodology that goes beyond the traditional dual outcomes of Action Research (social good and academic understanding). By facilitating new business models and opportunities, democratic innovation and academic research through design practice we propose that this (still very much emerging) methodology has the potential to become one of the few research approaches to come out of design itself rather than the social, physical or technical sciences.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="77" page="10" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="78" page="10" column="1">Baldwin, C., Heinerth, C. and von Hippel, E. (2006) How User innovations become commercial product: A theoretical investigation and case study. Research Policy, 35: 1291-1313</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="10" column="1">Benkler, Y. (2006) The Wealth of Networks: How social Production Transforms Markets and Freedom, Yale University Press, New Haven</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" page="10" column="1">Bilgram, V.; Brem, A.; Voigt, K.-I. (2008) User-Centric Innovations in New Product Development; Systematic Identification of Lead User Harnessing Interactive and Collaborative Online-Tools, in: International Journal of Innovation Management, Vol. 12, No. 3, pp. 419-458</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="10" column="1">Bodker, S. (1996) Creating conditions for participation: conflicts and resources in systems design. HCI, 11 (3), 215-236</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="82" page="10" column="1">Bogers, M, Afuah, A and Bastian,B. (2009) Users as Innovators: A Review, Critique, and Future Research Directions. Journal of Management, Vol. 36, No. 4, 2010.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="84" page="10" column="1">Brown, J.S. (2005) New Learning Environments for the 21st Century, [online] available at " HYPERLINK "<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.johnseelybrown.com/newlearning.pdf" id="83">http://www.johnseelybrown.com/newlearning.pdf</ext-link>" http:// www.johnseelybrown.com/newlearning.pdf" [Accessed Sept. 2010]</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="10" column="1">Brown, T. (2010) OpenIDEO [online] available at: " HYPERLINK "http:// designthinking.ideo.com/?p=482#content" <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://designthinking.ideo.com/?" id="85">http://designthinking.ideo.com/?</ext-link> p=482#content" [Accessed Sept. 2010]</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="10" column="1">Chesbrough, H. (2003) Open Innovation: The new imperative for creating and profiting from technology. Harvard Business School Press, Boston</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="10" column="1">Cox, G. (2005) Sir George Cox, Cox Review of Creativity in Business: Building on the UK’s Strengths. (London: HM Treasury)</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="89" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Cross, N. (Ed.) (1972) Design participation: Proceedings of the design research society’s conference 1971, Academy editions, London, UK</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" page="10" column="1">Cruickshank, L. (2010) The Innovation Dimension: Design Issues, Massachusetts Institute of Technology,: Volume 26, Number 2 Spring 2010</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="91" page="10" column="1">Ericsson, K., and Simon, H. (1993) Protocol Analysis: Verbal Reports as Data (2nd ed.). Boston: MIT Press</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="92" page="10" column="1">Fagerberg, J., Mowery, D. and Nelson, R. eds. (2005), The Oxford Handbook of Innovation, Oxford University Press, Oxford</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" page="10" column="1">Fischer, (2002) Beyond ‘Couch Potatoes’:From Consumers to Designers and Active Contributors. in First Monday, [online] available at " HYPERLINK " HYPERLINK "http:// <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> firstmonday.org/issues.issue7_12/fischer/" <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://firstmonday.org/issues.issue7_12/" id="94">http://firstmonday.org/issues.issue7_12/</ext-link> fischer/"" [Accessed Sept. 2010]</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" page="11" column="1">Fischer, G. (2009) End-User Development and Meta-design: Foundations for Cultures of Participation Lecture notes in computer science, Volume 5435/2009, 3-14</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="97" page="11" column="1">Franke, N. and Piller, F. (2004) Value Creation by Toolkits for User Innovation and Design: The Case of the Watch Market. Journal of Product Innovation Management Vol. 21 Issue 6, 2004, pp. 401-415</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="98" page="11" column="1">Gaver, B., Dunne, T., &amp; Pacenti, E. (1999) Design: Cultural probes, interactions, v. 6 n. 1. Jan./ Feb, 21-29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="11" column="1">Hannu, K., and Pallab, P. (2000) A comparison of concurrent and retrospective verbal protocol analysis, American Journal of Psychology (University of Illinois Press) 113 (3): 387–404</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="100" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Homesense Project (2009) Homesense. [Online] Available from: http:// www.homesenseproject.com/ [Accessed Sept. 2010].</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="101" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Homesense Households (2010) Homesense. [Online] Available from: http:// www.homesenseproject.com/households/ [Accessed Sept. 2010].</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" page="11" column="1">Leadbeater, C. (2008) We -Think: Mass Innovation not Mass production. Profile Books. UK</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="105" page="11" column="1">Leadbeater, C. and Miller, P. (2008) The Pro-Am Revolution - how enthusiasts are changing our economy and society, [online] available at " HYPERLINK "<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.demos.co.uk/files/" id="103">http://www.demos.co.uk/files/</ext-link> proamrevolutionfinal.pdf" <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.demos.co.uk/files/proamrevolutionfinal.pdf" id="104">http://www.demos.co.uk/files/proamrevolutionfinal.pdf</ext-link>" [Accessed Sept. 2010]</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Nelson, R. (1982) The role of knowledge in R&amp;D efficiency. Quart. J. Economy. 97(3) 453-470. Pavitt, K. (1987) The objectives of technology policy. Sci. Pub. Policy, 14(4) 182-188.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Postman, N. (1985) Amusing Ourselves to Death - Public Discourse in the Age of Show Business, Penguin Books, New York</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" page="11" column="1">Poynor, R. (2008) Down with Innovation: Today’s Business Buzzwords Reflect a Bad Attitude About Design, The International Design Magazine 55:3 41</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Sanders, E. (2006) Scaffolds for Building Everyday Creativity. In Design for Effective Communications: Creating Contexts for Clarity and Meaning. Jorge Frascara (Ed.) Allworth Press, New York, New York. Sanders, E.B.-N.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="11" column="1">Sanders, E. and Stappers, P. (2008) Co creation and the new landscapes of design. Co Design, Vol. 4, No. 1, March, 5-18</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" page="11" column="1">Shah, S. and Tripsas, M. (2007) The accidental entrepreneur: The emergent and collective process of user entrepreneurship. Strategic Entrepreneurship Journal, 1: 123-140</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" page="12" column="1">Tapscott, D., &amp; Williams, A. D. (2006) Wikinomics: How mass Collaboration Changes Everything, Portfolio, Penguin Group, New York, NY</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" page="12" column="1">Thomke, S., and von Hippel, E. (2002) Customers as Innovators: A New Way to Create Value. Harvard Business Review, 80(4), 74-81</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" page="12" column="1">von Hippel, E. (2005) Democratizing Innovation, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="115" page="12" column="1">Zakaria, F. (2007) The Future of Freedom: Illiberal Democracy at Home and Abroad, W. W. Norton &amp; Company, London</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
