<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>4fe43bf5531d401ce89938801111067b11555ab949844e53ad8d4399e11812fe</job>
    <base_name>62ml</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2317956.2317961</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">DIS 2012 • In the Wild</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">June 11–15, 2012 • Newcastle, UK</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Design Tools in Practice: Studying the Designer-Tool Relationship in Interaction Design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Erik Stolterman</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">School of Informatics and Computing Indiana University, Bloomington th 919 E. 10 Street, Bloomington, 47408, USA <email id="5">estolter@indiana.edu</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7">This paper presents findings from semi-structured interviews with professional interaction designers. The purpose of the study was to examine the relationship between interaction designers and their design tools— specifically the reasons behind their choice of tools. The findings show that the relationship between designers and their tools is more complex than commonly assumed. The paper argues that a deeper understanding of the complexity of the designer-tool relationship can make a difference for both education and practice.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Author Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">Interaction design, design tools, design practice.</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="16">James Pierce</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Classification Keywords</h2>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="1" column="1">H5.m. Information interfaces and presentation (e.g., HCI): Miscellaneous.</region>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" page="1" column="1">Tools are essential to most any skilled practice, and interaction design practice is certainly no exception. Indeed, if we include theoretical and conceptual tools in addition to material artifacts under the notion of “tool”, the range of tools that may be productively drawn on in design practice seems almost limitless, ranging over tools such as pen and paper, sketches, brainstorming techniques, contextual inquiry, physical prototypes, and so on. While some traditional design tools remain indispensible to most areas of professional design practice (e.g., pen and paper), new design tools are constantly being designed, introduced, and refined. This is evidenced both in theoretical and educational writings on design tools, methods, and frameworks, as well as the design and evaluation of new types of interactive tools to support design practice and creative practice more generally.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. DIS 2012, June 11-15, 2012, Newcastle, UK.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18" page="1" column="2">Human-Computer Interaction Institute Carnegie Mellon University 5000 Forbes Avenue, Pittsburgh, PA, USA <email id="17">jjpierce@cs.cmu.edu</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" page="1" column="2">Despite all this, we find there is a surprising lack of research that seeks to examine interaction design practice itself in order to develop robust and vivid descriptions and explanations of the relationships between designers and their tools. While the design community at large and interaction design in particular have witnessed a rise in “user centered design (UCD)” and related approaches to design informed by grounded understandings of actual users, the design of design tools themselves has been slower to embrace this type of perspective. Here we argue that there is a need for more developed understandings of how practicing designers use, understand, and interact with their tools. This argument is in line with Goodman, Stolterman and Wakkary’s recent discussions on the importance of studying interaction design practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="19" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>], as well as work that argues that approaches proposed by researchers do not always adequately fit interaction design practice as experienced by practicing professionals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="20" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="21" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. In this study we focus specifically on the relationships between professional interaction designers and their tools. While previous research has looked at the effectiveness of design tools [e.g., 3,7,12,15] there is surprisingly little work investigating how interaction designers think about their tools and the ways they use them. To make our study more manageable, we specifically focus on how interaction designers choose and use tools for generating ideas. We focus here on generative design tools, which we here define as tools that support a designer to come up with new ideas, concepts, or solutions at any stage during the design process. Our notion of generative design tool is intentionally broad, encompassing simple material tools such as the pen and paper and the whiteboard, but also including methods and techniques such as brainstorming, and dialoguing, as well as more abstract tools such as conceptual frameworks and theories. The primary goal and contribution of this initial study is to begin to work toward the development of more refined understandings of design tools from the designer’s perspective, that is, an understanding of how designers think about and use tools. Our goal then is not to examine what constitutes effective use of design tools or to in any way evaluate the effectiveness of specific tools per se.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="1" column="2">Copyright 2012 ACM 978-1-4503-1210-3/12/06...$10.00.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="24" page="1" column="2">25</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="2" column="1">DIS 2012 • In the Wild</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="26" page="2" column="1">June 11–15, 2012 • Newcastle, UK</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" page="2" column="1">INTERACTION DESIGNERS AND THEIR TOOLS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="2" column="1">The interaction design process is highly complex and includes a large number of activities and challenges. Each of these activities can be addressed with an almost infinite range of tools. For instance, one of the most crucial activities and challenges during the design process for a designer is to “be creative” and to come up with new ideas, concepts, and designs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="28" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="29" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="30" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="31" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. A designer may choose almost any kind of tool to support the needed inspiration and creativity. There exist a multitude of highly formal techniques and methods that provide step-by-step instructions or “recipes” to enhance creativity. There are also highly un-structured approaches used by designers (which in the context of this paper we also consider as “tools”) such as taking a walk, playing games, listening to music, etc. Many of the creativity tools found in interaction design are also commonly found in other design disciplines, such as brainstorming and sketching. Tools are understood and treated differently in different fields. In some design fields there is a strong sense of what constitutes a core set of tools that every designer must be able to master. We believe that this is for the most part not (yet) the case in interaction design, where the range of tools is broader, more open, and still relatively undefined. There is not a clear and developed set of core tools that have been commonly accepted and given a well-defined purpose and place in the interaction design process. Furthermore, as our study participants suggest, interaction designers often draw upon many different existing design traditions and tools from fields as diverse as fine arts and graphic design to mechanical engineering. This suggests that interaction designers may be more open to exploration and experimentation when it comes to using new tools for design in comparison to designers in more traditional and established design disciplines. There have been a number of prior attempts to understand the nature of tools in general. There are, for instance, highly influential theories on the nature of tools from notable philosophers of technology including Martin Heidegger, Albert Borgmann, Don Ihde, and Peter-Paul Verbeek. Some of these philosophical contributions have led to specific applications in the field of digital artifacts [e.g.,4,19]. There are also some influential writings on the nature of tools in relation to design emphasizing notions of craft and craftsmanship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="32" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="33" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]. Although there are to our knowledge no studies specifically focused on how interaction designers choose their design tools, there are some studies of tools for generative stages in design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="34" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="35" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="36" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="37" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>].</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="2" column="1">STUDY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="2" column="1">We conducted semi-structured interviews with a total of eleven interaction design practitioners. Our participants all had at least three years of industry experience, and in some cases considerably more. All participants held a job title as “interaction designer” or similar titles such as “user experience designer”. Educational backgrounds varied and <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> included Computer Science, Interaction Design, Information Technology, Fine Arts, Visual Design, and Mechanical Engineering. Interviews were conducted either by phone or in person and typically lasted 1-3 hours. Interviews were audio recorded and relevant portions transcribed. The interviewer began by defining what the study referred to as a generative design tool, that is, as “anything that can support a designer to come up with new ideas at any stage in the design process.” The interviewer further emphasized our broad notion of tool, giving the participant flexibility in interpreting what is and is not a tool. We approached the interviews and our initial analysis without any strong preconceived notions of what to find. In this respect our approach is aligned with Strauss and Corbin’s grounded theory approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="41" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. However, various works from design theory and other areas inevitably informed our work, and we explicitly address certain relevant works in our discussion of findings (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="42" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]). Our analysis consisted of reviewing interview notes and transcriptions, identifying emerging themes within and across participants, and extracting particularly interesting cases, which sometimes resisted generalization. A limitation of our method is that it is based primarily on interviewing, that is, on what designers say they do (rather than, say, what we observe them doing firsthand). Another limitation of our study is that we did not conduct our interviews in the context of the participants work environment. Future studies would certainly benefit from contextual interviews allowing for concrete observation and discussion of physical design tools and work environments. While observational techniques would certainly complement future work in this area well, there is nonetheless much value in obtaining descriptive accounts of how designers talk about and makes sense of their own practical use of tools. Indeed, as our findings will show, our analysis of the interviews suggests possible differences in how designers rationalize their use of tools from how they actually use tools in practice. A focus on the interviews further allowed us to gain insight into aspects of tool use such as the relationship between design tools and the designers’ self-perceived identity as an expert practitioner.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" page="2" column="2">FINDINGS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" page="2" column="2">We present our findings in two groups. First, we discuss findings that we interpret to be aligned with a “rational” model of tool usage in which designers explain tools in terms of the ability to accomplish tasks. Next, we present a number of examples of findings that suggests other factors at play that complicate or may even contradict designers’ rationales for tool selection. These factors were in some cases more personal and related to social and cultural aspects of tools-in-use.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="46" page="2" column="2">26</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47" page="3" column="1">DIS 2012 • In the Wild</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="48" page="3" column="1">June 11–15, 2012 • Newcastle, UK</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="49" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Rationale’s for tool use</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" page="3" column="1">Our interviewees expressed a number of reasons for why they choose a particular design tool. Commonly mentioned reasons for selecting a tool were: (1) how a specific tool can make the process faster or more efficient, (2) how easy to use a tool is, (3) how flexible the tool is or how much freedom it provides, (4) how it fits individual versus team work and collaboration, and (5) how available and accessible the tool is. These themes were clearly evidenced in the recurrent use of specific words and phrases. For example, almost every participant mentioned words and phrases such as “speed”, “flexibility”, and “ease of use” in describing useful and valuable tools they relied upon. Our interpretation of these reasons is that they all belong to a similar type of rationale for tool selection and usage. This rationale can be understood as based on a logical, rational perspective or model of a practitioner’s relationship to a design tool. This explanation of tool use, as a consequence of a rational choice, roughly follows a model in which one selects an appropriate tool based on a clear understanding of the design situation, the desired outcome of the situation, the types of activity needed to reach that outcome, and the types of tools that can satisfy the desired outcomes of the situation. This corresponds to an ideal process in which an indentified problem leads to the selection of suitable tools that then leads to the expected desired outcome. While these findings were the most salient themes to emerge from our study, they are not necessarily the most important or interesting. In the following section we discuss several less salient themes, which point to relationships between designers and their tools that do not necessarily follow a “rational” model of tool usage. This suggests that there may be some significant discrepancy between how designers rationally describe their use of tools (to themselves, to other designers, to researchers) and how tools are actually used, experienced, and understood during the course of practical design activity. This discrepancy may be explained in terms of Argyris and Schön’s distinction between espoused theory and theory in use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="50" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>], which we will return to later.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="52" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Personal nuance and tools-in-use</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="3" column="1">In this section we highlight a different cluster of findings that were less salient, and also more difficult to generalize across participants. Indeed, in some cases these findings were particular to only one or two participants. Nonetheless these findings are crucial for two reasons. First, they tend to contradict or otherwise contrast with findings discussed previously concerning designers’ rationales for selecting and using tools. This suggests a distinction between tools- in-use (i.e., how tools are actually used and engaged with in practice) and reflective explanation of tool use (which our study suggests is often explained using some form of “rational choice”). Secondly, and perhaps even more importantly, these findings point to promising areas for further investigation, both in terms of specific aspects of the <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> designer-tool relationships as well as more generally in terms of the nuance and complexity in the designer-tool relationship that are not explained satisfactorily by a “rational” model of tool usage. Below we highlight several such themes. Familiarity and habit. We found that our interviewees reported a tendency to choose tools that they are familiar with. Familiarity with a tool appeared, in some cases, to play a more important role than many of the reasons mentioned above. For example, after a lengthy discussion of reasons for using a tool, one designer finally mentions familiarity as an important factor in her use of these tools: “Well, you know, I think one of the reason I use pen and paper and whiteboarding is because they are very easy to use, and I’ve been using them for years and years and there is a familiarity and comfort-ability with that form factor.” Openness, control, and expertise. We found that our interviewees often valued tools that were not perceived as overly prescriptive. For example, one designer describes issues regarding software with built-in design solutions: “With many tools there's so many solutions already built in. Like OmniGraph has so many built in solutions, for example grids. But is this the best way to represent certain ideas? Well, not necessarily...” The ability to use and control a tool that is not overly prescriptive was apparently seen by some designers as a sign of expertise. For example, one designer describes how pattern libraries are useful for inexperienced designers, but not necessarily for expert designers: “I like design patterns because they help junior people ramp up quickly, but they kind of short-cut your thinking with allowing you to explore the problem.” While these types of findings can perhaps be explained in terms of a rational choice for efficiency and control, they importantly also suggest issues of personal identity such as a designers’ pride in her craft and expertise. They also suggest a practical knowledge or sensibility for selecting and using tools appropriate for a given situation Branding/identity. We found that some designers indicated ways that a tool or set of tools constitutes a part of her or his identity as a designer. This was suggested in part by the frequency with which participants prefaced an explanation for why they choose and use a tool with sayings such as “Well, personally I like this tool because...” Oftentimes, the designer would further go on to emphasize that other designers may not agree with their specific decision or general approach. Some designers made it explicitly clear that they thought of their choice of tools as part of their personal “branding” as a designer. For example, one participant, who ran a small interaction design consultancy, describes how Visio has become part of his branding: “I know people: they love it, they hate it [Visio], but I’ve been using it for so long and I’ve got built in macros...that it has become almost an extension of my brand at this point.” Tools, community, and design/disciplinary culture. We found that choosing a tool is also a way of identifying one’s<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> self as a designer within a particular community. For instance, an interaction designer might want to pick tools that are commonly associated with another field of design, such as graphic design or architecture, in order to gain respect or status. Choice of tools further appeared closely correlated with a designer’s background and education, and the broader design culture they were (or were not) raised in. For example, one participant with a visual design background emphasized the importance of “quality” in selecting paper, pens, and markers, while a designer with a background in information architecture discussed tool selection primarily in terms of methods, processes, and managing complexity. We found several other similar and related reasons for choosing tools when we delved further into dialogue with the interviewees.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="55" page="3" column="2">27</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="4" column="1">DIS 2012 • In the Wild</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="57" page="4" column="1">June 11–15, 2012 • Newcastle, UK</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="4" column="1">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="4" column="1">It is important to remember that this study only highlights some of the reasons and arguments behind the choices designers make. Our overall conclusion is that there is no simple way to summarize the reasons and arguments that truly guide a designer’s choice of tools. While criteria such as “efficiency” and “ease of use” may appear initially to capture key aspects of designers’ use of tools, we have surfaced a range of issues that complicate such a simplistic understanding of the designer-tool relationship. One, perhaps most important interpretation of our study is that the way designers choose their tools is influenced by their personal character and experience, and the social, material, and cultural context in which the design process takes place. We also found that our results both resonate and can be interpreted with the concepts of espoused theory and theory-in-use, as described by Argyris and Schön: When someone is asked how he would behave under certain circumstances, the answer he usually gives is his espoused theory of action for that situation. This is the theory of action to which he gives allegiance, and which, upon request, he communicates to others. However, the theory that actually governs his actions is this theory-in-use. [1, p. 6-7]. Our “rational reasons” have the character of espoused theories while our second set of findings more strongly resemble theories-in-use. Indeed it appears, and perhaps not surprisingly, that personal and contextual factors are more difficult to uncover and explicate than the espoused reasons (even though the latter are perhaps more salient and conveniently reported). Overall our study unapologetically raises more questions than answers. How can we adequately describe the relationship between designers and design tools? To what extent does the actual use of tools in practice differ from designers’ reflective explanations of their use of tools? In addition to “rational” reasons of speed, efficiency and ease of use, what is the significance of habit, identity, material environment, and culture in the use of design tools? <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> We see primarily the significance of these results when it comes to the education of interaction designers but also when it comes to strategic considerations and planning of what methods to use in professional settings. We believe that a deeper understanding of the complexity of the designer-tool relationship can make a difference for both education and practice.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="4" column="2">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="4" column="2">We thank Laura Brunetti and Jordan Fugate for their help with this project. We also thank the participants in our study and the anonymous reviewers.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" page="4" column="2">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="65" page="4" column="2">1. Argyris, M. &amp; Schön, D. 1974. Theory in Practice. Increasing professional effectiveness. Jossey-Bass.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="66" page="4" column="2">2. Buxton, B. 2007. Sketching User Experiences: Getting the Design Right and the Right Design. Morgan Kaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="67" page="4" column="2">3. Dow, S., Saponas, T.S., Li, Y., &amp; Landay, J.A. 2006. External Representations in Ubiquitous Computing Design and the Implications for Design Tools. In Proc. of DIS ’06. ACM Press, New York, NY. 241-250.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="68" page="4" column="2">4. Ehn, P. 1988: Work-Oriented Design of Computer Artifacts. Arbetslivscentrum. Stockholm.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="69" page="4" column="2">5. Goodman, E., Stolterman, E. &amp; Wakkary, R. 2011. Understanding Interaction Design Practicies. CHI 2011, May 7–12, 2011, Vancouver, BC, Canada</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="70" page="4" column="2">6. Hoeben, A., &amp; Stappers, J. 2001. Ideas: A Vision of a Designer’s Sketching Tool. Ext. Abs. CHI ’01.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="71" page="4" column="2">7. Johnson, H. &amp; Carruthers, L. 2006. Supporting Creative and Reflective Processes. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 64(10), 998-1030.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="72" page="4" column="2">8. Krippendorff, K. 2006. The Semantic Turn – a new foundation for design. Taylor &amp; Francis.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="73" page="4" column="2">9. Lawson, B. 2005. How designers think – the design process demystified. Architectural Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="74" page="4" column="2">10. Löwgren, J. &amp; Stolterman, E. 1999. Methods and Tools: Design Methodology and Design Practice. ACM interactions VI(1), ACM Press, New York, NY, 13-20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="75" page="4" column="2">11. Moggridge, B. 2007. Designing Interactions. MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="76" page="4" column="2">12. Olsen, Jr., D.R. &amp; Klemmer, S.R. 2005. The Future of User Interface Design Tools. In Ext. Abs. CHI ’05.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="77" page="4" column="2">13. Pye, D. 1969. The Nature and Aesthetics of Design. Cambium Press; Reprint edition (July 1995).</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="78" page="4" column="2">14. Rogers, Y. 2004. New Theoretical approaches for Human-Computer Interaction. In Annual Review of Information, Science and Technology, 38, 87-143.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="4" column="2">15. Rosson, M.B., Maass, S. &amp; Kellogg, W.A. 1998. The Designer as User: Building Requirements for Design Tools from Design Practice. Comm. of the ACM 31.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" page="4" column="2">16. Sennett, R. 2008. The Craftsman. Yale University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="4" column="2">17. Strauss and Corbin. 1994. Grounded theory methodology: An overview. Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="82" page="4" column="2">18. Stolterman, E., McAtee, J., Royer, D., &amp; Thandapani, S. 2008. Designerly Tools. In Proc. of DRS 2008.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" page="4" column="2">19. Winograd, T. &amp; Flores, F. 1986. Understanding computers and cognition. Ablex Publishing Corp.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84" page="4" column="2">28</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
