<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>242458ef022d7ca21dc582bb2d535e05431e4314f6bfe160975ba8c5744907c4</job>
    <base_name>62pb</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.2144/000112238</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Crafting Caring Communication:</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Hazel White</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Joanne Hodge</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Paul Mackinnon</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Sara Nevay</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Mike Press University of Dundee</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">UK h.white@dundee.ac.uk</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="9">What are the implications and benefits of collaborative making for design? This paper reports on the initial stages of research to develop a communication system with staff, parents and children at the Children’s Hospice Association Scotland’s Rachel House and a design team from the University of Dundee. The system is intended to enable Children’s Hospice Association Scotland (CHAS) staff, parents and relatives of children with complex communication needs to share the likes and dislikes of the child through a combination of workshops, handcrafted objects and an online interface.   In a series of workshops, CHAS activities staff and carers, children and their parents and siblings came together with a design team to focus on the act of making as a platform for communication. The aim was to develop innovative methods for children with reduced motor movement to access online content. However, the collaborative making workshops uncovered a different latent need: for products and services to help the parents and carers of children with complex communication needs to share information about their child’s personality, likes and environmental needs.   The research builds on two previous projects by members of the research team exploring the value of communication systems integrating bespoke handcrafted components: Pigeon Post research into communication between parents and children who are separated through illness or family breakdown and Hamefarers' Kist, a system to connect older people in the remote Shetland islands with their far-flung relatives, using networked knitted objects.   The paper discusses this initial study with CHAS - using making as a collaborative co-design method, drawing out conclusions and implications for design practice in a care context. It argues that making is a fundamental part of eliciting understanding, needs and developing trust and mutual respect between diverse stakeholders. Furthermore it demonstrates the value of craft knowledge and practice in such demanding contexts.  This initial research was funded by</abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible">the Scottish Funding Council through its Spirit Innovation Voucher Scheme.   KEYWORDS: design, collaboration, craft, co- design, healthcare, public services, service design</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="2" page="1" column="1">A case study on the value of collaborative making in a care context.</h1>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="3" column="1">Overview and Aims</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">“Give my child a voice, and me, peace of mind” 1</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="3" column="1">The aim of the KISTproject was to work with children with life-shortening conditions and their families and carers to design bespoke, handmade playful objects to enable independent access to online communication. <marker type="block"/> The objective of the research discussed in this paper was to explore with children - some of whom have complex communication needs, their families and carers at the Children’s Hospice Association Scotland (CHAS), their thoughts and preferences on designs for toys and accessories that could be used as internet controllers. We will discuss how the insights gained from the research changed the aims of the KISTproject.<marker type="block"/> Two workshops were developed using a co-design methodology – grounded in the understanding of the real life experiences, ideas and skills of the people, who use, need and run services such as CHAS. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Szebeko and Tan, 2010</xref>). Design and craft methods were used to create an environment in which observation, participation, conversation, prototyping and manufacturing could happen in the same space.<marker type="block"/> Funding was secured from the Scottish Funding Council’s Spirit Innovation Voucher scheme to run two workshops as part of a feasibility study at CHAS’ Rachel House, Kinross, one of Scotland’s two children’s hospices run by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="17" class="deo:Reference">CHAS in March and April 2012</xref>.   In this paper we will discuss two workshops which brought together design researchers from the University of Dundee with Rachel House staff, children and parents to co-design, develop and test and develop prototypes of a service system which enables access to the internet using simple handcrafted objects as ‘remote controls’. We aimed to apply an understanding of how people accept handcrafted objects as mediators of technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="18" class="deo:Reference">White &amp; Steel, 2007</xref>) and to use collaborative making of handcrafted objects as a key part of the co-design process. </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="20" page="3" column="1">1 Parent, in Workshop 1</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="4" column="1">Background and Context CHAS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" page="4" column="1">The Children’s Hospice Association Scotland is the only charity that provides hospice services in Scotland for children and young people with life-shortening conditions. CHAS offers care in two children’s hospices, Rachel House in Kinross and Robin House in the west of Scotland. The hospices support the whole family by offering short planned breaks, emergency support, end of life care and a range of bereavement services. CHAS also provides a home care service, CHAS at Home, staffed from both hospices and with dedicated teams in the north of Scotland.  CHAS supports over 300 children and their families, as well as a significant number of families who receive bereavement support (CHAS, 2012).  The families that the team worked with were visiting Rachel House in Kinross for one week’s respite care, which they will do on average, twice a year.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" page="4" column="1">Previous Research</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" page="4" column="1">The research builds on two previous projects by members of the research team exploring the value of communication systems integrating bespoke handcrafted components: Pigeon Post ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="24" class="deo:Reference">figure 1</xref>) is doctoral research exploring communication between parents and children who are separated through illness or family breakdown. Hamefarers' Kist (figure 2) is a system developed to connect older people in the remote Shetland islands with their far-flung relatives, using networked knitted objects to link people and events. Pigeon Post demonstrates the use of digitally tagged toys and accessories which enable very young children to activate Skype calls or send texts to family and relatives from whom they are separated due to illness, family breakdown or work. The soft textile based ‘input devices’ are very simple and easy to use, each is tagged with a single URL which means the object can only take the child to a pre-specified online activity or person. It is impossible to make a call to a stranger or visit an inappropriate webpage making it safe for children to use and giving the parents peace of mind.<marker type="block"/> The Hamefarers’ Kist was developed following research in Shetland into family bonds and relationships. Shetland is a group of islands halfway between Scotland and Norway famous for its distinctively patterned Fair Isle knitting. The Hamefarers’ Kist is a system to enable the Shetland diaspora, wherever in the world they live, to connect and share the events in their lives with their older relatives back in Shetland using their smartphones and tablets to generate and upload images and messages. Back in the living rooms and care homes of Shetland the content is viewed using crafted vernacular products, which fit comfortably into their surroundings. The system is powered by an iPhone and ‘Knitted Remote’, an app created by the research team’s programmer.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">The project explores how technology can be humanised by using handcrafted, often lo-fidelity artefacts created by the users to give meaning and purpose to interactions with online social</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">networks. The lo-fi approach enables non-designers to participate in the creation and development of the system.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" page="5" column="1">The relationship between the design team and CHAS was facilitated by Nora Kearney, Professor of Cancer care at the University of Dundee who had seen a demonstration of the Hamefarers' Kist and recognised its potential application in a new care environment. <marker type="block"/> The design team presented the Hamefarers' Kist and Pigeon Post to the CHAS CEO, Rachel House Director of Care, Activities Coordinator and the activities team as part of initial exploratory discussions. All were interested in exploring how these ideas could be developed further as part of Chas Plan 2011 1 2016 to "use IT to enable independence for young people by being at the heart of the development of products which enable independence and increase confidence" (CHAS, 2012) and recognised the potential for a simple service system of tagged personal objects to be used both in and beyond the hospice environments to enable access to online content.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="31" page="5" column="1">Approach and Methods</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" page="5" column="1">Input from the Rachel House activities team helped the design team develop a research question and secure funding from the Scottish funding Council's Spirit Innovation voucher scheme.  The initial question focused around how tagged textile objects could enable young people with muscular dystrophy to continue to access their favourite online content independently. Muscular dystrophy causes motor functions to diminish over time, making it increasingly difficult to use computers for socialising and entertainment, without assistance.     Two one day, co-design workshops were designed to run 4 weeks apart at Rachel House, Kinross. The research team aimed to create a natural and safe environment in which they could work over a sustained period with children, their siblings, parents and staff to understand the needs and abilities of children and their families and carers and the requirements for the system. With backgrounds in design, programming and craft, the team used their knowledge and experience of visualisation and making objects to facilitate the participating families and staff in becoming designers themselves within the co-design process, imagining how they might use the system in the future and making their ideas tangible. <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> Before the workshops the design researchers created a demonstrator system using 'fabric fobs' small RFID tagged padded pockets which could be customised by painting with fabric paint, or embroidering or embellishing with buttons, eyes, and bells, or applying transfers of drawings and photographs (figure 3). The fobs were a synthesis of the learning from the Pigeon Post and Hamefarers’ Kist projects: The plain cotton fobs were a neutral object for participants to customise – we had found that using toys in Pigeon Post made the system very age specific, which reduced interest from older children. We used RFID technology which activates without needing to be accurately placed, as we would potentially be working with young people with limited motor movement. A new iPad version of the app, which powered Hamefarers’ Kist, was programmed so that the online content could be shown on tablet technology which was familiar and readily in use by the children and staff at Rachel House.<marker type="block"/> The application used a phidgets RFID reader - a USB device attached to a Macintosh OS X laptop (www.phidgets.com). This product and supplied drivers offered a plug and play prototyping building block. The reader is a small (5cm x 5cm x 4mm) PCB circuit board powered by USB and hosting the RFID antenna and functional circuitry. The RFID tags as supplied from Phidgets are small flat plastic discs (~3cm diameter, 1mm thick). Each tag has a unique identification number which is read wirelessly when in close proximity to the reader. These tags are passive and have no power source except from the RF energy provided by the reader. The tag is activated only when close to the reader and the tag ID is transmitted to the reader. This information is sent to the iPad via the driver and server software running on the USB attached laptop. The setup is documented on the phidgets web site.<marker type="block"/> The workshops were timetabled well in advance, so the design team had no prior knowledge of which children would be visiting or what their particular needs would be, so with the support of Rachel House staff, a fairly open approach was taken in planning the format.   In the workshops, participants – children, siblings, parents and CHAS carers and activity staff could try out the demonstrator with various handmade, tagged fabric fobs which connected to online content on the iPad. For example, placing a fabric fob with 'Zola' emblazoned on it onto a reader connected to the iPad, called up an online video of footballer, Gianfranco Zola scoring a goal for Chelsea; a fabric fob with a photo transfer portrait of a young boy took the viewer to an online photo stream of the boy's holiday photographs in Greece.  The participants were enchanted; finding this interaction 'magical', they expressed delight and wonder, that such a simple, handmade object could control the iPad's online content. This sense of enchantment echoes the description by Wallace et al. concerning delight in digital craft interaction:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">" Enchantment does not necessarily imply that the object of enchantment must be novel or extraordinary, rather that the person sees how rich and extraordinary the everyday and familiar</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">can be...An object or interactive system that is likely to evoke enchantment should offer the potential for the unexpected, give the chance of new discoveries, and provide a range of possibilities." (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Wallace et al., 2005</xref>)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" page="7" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Hodge (2011)</xref> describes the use of the technology in familiar objects and toys as magical and very intuitive, especially for children. Small artifacts can be tagged and re-tagged to different content then sent or gifted to a distant child from the parent and vice versa. This aspect has the ability to randomise the act of communication and helps to keep it fun and fresh and prevents users from getting into a ‘boring’ or ‘stale’ routine of communication where both sides can become frustrated and feel isolated from each other. While the use of RFID tagging has been developed and is being developed for a more commercial and business route (e.g. fast secure payments via a hand held mobile device) there is scope for this type of technology to be used in communication in a more emotive and mindful way. This enables messages, images and videos to be played through a computer or internet ready television set simply by swiping or placing the object onto a reader. Each object represents a different person or trip or time apart. The possibilities for this type of communication object are vast alongside the customisable aspect of the objects, where each object can be easily tailored to the individual allowing for a greater connection and resonance with the object and communication system. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Hodge (2011)</xref> suggests that textile objects offer an appealing platform for communication objects due to the tactile and familiar nature of fabric. Wallace (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="41" class="deo:Reference">McCarthy et al., 2005</xref>) reflects this sentiment “our interest in enchantment ... seems more like an active engagement with the sensory qualities of the artifact”.<marker type="block"/> We interacted with around six children, seven parents and nine activity and care team staff from Rachel House over the two day workshops. Below we discuss interactions and findings from two families. The children of both families had very complex communication needs, so their parents, siblings and CHAS staff told us about their lives.<marker type="block"/> The concept of a tangible object activating a known web resource on the iPad was easily communicated and demonstrated. The simplicity and power of the idea was immediately apparent and did not need any great explanation or justification. However, an immediate problem was also readily communicated in the demonstrations. The first prototype required the child to drop the fabric fob into a bowl with sloping sides to help place the cushions near the RFID reader. This was awkward to do, and impossible to retrieve for someone with limited movement, so a simpler solution was discussed. The demonstrations were powerful in allowing the design researchers to recognise the wide range of physical and cognitive abilities of the children, and therefore their differing needs. The assumption that we would be working with children with full cognitive abilities and slowly diminishing motors functions, and their families, seemed now somewhat naïve and limited.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> In both workshops the hands-on demonstration of fobs connecting to the internet helped participants to think firstly about the online content that would be relevant to them and secondly imagery they would like to apply to the fabric fobs.  In workshop one we worked with a family which was fairly new to the hospice; this was their second visit.  Amy (name changed) who has cerebral palsy, was staying in the hospice for a week with her mother, father and younger sibling.<marker type="block"/> Following demonstrations of the prototype, Amy’s father was very quickly able to imagine and articulate ways in which Amy might benefit from an adapted version of the system. For example, small movements of tagged objects could be tagged to sounds. Amy wore a number of accessories including hair bands and bracelets which led her father to suggest that if Amy could use a small amount of voluntary movement to move a tagged bracelet across a reader(s) she might independently indicate basic needs, such as needing the toilet. Together the researchers, family, child and staff developed the idea of a mat which could sit in the tray of Amy's wheelchair. Amy could move her wrist across the different sections of the mat, and this would link to different online content, from recorded voice commands such as  ‘I need the toilet’ to playing films that Amy likes. Technically, this could be achieved by arranging multiple RFID readers in a tray or a similar type of development to expand the capability of the sensing environment.<marker type="block"/> Amy's mother and sibling participated very actively in the making part of the workshop, creating painted, embroidered and embellished fabric fobs which represented both their own and Amy's interests, from music and dance to favourite toys. Amy’s family spent 90 minutes sitting together with the design researchers and the activities' staff and carers from CHAS, chatting naturally about home, holidays and family life. Participants could use paper or fabric to work with; when designs were completed, they were sewn up, padded and tagged in the workshop. Amy’s mother, sibling and CHAS staff created a number of fabric fobs including a fairy with a magic wand drawn with fabric paints designed to connect to videos of jazz dancing, fobs embellished with buttons and bells which would connect to favourite online stories and videos and photographic transfer images that could connect to family photographs.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">The first workshop uncovered a range of design opportunities, including validating the original premise of enabling independent access to online content with some of the children, but suggesting other needs for children with more complex communication requirements. In the interim, the design team made a prototype sensor mat to present to new children and families. This was a multi-pocket felt construction, designed so that each individual coloured pocket contained sensors for different functions. This mat was trialled at the second workshop with the caveat that it had not taken a long time to make and we work to the principle of ‘prototype like you’re right, listen like you’re wrong’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Moon, 2011</xref>). The feedback from staff</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="9" column="1">indicated that the mat we had constructed was functionally very similar to a command button, a decision making product already available to scroll through a limited number of communication options. The making of the prototype was however very valuable as a tangible example of what we had discussed at the previous workshop - it helped us to see that it essentially replicated an existing product, if not in form, then in function, and prevented us losing time pursuing it further.   The family we worked with most closely in workshop two was a mother and father and their son who has very complex communication needs. Connor (name changed) cannot independently communicate and has little voluntary movement. His parents were very interested in working with us having seen a demonstration of the fobs linking to content on an iPad. We spent some time discussing Connor’s home life whilst sitting around the table with the sewing materials and thinking of imagery, which might be used on textile fabric fobs. This elicited a wealth of information from family boat trips to sounds Connor responded to in his grandparent’s house to revealing that a piece of music had been composed in his name. The conversation whilst sitting around the table drawing and looking at the craft materials led to discussions about the view from Connor’s living room window, which prompted his mother to go and get her laptop and share their recent family photographs with us. During these conversations Connor's mother, the design team and carers were drawing and assembling fabric fobs reflecting the discussion. Connor's parents had painted such a vivid picture of their life with their son, we undertook to make a very quick prototype. Over the next two hours a system of handmade objects was prototyped that could connect to an online interface enabling both staff at Rachel House and Connor's grandparents to easily access music, images and video associated with Connor. For example, a fabric fob with a picture of a fiddle connected to the piece of music which had been composed especially for Connor, and a fob with a picture of the boat referring to recent family trips. The parents were clearly delighted with the results and were able to try out the completed fabric interfaces and imagine how they might work at home with Connor's grandparents and at Rachel House with staff. The discussion and evaluation of this rapidly constructed hand crafted demonstrator with the family and CHAS staff led to the development of the key requirements for the next iteration of the system.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1"> </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="52" page="10" column="1">Key Findings</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">  Latent needs In both the families we worked with, the child receiving care had both complex communication needs and limited or non-existent voluntary movement. This was a very different scenario from the initial research question of supporting children with muscular dystrophy to continue accessing the internet independently. This led us to uncover a latent need: for products and services to help the parent and carers of children with complex communication needs to share information about their child/s personality, likes and home life. Communication</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="10" column="1">The activity of sitting, making at a table covered with fabric, paints, pens and buttons created a relaxed, peaceful environment. It was very natural to sit in silence whilst drawing or sewing, so conversation was unforced. This activity allows things to happen in a non-linear way, both mentally and physically, echoing experience from the Hamefarer's Kist project in Shetland. In this project, White learned to knit with residents and discovered that this shared activity elicited conversation and engendered trust. Rachel House staff commented that they had ‘got to know’ the family in Workshop 1, well, in a relatively short time, whereas they might have expected to have built that relationship over a number of visits. CHAS staff also commented that they themselves were not particularly ‘tech savvy’, so they would value a simple, engaging tangible method of accessing personal, emotional information about the children and they would also value the service system being used to upload pictures from the children’s school’s so that they had a quick way of assessing the child’s development between visits.   Privacy</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">It was also clear that a service used to store or index online content would need to have easily understood privacy controls as there were trust issues expressed about existing social networks and there are clear privacy and ethical issues surrounding storing children and families’ personal information and images.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="11" column="1">The wider value of collaborative making</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="11" column="1">This project demonstrates the value of craft-based collaborative making in a healthcare context in ways rarely explored by previous research. Much of the research on the value of craft in health contexts focuses on its therapeutic benefits. As Betsan has argued, knitting has a role in replacing addictive behaviours such as smoking, alcoholism, and the symptoms of Obsessive Compulsive Disorder. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Argyle and Bolton (2005)</xref> outline further therapeutic benefits of art and craft, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Fratiglioni et al (2004)</xref>, in the context of dementia care, attribute benefits to craft’s role as a social activity.<marker type="block"/> As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Yair (2011)</xref> rightly observes, “Craft’s contribution to wellbeing is not limited to clinical and therapeutic settings. In the wider community, there are very specific ways in which craft can bring us together and strengthen our sense of connectedness.” Yair cites examples of how craft can contribute to community development, skills development and employability, thus contributing indirectly to health and wellbeing.<marker type="block"/> Yair also refers to research and creative practice by Jayne Wallace who has explored the value of creating jewellery objects for use in clinical contexts. As Wallace has explained (ibid): “One aim in this research is to use the fact that jewellery objects have the ability to accompany us through our experiences and to act as anchor points to events in our lives and consequently our sense of who we are.”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Wallace has clearly demonstrated the power of objects as signifiers and storytellers in healthcare settings, and the potential of designers and makers to orientate their practices to the specific demands of such settings. Research has thus demonstrated (i) the therapeutic value of making both in itself and as a consequence of its social dynamics, (ii) the community based value of craft that has indirect health and wellbeing benefits and (iii) the value of handmade objects in some clinical contexts. However, there has been less attention paid to studying the processes of creative making as a mediator between providers and recipients of healthcare. The value of this study is in demonstrating the potential value of this, not only as a means of enhancing communication per se, but very specifically as a process by which families and carers can be encouraged and enabled to become designers of their own interactions.  </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" page="12" column="1">Future Implications</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="12" column="1">Subsequent analysis of the workshop findings suggested that an innovative and useful development would be a service system where families could create their own (multiple) controllers at Rachel House or at home and share them with carers and family, to access private social networks to share the lives, likes, dislikes and personalities of children with very complex communication needs. The emphasis shifted to families and carers using the system, rather than children themselves. This has significant beneficial cost implications, in that the technology used to enable this is simpler, cheaper and more easily available. Integral to the development of a new service is the ease of its integration into the daily routine, its’ accessibility and privacy; the lives of the families using CHAS services are busy and so a system tailored to their needs, yet familiar in format would be ideal. <marker type="block"/> The proposed social network will encapsulate the importance of the tangible object. The latest iterations of ‘remote control’ objects developed following the workshops at Rachel House were customized mugs, key rings and cards - all familiar, everyday items that can be easily personalised. These could be given as gifts or used to commemorate an event. Children and families can make these objects in reflection of their life and share them with family, friends and carers. Using easily available products and customising them through drawing and further craft embellishments allows for a more manageable activity.<marker type="block"/> The outcome of the project has been the development of design requirements for a system which will enable staff at CHAS and the families and relatives of children with complex communication needs to share the personality of a child through bespoke handcrafted objects which link to private social networks. This secure communication platform will connect key relationships in a child’s life by enabling children and families to safely share information, meaningful content and memories as they are made, interact with other families and services, and afford care providers deeper insight into a child’s life allowing for an overall greater quality of care.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">The impact of using a co-design process has been the uncovering of latent opportunities and needs: working together with children, their families and carers in ‘craft co-creation’ workshops enabled conversations about family relationships, home, music, films, sounds and other leisure and school activities to be shared and documented. The project enabled children, families and carers of children with complex communication needs to become designers of their own interactions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="13" column="1">The team has been invited to continue working with the organisation in a number of ways to support staff innovation and the partners will continue to collaborate to establish a bespoke private network, creating and testing further prototypes with the hospice team as well as seeking funding to scale. The project's development will be determined by CHAS and the families and children's needs. The team intend to develop a toolkit which will enable CHAS staff to run their own ‘making’ workshops , which will create further opportunities learn about the children and their families lives through making things together.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pb.page_014.image_01.png" thmb="62pb.page_014.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="71" page="14" column="1">Figure 1 Pigeon Post – Instant Messenger Teddy and Figure 2 Hamefarers' Kist</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx72">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pb.page_014.image_02.png" thmb="62pb.page_014.image_02-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="73" page="14" column="1">Figure 3 Customised Fabric Fobs</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx74">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pb.page_015.image_03.png" thmb="62pb.page_015.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Figure 4 fabric fob demonstration</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx76">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pb.page_015.image_04.png" thmb="62pb.page_015.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Figure 5 Workshop 1 and Figure 6 – fabric fob made by participant</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx78">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pb.page_015.image_05.png" thmb="62pb.page_015.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="79" page="15" column="1">Figure 7 – customized mugs as input devices</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="80" page="16" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="16" column="1">Argyle, E, Bolton, G (2005) Art in the community for potentially vulnerable mental health groups, Health Education, Vol. 105 Iss: 5, pp.340 – 354</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" page="16" column="1">Betsan Corkhill (2007) Therapeutic Knitting; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.knitonthenet.com/issue4/features/" id="82">http://www.knitonthenet.com/issue4/features/</ext-link> therapeuticknitting/ Accessed: 5/9/2012</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="85" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">CHAS, (2012) Annual Report and Accounts <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.chas.org.uk/assets/0000/6467/" id="84">http://www.chas.org.uk/assets/0000/6467/</ext-link> CHAS_Annual_Report_2011-12_LR.pdf, acessed 12.9.12</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="16" column="1">Fratiglioni, L, Paillard-Borg, S, Winblad, B (2004) , An active and socially integrated lifestyle in late life might protect against dementia, The Lancet Neurology, Volume 3, Issue 6, June 2004, Pages 343-353</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="16" column="1">Hodge, J (2011) Facilitating Communication over Distances Between Parent &amp; Child through Interactive Textile Objects. Arts and Humanities Research Council Funded PhD Transfer Report, University of Dundee.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="16" column="1">McCarthy, J., Wright, P., Wallace, J. and Dearden, A. M. (2005) The experience of enchantment in human computer interaction. Personal and ubiquitous computing, 10 (6) 369-378</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Moon, J. TED Global, Edinburgh 12.6.11<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://blog.ted.com/" id="89">http://blog.ted.com/</ext-link> 2011/07/12/%E2%80%9Ccreativity-is-the-life-force-of-the-universe%E2%80%9D-report- from-session-2-of-ted-university/ accessed 31/1/13</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="91" page="16" column="1">Szebeko, D &amp;Tan, L. (2010) Co-designing for Society. AMJ 2010;3(9):580-590.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="16" column="1">Wallace, J (2010) Personhood in dementia, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.digitaljewellery.com/jaynewallace/" id="92">http://www.digitaljewellery.com/jaynewallace/</ext-link> personhood_in_dementia.html accessed: 5/9/2012</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">White, H., Steel, E., (2007) Agents of Change: From Collection to Connection, The Design Journal, Vol. 10, No. 2, p.22-34, Ashgrove</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">White, H (2009) remotes/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://hazelsnotes.wordpress.com/interactive-craft/knitted-remotes/" id="95">http://hazelsnotes.wordpress.com/interactive-craft/knitted-remotes/</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="16" column="1">Yair, K (2011) Craft and Wellbeing; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.craftscouncil.org.uk/about-us/press-room/" id="97">http://www.craftscouncil.org.uk/about-us/press-room/</ext-link> view/2011/craft-and-wellbeing?from=/about-us/press-room/list/ accessed: 5/9/2012<marker type="block"/>  </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
