<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>dabd6ecc0117137a8b900df67e9b1512cf29ac71b48f1e9c37ed9dbb13712bb7</job>
    <base_name>62l2</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.5465/amr.2008.32465708</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Academy of Management Review 2008, Vol. 33, No. 3, 649–668.</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">BRAINSTORMING RECONSIDERED: A GOAL-BASED VIEW</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">ROBERT C. LITCHFIELD Washington</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Jefferson College</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5" confidence="possible">In this paper I propose goal setting as a mechanism for linking brainstorming research to organizational creativity. Using the large body of literature on brainstorming as a prototype, I develop a goal-based view of intervention in idea generation. A goal-based view provides new insight into the conduct and evaluation of brainstorming research that improves its relevance to management, and it suggests a broader agenda for defining expectations for creative ideas and tailoring interventions to match these definitions.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">Idea generation is widely understood as an important stage or component process in models of creativity and innovation in organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="6" class="deo:Reference">Glynn, 1996</xref>; Shalley, Zhou, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95" id="7" class="deo:Reference">Oldham, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107" id="8" class="deo:Reference">West, 2002a</xref>). Yet when the topic turns to intervening to improve idea generation, we seem to know far less. In this article I aim to spark interest among management researchers in studying interventions to improve idea generation. I use insights from research on goals to connect the brainstorming and the organizational creativity literature, positing brainstorming as a goal- based intervention in idea generation processes. I focus on brainstorming because of its long history and large research base, but the goal-based view I propose is intended to examine the goal content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 2004</xref>) of this popular intervention and to compare it to alternatives. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="10" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> developed brainstorming as a means to improve idea generation, most brainstorming research does not directly assess its functioning as an intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Parnes, 1963</xref>; Taylor, Berry, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Block, 1958</xref>). On the contrary, virtually all brainstorming research conducted in the last thirty years confounds this intervention with the task of idea generation by providing Osborn’s (1957) set of four rules to all idea generators. The confound-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">I thank associate editor Randall Peterson and three anonymous reviewers for their many comments that immensely improved this paper throughout the review process. I also thank Greg Leatherman and Rachael Woldoff for comments on earlier drafts, and Jennifer Corbin for library assistance. I presented an earlier version of this paper at the 2006 an- nual meeting of the Academy of Management in Atlanta.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="2">ing is so complete that many now consider brainstorming as a task. One consequence of this confounding is that brainstorming research arguably tells us little about how the technique works as an intervention. A second consequence has been to obscure the fact that brainstorming is a complex intervention that reflects strong claims about how to improve idea generation. Not all agree with these claims. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> argued that generating as many ideas as possible offers the best chance of generating creative ideas. This proposition has received support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>, 1991), but there is also evidence of trade-offs between quantity and creativity in organizational contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Many questions remain about the types of actions managers should take to create expectations for idea generation (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>; Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99" id="19" class="deo:Reference">Tierney &amp; Farmer, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108" id="20" class="deo:Reference">West, 2002b</xref>). These questions reveal that expectations for creative ideas are often vague and complex. Ob- servers may frequently agree on creative ideas after the fact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>), but designing successful interventions to improve idea generation requires a more precise tailoring of our expectations in advance. I propose a goal-based view of intervention to accomplish this tailoring. I begin by outlining a rationale for continuing research on ways to improve idea generation. I then briefly discuss the need for research that considers brainstorming as an intervention and suggest goals as a bridge between the brainstorming and the organizational creativity literature. After that, I cast brainstorming as goal assignment and show how existing research supports the conceptualization of the four rules<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> of brainstorming as goals. In the next part of the paper, I present a goal-based view of brainstorming as a prototype for examining the broader question of goals in idea generation. I note links between the brainstorming and the creativity literature and fundamental ideas from goal-setting theory. I then expand the discus- sion to include a brief overview of research on multiple goal contexts. Finally, I show how a goal-based view suggests alternative interpretations of the meaning of a creative idea that can be used to focus idea generation in organizations.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23" page="1" column="2">649 Copyright of the Academy of Management, all rights reserved. Contents may not be copied, emailed, posted to a listserv, or otherwise transmitted without the copyright holder’s express written permission. Users may print, download, or email articles for individual use only.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24" page="2" column="1">650</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="2" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="26" page="2" column="1">July</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="2" column="1">IDEA GENERATION: WHY WORRY?</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="2" column="1">Are ideas cheap or dear? Although it is widely accepted that organizations need creative ideas, researchers have increasingly focused their attention on other aspects of innovation. This pattern may reflect a lack of agreement about whether generating ideas is easy or difficult (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108" id="30" class="deo:Reference">West, 2002b</xref>). After all, if good ideas are relatively easy to obtain, then perhaps researchers should focus on later stages of the innovation process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108" id="31" class="deo:Reference">West, 2002b</xref>). But two observations suggest caution in claiming that good ideas are easy to obtain. First, idea generation typically produces a high ratio of bad ideas to good ones, and idea selection mechanisms often function poorly (Goldenberg, Lehmann, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Mazursky, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="33" class="deo:Reference">March, 2006</xref>; Rietzschel, Nijstad, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Stroebe, 2006</xref>). These facts suggest that if idea selection processes can be conceived as draws from underlying distribu- tions containing ideas of varying quality, then improvements in idea generation might result in the selection of more good ideas, even if selection mechanisms themselves remain difficult to improve. Given the costs of sifting through mountains of poor ideas, even a marginal improvement in the targeting of idea generation efforts might convey substantial practical benefits. Second, managerial theorizing has often emphasized conscious, individual choice to engage in creativity (e.g., Drazin, Glynn, &amp; Kazanjian, 1999; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>). Thus, treating ideas as if they are cheap seems likely to reduce employees’ motivation for creative action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>). There is some evidence that managers can act to improve idea generation. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Scott and Bruce (1994)</xref> found that the degree to which employees perceived organizational support for<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> innovation, including support for new ideas, mediated the relationship between leader-member exchange and a measure of innovative behavior that included idea generation. More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Tierney and Farmer (2004)</xref> found that the effects of management expectations for creativity on employees’ creative behavior were mediated by employee perceptions of management behaviors to initiate, support, and recognize creative efforts. Finally, in their qualitative study of brainstorming at the design firm IDEO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Sutton and Hargadon (1996)</xref> observed that IDEO’s use of the intervention for idea generation led to a variety of beneficial outcomes. Other research indicates that interventions may have negative effects on creativity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>), and success at one stage of the innovation process is no guarantee of innovation success as a whole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107" id="42" class="deo:Reference">West, 2002a</xref>). Together, the potential positive effects from intervening to improve idea generation and the potential negative effects of doing it incorrectly signal a continuing need for research (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 2002</xref>). As the largest body of research on intervening to improve idea generation, brainstorming deserves special attention.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="2" column="2">BRAINSTORMING AS AN INTERVENTION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="2" column="2">Brainstorming ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Osborn, 1957</xref>) is an intervention in which individuals, groups, and organizations adhere to a set of four rules while working in sessions designated to generate ideas. The rules are (1) to generate as many ideas as possible, (2) to avoid criticizing any of the ideas, (3) to attempt to combine and improve on previ- ously articulated ideas, and (4) to encourage the generation of “wild” ideas. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> called this last rule “free-wheeling.” In a typical application, members of a group attempt to follow the rules while providing ideas about a topic until they either run out of ideas or use up the allotted time. Despite its initial framing, two major themes in brainstorming research have drawn attention away from investigating brainstorming’s function as an intervention. First, most brainstorming research has focused on the question of whether individuals or groups are more produc- tive idea generators (for reviews, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Kerr &amp; Tindale, 2004</xref>; Mullen, Johnson, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Salas, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Brown, 2003</xref>). Studies conducted in this tradition have produced a wealth of knowledge<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> about possible variations in the procedures ac- companying the brainstorming rules (e.g., speaking versus writing ideas, individual versus group accountability, electronic versus face- to-face meetings 1 ), but because all participants in these studies were provided with the four brainstorming rules, this research did not really test brainstorming per se as an intervention to improve idea generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Parnes, 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Taylor et al., 1958</xref>). As a result, we simply do not know whether all of the brainstorming rules are necessary or even helpful for idea generation. Second, brainstorming research has increasingly emphasized cognitive processes. As many researchers began to conclude that classic approaches to group motivation did not explain differences in idea generation between individuals and groups (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Paulus, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>, 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Mullen et al., 1991</xref>), some began to examine whether a cognitive approach formed a better basis for understanding the task (e.g., Brown, Tumeo, Larey, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Paulus, 1998</xref>; Nijstad, Diehl, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Stroebe, 2003</xref>). Cognitive research is clearly important because it shows that many questions remain about how knowledge is activated in idea generation, but the fact that it has also taken Osborn’s (1957) rules as givens has made separating its contributions to brainstorming interventions from those that ap- ply to idea generation tasks difficult. Management theorists agree that making a conscious, individual choice to produce and develop or articulate novel ideas is a starting point for organizational creativity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Drazin et al., 1999</xref>: 290 –291; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Glynn, 1996</xref>; Woodman, Sawyer, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Griffin, 1993</xref>). Goals, which are usually conceived as desired states or outcomes, directly address the conscious choices that individuals make to engage in cognition and behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Austin &amp; Vancouver, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>). Since theories of organizational creativity (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Drazin et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>) and goal-based research on work motivation (Locke</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="52" page="3" column="1">2008</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="53" page="3" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54" page="3" column="1">651</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">1 In this paper I do not discuss research on electronic brainstorming (EBS) as a separate phenomenon. Although its advocates have claimed many benefits of EBS, researchers continue to debate whether differences between EBS and other forms of brainstorming are more real or apparent (e.g., see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Dennis &amp; Valacich, 1999</xref>, and Pinsonneault, Barki, Gallupe, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Hoppen, 1999a</xref>,b). Most EBS studies are quite similar to those reviewed here (for a recent review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Dennis &amp; Williams, 2003</xref>). Importantly, the use of EBS does not affect the theoretical issues discussed in this paper.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="3" column="2">&amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Latham, 2004</xref>) share a common emphasis on conscious choice, goals form a logical basis for intervention that might also be used to develop a better connection between the brainstorming literature and the organizational creativity literature. Moreover, goals operate through cognitive processes, adding value by directing and sustaining attention and effort in knowledge activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Locke, 2000</xref>), so their use as an intervention technology is compatible with cognitive research on idea generation. The work motivation literature and organizational creativity literature are mostly separate, but researchers interested in the effects of goals have occasionally used idea generation tasks (for a review, see Wood, Mento, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Locke, 1987</xref>), and a few organizational creativity researchers have used goal-based approaches (Carson &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Carson &amp; Carson, 1993</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1991</xref>, 1995). Combining these perspectives with Osborn’s rules produces a view of brainstorming as goal assignment.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="81" page="3" column="2">BRAINSTORMING AS GOAL ASSIGNMENT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="92" page="3" column="2">Because individuals are asked to strive to follow Osborn’s (1957) four rules while generating ideas, the rules can be seen as constituting a set of goals. Thus, from the perspective of goal- based theories of motivation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>), brainstorming interventions attempt to simultaneously assign multiple goals for idea generation. Although it is relatively easy to define the four goals that brainstorming rules seek to assign, other goals may be inadvertently activated because of individual differences in perception and trait goals (see below). The first rule—to generate as many ideas as possible—seems to constitute an obvious goal for quantity; how- ever, it may also trigger goals for matching one’s outputs to others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Paulus, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>). The second—to avoid criticism—suggests a goal to suppress evaluation of alternatives, but it may also prompt a goal to avoid conflict. The third rule—to combine and build—relates to a still broader variety of additional goals, including paying attention to others’ contributions, integrating ideas into categories, or even compet- ing with others to suggest the best ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Finally, the fourth rule—to encourage free-wheeling—is most directly associated with goals for creativity, but it also might<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> relate to other goals for personal status (e.g., to achieve status through humor or through providing the most creative ideas; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>) or goals about affect (e.g., to put everyone in a good mood with some funny ideas). In this section I provide a selective review of brainstorming research indexed by the four rules. My primary aim is to show how previous research is compatible with treating each rule as a goal, but I also assess the evidence that each rule reliably aids idea generation. I restrict my attention here to brainstorming studies. In the following section I add goal setting and organizational creativity research to the picture.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="88" page="4" column="1">652</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="89" page="4" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="90" page="4" column="1">July</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="93" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Rule 1: Generate Quantity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" page="4" column="1">It has become an accepted truth that brainstorming rules are better than nothing at facili- tating the generation of a large number of ideas, but only a few studies have contrasted brainstorming interventions with nonbrainstorming control groups ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Brown, 2003</xref>). Close examination reveals potential problems with all but one of these studies. For example, Parnes and Meadow (1959; see also Meadow, Parnes, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Reese, 1959</xref>) measured only the production of ideas rated as “good,” but their participants were not told anything about how good ideas would be scored. The control groups in these studies were told to write down only good ideas. Thus, this research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Parnes &amp; Meadow, 1959</xref>) found that brainstorming rules are better than do-your-best quantity goals constrained by vague quality goals (“good”) at stimulating individuals to produce ideas that will be rated as good according to criteria not provided to the participants themselves. Others have found that people given brainstorming instructions will generate more total ideas (regardless of quality) than those told to write down only good ideas (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Lamm &amp; Trommsdorff, 1973</xref>). The key problem with all of these studies is that brainstorming’s impact on quantity production was not tested against a quantity goal presented alone (i.e., without other explicit con- straints, such as quality). To date, the only study that appears to have conducted this sort of test failed to find reliable differences between brainstorming and nonbrainstorming instructions (Gerlach, Schutz, Baker, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Mazer, 1964</xref>). Beginning with the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Taylor et al. (1958)</xref>, the major questions studied by brainstorming<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> researchers have concerned whether individuals or groups produce more ideas. Like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Taylor et al. (1958)</xref>, most have concluded that equivalent numbers of individuals working alone (i.e., nominal groups, whose ideas are combined to create a group score) outperform interacting groups in terms of the total number of nonredundant ideas generated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Mullen et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Brown, 2003</xref>). Research comparing individuals to groups has also commonly assessed idea generators’ perceptions of the number of ideas generated, but such self-reports are known to be inaccurate (Paulus, Dzindolet, Poletes, &amp; Camacho, 1993). Whether they generate ideas alone or in a group, people exhibit a consistent “illusion of group productivity,” believing that productivity is higher in groups when, in fact, individuals working alone generate more ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Paulus et al., 1993</xref>). The findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Paulus et al. (1993)</xref> have been widely replicated, and it seems safe to say that if one seeks an objective measure of quantity, self-reports should not be trusted. However, the illusion of productivity might be a valuable affective outcome in some work contexts (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Paulus, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Overall, viewing brainstorming as an intervention that assigns goals reveals a surprising lack of evidence that the use of brainstorming rules provides an advantage over a quantity goal presented alone for bringing about the generation of a large number of ideas. Evidence that individuals generate more ideas than groups is strong, but individuals may feel better about their productivity when working in groups.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="109" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">Rule 2: Avoid Criticism</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" page="4" column="2">In early research scholars assumed that avoiding criticism was the critical rule of brainstorming ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Lamm &amp; Trommsdorf, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Parnes, 1963</xref>), which explains why nonbrainstorming participants in comparative studies were typically told to criticize ideas (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Bouchard, 1969</xref>: Experiment 2). However, studies using nonbrainstorming conditions have not provided a clean test of this goal, because the nonbrainstorming procedures typically have included additional instructions that conflict with other brainstorming rules (e.g., instructions to generate “useful” ideas, which conflict with Osborn’s free-wheeling rule). A further problem is that both early studies (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Lamm &amp; Trommsdorf, 1973</xref>) and more recent studies (Nemeth, Person-<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> naz, Personnaz, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Goncalo, 2004</xref>) have failed to produce a consistent picture of the effect of avoiding criticism on idea generation. One reason for this difficulty may be that individuals often do not pursue this goal, nor do they believe that others will achieve it. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Sutton and Hargadon (1996)</xref> observed that frequent vi- olations of this rule in the organization that they studied created what they termed status auc- tions, where individuals’ reputations at work were determined in part by judgments about the quality of their contributions in idea generation sessions. This can deliver a morale boost to some employees, but others find the pressure threatening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Some participants in laboratory brainstorming studies also seem to anticipate that this rule will be violated, and researchers have found that anxiety about having one’s contributions judged, termed evaluation apprehension, contributes to productivity loss as some individuals preemp- tively censor their contributions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Camacho &amp; Paulus, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>). Overall, some people seem to be threatened by potential criticisms of their contributions, raising the question of whether this goal reduces feelings of threat or makes them even more salient. A second reason for the conflicting findings regarding this goal may be that some individuals construe it as a broad prohibition against comment on ideas. Laboratory research often aims to suppress all social aspects of group interaction (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Yang, 2000</xref>), but this practice may not be desirable in organizations. After all, a prohibition against comment on others’ ideas also prohibits verbalizations of the form “Wow, that’s great, have you thought about . . . ?” that could aid incubation while preserving individual credit for the initial idea (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Thus, the apparent obviousness of this goal may mask an underlying complexity.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="115" page="5" column="1">2008</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="116" page="5" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="117" page="5" column="1">653</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="128" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Rule 3: Combine and Improve on Previous Ideas</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" page="5" column="1">To date, it seems that no study has directly examined the combination and spontaneous improvement of ideas under brainstorming instructions. Cognitive researchers have sought to understand knowledge activation in idea generation by measuring whether exposure to other <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ideas results in such effects as cognitive stimulation or interference in terms of the number (Dugosh, Paulus, Roland, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Yang, 2000</xref>) and type of ideas generated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Larey &amp; Paulus, 1999</xref>; Nijstad, Stroebe, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Lodewijkx, 2002</xref>), but the lack of focus on combining and/or improving previous ideas makes it impossible to draw any firm conclusions about the effects of this goal. It is possible to view the combine and improve goal more broadly as an attempt to influence relationships between generated ideas. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Coskun, Paulus, Brown, and Sherwood (2000)</xref> found that stimulating individuals with category information enhanced the quantity and breadth of ideas. These researchers (2000) interpreted their results in terms of cognitive prim- ing, but because participants were presented with categories within an overall problem and were instructed to generate ideas in these categories, the category primes can be considered as goals that refined the quantity goal of brainstorming by increasing the number of categories to which ideas were to be contributed. When category goals were presented in a uniform time structure (i.e., repeated every three minutes), Coskun et al. (2000: Experiment 2) found that presenting participants with higher numbers of categories led to more idea generation. This finding is consistent with the associative mem- ory perspective on brainstorming developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Brown et al. (1998)</xref>, but it can also be seen as assigning and reiterating a set of goals that vary in difficulty (i.e., number of categories). In organizations, combining and building goals may cause negative effects if employees view this in competitive terms (Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996). Together with a construal of avoiding criticism as avoiding comment, a possible negative outcome of brainstorming interventions could be to reward individuals for withholding their own less developed ideas while combining and building on others’ ideas in a bid to seize credit. Although far-fetched as an explanation for effects in laboratory studies of idea generation, these patterns of goals could occur in work contexts. Despite these concerns, the approach taken by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Coskun et al. (2000)</xref> is important because it suggests that goals can shape idea generation in complex ways. Stimulating individuals to combine categories or form new ones could be a useful focus for future research integrating<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> goals and cognition. 2 The assertion that the effects in studies like those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Coskun et al. (2000)</xref> could be due in part to assigned goals may be controversial to some because attentional prompting is a common element of cognitive research. However, if we treat each brainstorming rule as a goal, then it is important to treat additional prompts in a similar fashion.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="137" page="6" column="1">654</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="138" page="6" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="139" page="6" column="1">July</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="142" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Rule 4: Encourage Free-Wheeling</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" page="6" column="1">Given the association between brainstorming and creativity, it is notable that the degree of free-wheeling is frequently ignored as a depen- dent measure (for a similar point, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="143" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). This may be due to the fact that brainstorming research has concluded that quality (i.e., creativity) and quantity in idea generation are strongly linked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>, 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Mullen et al., 1991</xref>). Similar conclusions have been reached elsewhere in the creativity literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Simonton, 2003</xref>). However, many problems with quality measures have been noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>, 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>), which may explain the incon- sistent effects found in the few studies that have compared brainstorming and nonbrainstorming groups on this dimension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Lamm &amp; Trommsdorff, 1973</xref>). A recent investigation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Rietzschel et al. (2006)</xref> illustrates the difficulty in measuring quality. These authors attempted to respond to Sutton and Hargadon’s (1996) call to look beyond quantity measures by incorporating idea selection into a brainstorming study. They reached the provocative conclusion that average creativity is important because individuals do not seem to select the best ideas from their lists when given the chance, but this conclusion is open to question because participants in their study interpreted their quality goal in multiple ways. The differing interpretations highlight the fact that creativity is not really a single goal. Instead, creativity is defined in brainstorming studies as some combination of originality and feasibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="151" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>, 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="152" class="deo:Reference">Rietzschel et al., 2006</xref>). Another problem with quality measures is that Osborn’s (1957) concept of free-wheeling</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">2 I thank an anonymous reviewer for suggesting this point.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" page="6" column="2">does not focus on the average creativity of responses. Rather, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="155" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> wanted extreme responses (i.e., wild ideas). If one assumes that the goal of brainstorming is often to generate as little as a single idea that is really creative, the tendency to balance feasibility and originality in assessing this rule seems to run counter to Osborn’s proposal. One alternative might be to focus on the creativity of the most extreme response. Another strategy involves disaggregating feasibility and originality into separate goals. I return to this strategy below. It is interesting to note, in concluding this section, that brainstorming studies measure creativity of ideas in a fashion similar to that in the organizational creativity literature: as a combination of novelty and usefulness. However, brainstorming interventions reflect a claim that the goals necessary to produce creative ideas are for quantity and novelty. In contrast, organizational creativity research seems to favor focusing directly on combining usefulness and novelty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="156" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>). A goal-based view of brainstorming can provide a framework to compare these and other alternatives.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="158" page="6" column="2">A GOAL-BASED VIEW OF BRAINSTORMING</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" page="6" column="2">In the previous section I proposed that the four rules of brainstorming can be viewed as goals, and I related existing brainstorming research to each goal. A goal-based view of brainstorming applies the principles of work motivation theories to describe brainstorming interventions. To develop this view, I begin with a brief review of well-known principles of goal setting. Then, because I argue that brainstorming attempts to assign multiple goals, I discuss how goal-setting principles have been applied in multiple-goal environments. Throughout, I link research on goal setting to the brainstorming literature discussed above. I also begin to expand the con- versation by identifying goal-based research and organizational creativity research that address these themes. In this section I show how a goal-based view offers new ideas that could bring the brainstorming and the organizational creativity literature together by focusing on intervention. These ideas form a basis for my argument that a goal-based view can contribute to organizational creativity and innovation research by offering a framework to match a priori definitions of a <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> creative idea to the creative context. I explore that topic in the next section.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="160" page="7" column="1">2008</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="161" page="7" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="162" page="7" column="1">655</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="164" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Fundamentals of Goal Setting</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="174" page="7" column="1">Goals increase performance because they direct and sustain attention and effort toward goal-related activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>). Goal content is the domain of the goal defined in terms of “the object or result being sought” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>: 25). This is usually di- vided into two attributes: specificity and level (also termed difficulty; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 2004</xref>). To be most effective, goals must usually be both challenging and specific and accompanied by commitment and feedback about progress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>). Commitment, which is one’s determination to reach a goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="169" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>), is most critical in the presence of difficult goals (Klein, Wesson, Hollenbeck, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="170" class="deo:Reference">Alge, 1999</xref>). Each of these fundamentals of goal setting is important to a goal-based view of brainstorming. Goal level and specifity. Paulus and Dzindolet (1993: Study 5) conducted the only test of goal level and specificity effects in brainstorming research to date. 3 They found that providing a specific, challenging quantity goal in addition to brainstorming rules increased the quantity of ideas generated by both individuals and groups as compared to sessions where only the brainstorming rules were provided (Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993). No brainstorming study appears to have used specific, challenging goals for any of the rules beyond quantity. Researchers studying goals have long used idea generation tasks (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="171" class="deo:Reference">Locke, 1966</xref>). Chal- lenging, specific goals result in the generation of more ideas compared to easy or do-your-best goals for both individuals and groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106" id="172" class="deo:Reference">Weingart &amp; Weldon, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109" id="173" class="deo:Reference">Wood et al., 1987</xref>). In addition, several studies have found positive effects of</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="179" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">3 Two other studies have used both the full complement of brainstorming rules and specific quantity goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="175" class="deo:Reference">Hyams &amp; Graham, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="176" class="deo:Reference">Larey &amp; Paulus, 1995</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Hyams and Graham (1984)</xref> found no main effect of an assigned goal on quantity performance, but it is unclear whether the goals were challenging enough to qualify as difficult goals, and their sample size was too small to confirm a null effect (n 10 per condition). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="178" class="deo:Reference">Larey and Paulus (1995)</xref> used self-set goals, but their data revealed that participants in all conditions set easy goals (actual performance for all conditions was above the goals).</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="252" page="7" column="2">setting goals for novelty or creativity, although the contribution of specificity and difficulty to these results is unclear (cf. Carson &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="180" class="deo:Reference">Carson &amp; Carson, 1993</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="181" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1991</xref>, 1995; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103" id="182" class="deo:Reference">Ward, 1994</xref>: Experiment 4; Ward, Patterson, Sifonis, Dodds, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104" id="183" class="deo:Reference">Saunders, 2002</xref>: Experiment 4). One reason for this ambiguity may be that, despite the fact that specific, difficult goals can vary in the extent to which they are expressed as numbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="184" class="deo:Reference">Austin &amp; Vancouver, 1996</xref>; e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103" id="185" class="deo:Reference">Ward, 1994</xref>), little attention has been given to developing specificity and level with nonnu- meric measures. Goal content can nonnumeri- cally restrict the domain of the goal through linguistic cues that explain how individuals should leverage their knowledge. For example, in a task to generate ideas for imaginary fruit on a planet different from Earth, Ward et al. (2002: Experiment 4) found evidence that assigning certain individuals a more specific goal to “use their wildest imagination and not feel bound by what fruit is like on Earth” (2002: 207) caused the individuals to access different knowledge compared to those who were assigned either a more general goal to “be as creative as they could be” (2002: 207) or no goal at all. Given the challenge of operationalizing some creative goals numer- ically, this is an important area for future research (cf. Locke, Chah, Harrison, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="186" class="deo:Reference">Lustgarten, 1989</xref>). Such efforts should benefit from this con- ception of specificity as domain restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="187" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>), although adding quantitative specificity where possible is likely to convey additional benefit if it is matched to domain content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89" id="188" class="deo:Reference">Seijts &amp; Latham, 2001</xref>). Most organizational creativity research does not focus on goals, but difficulty and specificity are emerging as important themes even in studies that adopt other perspectives. In a large- scale study of factors influencing the work environment for creativity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="189" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, Conti, Coon, Lazenby, and Herron (1996)</xref> found that challenge and supervisory encouragement (a key element of which was goal clarity— one aspect of goal specificity) were important differentiators between projects that were high and low in creativity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="190" class="deo:Reference">Gilson and Shalley (2004)</xref> observed that, in teams, shared goal content was associated with creative engagement. At the organizational level, researchers have found relationships between specific goals and creativity and innovation in the semiconductor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="191" class="deo:Reference">Abbey &amp; Dickson, 1983</xref>), food processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="192" class="deo:Reference">Ettlie, 1983</xref>), and pharma-<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ceutical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="197" class="deo:Reference">Cardinal, 2001</xref>) industries. Overall, there are indications that challenging, specific goals aid idea generation. Commitment. Although brainstorming research has not addressed goal commitment directly, two motivational factors that might be associated with commitment have received consistent albeit not necessarily strong support in brainstorming studies: free riding (e.g., see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="198" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>) and matching (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="199" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Paulus, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="200" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>). Free riding occurs when individuals’ motivation to contribute in a group is reduced because of fea- tures of the group environment, such as the di- lution of the identifiability of individual outputs that occurs when contributions are pooled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="201" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>). Matching is when individuals attempt to contribute at a level similar to others in the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="202" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Paulus, 1996</xref>). Downward matching, which is the usual concern, occurs when high contributors reduce their output to be more like the average (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="203" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Paulus, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="204" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>). In essence, motivational problems such as downward matching and free riding can be cast as either low commitment to a given goal level or, in a slightly different tradition, as a case of individuals choosing to accept a lower goal level than the one that was assigned. Goal acceptance has since been subsumed within the goal commitment construct by incorporating contextual factors as antecedents of goal commitment and by focusing measurement of the construct on acceptance issues (Klein, Wesson, Hollenbeck, Wright, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="205" class="deo:Reference">DeShon, 2001</xref>; Locke, Latham, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="206" class="deo:Reference">Erez, 1988</xref>). One important insight from goal commitment is that individuals can be as committed to assigned goals as participative goals when the authority figure assigning the goals provides a reasonable explanation of the goals and makes supportive statements about the possibility of goal attainment (Latham, Erez, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="207" class="deo:Reference">Locke, 1988</xref>). This tell and sell approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="208" class="deo:Reference">Latham et al., 1988</xref>) is absent from most communications of goals in brainstorming research (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="209" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="210" class="deo:Reference">Taylor et al., 1958</xref>). Other research related to commitment to brainstorming goals manipulates identifiability of individual contributions and the expectation that one’s contributions will be evaluated. Although these studies are not specifically grounded in accountability research, scholars<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> have posited identifiability and the expectation of evaluation as important dimensions of accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="212" class="deo:Reference">Lerner &amp; Tetlock, 1999</xref>). Account- ability has at least three possible sources in brainstorming research. First, since individuals working alone expect to have their production individually scored (even if only to combine it with others’ contributions), so-called nominal group members are always subject to an identifiability manipulation. This creates a naturally occurring difference between nominal and interacting groups. Research that counteracts this difference through techniques such as recording the contributions of each group member via separate microphones suggests that identifiability of contributions may have an effect on commitment in idea generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="213" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>: Study 1). Second, researchers sometimes assign an additional goal requiring idea generators to pay attention and then test them on their compli- ance. However, researchers have found both positive and negative effects of such goals on idea quantity (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="214" class="deo:Reference">Dugosh &amp; Paulus, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="215" class="deo:Reference">Dugosh et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="216" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Yang, 2000</xref>). Overall, it seems questionable whether a recall goal, which seems to use a combination of identifiability and expected evaluation, improves commitment to quantity goals. Third, researchers have manipulated idea generators’ expectations regarding evaluation by telling them that their contributions are being scored by unseen judges or videotaped for use in teaching demonstrations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="217" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>: Experiment 2). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="218" class="deo:Reference">Diehl and Stroebe (1987)</xref> found that such manipulations produced some minor reductions in quantity performance, and they interpreted this as weak evidence of evaluation apprehension as a mechanism that reduces performance in idea generation. Yet, since affective effects on effort may be mediated by goal commitment (Seo, Barrett, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88" id="219" class="deo:Reference">Bartunek, 2004</xref>), these findings are also consistent with a goal-based view of brainstorming. Organizational creativity researchers have found more positive effects of expected evaluation on creativity when the type of evaluation expected is developmental, as opposed to merely judgmental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="220" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>). Two aspects of this work fit nicely with what is known about antecedents to goal commitment. First, as in the brainstorming literature, the framing of the judgmental evaluation in these<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tasks has a sort of negative valence to it. That is, since there is typically no reward for a positive evaluation, one’s goal is arguably to avoid a negative evaluation rather than to gain a positive one. Instructions from a study by Zhou viv- idly make this point: “But remember, you must keep your creativity at this level so that we can use your data” (1998: 267). Second, whereas judgmental evaluations are phrased in a neutral or even negative tone with regard to expectancy, as in the previous quotation, developmental evaluations are typically infused with senti- ments that express expectancy-building opti- mism about being creative (e.g., Shalley &amp; Perry- <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="225" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R111" id="226" class="deo:Reference">Zhou, 1998</xref>). This is important, because the two key antecedents of goal commitment are valence and expectancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Klein et al., 1999</xref>). In sum, quite a bit of brainstorming and organizational creativity research relevant to goal commitment exists, but the research is hard to interpret because researchers have not been try- ing to investigate goal commitment per se. However, research suggests that the antecedents of goal commitment (identifiability of performance, feelings of efficacy, expectation of outcomes with positive valence) have beneficial effects that are relevant to idea generation. Feedback. The use of nominal versus interacting group conditions in brainstorming research also creates a naturally occurring difference in feedback. Specifically, interacting groups have access to other members’ contributions, whereas individuals generating ideas alone have access only to their own thoughts. The conditions under which individuals or groups benefit from this feedback asymmetry are open to debate (e.g., see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="228" class="deo:Reference">Brown et al., 1998</xref>). Mostly, the feedback that interacting groups receive reduces performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="229" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1991</xref>). However, some types of feedback interventions in brainstorming groups have shown promise. One bright spot is Paulus and Dzindolet’s (1993: Study 5) combination of a feedback intervention with a challenging, specific quantity goal, which led to improved performance. As a second example, consider Paulus and Yang’s (2000) unusual finding that interacting groups can outperform nominal groups in the quantity of ideas generated on a written idea generation task. Paulus and Yang’s (2000) procedure highlights three types of feedback that are available when ideas are generated by groups: (1) partic-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ipants’ generation rate relative to others, (2) the possibility of continuing to generate new ideas, and (3) the qualitative content of the ideas. Although it is difficult to identify separate feedback effects in brainstorming research, since there are always other aspects of goals and cognition in operation, these studies suggest that feedback can have meaningful, positive effects on idea generation. Research on goal setting has long noted the importance of combining goals and feedback (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="231" class="deo:Reference">Erez, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="232" class="deo:Reference">Kluger &amp; DeNisi, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="233" class="deo:Reference">Latham &amp; Locke, 1991</xref>), and feedback manipulations have been incorporated into organizational creativity research on the type of evaluation expected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91" id="234" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1995</xref>; Shalley &amp; Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="235" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>). Since one could promise participants in laboratory studies that their results will be evaluated for developmental implications without feeding this information back, this creativity research technically confounds the promise of a type of evaluation with a type of feedback (see the instructions in Shalley &amp; Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="236" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>: 9 –10). However, field research on creativity using self- report data suggests that, in practice, employees do not separate these two factors (e.g., see the scale development results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="237" class="deo:Reference">Oldham &amp; Cummings, 1996</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99" id="238" class="deo:Reference">Tierney &amp; Farmer, 2004</xref>). This makes sense, because employees are not seeing a single performance event (as in a laboratory study) but, rather, a stream of events in their ongoing relationship with their manager. Shalley’s (1995; see also Shalley &amp; Perry- <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="239" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>) work examines intrinsic motivation, and Shalley and Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="240" class="deo:Reference">Smith (2001)</xref> define it through participants’ self-reported interest in and enjoyment of the task. This operational definition is essentially identical to psychological treatments of valence (a key antecedent to goal commitment), which is usually defined in terms of individual feelings of attraction toward a specific target (see American Heritage Dictionary). Similarly, Shalley and Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="241" class="deo:Reference">Smith (2001)</xref> measure feelings of control over performance, cap- turing the essence of expectancy, even though they do not use this label. Considered from this perspective, Shalley and Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="242" class="deo:Reference">Smith (2001)</xref> find that effects of the type of expected evaluation on valence for the task are mediated by feelings of control over performance (i.e., expectancy). When considered in light of field research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="243" class="deo:Reference">Oldham &amp; Cummings, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99" id="244" class="deo:Reference">Tierney &amp; Farmer, 2004</xref>), Shalley and Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="245" class="deo:Reference">Smith (2001)</xref> make an<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> important contribution by suggesting how different types of feedback can strengthen commitment in creative tasks. To summarize, brainstorming and organizational creativity research have only sporadi- cally engaged with any of the four key elements of goal setting, and many studies have included conditions in which none of the prerequisites for the successful use of goals seems to be in place (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="250" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1991</xref>: Experiment 1). Yet fundamentals of goal setting have strong relevance to these fields. Several of the most successful applications of brainstorming have fol- lowed, though perhaps unwittingly, at least some of the recommendations derived from goal-setting theory. Creativity research has also implicated some principles of goal setting, even when not specifically adopting a goal-setting focus. However, brainstorming interventions assign multiple goals, and organizational creativity theory has proposed that creativity goals compete with other goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="251" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>). Brainstorming research has yet to address this issue, but goal-setting research has increasingly sought to examine multiple-goal contexts.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="194" page="8" column="1">656</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="195" page="8" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="196" page="8" column="1">July</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="222" page="9" column="1">2008</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="223" page="9" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="224" page="9" column="1">657</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="247" page="10" column="1">658</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="248" page="10" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="249" page="10" column="1">July</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="253" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Multiple-Goal Environments</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="301" page="10" column="1">In research on multiple goals, scholars tend to use one of two paradigms, with goals cast in either competitive or supportive relationships with one another. In the first, individuals are asked to simultaneously monitor multiple (usually two) goals that are in competition with one another. This paradigm is of interest because it tests individuals’ ability to pursue multiple goals simultaneously and because some of these studies have been conducted using creative tasks. The general conclusion of this literature is that multiple goals do not necessarily hurt performance (Carson &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="254" class="deo:Reference">Carson &amp; Carson, 1993</xref> DeShon, Brown, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="255" class="deo:Reference">Greenis, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="256" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1991</xref>; Vancouver, 1997). This conclusion also applies to groups. Edmister and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Locke (1987)</xref> showed that groups of bank officers engaged in a commercial lending simulation could monitor and pursue five specific goals. Their study is also interesting because the weights assigned to the goals were not all equal and because they used both assigned and self-set goal weights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="258" class="deo:Reference">Edmister &amp; Locke, 1987</xref>). Also, when these researchers eliminated one goal, performance in the relevant area immedi-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ately dipped, suggesting that groups are able to stop monitoring a de-emphasized goal. Thus, multiple goals do not always force performance trade-offs. However, emphasizing one goal can adversely affect performance on another goal when that emphasis leads to goal conflict (Locke, Smith, Erez, Chah, &amp; Shaffer, 1994). This is interesting for brainstorming research, because previous studies attained results by either focusing participants on particular goals related to a subset of the brainstorming rules (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="260" class="deo:Reference">Coskun et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="261" class="deo:Reference">Paulus &amp; Dzindolet, 1993</xref>: Study 5) or by emphasizing additional goals on top of those implied by the brainstorming rules (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="262" class="deo:Reference">Dugosh &amp; Paulus, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="263" class="deo:Reference">Dugosh et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="264" class="deo:Reference">Nijstad et al., 2002</xref>). Extending these effects to organizational creativity, Ford’s (1996) theory of creative action proposes that the usual pressure in organizations is toward habitual action, which may drive out creativity (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="265" class="deo:Reference">March, 1991</xref>). Thus, even though multiple goals do not always result in trade-offs, the findings from goal-setting research on the effects of conflict (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="266" class="deo:Reference">Locke et al., 1994</xref>) and groups’ ability to stop pursuing a de- emphasized goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="267" class="deo:Reference">Edmister &amp; Locke, 1987</xref>) suggest that it is unwise to assume that multiple goals will survive the communication process intact and in the intervener’s implicitly desired weighting. Organizational creativity research strengthens this caveat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="268" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>). The second paradigm for multiple-goal research involves goals that exist in a supportive relationship with one another. Usually, this is assumed to be a hierarchical relationship, where one goal is subordinate to another. For example, in classroom studies of work motivation, goals for a course grade are supported by goals for exam grades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="269" class="deo:Reference">Campion &amp; Lord, 1982</xref>; Cropanzano, Citera, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="270" class="deo:Reference">Howes, 1995</xref>). Although it may not be obvious at first glance how this research relates to idea generation, much brainstorming research essentially treats the quantity goal as superordinate to the other three goals by measuring only quantity outcomes. However, the question of whether the other goals really do support the quantity goal has not been answered. The question of how multiple goals interact is also important to the broader literature on organizational creativity. Creativity is generally treated as a composite of novelty and utility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>), but research has yet to<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> carefully examine the effects of these dual goals. Indeed, the three most relevant laboratory studies have treated creativity either as a composite goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="276" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1991</xref>) or in terms of novelty alone (Carson &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="277" class="deo:Reference">Carson &amp; Carson, 1993</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103" id="278" class="deo:Reference">Ward, 1994</xref>). This is likely to be an important area of future investigation because both brainstorming and organizational creativity research have shown that novelty and usefulness are unrelated dimensions of ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="279" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="280" class="deo:Reference">Ford &amp; Gioia, 2000</xref>). I return to this issue below. A second example of hierarchical goal research focuses on effects of goals that transcend any particular situation, often represented as personality traits (Cropanzano, James, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="281" class="deo:Reference">Citera, 1993</xref>). Both early (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="282" class="deo:Reference">Bouchard, 1969</xref>) and more recent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="283" class="deo:Reference">Camacho &amp; Paulus, 1995</xref>) brainstorming research have turned up evidence that overarching social goals could affect idea generation. Individuals’ preferences for divergent and convergent thinking may also affect idea generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="284" class="deo:Reference">Brown et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="285" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>), raising the possibility that traits such as need for cognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="286" class="deo:Reference">Cacioppo &amp; Petty, 1982</xref>) could prove worthy of investigation (for an explicit framing of need for cognition in terms of goals, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="287" class="deo:Reference">DeShon &amp; Gillespie, 2005</xref>). Organizational creativity research shows some indications that similar traits could be important (e.g., openness to experience; for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="288" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>). Goal orientations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="289" class="deo:Reference">Dweck &amp; Leggett, 1988</xref>) might also affect the types of contributions individuals pursue in idea generation. Although the status of goal orientations as traits is by no means settled (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="290" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 2004</xref>; for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="291" class="deo:Reference">DeShon &amp; Gillespie, 2005</xref>), these constructs are of particular interest because their underlying goal content of approach and avoidance is similar to that found in models of individual creativity (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="292" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="293" class="deo:Reference">Austin &amp; Vancouver, 1996</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="294" class="deo:Reference">Elliot, 1999</xref>). For example, individuals who adopt so-called proving goals are concerned with demonstrating competence, so their efforts may be better focused when contributions are visible and the goal is specific and within their perceived competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102" id="295" class="deo:Reference">VandeWalle, 1997</xref>). In contrast, learning-fo- cused individuals may be willing to accept more exploratory goals, and avoiding-focused people may be more susceptible to evaluation apprehension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102" id="296" class="deo:Reference">VandeWalle, 1997</xref>). Research is needed<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> to determine whether and how goal orientations interact with assigned goals in idea generation.<marker type="block"/> Summary A goal-based view of brainstorming reveals gaps in what we know about how to improve idea generation. Clearly, no single study can resolve the many questions raised here. At a minimum, future research should pay attention to fundamental goal-setting principles. Beyond that, more attention to design considerations, such as isolating goals to determine their effects and carefully selecting comparison conditions, should improve our ability to evaluate brainstorming and other goal-based interventions. Indeed, disaggregating, respecifying, and recon- sidering the combinations of goals used in interventions all appear to be promising ave- nues of future research aimed at improving idea generation. At the same time, multiple bodies of literature converge on a reasonably clear pre- scription: challenging, specific goals may aid idea generation, especially when goals and feedback are communicated in ways that build commitment in capable idea generators. A goal-based view does not tell us what goals should be set. This can create confusion about the target of the intervention. For example, Sutton and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="299" class="deo:Reference">Hargadon (1996)</xref> proposed several outcomes (e.g., providing skill variety to participants) that expand the mission of idea generation tasks and, perhaps, brainstorming interventions, beyond the realm of generating creative ideas. Similarly, recent laboratory research suggests additional goals that could supplement brainstorming rules (e.g., maintain flow; Paulus, Nakui, Putman, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81" id="300" class="deo:Reference">Brown, 2006</xref>). Any of these could be legitimate goals, but since there is undoubtedly some maximum number of goals that can be attended to, it is important to be clear about what particular interventions are supposed to achieve. Although goals are likely to increase the raw quantity of ideas, if these interventions are to be tightly coupled to organizational concerns about generating creative ideas, they must somehow address the definition of a creative idea. This may be where a goal-based view of intervention can have its greatest impact.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="273" page="11" column="1">2008</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="274" page="11" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="275" page="11" column="1">659</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="302" page="12" column="1">660</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="303" page="12" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="304" page="12" column="1">July</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="305" page="12" column="1">DEFINING EXPECTATIONS FOR CREATIVE IDEAS IN ADVANCE: IMPLICATIONS OF A GOAL-BASED VIEW</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="326" page="12" column="1">What is a creative idea? If we are to learn to intervene with reliable success to produce improvements in the generation of creative ideas, then we must be able to develop a good sense of what we mean by a creative idea before idea generation. The usual definition—that a creative idea must be both novel and useful— works for understanding why a product is judged creative by others after the fact (Amabile, 1996; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="306" class="deo:Reference">Shalley et al., 2004</xref>). However, this definition may be less helpful for structuring efforts ahead of and during creative production because it involves an often ambiguous combination of two orthogonal, continuous variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="307" class="deo:Reference">Diehl &amp; Stroebe, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="308" class="deo:Reference">Ford &amp; Gioia, 2000</xref>; Mumford &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="309" class="deo:Reference">Gustafson, 1988</xref>). Although employees may sometimes be able to intuit the appropriate content of aggregate goals for creativity (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="310" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 1991</xref>), aggregated assessments likely will contribute to creativity’s criterion problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="311" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100" id="312" class="deo:Reference">Unsworth, 2001</xref>). In practice, would-be innovators often must explicitly consider trade-offs between novelty and usefulness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="313" class="deo:Reference">Hargadon &amp; Douglas, 2001</xref>). A goal-based view provides a structure for formalizing these trade- offs in idea generation. To understand the value of a goal-based definition of a creative idea, consider how goals affect idea generation. Goals direct attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="314" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>). Difficulty and specificity, defined in terms of the perception of challenge and domain restriction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="315" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>), increase the prominence of a goal by increasing the likelihood (relative to vague or easy goals) that a discrepancy will be detected between perceptions of the current state and the goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="316" class="deo:Reference">Austin &amp; Vancouver, 1996</xref>). Since brainstorming interventions can trigger unintended goals, specificity is crucial for minimizing such side effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="317" class="deo:Reference">Locke et al., 1989</xref>). Although even a vague goal may direct attention to some degree, specific goals focus idea generation by reducing ambiguity in the detection of discrepancies. Once detected, discrepancies between current states and goals serve as a form of feedback on progress and increase the likelihood that effort will be directed toward goal-related activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="318" class="deo:Reference">Latham &amp; Locke, 1991</xref>). Over time, specific, difficult goals will increase the likelihood that em-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ployees will continue to perceive discrepancies, which will tend to increase persistence in the task. These effects will be greatest when idea generators are committed and receive explicit, appropriately presented feedback (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="320" class="deo:Reference">Locke &amp; Latham, 1990</xref>). Commitment leads to discrepancy creation through acceptance of difficult goals, and to persistence, rather than goal revision or abandonment as a way to reduce discrepancies when performance is perceived to be below the goal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="321" class="deo:Reference">Latham &amp; Locke, 1991</xref>). Feedback influences both commitment and the perception of discrepancies, aiding idea generators’ evaluations of their own ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="322" class="deo:Reference">Kluger &amp; DeNisi, 1996</xref>). These internal evaluations (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="323" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>) suggest an internal, goal-based definition of a creative idea: People will evaluate their own ideas as creative to the extent that they perceive smaller discrepancies between goal- relevant characteristics of the ideas and their creativity goal(s). Now, consider how goals might help to atten- uate creativity’s criterion problem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="324" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100" id="325" class="deo:Reference">Unsworth, 2001</xref>) by tailoring idea generation to different contexts. Figure 1 depicts novelty and usefulness as orthogonal goals. I use the diagonal as a default weighting for creativity, but the mix can be varied by setting different goal levels for each component. Suppose that a manager of an upscale boutique hotel wishes to assign goals to employees to generate ideas for welcoming guests. One possibility would be to encourage novelty to the exclusion of usefulness. The manager could ask for ideas that seem impractical but that would create a unique wel- come. Employees who commit to novelty and impracticality goals will strive to produce responses that seem novel and impractical to them. However, these goals are very broad. Should staff try to produce ideas that are novel and impractical for this hotel, or for the hospitality industry as a whole? Should the ideas all be novel and impractical, or should they vary in novelty and/or impracticality? Should the ideas pertain to signage, decoration, in-room ameni- ties, or what? Now, imagine that the manager improves the specificity and difficulty of the goals by asking employees to generate ideas for reimagining the check-in process as something so unique that a typical guest would never have experi- enced it at another hotel, and so impractical that</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="327" page="13" column="1">2008</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="328" page="13" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="329" page="13" column="1">661</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="330" page="13" column="1">FIGURE 1</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="331" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Disaggregating Goals for Creativity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx332">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62l2.page_013.image_01.png" thmb="62l2.page_013.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="358" page="13" column="1">it requires a complete redesign of the current system. Although these restated goals do not ensure that the manager will appraise any generated ideas as having the desired attributes, they do provide much more guidance in employees’ search for and evaluation of ideas. Adding a quantitative component to these goals might further improve their effects. Such a goal structure takes Osborn’s (1957) free-wheeling rule to its extreme. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="333" class="deo:Reference">March (1976)</xref> argued for limited use of a similar strategy and recently noted (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="334" class="deo:Reference">Coutu, 2006</xref>) that values for usefulness are so deeply ingrained that efforts to encourage this type of novelty may need to be extreme to have an effect. In Figure 1 I use this recent wisdom as a basis to label novelty goals in the range of “low usefulness” with March’s (1976) term foolishness. Another strategy might be to set a difficult novelty goal and let usefulness fall where it<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> may. Our hotel manager might omit the goal for impracticality, focusing only on the novelty goal. One might conceptualize foolishness in this fashion, but a more common way to think of this strategy is through the terms radicalism and exploration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="336" class="deo:Reference">March, 1991</xref>). Alternatively, one might aim for ideas that are low in novelty but that vary in usefulness. Our manager could request ideas using goals to make the current check-in process 10 percent faster without altering its essential character. Creativity theory rarely focuses on this type of idea generation, generally termed incremental creativity or exploitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="337" class="deo:Reference">March, 1991</xref>), even though it is critical for effective organizational functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="338" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>). Although not focused on goals, Cardinal’s (2001) study of phar- maceutical researchers suggests that goal content can be tailored to affect the mix of exploratory and incremental innovation.<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Finally, one might imagine goals for producing uniformly useful ideas that vary in novelty. Our manager might have prompted the staff to generate ideas for using the check-in process to make clients feel that they are in a unique place and that can be implemented for less than $2 per guest. After <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="343" class="deo:Reference">March (2006)</xref>, varying goals for novelty while constraining usefulness to be high might be seen as within the realm of rationality. However, I have opted instead for the slightly less encumbered descriptor grounded. I borrow this term from the research technique known as grounded theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="344" class="deo:Reference">Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967</xref>) because of its twin emphases on short feedback cycles and theory-based generation in response to complex phenomena. If one wishes to con- strain usefulness to be high while allowing novelty to vary, it seems that quick feedback must be maintained to avoid a drift into foolishness. Similarly, theory-based generation is needed to ensure some push away from the competency traps that can occur when current success con- strains the search for new ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="345" class="deo:Reference">Levitt &amp; March, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="346" class="deo:Reference">March, 2006</xref>). Thus, in contrast to the sepa- ration of theory and data that rationality advocates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="347" class="deo:Reference">March, 2006</xref>), the grounded pattern explicitly requires their mixture. In this case, our manager should take extra care to solicit ideas from knowledgeable employees (e.g., those who understand the check-in process) and to ensure prompt, developmentally oriented feedback (Shalley &amp; Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="348" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>). Although the patterns I have highlighted are not exhaustive, each sends a distinct signal to employees about the desired priority structure of idea generation. This is important because employees attend to and act on their perceptions of the type and amount of creativity desired by their employer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="349" class="deo:Reference">Amabile et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="350" class="deo:Reference">Cardinal, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83" id="351" class="deo:Reference">Peters &amp; Roberts, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87" id="352" class="deo:Reference">Scott &amp; Bruce, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="353" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>) and because ideas generated with no referent beyond the mind of the inventor are particularly likely to fail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="354" class="deo:Reference">Goldenberg et al., 2001</xref>). Thus, the patterns in Figure 1 illustrate how goals can indirectly improve external evaluations of ideas (i.e., evaluations by others; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="355" class="deo:Reference">Amabile, 1996</xref>) by making the basis for these judgments explicit prior to idea generation. Together with effects on persistence, this improved matching of internal and external perspectives on the search for and evaluation of ideas is why a goal-based view is likely to aid idea generation.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> To reinforce this view, consider its opposite: managers’ failure to specify goals may exagger- ate the effects of flawed perceptions and trait- level goals, leading employees to adopt a wider dispersion of idea generation goals in the space depicted in Figure 1. Thus, vague goals may strengthen observed links between quality and quantity in idea generation by making the variation in observed ideas more random than it needs to be. Specific goal patterns do not eliminate the long-standing association between variance and creativity, but they do aim to nar- row the “blindness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="357" class="deo:Reference">Campbell, 1960</xref>) of idea generation by reducing variance stemming from goal choice. This has a cost in the sense that some lost ideas might have been creative in other ways, but in most organizational contexts such losses are a small price to pay for improved focus. Decisions about what goals to assign require context. Below, I consider implications for research from three different angles: (1) according to time and stage of the creativity and innovation process; (2) across tasks, jobs, and employees; and (3) in larger units of analysis, such as groups and organizations.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="340" page="14" column="1">662</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="341" page="14" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="342" page="14" column="1">July</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="359" confidence="possible" page="14" column="2">Defining Creative Ideas Across Time and Process Stage</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="380" page="14" column="2">Goals for creative ideas may change across time and stage of the creativity and innovation process. For example, it might be the case that, all else being equal, novelty goals should take precedence at early stages, and usefulness goals should dominate the later stages (Ford &amp; Sullivan, 2004). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="360" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> suggested that idea generation should focus on novelty with explicit disregard for utility, but should usefulness be actively disfavored or merely ignored? Figure 1 suggests that choosing explicitly between exploration goals (ignoring usefulness) and foolishness goals (disfavoring usefulness) may affect the range and skew of ideas generated. Since very extreme ideas might affect problem framing, consider whether problem redefinition is a desirable outcome early in the creative process. If so, then one might assign foolishness goals for their potential to affect the meaning of usefulness. In the hotel example, usefulness might initially be thought of in terms of effi- ciency (e.g., the idea does not increase the line at the reception desk), but if foolishness goals<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> result in ideas that eliminate the reception desk, then the old definition of usefulness loses its meaning. Ideas must obviously prove their utility at some point if they are to become successful innovations, but novel ideas need to be given time to establish their potential usefulness. Presum- ably, wilder ideas may require longer gestation periods. Brainstorming research provides some evidence that taking short breaks may aid idea quantity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81" id="365" class="deo:Reference">Paulus et al., 2006</xref>). The need to allow time for incubation of ideas is supported by cognitive research on creativity (Ward, Smith, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R105" id="366" class="deo:Reference">Finke, 1999</xref>) and by management theory that casts creative actions on a continuum breaking away from habits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="367" class="deo:Reference">Ford, 1996</xref>). Many employees may have difficulty enacting goals for novelty at first (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="368" class="deo:Reference">March, 1976</xref>). Thus, incubation periods may help employees to expand on their initially bland conceptions and to refine their more out- landish ideas. It may be easier to see what additional goals will support incubation once goal patterns from Figure 1 have been articulated. For example, depending on the degree of novelty desired, assigning goals to employees to prompt others who generate ideas to refine and/or expand their contributions may support incubation, especially when combined with positive feedback and recognition (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="369" class="deo:Reference">Sutton &amp; Hargadon, 1996</xref>). Goals for helping-oriented criticism partition the traditional brainstorming goal of avoiding criticism so as to distinguish avoiding judgment of ideas from avoiding developmental comment on ideas (e.g., Shalley &amp; Perry-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="370" class="deo:Reference">Smith, 2001</xref>). Such goals can also differentiate developmental comment, which preserves individual credit for ideas, from combining and building on others’ ideas, which may transfer credit for ideas to other individuals and groups. Imagine how others might respond to a hotel employee who generates an idea to remove the reception desk and arrange seating in the lobby so that guests can relax and wait for someone to sit down with them to check them in. A coworker who has been assigned a goal to ask questions to help refine ideas might ask, “Could you draw the seating arrangement?” whereas others with goals to avoid comment or even to usurp credit might behave differently. A coworker with a goal to prompt expansion might ask, “What are you thinking about for the check-in process? Do we need a lobby at all?”<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Other goal patterns from Figure 1 suggest different foci for supporting incubation. For in- stance, goals for feedback speed might be critical for supporting the grounded pattern identified in Figure 1. Goals for combining and building on others’ ideas may be appropriate when incremental creativity with little incubation is desired and credit for ideas is expected to be team based, as often occurs in quality management contexts (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="372" class="deo:Reference">Naveh &amp; Erez, 2004</xref>). Of course, usefulness needs to have its day, but brainstorming research offers many hints that focusing excessively on usefulness criteria during idea generation may be counterproduc- tive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="373" class="deo:Reference">Meadow et al., 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="374" class="deo:Reference">Parnes &amp; Meadow, 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="375" class="deo:Reference">Rietzschel et al., 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="376" class="deo:Reference">Ford and Sullivan (2004)</xref> have proposed that, in many projects, the appropriate degree of novelty across time can be visualized as an inverted S shape such that, in Figure 1, one would desire a transition from foolishness to incrementalism. However, goal transitions across the process of innovation can also be much more complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="377" class="deo:Reference">Drazin et al., 1999</xref>). A goal-based view does not eliminate this complexity, but it offers explicit flexibility through revision and even reprioritization of specific, challenging goals. Future research is needed to examine goal revision in idea generation. For example, one might hypothesize about how various changes in goals in the space defined by Figure 1 during an idea generation session could spur different kinds of contributions (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="378" class="deo:Reference">Coskun et al., 2000</xref>). Given March’s (1976; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="379" class="deo:Reference">Coutu, 2006</xref>) concerns about the difficulty of getting employees to pursue foolishness, one might imagine that some idea generation sessions could benefit by beginning with more incremental goals and then working toward more exploratory or fool- ishness-oriented goals.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="362" page="15" column="1">2008</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="363" page="15" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="364" page="15" column="1">663</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="381" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">Defining Creative Ideas Across Tasks, Jobs, and Employees</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="393" page="15" column="2">Creativity requirements vary across tasks, jobs, and employees (Shalley, Gilson, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93" id="382" class="deo:Reference">Blum, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100" id="383" class="deo:Reference">Unsworth, 2001</xref>). Because employees evaluate the ideas they generate as “good” to the extent that they are perceived as closer to the goal level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="384" class="deo:Reference">Austin &amp; Vancouver, 1996</xref>), varying goals aid employees in calibrating ideas to meet different task and job requirements. In some cases, the sign of the discrepancy may be<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> important. Just as too much novelty might be a problem later in innovation processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="389" class="deo:Reference">Ford &amp; Sullivan, 2004</xref>), such issues also arise across tasks and jobs. For example, if our hotel manager sets foolishness goals for idea generation, then too much novelty is unlikely to be regarded as a problem, but too much practicality might (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="390" class="deo:Reference">March, 1976</xref>). Task characteristics weigh heavily in goal choice, but job and employee characteristics are also important for creativity (Oldham &amp; Cummings, 1996). Managers should ask whether conditions are favorable for their desired goal content to facilitate idea generation. For example, some jobs may not offer employees enough time or freedom of attention to contemplate novelty very effectively. Assigning a goal to generate novel ideas to employees in such jobs might leave them without the expectancy needed to develop commitment. Similarly, individual differences in overarching goals and knowledge deserve attention in goal setting. Our hotel manager may achieve very different results from foolishness goals by assigning them to profes- sionals with worldwide experience in upscale hospitality management versus—to take another extreme—assigning them to housekeep- ing employees. Research is needed to better understand how assigned goals affect the interactions between individuals’ knowledge and overarching goals that occur during idea generation. For example, future studies might examine whether careful application of goals can overcome evaluation apprehension in individuals with strong anxiety or an avoiding orientation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="391" class="deo:Reference">Camacho &amp; Paulus, 1995</xref>) and whether these effects differ across levels of knowledge. Because they offer the potential to test a range of assumptions about knowledge activation using simulation methods, cognitive models of idea generation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="392" class="deo:Reference">Brown et al., 1998</xref>) also represent a promising platform for initiating studies of the effects of goal-based interventions that take individual differences into account.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="386" page="16" column="1">664</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="387" page="16" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="388" page="16" column="1">July</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="394" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Defining Creative Ideas Across Groups and Organizations</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="402" page="16" column="1">Requirements for creative ideas also differ across groups and organizations. For organizations, March’s (1991) conceptualization of exploration and exploitation has been the influential <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> model for understanding innovation (Gupta, Smith, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="396" class="deo:Reference">Shalley, 2006</xref>). Unlike individuals, groups and organizations may divide into loosely coupled subunits, allowing them to simultaneously adopt multiple-goal patterns in the space indicated by Figure 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="397" class="deo:Reference">Gupta et al., 2006</xref>). Because of this ambidexterity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="398" class="deo:Reference">Benner &amp; Tushman, 2003</xref>), no firm conclusions can be drawn about the effects of goals on idea generation in these larger units. However, it does seem possible to conclude that if organizations want creative ideas, they must partition enough space for some subunits to enact novelty goals. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="399" class="deo:Reference">Denrell and March (2001)</xref> have made the case that novel ideas are more likely to get a fair hearing when entities do not “learn” too quickly that novel ideas are inferior, defeating their opportunity to improve with incubation. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="400" class="deo:Reference">Osborn (1957)</xref> equated avoiding criticism with deferring judgment, I have noted that these could be separate goals. If novel ideas are desired, it is important to build in enough judgment delay in the organizational structure to allow incubation to occur. How to do that is beyond the scope of this paper, but as the recent special forum edited by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="401" class="deo:Reference">Gupta et al. (2006)</xref> demonstrates, it is an active research topic. At the same time, within tightly coupled subunits charged with producing creative ideas, Figure 1 identifies trade-offs that need to be considered when setting goals.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="403" page="16" column="2">CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="410" page="16" column="2">Idea generation inevitably involves an element of chance ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="404" class="deo:Reference">Campbell, 1960</xref>), but might it be refined? I have proposed goal setting as a mechanism for linking brainstorming research to organizational creativity in the hope that a goal- based view might help us answer this question. A substantial quantity of research offers the hope that goals may improve both the quantity and targeting of ideas, but there is still much work to be done. To date, goals have been applied only sparingly in creativity and innovation research. Indeed, a recent review that catalogs facilitators of innovation at the individual, group, and organizational levels of analysis does not include goals at all (Anderson, De Dreu, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="405" class="deo:Reference">Nijstad, 2004</xref>). Using the large body of literature on brainstorming as a prototype, this paper contributes to organizational creativity and in-<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> novation research by articulating a goal-based view of intervention in idea generation. Throughout this paper I have advocated treating the intervention and the process through which it occurs as separate, if mutually informa- tive, foci for research. This is not a panacea: a goal-based view does nothing to lessen the need for research on cognition or any of the other important aspects of organizational creativity and innovation. However, a goal-based view provides a structure for considering how to tailor expectations for idea generation to the creative context. In a world where creative ideas are needed, specifying the key elements of creativity for a particular context before idea generation offers one way to improve this important process.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="407" page="17" column="1">2008</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="408" page="17" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="409" page="17" column="1">665</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="411" page="17" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="412" page="17" column="1">Abbey, A., &amp; Dickson, J. W. 1983. R&amp;D work climate and innovation in semiconductors. Academy of Management Journal, 26: 362–368.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="413" page="17" column="1">Amabile, T. M. 1996. Creativity in context. Boulder, CO: West- view Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="414" page="17" column="1">Amabile, T. M., Conti, R., Coon, H., Lazenby, J., &amp; Herron, M. 1996. Assessing the work environment for creativity. Academy of Management Journal, 39: 1154 –1184.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="415" page="17" column="1">Anderson, N., De Dreu, C. K. W., &amp; Nijstad, B. A. 2004. The routinization of innovation research: A constructively critical review of the state-of-the-science. Journal of Organizational Behavior, 25: 147–173.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="416" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Austin, J. T., &amp; Vancouver, J. B. 1996. Goal constructs in psychology: Structure, process, and content. Psychological Bulletin, 120: 338 –375.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="417" page="17" column="1">Benner, M. J., &amp; Tushman, M. L. 2003. Exploitation, exploration, and process management: The productivity di- lemma revisited. Academy of Management Review, 28: 238 –256.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="418" page="17" column="1">Brown, V., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 1996. A simple dynamic model of social factors in group brainstorming. Small Group Research, 27: 91–114.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="419" page="17" column="1">Brown, V., Tumeo, M., Larey, T. S., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 1998. Modeling cognitive interactions during group brainstorming. Small Group Research, 29: 495–526.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="420" page="17" column="1">Bouchard, T. J. 1969. Personality, problem-solving procedure, and performance in small groups. Journal of Applied Psychology Monograph, 53: 1–29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="421" page="17" column="1">Cacioppo, J. T., &amp; Petty, R. E. 1982. The need for cognition. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 42: 116 – 131.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="422" page="17" column="1">Camacho, L. M., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 1995. The role of social anxiousness in group brainstorming. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 68: 1071–1080.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="424" page="17" column="1">Campbell, D. T. 1960. Blind variation and selective retention <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> in creative thought as in other knowledge processes. Psychological Review, 67: 380 – 400. Campion, M. A., &amp; Lord, R. G. 1982. A control systems conceptualization of the goal-setting and changing process. Organizational Behavior and Human Performance, 30: 265–287.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="425" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Cardinal, L. B. 2001. Technological innovation in the phar- maceutical industry: The use of organizational control in managing research and development. Organization Science, 12: 19 –36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="426" page="17" column="2">Carson, P. P., &amp; Carson, K. D. 1993. Managing creativity enhancement through goal-setting and feedback. Journal of Creative Behavior, 27: 36 – 45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="427" page="17" column="2">Coskun, H., Paulus, P. B., Brown, V., &amp; Sherwood, J. J. 2000. Cognitive stimulation and problem presentation in idea-generating groups. Group Dynamics: Theory, Research, and Practice, 4: 307–329.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="428" page="17" column="2">Coutu, D. 2006. Ideas as art. Harvard Business Review, 84(10): 82– 89.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="429" page="17" column="2">Cropanzano, R., Citera, M., &amp; Howes, J. 1995. Goal hierarchies and plan revision. Motivation and Emotion, 19: 77–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="430" page="17" column="2">Cropanzano, R., James, C., &amp; Citera, M. 1993. A goal hierar- chy model of personality, motivation, and leadership. Research in Organizational Behavior, 15: 267–322.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="431" page="17" column="2">Dennis, A. R., &amp; Valacich, J. S. 1999. Electronic brainstorming: Illusions and patterns of productivity. Information Systems Research, 10: 375–377.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="432" page="17" column="2">Dennis, A. R., &amp; Williams, M. L. 2003. Electronic brainstorming: Theory, research, and future directions. In P. B. Paulus &amp; B. A. Nijstad (Eds.), Group creativity: Innovation through collaboration: 160 –178. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="433" page="17" column="2">Denrell, J., &amp; March, J. G. 2001. Adaptation as information restriction: The hot stove effect. Organization Science, 12: 523–538.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="434" page="17" column="2">DeShon, R. P., Brown, K. G., &amp; Greenis, J. L. 1996. Does self- regulation require cognitive resources? Evaluation of resource allocation models of goal setting. Journal of Applied Psychology, 81: 595– 608.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="435" page="17" column="2">DeShon, R. P., &amp; Gillespie, J. Z. 2005. A motivated action theory account of goal orientation. Journal of Applied Psychology, 90: 1096 –1127.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="436" page="17" column="2">Diehl, M., &amp; Stroebe, W. 1987. Productivity loss in brainstorming groups: Toward the solution of a riddle. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 53: 497–509.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="437" page="17" column="2">Diehl, M., &amp; Stroebe, W. 1991. Productivity loss in idea- generating groups: Tracking down the blocking effect. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 61: 392– 403.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="438" page="17" column="2">Drazin, R., Glynn, M. A., &amp; Kazanjian, R. K. 1999. Multilevel theorizing about creativity in organizations: A sense- making perspective. Academy of Management Review, 24: 286 –307.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="439" page="17" column="2">Dugosh, K. L., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 2005. Cognitive and social comparison processes in brainstorming. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 41: 313–320.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="443" page="18" column="1">Dugosh, K. L., Paulus, P. B., Roland, E. J., &amp; Yang, H. 2000. Cognitive stimulation in brainstorming. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 79: 722–735.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="444" page="18" column="1">Dweck, C. S., &amp; Leggett, E. L. 1988. A social-cognitive approach to motivation and personality. Psychological Review, 95: 256 –273.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="445" page="18" column="1">Edmister, R. O., &amp; Locke, E. A. 1987. The effects of differential goal weights on the performance of a complex financial task. Personnel Psychology, 40: 505–517.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="446" page="18" column="1">Elliot, A. J. 1999. Approach and avoidance motivation and achievement goals. Educational Psychologist, 34: 169 – 189.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="447" page="18" column="1">Erez, M. 1977. Feedback: A necessary condition for the goal setting–performance relationship. Journal of Applied Psychology, 62: 624 – 627.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="448" page="18" column="1">Ettlie, J. E. 1983. Organizational policy and innovation among suppliers to the food processing sector. Academy of Management Journal, 26: 27– 44.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="449" page="18" column="1">Ford, C., &amp; Sullivan, D. M. 2004. A time for everything: How the timing of novel contributions influences project team outcomes. Journal of Organizational Behavior, 25: 279 – 292.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="450" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Ford, C. M. 1996. A theory of individual creative action in multiple social domains. Academy of Management Review, 21: 1112–1142.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="451" page="18" column="1">Ford, C. M., &amp; Gioia, D. A. 2000. Factors influencing creativity in the domain of managerial decision making. Journal of Management, 26: 705–732.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="452" page="18" column="1">Gerlach, V. S., Schutz, R. E., Baker, R. L., &amp; Mazer, G. E. 1964. Effects of variations in test directions on originality test response. Journal of Educational Psychology, 55: 79 – 83.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="453" page="18" column="1">Gilson, L. L., &amp; Shalley, C. E. 2004. A little creativity goes a long way: An examination of teams’ engagement in creative processes. Journal of Management, 30: 453– 470.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="454" page="18" column="1">Glaser, B. G., &amp; Strauss, A. L. 1967. The discovery of grounded theory: Strategies for qualitative research. New York: Aldine de Gruyter.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="455" page="18" column="1">Glynn, M. A. 1996. Innovative genius: A framework for relat- ing individual and organizational intelligences to innovation. Academy of Management Review, 21: 1081–1111.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="456" page="18" column="1">Goldenberg, J., Lehmann, D. R., &amp; Mazursky, D. 2001. The idea itself and the circumstances of its emergence as predic- tors of new product success. Management Science, 47: 69 – 84.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="457" page="18" column="1">Gupta, A. K., Smith, K. G., &amp; Shalley, C. E. 2006. The interplay between exploration and exploitation. Academy of Management Journal, 49: 693–706.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="458" page="18" column="1">Hargadon, A. B., &amp; Douglas, Y. 2001. When innovations meet institutions: Edison and the design of the electric light. Administrative Science Quarterly, 46: 476 –501.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="459" page="18" column="1">Hyams, N. B., &amp; Graham, W. K. 1984. Effects of goal setting and initiative on individual brainstorming. Journal of Social Psychology, 123: 283–284.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="460" page="18" column="1">Kerr, N. L., &amp; Tindale, R. S. 2004. Group performance and decision making. Annual Review of Psychology, 55: 623– 655.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="461" page="18" column="2">Klein, H. J., Wesson, M. J., Hollenbeck, J. R., &amp; Alge, B. J. 1999. Goal commitment and the goal setting process: Concep- tual clarification and empirical synthesis. Journal of Applied Psychology, 84: 885– 896.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="462" page="18" column="2">Klein, H. J., Wesson, M. J., Hollenbeck, J. R., Wright, P. M., &amp; DeShon, R. P. 2001. The assessment of goal commitment: A measurement model meta-analysis. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 85: 32–55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="463" page="18" column="2">Kluger, A. N., &amp; DeNisi, A. 1996. The effects of feedback interventions on performance: A historical review, a meta-analysis, and a preliminary feedback intervention theory. Psychological Bulletin, 119: 254 –284.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="464" page="18" column="2">Lamm, H., &amp; Trommsdorff, G. 1973. Group versus individual performance on tasks requiring ideational proficiency (brainstorming): A review. European Journal of Social Psychology, 3: 361–388.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="465" page="18" column="2">Larey, T. S., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 1995. Social comparison and goal setting in brainstorming groups. Journal of Applied Social Psychology, 25: 1579 –1596.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="466" page="18" column="2">Larey, T. S., &amp; Paulus, P. B. 1999. Group preference and convergent tendencies in small groups: A content analysis of group brainstorming performance. Creativity Research Journal, 12: 175–184.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="467" page="18" column="2">Latham, G. P., Erez, M., &amp; Locke, E. A. 1988. Resolving scien- tific disputes by the joint design of crucial experiments by the antagonists: Application to the Erez-Latham dis- pute regarding participation in goal setting. Journal of Applied Psychology, 73: 753–772.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="468" page="18" column="2">Latham, G. P., &amp; Locke, E. A. 1991. Self-regulation through goal setting. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 50: 212–247.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="469" page="18" column="2">Lerner, J. S., &amp; Tetlock, P. E. 1999. Accounting for the effects of accountability. Psychological Bulletin, 125: 255–275.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="470" page="18" column="2">Levitt, B., &amp; March, J. G. 1988. Organizational learning. Annual Review of Sociology, 14: 319 –340.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="471" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A. 1966. The relationship of intentions to level of performance. Journal of Applied Psychology, 50: 50 – 66.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="472" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A. 2000. Motivation, cognition, and action: An analysis of studies of task goals and knowledge. Applied Psychology: An International Review, 49: 408 – 429.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="473" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A., Chah, D., Harrison, S., &amp; Lustgarten, N. 1989. Separating the effects of goal specificity from goal level. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 43: 270 –287.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="474" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A., &amp; Latham, G. P. 1990. A theory of goal-setting and task performance. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice- Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="475" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A., &amp; Latham, G. P. 2004. What should we do about work motivation theory? Six recommendations for the twenty-first century. Academy of Management Review, 29: 388 – 403.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="476" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A., Latham, G. P., &amp; Erez, M. 1988. The determinants of goal commitment. Academy of Management Review, 13: 23–39.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="481" page="18" column="2">Locke, E. A., Smith, K. G., Erez, M., Chah, D., &amp; Schaffer, A. 1994. The effects of intra-individual goal conflict on performance. Journal of Management, 20: 67–91. <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> March, J. G. 1976. The technology of foolishness. In J. G. March &amp; J. P. Olsen (Eds.), Ambiguity and choice in organizations: 69 – 81. Oslo: Universitetsforlaget.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="482" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">March, J. G. 1991. Exploration and exploitation in organizational learning. Organization Science, 2: 71– 87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="483" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">March, J. G. 2006. Rationality, foolishness, and adaptive in- telligence. Strategic Management Journal, 27: 201–214.</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="484" page="19" column="1">Meadow, A., Parnes, S. J., &amp; Reese, H. 1959. Influence of brainstorming instructions and problem sequence on a creative problem solving test. Journal of Applied Psychology, 43: 413– 416.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="485" page="19" column="1">Mullen, B., Johnson, C., &amp; Salas, E. 1991. Productivity loss in brainstorming groups: A meta-analytic integration. Ba- sic and Applied Social Psychology, 12: 3–23.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="486" page="19" column="1">Mumford, M. D., &amp; Gustafson, S. B. 1988. Creativity syndrome: Integration, application, and innovation. Psychological Bulletin, 103: 27– 43.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="487" page="19" column="1">Naveh, E., &amp; Erez, M. 2004. Innovation and attention to detail in the quality improvement paradigm. Management Science, 50: 1576 –1586.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="488" page="19" column="1">Nemeth, C. J., Personnaz, B., Personnaz, M., &amp; Goncalo, J. A. 2004. The liberating role of conflict in group creativity: A study in two countries. European Journal of Social Psychology, 34: 365–374.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="489" page="19" column="1">Nijstad, B. A., Diehl, M., &amp; Stroebe, W. 2003. Cognitive stimulation and interference in idea-generating groups. In P. B. Paulus &amp; B. A. Nijstad (Eds.), Group creativity: Innovation through collaboration: 137–159. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="490" page="19" column="1">Nijstad, B. A., Stroebe, W., &amp; Lodewijkx, H. F. M. 2002. Cognitive stimulation and interference in groups: Exposure effects in an idea generation task. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 38: 535–544.</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="491" page="19" column="1">Oldham, G. R., &amp; Cummings, A. 1996. Employee creativity: Personal and contextual factors at work. Academy of Management Journal, 39: 607– 634.</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="492" page="19" column="1">Osborn, A. F. 1957. Applied imagination. New York: Scribner.</ref>
          <ref rid="R76" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="493" page="19" column="1">Parnes, S. J. 1963. The deferment-of-judgment principle: A clarification of the literature. Psychological Reports, 12: 521–522.</ref>
          <ref rid="R77" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="494" page="19" column="1">Parnes, S. J., &amp; Meadow, A. 1959. Effects of “brainstorming” instructions on creative problem solving by trained and untrained subjects. Journal of Educational Psychology, 30: 171–176.</ref>
          <ref rid="R78" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="495" page="19" column="1">Paulus, P. B. 2000. Groups, teams, and creativity: The creative potential of idea-generating groups. Applied Psychology: An International Review, 49: 237–262.</ref>
          <ref rid="R79" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="496" page="19" column="1">Paulus, P. B., &amp; Brown, V. R. 2003. Enhancing ideational creativity in groups: Lessons from research on brainstorming. In P. B. Paulus &amp; B. A. Nijstad (Eds.), Group creativity: Innovation through collaboration: 110 –136. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R80" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="497" page="19" column="1">Paulus, P. B., &amp; Dzindolet, M. T. 1993. Social influence processes in group brainstorming. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 64: 575–586.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="499" page="19" column="1">Paulus, P. B., Dzindolet, M. T., Poletes, G., &amp; Camacho, <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> L. M. 1993. Perception of performance in group brainstorming: The illusion of group productivity. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 19: 78 – 89.</ref>
          <ref rid="R81" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="500" page="19" column="2">Paulus, P. B., Nakui, T., Putman, V. L., &amp; Brown, V. R. 2006. Effects of task instructions and brief breaks on brainstorming. Group Dynamics: Theory, Research, and Practice, 10: 206 –219.</ref>
          <ref rid="R82" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="501" page="19" column="2">Paulus, P. B., &amp; Yang, H. C. 2000. Idea generation in groups: A basis for creativity in organizations. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 82: 76 – 87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R83" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="502" page="19" column="2">Peters, D. H., &amp; Roberts, E. B. 1969. Unutilized ideas in uni- versity laboratories. Academy of Management Journal, 12: 179 –191.</ref>
          <ref rid="R84" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="503" page="19" column="2">Pinsonneault, A., Barki, H., Gallupe, R. B., &amp; Hoppen, N. 1999a. Electronic brainstorming: The illusion of productivity. Information Systems Research, 10: 110 –133.</ref>
          <ref rid="R85" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="504" page="19" column="2">Pinsonneault, A., Barki, H., Gallupe, R. B., &amp; Hoppen, N. 1999b. The illusion of electronic brainstorming productivity: Theoretical and empirical issues. Information Systems Research, 10: 378 –380.</ref>
          <ref rid="R86" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="505" page="19" column="2">Rietzschel, E. F., Nijstad, B. A., &amp; Stroebe, W. 2006. Productivity is not enough: A comparison of interactive and nominal brainstorming groups on idea generation and selection. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 42: 244 –251.</ref>
          <ref rid="R87" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="506" page="19" column="2">Scott, S. G., &amp; Bruce, R. A. 1994. Determinants of innovative behavior: A path model of individual innovation in the workplace. Academy of Management Journal, 37: 580 – 607.</ref>
          <ref rid="R88" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="507" page="19" column="2">Seo, M., Barrett, L. F., &amp; Bartunek, J. M. 2004. The role of affective experience in work motivation. Academy of Management Review, 29: 423– 439.</ref>
          <ref rid="R89" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="508" page="19" column="2">Seijts, G. H., &amp; Latham, G. P. 2001. The effect of distal learning, outcome, and proximal goals on a moderately complex task. Journal of Organizational Behavior, 22: 291– 307.</ref>
          <ref rid="R90" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="509" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E. 1991. Effects of productivity goals, creativity goals, and personal discretion on individual creativity. Journal of Applied Psychology, 76: 179 –185.</ref>
          <ref rid="R91" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="510" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E. 1995. Effects of coaction, expected evaluation, and goal setting on creativity and productivity. Academy of Management Journal, 38: 483–503.</ref>
          <ref rid="R92" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="511" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E. 2002. How valid and useful is the integrative model for understanding work groups’ creativity and innovation? Applied Psychology: An International Review, 51: 406 – 410.</ref>
          <ref rid="R93" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="512" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E., Gilson, L. L., &amp; Blum, T. C. 2000. Matching creativity requirements and the work environment: Effects on satisfaction and intentions to leave. Academy of Management Journal, 43: 215–223.</ref>
          <ref rid="R94" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="513" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E., &amp; Perry-Smith, J. E. 2001. Effects of social- psychological factors on creative performance: The role of informational and controlling expected evaluation and modeling experience. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, 84: 1–22.</ref>
          <ref rid="R95" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="518" page="19" column="2">Shalley, C. E., Zhou, J., &amp; Oldham, G. R. 2004. The effects of personal and contextual characteristics on creativity: <marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Where should we go from here? Journal of Management, 30: 933–958.</ref>
          <ref rid="R96" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="519" page="20" column="1">Simonton, D. K. 2003. Scientific creativity as constrained stochastic behavior: The integration of product, person, and process perspectives. Psychological Bulletin, 129: 475– 494.</ref>
          <ref rid="R97" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="520" page="20" column="1">Sutton, R. I., &amp; Hargadon, A. 1996. Brainstorming groups in context: Effectiveness in a product design firm. Administrative Science Quarterly, 41: 685–718.</ref>
          <ref rid="R98" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="521" page="20" column="1">Taylor, D. W., Berry, P. C., &amp; Block, C. H. 1958. Does group participation when using brainstorming facilitate or in- hibit creative thinking? Administrative Science Quarterly, 3: 23– 47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R99" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="522" page="20" column="1">Tierney, P., &amp; Farmer, S. M. 2004. The Pygmalion process and employee creativity. Journal of Management, 30: 413– 422.</ref>
          <ref rid="R100" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="523" page="20" column="1">Unsworth, K. 2001. Unpacking creativity. Academy of Management Review, 26: 289 –297.</ref>
          <ref rid="R101" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="524" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Vancouver, J. B. 1997. The application of HLM to the analysis of the dynamic interaction of environment, person and behavior. Journal of Management, 23: 795– 818.</ref>
          <ref rid="R102" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="525" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">VandeWalle, D. 1997. Development and validation of a work domain goal orientation instrument. Educational and Psychological Measurement, 57: 995–1015.</ref>
          <ref rid="R103" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="527" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Ward, T. B. 1994. Structured imagination: The role of category structure in exemplar generation. Cognitive Psychology, 27: 1– 40. Robert C. Litchfield (<email id="526">rlitchfield@washjeff.edu</email>) is assistant professor of management in the Department of Economics &amp; Business at Washington &amp; Jefferson College. He received his Ph.D. in industrial/organizational psychology from The Ohio State University. His current research focuses on psychological underpinnings of management interventions.</ref>
          <ref rid="R104" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="528" page="20" column="2">Ward, T. B., Patterson, M. J., Sifonis, C. M., Dodds, R. A., &amp; Saunders, K. N. 2002. The role of graded category structure in imaginative thought. Memory &amp; Cognition, 30: 199 –216.</ref>
          <ref rid="R105" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="529" page="20" column="2">Ward, T. B., Smith, S. M., &amp; Finke, R. A. 1999. Creative cognition. In R. J. Sternberg (Ed.), Handbook of creativity: 189 – 212. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R106" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="530" page="20" column="2">Weingart, L. R., &amp; Weldon, E. 1991. Processes that mediate the relationship between a group goal and group member performance. Human Performance, 4: 33–54.</ref>
          <ref rid="R107" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="531" confidence="possible" page="20" column="2">West, M. A. 2002a. Sparkling fountains or stagnant ponds: An integrative model of creativity and innovation imple- mentation in work groups. Applied Psychology: An International Review, 51: 355–387.</ref>
          <ref rid="R108" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="532" confidence="possible" page="20" column="2">West, M. A. 2002b. Ideas are ten a penny: It’s team imple- mentation not idea generation that counts. Applied Psychology: An International Review, 51: 411– 424.</ref>
          <ref rid="R109" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="533" page="20" column="2">Wood, R. E., Mento, A. J., &amp; Locke, E. A. 1987. Task complexity as a moderator of goal effects: A meta-analysis. Journal of Applied Psychology, 72: 416 – 425.</ref>
          <ref rid="R110" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="534" confidence="possible" page="20" column="2">Woodman, R. W., Sawyer, J. E., &amp; Griffin, R. 1993. Toward a theory of organizational creativity. Academy of Management Review, 18: 293–321.</ref>
          <ref rid="R111" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="535" page="20" column="2">Zhou, J. 1998. Feedback valence, feedback style, task auton- omy, and achievement orientation: Interactive effects on creative performance. Journal of Applied Psychology, 83: 261–276.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="440" page="18" column="1">666</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="441" page="18" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="442" page="18" column="1">July</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="478" page="19" column="1">2008</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="479" page="19" column="1">Litchfield</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="480" page="19" column="1">667</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="515" page="20" column="1">668</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="516" page="20" column="1">Academy of Management Review</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="517" page="20" column="1">July</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
