<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>f42aac855a9a701c14d18964b3c6ddeb4896ada72b1128c428feb4c118d1993f</job>
    <base_name>62mn</base_name>
    <doi>10.1108/14637151011017958</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62mn.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62mn.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">The current issue and full text archive of this journal is available at www.emeraldinsight.com/1463-7154.htm</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">BPMJ</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="4">16,1</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">Methodological choices in enterprise systems research</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="6">Melissa Sedmak</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="10">Phil Longhurst</name></contrib></contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="7">76</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="8">School of Risk and Safety Sciences, The University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia, and</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="11">School of Applied Sciences, Cranfield University, Cranfield, UK</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="12">Purpose – The purpose of this paper is to present the choices to researchers when approaching the topic of enterprise systems from a social science perspective. Design/methodology/approach – A selected bibliography is presented, on the themes relevant to methodological choices in studying enterprise systems in an organisational context. The themes encompass epistemology, causality, research approach and type of data, research design, researcher role in data collection, research strategy, method, techniques and researcher role in relation to the setting. Findings – The paper presents theoretical approaches and illustrates the application of theory on the specific case of enterprise system implementation in an organisational context. Research limitations/implications – A breadth of themes is considered here, however the review of the literature is not exhaustive, but selective. Practical implications – The paper argues for making research method explicit and transparent and for greater awareness of the researchers studying enterprise systems of the methodological choices available when engaging with the subject of study. Originality/value – The paper brings together available and well-developed research methods, mainly used in information systems (IS) research and organisation studies, and which have been used in enterprise systems somewhat sparsely and without particular transparency, closer to research practice. Keywords Research methods, Systems analysis, Communication technologies, Case studies Paper type Literature review</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="14" page="1" column="1">Process Management</region>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="1">IT systems and enterprise systems are particularly problematic to approach as an area of study, considering that their implementation and use are very much related to the organisational context in which they are embedded. Added to the complexity of technology itself is the fact that the end of an implementation of an enterprise system, i.e. the system going live, is merely an “end of the beginning” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Deloitte, 1999</xref>). The organisations need to take further actions in order to achieve full benefits of an enterprise system. Actions to this effect beyond the go-live comprise the “second wave”. An enterprise resource planning system often does not drive all the organisational processes, but is extended and complemented by other technological solutions within an</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="17" page="1" column="1">No. 1, 2010</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18" page="1" column="1">Emerald Group Publishing Limited</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19" page="1" column="1">Business Journal Vol. 16 pp. 76-92 q 1463-7154 DOI</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="20" page="1" column="1">10.1108/14637151011017958</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">The case study was supported by European Commission, as a part of BEST – Better Enterprise SysTem Implementation Project, IST-2001-35385.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="22" page="2" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="23" page="2" column="1">77</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="2" column="1">organisation ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Deloitte, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Moon, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Seddon et al., 2003</xref>). The size of an organisation will have an effect on the benefits achieved from an implementation, where intraorganisational issues within a global, multinational organisation, where the enterprise system is used in different cultural context of each country will be very different to issues that a small or medium organisation might face due to lack of financial resource and in-house IT professionals. Problems of integration also span beyond the enterprise itself, notably integration with the rest of the supply chain in business-to-business environments, or in order to provide an interface with a consumer via customer relationship management in a business-to-consumer environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Seethamraju, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Stefanou and Revanoglou, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Chuang and Shaw, 2008</xref>). As such, there are various ways in which these systems and respective organisational settings can be studied, depending on the research questions which are being asked. However, in order to answer the research questions, a reliable, systematic and transparent research method needs to be utilised. The purpose of this paper is to present choices that a researcher has, which need to be addressed when designing research. If we compare a research design to a building, then our understanding and views on the nature of knowledge form the foundation of that building, from which we build the rest. So the pertinent question is then: how we see reality and how we can gain valid and reliable knowledge about this reality. This is what is addressed by the method: in what way do we collect the data so that the findings are representative of reality we are aiming to explore. The sections that follow relate to the foundation, i.e. the research perspective, the building blocks as the methods and tools we use, and the design of the building, the design of inquiry in IT and enterprise systems research, built on that foundation. The aim of the paper is to understand and present the foundation, the building blocks and the building in a clearer light, thus creating researcher awareness of choices available. The expected audience for this paper is primarily the research community as well as the practitioners who are interested in various means of study of IS and enterprise systems in practice. As the field of interest in how to conduct research in the areas of the social sciences and IT systems is as diverse as the members of the research community itself, it appears that a standardised, common language is absent. The lack of such language and commonly agreed upon terminology makes the study of this field somewhat laborious. The terminology used here encompasses more commonly used terms, and in addition includes some less standard terms and respective choices. What is suggested in the following sections presents a brief, and somewhat simplified overview of the research philosophies, methods, approaches and techniques, as choices available to a researcher. It aims to present, the most prevalent and frequently used building blocks of research, which eventually form a research design, to compare and contrast them, and to highlight the importance of making specific choices during research projects. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> shows the choices described below and is helpful in providing visual display of various choices available to tackle research questions. However, the authors caution the researchers of enterprise systems that the choice of the specific method, tool, or type of data to be collected, cannot be prescribed. This choice is left to the researchers to make in accordance with the research questions they are posing.<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> Example An example of enterprise system implementation is used to illustrate various topics within this paper. The example is based on a study of an enterprise system implementation in the context of a manufacturing organisation. The organisation is a large UK located site of a manufacturer of durables. The company has two million customers ranging from start-up companies to established businesses in 120 countries. Owing to a strategic decision and the way the company is structured globally, only the “back-office” in the UK – logistics and sales, had an off-the-shelf system implemented in the 1990s. Finally, in the mid-2000s it was recognised that there was a lack of system integration between the manufacturing and the sales and logistics, which was seen as a restriction. As the number of configure-to-order and procurement and planning processes had been increasing on a global level it was decided to implement the system in the manufacturing. The research questions aimed to develop a comprehensive picture of the processes affecting the implementation of the system, and to investigate which of the processes during implementation play a significant role in that implementation. Specific choices with regards to research methodology were made in accordance with research questions.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="33" page="3" column="1">BPMJ</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="34" page="3" column="1">16,1</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="35" page="3" column="1">Researcher engagement External/observing Internal/ Intentional with the setting Etic Emic participating intervention Techniques for Participant data collection Questionnaire Standardised tests observation Interviews Focus groups Method of inquiry Survey Experiment Case study Grounded theory</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="36" page="3" column="1">78</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="37" page="3" column="1">Research strategy Deductive Inductive Retroductive Abductive Researcher role in data collection Primary Secondary Research design Fixed Flexible Research approach/data Quantitative Qualitative Variance Process Causality theory theory Epistemology Positivist Interpretive Critical</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="38" page="3" column="1">Figure 1. Research choices and options</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="40" page="3" column="1">Source: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Myers (1997)</xref></region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="42" page="3" column="1">2. Perspectives in IT systems research</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="3" column="1">The literature on IT systems research methods shows that there has been a long-term debate about the plurality of research perspectives, and which of these perspectives are most suitable for the IT systems research. Numerous authors have studied the types of articles published in prestigious IT systems journals and in proceedings of IT systems conferences, particularly with respect to the dominant set of assumptions which inform IT systems research ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Schwartzman, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Agar, 1986</xref>). The design of research was studied, as well as its epistemology. Epistemology is concerned with the nature of knowledge and the methods of inquiry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Strauss, 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Baroudi (1991)</xref> classified articles by epistemology as positivist, interpretive<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> and critical, according to the classification put forward by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Chua (1986)</xref>. The paper defines them as: . Positivist. A priori fixed and observable or measurable relationships exist which are investigated with structured tools. These studies are used to test theories, and the classification criteria used are: evidence of formal propositions, quantifiable measures of variables, hypotheses testing and the drawing of the inferences about a phenomenon from the sample to the population. The reality as such is outside, observable and measurable. . Interpretive. People create and associate their subjective meanings as they interact with the world around them. The phenomena are understood through accessing the meanings that participants assign to them. The intention is to gain a deeper understanding of the phenomenon, which can then inform other settings, rather than to generalise. The intention of the research is to increase understanding of the phenomenon within particular situations, where the phenomenon is studied in its natural setting from the participants’ perspective and where the researcher does not try to impose his/her a priori understanding of the situation. In interpretive research, it is not important to verify that what was perceived to have been done was actually done. However, it is important to understand how what was done was perceived by the people involved. The reality is in the eye of the beholder, constructed by the research participant. . Critical. Exposure of structural contradictions within social systems allows the critique of the status quo which transforms the social conditions. Criteria for classification are a critical stance to assumptions about organisations and IT systems, and an analysis attempting to reveal the nature of existing social practices. They found that out of 155 articles and papers published between 1983 and 1988, 96.8 per cent had positivism as the dominant epistemology, while only 3.2 per cent were interpretive. There were no critical studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Alavi and Carlson (1992)</xref> conducted a more extensive study of 908 articles published between 1968 and 1988. They found that field studies comprised 33.4 per cent of the empirical articles (48.8 per cent of the total), while the laboratory experiments accounted for 15.1 per cent, and case studies for 9.1 per cent. On the other, more recent, side of the spectrum are Galliers et al. (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Mingers, 2001</xref>, p. 248) who conducted a survey of IT systems academics in the UK to find that many (41 per cent) use case studies, interviews and qualitative analysis. In terms of the epistemology used among the respondents, the most common was interpretivism (40 per cent). One more recent development which became particularly established after the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Baroudi (1991)</xref> is the notion of critical realism, where reality is observed and studied through the participants. However, it is not possible to totally “access” it but only to gather “portions” of it as seen through a lens of any particular participant. Reality is overarching and inaccessible in whole. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Fleetwood (2005)</xref> gives an overview of critical realist approach in organisation studies. In terms of the research methods used building on the above-mentioned perspectives, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Alavi and Carlson (1992)</xref> assert that the adoption of a plurality of research perspectives, rather than adhering solely to positivism, would enhance the progress in the field. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Mingers (2001)</xref> for example, is in favour not only of pluralism of research perspectives<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> within the discipline, but of routinely combining the different research methods from different research perspectives in order to achieve better and richer results. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Silverman (1998)</xref> argues that instead of focusing on what people perceive to be done, it is important to understand what is done. Opposed to that is Gummesson’s (2000) view that all research is interpretive, as both numbers and words require interpretation. In our example, the research questions revolve around developing a comprehensive picture of the processes affecting the implementation of the system. As it is seen as important how particular events were perceived and what their effect was or was perceived to be, it was deemed to be irrelevant and impossible to study the events objectively, as none of the actors would have a complete knowledge of what was happening. The interpretive perspective was deemed most suited and most appropriate perspective to take in order to answer the research questions.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="48" page="4" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="49" page="4" column="1">79</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="58" page="5" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="59" page="5" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="60" page="5" column="1">80</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="63" page="5" column="1">3. Causality</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="5" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Mohr (1982)</xref> has addressed the issue of developing and testing theories in organisational behaviour. He presents a dichotomy of variance and process theory depending on the approach that a researcher takes to build a theory in their work. Markus and Robey (1988, p. 589), in their seminal paper on causal structure in theory and research, examine theories in terms of the authors’ assumptions about the nature and direction of causality, based on the theoretical models in information technology and organisation change literature. The variance and process theories are given as examples of two different types of logical structure, which involves the “logical formulation of the theoretical argument”. Variance theory assumes that a particular cause is a necessary and sufficient condition for a particular outcome to occur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Markus and Robey, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Mohr, 1982</xref>). The assumption in variance theory is that an outcome will occur if all the conditions which are necessary and sufficient are present. The research stream on critical success factors is an example of variance theory in use. However, process theory assumes that a cause is a necessary, but not sufficient condition for an outcome to occur, so an outcome might not occur even when conditions are present. There is no particular combination of conditions and causes which ensures the occurrence of an outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Mohr, 1982</xref>). However, particular outcomes still happen. Then particular outcomes occur by chance, i.e. governed by the laws of chance. The process theory according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Mohr (1982)</xref> deals not only with probabilistic processes, but also with the external forces which influence the system, such as organisation and people, and the causes of those forces, to move the system in a particular direction and towards a particular outcome. Many researchers have complained about the state of affairs in organisational and social sciences due to the under-representation of dynamic or process approaches in the field of organisation change and IS, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Monge (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Markus and Robey (1988)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Monge (1990)</xref> has also addressed the process theory, but in a different way from the approach discussed above. His focus is on the causality of occurring events, and the relationships of influence between two or more variables over time. Although Monge’s approach is in essence processual, it is heavily based on the technical sciences and systems approach, where the influence of events is mechanistic and measurable. His approach to cause and effect dynamics can be associated with closed systems where there are no external and unaccounted for influences. As such, it is unrealistic and not sufficiently useful in the context of a complex social system.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Shaw and Jarvenpaa (1997)</xref> criticise the approach of the theorists, particularly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Mohr (1982)</xref>, who recommends using either variance or process theory in IT systems research. They developed a framework with several classes of what they call “hybrid models”, which lie between the pure variance and pure process models. The type of a hybrid model depends on the nature of the concepts forming the research model, such as variables or events/states, their occurrence, e.g. non-temporal, temporal or sequential, and their predictability – predictable or not predictable. The literature they used to populate the framework fell into four distinctive categories of hybrid models. One of the problems with the use of the process approach is the “methodological determinism” which indicates that the methods available to researchers determine and limit how the researchers approach the problem and pose research questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Monge, 1990</xref>). Another possible reason for the stigma on phase models in process research can be traced to the fact that they lack the transparency of the mechanism, which enables the occurrence of the phases that follow (Mohr, cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Markus and Robey, 1988</xref>, p. 592). However, outside of the IT systems field, the debate about inadequacy of causality and our inability to use it is ongoing, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Savage and Burrows (2007)</xref>. In our specific case of enterprise system implementation in a complex organisational context, studying the processes was seen to be more beneficial than studying causality. Additionally, there is a noted field of critical factor research in enterprise system implementation coming from the variance theory perspective, where all the factors are necessary for a successful implementation to occur. This practical use of variance theory lists out factors either throughout the implementation or at different phases of the implementation, but does not explain the details of what, e.g. top management support involves, when, how, and how this fits in any specific organisational context. With this in mind, process theory was expected to reveal issues within a complex implementation activity in more detail.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="73" page="6" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="74" page="6" column="1">81</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="81" page="6" column="1">4. Research approach: quantitative and qualitative</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" page="6" column="1">The research method is used in order to ensure that reliable knowledge is obtained through the research process. The method used in research is directly related to the prevailing epistemology. Sometimes, the terms related to the method and the epistemological positioning can be seen as interchangeable, e.g. when the authors refer to quantitative, positivist research methods[1]. In general, quantitative research is associated with positivist research perspective, while qualitative research is predominantly associated with interpretive perspective (Beynon- <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Davies, 2002</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Myers (1997)</xref> argues that qualitative research can have any underlying epistemology – positivist, interpretive or critical. Additionally, quantitative representation in terms of frequencies of occurrence of qualitative data, can also be rooted in interpretive perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Sedmak et al., 2004</xref>). It is important to note, however, that quantitative and qualitative “method” actually refers to the type of data used, rather than the method of inquiry itself. Quantitative research deals with quantities and the data are always analysed numerically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>). Statistical analysis of data are usually utilised in this type of research, and the numbers then explain the phenomenon. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris (2002)</xref> classify quantitative research into three categories: descriptive, comparative and prescriptive. Descriptive research attempts to explain a phenomenon<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> by using numbers. Comparative research compares the statistical data relating to more than one group, where there are dependent and independent variables. The differences in independent variables between the groups are then seen to affect the dependent variables. Prescriptive research has prescription as its objective. The model for prescriptive research is that there is a cause and effect, and that this relationship can be described in the form of mathematical equations. The advantages of quantitative research include theory testing, replicability and generalisability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>). However, in order to be able to test a theory, it is necessary to have enough knowledge of the phenomenon already in order to be able to test the constructs, variables and relationships. In order to make quantitative research replicable it is also necessary to have a structured data analysis process, where data are less dependent on the researcher’s interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>). Appropriate sampling should address the issue of generalisability and allow for the responses to be generalisable to a specific a priori defined population. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris (2002)</xref> also argue against the common perceptions of quantitative research. One of them is that quantitative research is seen as objective, while they believe that the subjectivity in this approach is in the scales included or not included in the questionnaire, the sampling, and the data which is the focus of research. Another is an illusion of precision of the type of data. They give an example of using the scales where we might wonder what a 3.27 mean score represents if scale point 3 is “no strong feelings” and point 4 is “disagree”. Qualitative research is that in which the data obtained is in the form of words and observations, rather than numbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Miles and Huberman, 1994</xref>). The advantages of qualitative research are that it requires in-depth data which gives descriptions and explanations placed in a particular context, and as such can help in generation or revision of conceptual frameworks. One of the major advantages is that, apart from answering the initial research questions, qualitative research can provide answers to research questions not originally asked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>). Additionally, the research can be conducted in order to compare two sets of data and reveal similarities between processes. The disadvantages of qualitative research are the length of time and effort required for data collection, data overload, the possibility of researcher bias, extensive data processing and coding, reliability of sampling methods, generalisability of findings, credibility of conclusions and the lack of methods of analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Johnson and Harris, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Miles and Huberman, 1994</xref>). However, some of these issues, e.g. generalisability, would only be raised by researchers using quantitative research approach and would not be as relevant to a qualitative researcher. The debate between the use of qualitative and quantitative research approach is ongoing. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Bryman (1988)</xref> argues that there are situations where the differences between the quantitative and qualitative approach are technical rather than epistemological. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Silverman (1998)</xref> argues that both quantitative and qualitative research neglect people interaction, and that both are more concerned with the environment around the phenomenon than with the phenomenon itself. In our example, the study of an implementation of an enterprise system in a manufacturing organisation, the objective of the research was to develop a comprehensive picture of the processes affecting the implementation of the system, and to investigate which of the processes during implementation play a significant role<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> in that implementation. Both qualitative and quantitative approaches were adopted in this research. The qualitative analysis looked more deeply into what the events were, how they interrelated, and the perceptions of the participants. The quantitative analysis looked into the number of occurrences of a specific category of events or states, but was based on the qualitative data. In the light of the research questions and objectives, qualitative approach was seen as the most appropriate as it is adopted towards answering the research questions. Quantitative approach as a part of the overall research strategy was deemed as appropriate to show the importance or the predominance of one category of elements of the process – events, states, activities, over others. For example, if a particular incidence of top management communication was seen as important in 50 per cent of interview responses, then these kind of events are significant and had a memorable effect on the interviewees. This choice helps in putting into perspective which elements of the process are seen as more important.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="88" page="7" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="89" page="7" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="90" page="7" column="1">82</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="102" page="8" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="103" page="8" column="1">83</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="105" page="8" column="1">5. Fixed and flexible research design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="8" column="1">According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref>, flexible and fixed designs are better descriptions of research design than qualitative and quantitative research. In the case of fixed design research, the design needs to be established prior to data collection. The specific method needs to be decided upon at the early stages. In the case of flexible research, the design emerges and develops during data collection, so the techniques used for data collection can change during the research. It is developed during the research process, in the light of the findings and additional input from the participants and experts who are willing to engage with a researcher in the method development and evaluation. In our example of enterprise system implementation, the decision about the qualitative approach is made in the light of the choices addressed in the previous section and the exploratory nature of the research questions. Choosing flexible research design in our context is justifiable, as the initial approach and the tools used for data collection needed further moulding in the light of the feedback of the involved parties and based on the findings.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="8" column="1">6. Researcher role in data collection</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="8" column="1">The researcher can be directly involved in the data-collection process. In this case, the data collected is primary data. However, there are many cases of the reuse of other researchers’ data. Secondary analysis is the term used for re-analysis of someone else’s data ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Rosenthal and Rosnow, 1991</xref>), and secondary data constitutes data collected by another researcher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Blaikie, 2000</xref>). Meta-analysis is a type of secondary analysis which summarises and combines the results of a number of studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Rosenthal and Rosnow, 1991</xref>). This type of research study usually refers to analysing datasets. Secondary data may be quantitative or qualitative. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Hakim (1982)</xref> identifies different sources and types of quantitative data, including censuses and datasets derived from administrative and public records. In contrast to this, Weber defines content analysis as a “research method that uses a set of procedures to make valid inferences from text” (Weber, cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Neuendorf, 2002</xref>, p. 10). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Yin (1994)</xref> recognises the use of both quantitative and qualitative data for further analysis, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Corti (2000)</xref> points out the lack of evidence to date about successful reuse of qualitative data compared with the evidence for quantitative survey data<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> and historical texts. This, she suggests, intimidates researchers from making the most of available qualitative data. Additionally, a combination of both primary and secondary data can be used. Primary data are collected by the author being directly involved in the research process. Secondary data can also be analysed, e.g. from company literature, presentations, formal correspondence and financial information, or data from descriptions of cases of enterprise system implementation or experiences of projects published by other researchers, e.g. in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Sedmak et al., 2004</xref>). Primary data are generally collected as major base for findings as it is taken directly from the context. However, secondary data can provide additional base for more findings from the research which has already been conducted, or for the purposes of confirmation of the findings from primary data. This was the case of our study, where primary data were collected by the researcher being directly involved in the data-collection process, while company literature, such as annual reviews and newsletters, company web site, project web site and project announcements were used to support primary data.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="117" page="9" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="118" page="9" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="119" page="9" column="1">84</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="122" page="9" column="1">7. Research strategy</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" page="9" column="1">An additional distinction can be made between deductive and inductive research strategies. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Blaikie (2000)</xref>, research strategies provide a set of steps in order to answer the research questions. Deductive research starts with a theory or a concept that requires explanation. Starting from hypotheses deduced from theory, the data are found to either confirm the hypotheses, and in that way support the theory, or, if the data does not confirm the hypotheses, the theory needs to be appropriately modified or rejected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Blaikie, 2000</xref>). Inductivism is defined as a doctrine according to which science and scientific theories are a result of the field of knowledge of empirically established facts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Bryman, 1988</xref>). Inductive research strategy then involves the building of theories based on the data. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Blaikie (2000)</xref> identifies an additional strategic category as retroductive. This strategy starts from a similar point as deductive, from the point where a specific theory, or regularity as he calls it, exists, but then the strategy leads to uncovering the reasons and causes for the regularity. In order to discover, the reasons and causes, the researcher needs to create hypotheses about the reasons for this regularity to be in existence, and then confirm or disprove the hypotheses. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Gummesson (2000)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Bryman (1988)</xref> argue that the starting points of research may be different, but that after the initial stages, all research is a combination of inductive and deductive, as the researcher goes through the stages of iteration and refinement of the theories and data collection and analysis. The term <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Gummesson (2000)</xref> uses for this process is abductive research strategy. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Blaikie (2000)</xref> defines abductive research strategy differently. He defines it as having different logic to deductive, inductive and retroductive research. The researcher needs to abstract the actors’ motives and reasons for activities into “typical motives for typical actions in typical situations” (p. 25). The end point of this strategy is to provide an understanding of the activities seen through the lens of actors and the way they see their own motives and reasons. In our example of an enterprise system implementation, the research strategy which was used can be described as retroductive, according to Blaikie (above). The regularity<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> which exists – a problematic enterprise system implementation, is studied to uncover the reasons and causes for its occurrence in a particular organisational context. However, when the causes are identified, further research can follow inductive strategy to build new theories from data, for example about the effects of power and hierarchy on the implementation to become problematic, or company size, communication channels, etc. This coincides with flexible research design defined above, as the findings from the first phase of the research based on a particular method focused the research efforts and appropriately affected the method further in the research process.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="132" page="10" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="133" page="10" column="1">85</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="135" page="10" column="1">8. Methods of inquiry</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="150" page="10" column="1">In this section, we focus on various ways of conducting research, or methods of inquiry. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="136" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> describes experimental and non-experimental design as forms of fixed design. In the case of experimental design, the participants are in different conditions where the researcher can influence the independent variables. This affects the dependent variables, which are measured, and all other variables are controlled. Non-experimental fixed design is very similar to experimental design, but the independent variables are not, should not – for ethical reasons, or cannot be directly influenced by the researcher. He classifies case study research, grounded theory and ethnography as “influential design traditions” in flexible design inquiry (p. 164). However, the notion of trustworthiness of findings coming from this type of research is raised as the subject of much debate. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Yin (1994)</xref> states that case studies, as a means of research, can satisfy the desire of a researcher to better understand complex social phenomena, while retaining the bigger picture and meaning of the events. As such, a case study is an enquiry exploring a phenomenon set within a specific context, in which the boundaries between the two are not clear, or in which the context might be relevant to the studied phenomenon. When selecting a method of inquiry, it is important to have the research questions, the control over the events and the timing of the events in mind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Yin, 1994</xref>). Case studies can be used in a current setting or when dealing with past events, where the witnesses or people involved in them are still available to report, while there is no need to control the behaviour of events. The case study is best used with research questions which start with “how” and “why”, as an explanation of operational links, rather than frequency of incidents. However, for “what” questions, where “what” refers to exploration, an exploratory case study can be used in order to develop a hypothesis or ideas for further research. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="139" class="deo:Reference">Gummesson (2000)</xref>, case studies are a good method for studying company processes, as well as for exploratory, descriptive and explanatory purposes. The grounded theory method was developed by Glaser and Strauss in the, 1960s. It uses a set of steps – procedures, in order to build a theory that is grounded in data. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref>, grounded theory originated as a reaction to the usual sociological approach of the 1960s, in which the research strategy was deductive, with its starting point in theory. Glaser and Strauss had as an aim to develop a method for data analysis which would be systematic and explicit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Strauss, 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="142" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> states that the benefits of the method include its usefulness in the areas of research where the theoretical approach is not developed. However, he also points out that any research needs some pre-existing theories and that there might be a tension between<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> the evolving and inductive strategies as opposed to the systematic approach to data analysis which the grounded theory method requires. Additionally, it is often the case that academics use the term grounded theory for inductive strategy to indicate that the findings are “grounded in data” rather than to denote the use of the strict grounded theory method. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Hammersley and Atkinson (1995)</xref> suggest that social scientists have felt the tension between the methods applied from natural sciences and the complexity of the social world and how it can be studied. According to them, the ethnographer immerses him or herself in the daily lives of people for a considerable length of time in order to understand the research problem and find answers to research questions. Agar (1986, p. 12) defines ethnography as a “social research style that emphasises encountering alien worlds and making sense of them”. This method developed initially in order to understand different, foreign cultures, and then in the 1930s and 1940s it started to gain ground in organisational research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Schwartzman, 1993</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> states the difficulties of using the ethnographic method to be: the ability to understand the concepts used in socio-cultural systems and apply them in descriptions, analysis and interpretation of the studied culture; time consuming; narrative writing style which might not be suitable for a social scientist; and the researcher “going native” – abandoning the study and becoming a part of the studied group. In our example of an enterprise system implementation, case study as the method of inquiry for the collection of primary data were deemed most suitable. A study of one or several cases in depth, as the case study method of inquiry allows, achieves the objectives and answers the research questions to study processes occurring in an organisation and between people and exploration of the contextual issues that affect the implementation. In this case, ethnography and grounded theory are alternative methods when a flexible research design is used. However, ethnography is suitable for use on a different level of inquiry, and might be helpful to reveal social forces in the context, for example. Grounded theory would be discarded as a significant body of knowledge already exists from the perspective of studying the factors influencing the implementation of an enterprise system, albeit from a varience theory perspective, as defined above.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="144" page="11" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="145" page="11" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="146" page="11" column="1">86</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="151" page="11" column="1">9. Techniques in research design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="158" page="11" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="152" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> suggests that the technique should be decided upon according to the research questions asked and the research strategy chosen. He classes techniques into direct observation, interviews, questionnaires, attitude scales and standardised tests, which vary according to what the researcher wants to find out – what people do in public, privately, or how they think or feel, or about their personality. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Savage and Burrows (2007)</xref> provide a succinct history of some of the techniques, such as the use of questionnaires and in-depth interviews as ways to collect data. Additionally, focus groups, workshops and group interviews can be useful techniques to collect data. They would normally involve a group of people, and in case of the focus groups, the researcher would provide the structure that the focus group would follow, which would involve questions or conversation topics and activities, in line with the research questions. Workshops would be set in a similar way to a focus group, but generally, the workshops would provide more benefit to the organisation studied. In case of an enterprise system implementation, a focus group would provide<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> more of a discussion ground and possibly consensus about the reasons behind the problematic aspects of the implementation, while a workshop would have as an outcome a list of actions that the participants would commit themselves to do. Both techniques are particularly useful to study, for example, group dynamics in the team or attributes of a project leader. However, due to the same group dynamics and power relationships within the group, as well as different personality types in the group, it cannot be expected that the data collected would not be biased in a particular way, either due to the participants not expressing themselves fully because their line managers might be present, or some being more introverted than others. An example of the use of group interview as a research method can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="157" class="deo:Reference">Steyaert and Bouwen (2004)</xref>. In our case of enterprise system implementation, one-to-one interviews were chosen as the main technique for data collection. However, due to the company’s request, a set of focus groups was conducted. In addition, a workshop could have taken place, both in order to validate the initial findings, and to elicit further actions necessary to improve the implementation process, based on the findings. On this occasion, however, due to time pressures on the project participants this was not possible.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="155" page="12" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="156" page="12" column="1">87</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="159" page="12" column="1">10. Researcher engagement with the setting</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="181" page="12" column="1">The researcher can take on different roles in relation to the setting where the data are collected. He/she can act as complete participant or a participant-as-observer ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="160" class="deo:Reference">Nachimias and Nachimias, 1981</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="161" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> adds two more distinctions: the marginal participant and the observer-as-participant. A complete participant is a researcher who becomes a full member of the group studied but whose role is concealed from the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="162" class="deo:Reference">Robson, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="163" class="deo:Reference">Nachimias and Nachimias, 1981</xref>). This is often justified by an expected refusal of the group to take in the researcher or by the behaviour of the group members changing due to the presence of the researcher. The participant-as-observer role can be defined as the one the researcher takes when the group is informed about the researcher’s intention to observe the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="164" class="deo:Reference">Robson, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Nachimias and Nachimias, 1981</xref>). Then the researcher’s focus shifts to establishing a relationship with the observed, who become informants and respondents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Nachimias and Nachimias, 1981</xref>). The marginal participant is a researcher who observes the behaviour of the group studied, but with a lower degree of participation than a participant-as-observer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Robson, 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Robson (2002)</xref> gives an example of a researcher in the role of a marginal participant as a spectator in the audience at a concert. Finally, the researcher in the role of an observer-as-participant does not take part in the group activity, but his or her status as a researcher is known to the group members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="169" class="deo:Reference">Robson, 2002</xref>). Additional distinction can be made between the above-mentioned participatory roles a researcher can take and an intentional interventionist role, e.g. in action research or consultancy. In its various forms, action research, which uses intervention to solve organisational problems while it contributes to knowledge at the same time, has been in use in the field of IS for considerable time (Baskerville and Wood-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="170" class="deo:Reference">Harper, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="171" class="deo:Reference">Davison et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="172" class="deo:Reference">Chiasson et al., 2009</xref>). However, its use in the area of enterprise systems to date has been limited. In our case of studying an implementation of an enterprise system, where the researcher conducts interviews and focus groups or workshops to collect qualitative<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> data as primary, his/her role in relation to the setting could be classed as participant-as-observer. The participants are fully informed of the research project. However, the researcher does not participate or observe the usual activities of the group. By the fact that an interview is a dialogue between a researcher and an interviewee or participants of the focus group, it can also be argued that the researcher initiated and imposed the activity of an interview or focus group, including the questions that were asked, on the actors, for the purposes of data collection. Again, this choice is usually made to achieve the depth of the study and in the light of the interpretive research perspective which is taken. In addition to the researcher roles above, a distinction should be made between “emic” and “etic” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Sinkovics et al., 2008</xref>). This terminology originated in the work of Kenneth Pike in, 1954, who coined the terms from the linguistic terms “phonetic” and “phonemic” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="178" class="deo:Reference">Headland, 1990</xref>). Phonemic refers to any unit of a particular sound – phoneme, in a language, while phonetic refers to the linguistic system that is devised externally – by the linguists, to represent the phonemes. Some researchers refer to emic as an insider perspective and etic as an outsider perspective, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="179" class="deo:Reference">Hodder (1994)</xref>. However, these terms tend to be used in a variety of ways in anthropology and other sciences and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="180" class="deo:Reference">Headland (1990)</xref> presents a brief review of their different uses. In terms of the distinction between the emic and etic relationship to the setting in relation to our example, an emic approach was initially adopted in order for the researcher to be able to understand the participants. Each participant would have their individual language and a way of expression, depending on their personal experiences and background, the department they were in and the company they worked for. For a researcher to be able to understand these different “languages” of the participants, it is necessary to become immersed very quickly during the interview into the world of the participant and the expression of that world through language. In the focus groups or a workshop, on the other hand, this is less so as the communication between the participants needs to be already moderated by each of the participants themselves to ensure that the other members of the focus group coming into it with different experiences and from different departments, would understand. However, when the focus shifts to data analysis, there is a need to take a more etic approach and create a distance between the individual participant’s expression and the more generalised language appropriate for studying enterprise systems.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="174" page="13" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="175" page="13" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="176" page="13" column="1">88</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="182" page="13" column="1">11. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="187" page="13" column="1">The field of enterprise systems is developing and ever-changing, in line with technology developments and the quest for increased integration of systems and related cost savings. Such change provides an opportunity for researchers to put into practice some of the methods and approaches which have not been popular among the researchers. As discussed, action research is one of those, particularly considering that there have been significant efforts to make this kind of research more rigorous and valid. In addition, organisations would benefit from researchers’ involvement and contribution to their projects. Pluralist action research which combines action research with other methods is another possible avenue. Introduction of new technology in organisations, such as Web 2.0 and technologies enabled by it, would benefit from multimethod research as advocated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="183" class="deo:Reference">Mingers (2001)</xref> in order to understand their implementation and use. If the rate of their development<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> and change in use is taken into account, researchers may not have the opportunity to conduct a several years long longitudinal study. They would therefore have to maximise on the potential that the time window when technology is in use provides. The objective of this paper was to bring the research design, based around particular research methods and on the epistemological foundation, closer to research practice. This was done in order to raise researchers’ awareness of various choices available when studying IS and enterprise systems more specifically. The above methodological choices come from various areas, such as IS research and organisational studies, and provide tools which can be used to study phenomena related to enterprise systems in organisational settings. Awareness of what is available in order to best answer specific research questions enables transparency of the research design and helps in reducing researcher bias. Additionally, being aware of methodological options reduces the possibility of “methodological determinism”. Each of the choices available has its shortcomings of course, and a researcher needs to address these, as well as find the appropriate ways of validating the research method and the findings. In our example of enterprise system implementation, prior and during the data-collection process and following brief data analysis after every instance of data collection, particular attention was paid to ensuring that the research choices made were in line with the research questions. As such, the research process incorporated continual evaluation of the choices made, in light of flexible research design. Most of the decisions taken were evaluated as bringing the researcher closer to answering the research questions. One exception was the data collection using a focus group as a technique, where the above-mentioned forces of group dynamics are in play and where the composition of the group is of significance. However, the same method provided insight into one problematic area – project communication, which did not transpire to a large degree in individual interviews, but was nonetheless valuable. Further contact with the company ensued one year after data-collection phase. The implementation was proved to be successful from the project management perspective, however no details were available with regards to, e.g. staffing changes or user satisfaction. To conclude, it is important to bear in mind that greater awareness of choices leads to more decisions that need to be made. Once the haze of research methodology settles down and we as researchers become more aware of what tools of trade we have at out disposal, we can make those decisions in a more informed way and in the light of the pertinent research questions, thus contributing more to practice and the body of knowledge.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="185" page="14" column="1">Enterprise systems research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="186" page="14" column="1">89</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="188" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Note</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="189" page="14" column="1">1. Here, we adopted the term “approach”. We used the term “method of inquiry” in another context further in the text where it is deemed appropriate.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="190" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="14" column="1">Agar, M.H. (1986), Speaking of Ethnography, Sage, Beverly Hills, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="14" column="1">Alavi, M. and Carlson, P. (1992), “A review of MIS research and disciplinary development”, Journal of Management Information Systems, Vol. 8 No. 4, pp. 45-62.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="14" column="1">Baskerville, R. and Wood-Harper, A.T. (1998), “Diversity in information systems action research methods”, European Journal of Information Systems, Vol. 7 No. 2, pp. 90-107.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="15" column="1">Beynon-Davies, P. (2002), Information Systems: An Introduction to Informatics in Organisations,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="15" column="1">Palgrave, Basingstoke.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="15" column="1">Blaikie, N. (2000), Designing Social Research: The Logic of Anticipation, Polity Press, Cambridge, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="15" column="1">Bryman, A. (1988), Quantity and Quality in Social Research, Unwin Hyman, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="15" column="1">Chiasson, M., Germonprez, M. and Mathiassen, L. (2009), “Pluralist action research: a review of the information systems literature”, Information Systems Journal, Vol. 19 No. 1, pp. 31-54.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="15" column="1">Chua, W.F. (1986), “Radical developments in accounting thought”, The Accounting Review, Vol. 61 No. 4, pp. 601-32.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="15" column="1">Chuang, M.-L. and Shaw, W.H. (2008), “An empirical study of enterprise resource management systems implementation: from ERP to RFID”, Business Process Management Journal, Vol. 14 No. 5, pp. 675-93.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="15" column="1">Corti, L. (2000), “Progress and problems of preserving and providing access to qualitative data for social research: the international picture of an emerging culture”, Forum Qualitative Sozialforschung/Forum: Qualitative Social Research, Vol. 1 No. 3, available at: www.qualitative-research.net/fqs-texte/3-00/3-00corti-e.htm (accessed 15 March 2008).</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="15" column="1">Davison, R.M., Martinsons, M.G. and Kock, N. (2004), “Principles of canonical action research”, Information Systems Journal, Vol. 14 No. 1, pp. 65-86.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="15" column="1">Deloitte (1999), ERP’s Second Wave: Maximising the Value of ERP-Enabled Processes, Deloitte Consulting, Atlanta, GA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="15" column="1">Fleetwood, S. (2005), “Ontology in organization and management studies: a critical realist perspective”, Organization, Vol. 12 No. 2, pp. 197-222.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Gummesson, E. (2000), Qualitative Methods in Management Research, 2nd ed., Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Hakim, C. (1982), Secondary Analysis in Social Research: A Guide to Data Sources and Methods with Examples, George Allen &amp; Unwin, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="15" column="1">Hammersley, M. and Atkinson, P. (1995), Ethnography: Principles in Practice, 2nd ed., Routledge, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="15" column="1">Headland, T.N. (1990), “A dialogue between Kenneth Pike and Marvin Harris on emics and etics”, in Headland, T.N., Pike, K.L. and Harris, M. (Eds), Emics and Etics: The Insider/Outsider Debate, Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA, pp. 13-27.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" page="15" column="1">Hodder, I. (1994), “The interpretation of documents and material culture”, in Denzin, N.K. and Lincoln, Y.S. (Eds), Handbook of Qualitative Research, Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA, pp. 393-402.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" page="15" column="1">Johnson, P. and Harris, D. (2002), “Qualitative and quantitative issues in research design”, in Partington, D. (Ed.), Essential Skills for Management Research, Sage, London, pp. 99-116.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="15" column="1">Lee, C.-P., Lee, G.-G. and Lin, H.-F. (2007), “The role of organizational capabilities in successful e-business implementation”, Business Process Management Journal, Vol. 13 No. 5, pp. 677-93.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="15" column="1">Markus, M.L. and Robey, D. (1988), “Information technology and organisational change: causal structure in theory and research”, Management Science, Vol. 34 No. 5, pp. 583-98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="15" column="1">Miles, M.B. and Huberman, A.M. (1994), Qualitative Data Analysis: An Expanded Sourcebook, Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="15" column="1">Mingers, J. (2001), “Combining IS research methods: towards a pluralist methodology”, Information Systems Research, Vol. 12 No. 3, pp. 240-59.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" page="15" column="1">Mohr, L.B. (1982), Explaining Organizational Behavior, Jossey-Bass, San Francisco, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="16" column="1">Monge, P.R. (1990), “Theoretical and analytical issues in studying organizational processes”, Enterprise Organization Science, Vol. 1 No. 4, pp. 406-30. systems research</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="16" column="1">Moon, Y.B. (2007), “Enterprise resource planning (ERP): a review of the literature”, International Journal of Management and Enterprise Development, Vol. 4 No. 3, pp. 235-64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="16" column="1">Myers, M.D. (1997), “Qualitative research in information systems”, MIS Quarterly, Vol. 21 No. 2, pp. 241-2 (MISQ Discovery, archival version, June 1997, available at: www.misq.org/ discovery/MISQD_isworld/. MISQ Discovery, updated version, last modified: January, 2007, available at: www.qual.auckland.ac.nz (accessed February 2007)).</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Nachimias, C. and Nachimias, D. (1981), Research Methods in the Social Sciences: Alternate Second Edition without Statistics, St Martin’s Press, New York, NY.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="16" column="1">Neuendorf, K.A. (2002), The Content Analysis Guidebook, Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" page="16" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. and Baroudi, J.J. (1991), “Studying information technology in organizations: research approaches and assumptions”, Information Systems Research, Vol. 2 No. 1, pp. 1-28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" page="16" column="1">Robson, C. (2002), Real World Research: A Resource for Social Scientists and Practitioner-Researchers, 2nd ed., Blackwell, Oxford.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" page="16" column="1">Rosenthal, R. and Rosnow, R.L. (1991), Essentials of Behavioral Research: Methods and Data Analysis, 2nd ed., McGraw-Hill, New York, NY.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Savage, M. and Burrows, R. (2007), “The coming crisis of empirical sociology”, Sociology, Vol. 41 No. 5, pp. 885-99.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="16" column="1">Schwartzman, H.B. (1993), Ethnography in Organizations, Sage, Newbury Park, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" page="16" column="1">Seddon, P., Shanks, G. and Willcocks, L. (2003), “Introduction: ERP – the quiet revolution?”, in Shanks, G., Seddon, P.B. and Willcocks, L.P. (Eds), Second – Wave Enterprise Resource Planning Systems: Implementing for Effectiveness, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, MA, pp. 1-19.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" page="16" column="1">Sedmak, M., Fan, I.S. and Wognum, P.M. (2004), “Hidden gems: what literature reveals about the cases of enterprise system implementation”, Proceedings of the British Academy of Management Conference, St Andrews, UK, pp. 1-21.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" page="16" column="1">Seethamraju, R. (2007), “Influence of enterprise systems on the management and performance of supply chains”, in Rahim, M. and Yeh, C.-H. (Eds), Proceedings of the 13th Asia Pacific Management Conference, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia, pp. 131-9.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" page="16" column="1">Shaw, T. and Jarvenpaa, S. (1997), “Process models in information systems”, in Lee, A.S., Liebenau, J. and DeGross, J.I. (Eds), Proceedings of the IFIP Working Group 8.2 Conference on Information Systems and Qualitative Research, Philadelphia, PA, USA, Kluwer Academic Publishers, Boston, MA, pp. 70-100.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" page="16" column="1">Silverman, D. (1998), “Qualitative research: meanings or practices?”, Information Systems Journal, Vol. 8 No. 1, pp. 3-20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" page="16" column="1">Sinkovics, R.R., Penz, E. and Ghauri, P.N. (2008), “Enhancing the trustworthiness of qualitative research in international business”, Management International Review, Vol. 48 No. 6, pp. 689-713.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" page="16" column="1">Stefanou, C.J. and Revanoglou, A. (2006), “ERP integration in a healthcare environment: a case study”, Journal of Enterprise Information Management, Vol. 19 No. 1, pp. 115-30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" page="16" column="1">Steyaert, C. and Bouwen, R. (2004), “Group methods of organizational analysis”, in Cassell, C. and Symon, G. (Eds), Essential Guide to Qualitative Methods in Organizational Research, Sage, London, pp. 140-53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" page="17" column="1">Strauss, A.L. (1987), Qualitative Analysis for Social Scientists, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Yin, R.K. (1994), Case Study Research: Design and Methods, 2nd ed., Sage, Thousand Oaks, CA.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="unknown" id="194" page="15" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="196" page="15" column="1">16,1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="200" page="15" column="1">90</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="221" page="16" column="1">91</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="238" page="17" column="1">BPMJ</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="239" page="17" column="1">16,1</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="242" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">About the authors</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="243" page="17" column="1">92</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="245" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Melissa Sedmak is an Associate Lecturer in Risk Management in the School of Risk and Safety Sciences, at the University of New South Wales. Her research interests include organisational and technology change and management of respective risks, as well as communication and organisational processes. Melissa Sedmak is the corresponding author and can be contacted at: <email id="244">m.sedmak@unsw.edu.au</email> Phil Longhurst is a Senior Lecturer in Waste Strategy in the Centre for Resource Management and Efficiency, School of Applied Sciences at Cranfield University. His research interests include resource flow of materials, mass balance and resource trading and technology assessment.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="246" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">To purchase reprints of this article please e-mail: Or visit our web site for further details:</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="248" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1"> <email id="247">reprints@emeraldinsight.com</email> www.emeraldinsight.com/reprints</h1>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
