<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>7677d0264d37ff1f023c5b88a1faa3217707b3741bcafff69c289ef02192a1e8</job>
    <base_name>62ce</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.3917/rac.006.0003</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ce.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62ce.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" confidence="possible">Cet article est disponible en ligne à l’adresse : <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cairn.info/article.php?ID_REVUE=RAC&amp;ID_NUMPUBLIE=RAC_006&amp;ID_ARTICLE=RAC_006_0003" id="2">http://www.cairn.info/article.php?ID_REVUE=RAC&amp;ID_NUMPUBLIE=RAC_006&amp;ID_ARTICLE=RAC_006_0003</ext-link></region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="4">Revisiting the notion of Boundary Object</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">par Pascale TROMPETTE et Dominique VINCK</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">| S.A.C. | Revue d'anthropologie des connaissances 2009/1 - Vol. 3, n° 1 ISSN 1760-5393 | pages 3 à 25</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="7">Pour citer cet article : — Trompette P. et Vinck D., Revisiting the notion of Boundary Object, Revue d'anthropologie des connaissances 2009/ 1, Vol. 3, n° 1, p. 3-25.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="8">Distribution électronique Cairn pour S.A.C.. © S.A.C.. Tous droits réservés pour tous pays. La reproduction ou représentation de cet article, notamment par photocopie, n'est autorisée que dans les limites des conditions générales d'utilisation du site ou, le cas échéant, des conditions générales de la licence souscrite par votre établissement. Toute autre reproduction ou représentation, en tout ou partie, sous quelque forme et de quelque manière que ce soit, est interdite sauf accord préalable et écrit de l'éditeur, en dehors des cas prévus par la législation en vigueur en France. Il est précisé que son stockage dans une base de données est également interdit.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="9">S PECIAL ISSUE “B OUNDARY O BJECT ”</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" page="2" column="1">REVISITING THE NOTION OF BOUNDARY OBJECT</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="11" page="2" column="1">1</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="12" page="2" column="1">P ASCALE TROMPETTE AND D OMINIQUE VINCK</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="2" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="2" column="1">In an article which has since achieved some renown, entitled “Institutional ecology, “translations”, and boundary objects: amateurs and professionals” – Susan L. Star and James R. Griesemer ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer, 1989</xref>) introduced the notion of boundary object on the basis of an ethnographical study of the coordination mechanisms of scientific work. This first conceptualisation proposed revisiting the actor-network theory (ANT) within an ecological perspective of collective action and innovation. The boundary object demonstrated the role of all sorts of artefacts – directories, classifications, materialised representations (maps, designs), standardised methods – involved in the collection, management and coordination of knowledge which is subsequently distributed.<marker type="block"/> Since, the concept has enjoyed a vigorous academic career, being deployed in particular in the field of knowledge management. It has paved the way to a conceptual progeny – boundary work, boundary spanning, boundary organisation -, traversed a variety of disciplinary fields (sociology, management, educa- tional science, design engineering, etc.) and incorporated increasingly diversified “genres” of knowledge objects and artefacts.<marker type="block"/> Throughout the social existence of the concept, its application has at least in part become autonomous from the original conceptualisation. Certain properties have attracted particular interest for their analytical scope in the description of activities: this applies to “interpretive flexibility” of the boundary object allowing it to operate as a support for heterogeneous translations as a knowledge integration mechanism, as a mediation in the coordination process of experts and non-experts, etc. In relative terms, other dimensions have lost momentum<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> and sometimes even been forgotten: this applies to the incorporation of an invisible infrastructure where the boundary object transports a set of conventions, standards and norms indexed to a community of practices, this property which facilitates reporting on activity delegation processes (i.e. the delegation of scientific work to amateurs) and to the formative action of knowledge artifices in the production of knowledge (classification, categorisation, material standardisation, etc.).<marker type="block"/> The purpose of this special issue is therefore to revisit the concept in order to look at its analytical scope whilst taking care to maintain the close articulation between interpretive flexibility and infrastructure. This will be achieved primarily through texts which propose an immersion through empirical studies and engage a description on the basis of the notion of boundary object, taking this theoretical inflection into account. We will keenly observe the importance of research in the STS field and the sociology of sciences in particular, as if loyalty to this original construction simultaneously reactivated a community of genres, whether in the authors’ projects (understanding coordination between scientific worlds) or in the ecology of situations (the distributed structure of the development of heterogeneous knowledge within epistemic communities) (see articles by Gilles Tetart and Didier Torny, and Martin Rémondet in this issue). This familiarity with the Griesemer and Star project leads us to revisit the activity of material collection in the ecology field (see the article by Céline Granjou and Isabelle Mauz) right through to the Natural History Museum (see the article by Morgan Meyer). Dominique Vinck’s text will punctuate this series of case studies at a more theoretical level of discussion which will be just as soundly based on the constant to-ing and fro-ing between numerous fieldworks concerning scientific activities or design work and so once again, firmly anchored in the STS field. The notion of boundary object is explored here as a counterpoint to that of the “intermediary object”, a notion introduced by the author; it comes out of this invested with a greater theoretical charge where the object which serves a linking purpose carries infrastructures and knowledge models.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="18" page="2" column="1">1 Translated by Neil Draper.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="19" page="2" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="20" page="2" column="1">a</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="21" page="3" column="1">b</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="22" page="3" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="25" page="3" column="1">THE ORIGINAL STAR AND GRIESEMER ARTICLE AND ITS CONTEXT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" page="3" column="1">The notion of boundary object is part of the “grounded theory” model in the sense that it emerges and is constructed as an element of theorisation for authors in their confrontation with their field materials. Star and Griesemer indeed, introduced the notion within the framework of an ethnographical study of scientific work coordination mechanisms inside a natural history museum. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> It is part of a tradition of thought which comes from symbolic interactionism 2 which seeks to qualify articulation mechanisms surrounding the perspectives of authors belonging to heterogeneous social worlds 3 . The problem of authors is to describe and characterise the process through which actors from different social worlds - called upon to cooperate - manage to coordinate with each other in spite of their differing points of view: how do they create common understanding without losing the diversity of their social worlds? Those involved in areas where knowledge is not yet stabilised come up against the need to reconcile different meanings given to objects upon which they are attempting to reach agreement. Actors (administrators, managers, researchers, amateurs, foundations, poli- ticians), organised around shared objectives (promoting the protection of species, drawing up a guide to fauna and flora), succeeded in cooperating over a long period (1907-1939) in creating a zoology museum in spite of their diverging points of view, in particular concerning the importance afforded to research and the categorisation plan of certain species. Those involved succeeded in coming to an understanding by working around objects. The process allowed them to maintain a plurality of points of view. Each of the parties was able to keep its identity and its targets and was able to carry on its work whilst articulating with others. As a student of Anselm Strauss who had taken an interest in the social processes via which human beings modelled their environment by the construction of a negotiated order (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Strauss et al, 1985</xref>), Susan L. Star was particularly interested in the construction of hybrid arrangements in the life sciences field where study objects are moving and constantly renegotiated between social worlds. She looked at the question of the stabilisation of definitions, and in particular patients’ switches between situated biographies and cases which come under a standardised classification. As early as her thesis, she took an interest in classification as knowledge infrastructures. It is within the framework of this research programme that she worked on the articulation between several heterogeneous social worlds. James R. Griesemer, a biologist and philosopher by training who was working on the conceptual foundation of sciences, was particularly interested in explanational models and in work surrounding modelisation (including material models used in biology). He was also particularly interested in ecology laboratories and a museum. After publication of his joint article with S. L. Star, he was to take even greater interest in material and intellectual instru- mentation in sciences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Griesemer, 1992</xref>). 2 A micro-sociology tradition which rejects both sociological and biological determinism and privileges explanation on the basis of dynamic interactions which are observable between individuals. It underlines the fact that the sense of phenomena results from interpretations made by actors in context. These interpretations are to do with interpretive frameworks which move away from interactions between actors (verbal and non-verbal symbolic interactions). 3 The term “Social worlds” refers to activity groups which have neither clear boundaries nor formal and stable organisations. They develop through the relationship between social interactions which move away from the primary activity and the definition of pattern and reality. The notion derives from the symbolic interactionism tradition.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> Returning to the notion of translation espoused by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Callon (1986)</xref>, Star and Griesemer questioned the asymmetric interpretation of translation operations, as deployed in the works of Callon, Law and Latour, where such operations are compared to the almost imperialist action of the innovator or scientific entrepreneur, who seeks to enrol other actors via, in particular, the creation of an obligatory passage point. Star and Griesemer propose a more ecological approach to the situation which makes no concession to the points of view present and which takes into account the coexistence of several translation processes of which the overall coherence constitutes the nub of the problem. The solutions invented by actors in context would seem to be of two types: the standardisation of methods and the development of boundary objects. And this concerns abstract or concrete objects, whose structure is sufficiently common to several social worlds to ensure minimum identity in terms of the intersection whilst being sufficiently flexible to adapt to the specific needs and constraints of each of these worlds. These boundary objects are supposed to maximise both the autonomy of these social worlds and communication between them. The notion is therefore closely linked to issues of shared meaning and interpretation. It supposes the existence of a minimal structure of knowledge which is recognised by the members of the different social worlds, which can take very diverse forms: the malleable object which can be shaped by each and every one; the library object from which each individual can take what he or she needs; the object which can be either simplified (abstraction), allowing us to ignore the properties we do not need; and finally, the interface or exchange standard. In the case of the research activities of the Natural History Museum in Berkeley, Star and Griesemer identify objects as specimens, field note and maps which are both concrete (material) and abstract (codified, symbolic and a component of categories). Analysis leads these authors to identifying four types of boundary object: • The repository: a set of classified and indexed objects which are grouped in a standardised fashion, such as a library or a collection where heterogeneity can be managed in a modular fashion • The ideal type: a general model which abandons local or singular specificities such as, for example, the notion of species which can be adapted and completed by different participants in the collective action area • Coincident boundaries: referring to objects which share the same boundaries with different internal forms such as the conventional boundaries of a region • The standardized forms: facilitates communication and the grouping of diverse content. The boundary object is “multiple”: abstract and concrete, general and specific, conventional and user-adapted, material and conceptual (a database, a pro- tocol). It is a partial and temporary bridge which is fairly unstructured when used jointly and highly structured when used within one of the worlds involved.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> It has different meanings in the different worlds, but those meanings are sufficiently structured to be recognised by the other. The notion is used to describe how actors maintain their differences and their cooperation, how they manage and restrict variety, how they coordinate in space and time. It qualifies the way in which actors establish and maintain coherence between interacting social worlds, without making them uniform or transparent from one to the other. Actors in these social worlds can, thanks to the boundary object, negotiate their differences and establish agreement on their respective points of view. Revisiting Star and Griesemer from the point of view of the knowledge management and associated communities of actors, Etienne <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Wenger (2000)</xref> specifies that the notion of boundary object can be broken down into four dimensions: • Abstraction: it facilitates dialogue between worlds • Multi-tasking: several activities or practices are possible • Modularity: different parts of the object can serve as a basis for dialogue between actors • Standardisation of the information contained in the object: render- ing the information interpretable. “Multiple translations versus Machiavellian actors: collective work versus fact stabilization”: thus, Joan H. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Fujimura (1992)</xref> differentiates the Star and Griesemer analysis model from that of actor network theory (ANT). First of all, the ecological perspective we refer to above shifts the focal point; it is not just a matter of monitoring the way the innovator gets everyone on board, step- by-step, but reporting more broadly on the work of coordination, alignment mechanisms and translation chains between the different actors and worlds involved. Translation operations are distributed without necessarily establishing the pre-eminence of one actor over the others. Subsequently, whilst Star and Griesemer, like Latour, are interested in the creation of associations, the target of the former is less in retracing the dynamic and uncertain process of “stabilisa- tion of facts” than getting to grips with the mechanism of associations itself and the way in which they tolerate the tension between cooperation and heterogeneity. We would add a third aspect to these two levels of distinction identified by Fujimura: as an analytical tool, the boundary object does not only report on connection processes but also on the weight of inertia affecting communication infrastructures. Transparent and invisible, they can be made visible through shortcomings, changes or tests, in particular during the innovation phase where the boundary object copes with existing architectures. “Infrastructure does not grow de novo; it wrestles with the inertia of installed base and inherits strengths and limitations from that base. Optical fibres run along old railroad lines; new systems are designed for backward-compatibility” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Star, 2007</xref>). The notion of boundary objects itself constitutes a boundary concept, as it seems to emerge at the crossroads of different “sociological worlds”. S. Star looked first at the American tradition of the Chicago School and Symbolic Interactionism. This first affiliation resulted in a whole series of influences in fundamental questioning such as in the author’s theoretical preconceptions:<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> hence the attention given to phenomena of cohabitation and intersection between heterogeneous worlds supported by the urban sociology of Parks 4 or indeed the idea of deploying an “ecological” perspective on situations (the town, work, etc.), attentive to the material component and to the diversity of actors and roles who are stakeholders in that activity. The notions of boundary object and infrastructure supplement the conceptual grammar developed by Hugues, Becker and Strauss (“worlds”, “conventions”, “roles”) focusing on describing interaction processes and cooperation chains. They transport this same attention given to conventions as more-or-less objectified forms of coordination (standards, rules, collective representations) which govern the interaction of all participants during an action. They accompany the project of monitoring actors and reporting on their effective activities and practices, including in terms of the shaping of knowledge, objects and social worlds. But they take it further by proposing not only to think about the existence of “worlds” and communities of practices, but to take into account the heterogeneity of social worlds from the sciences as well as the mechanisms of intersection of those worlds and their articulation within the framework of a coordinated activity. By being deployed in the realms of sociology of sciences and techniques, the conceptual environment in which Star and Griesemer evolve is also that of the emergence of materiality of things (bodies, artefacts, etc.) in the social sciences, in particular under the influence of the works of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Latour (1979, 1987)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Callon (1986)</xref>. With Star and Griesemer, we find this same attention paid to artefacts which are involved in individual collective action, to action vehicles, to material mediations of all sorts and therefore also to objects which are intermediary or boundary objects. The material basis of science is also one of the places from which we can retrace the production of categories, the construction of classifications and the deployment and persistence of standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Griesemer, 1992</xref>).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="27" page="4" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28" page="4" column="1">c</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="5" column="1">d</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="33" page="5" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="6" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="37" page="6" column="1">e</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="7" column="1">f</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="43" page="7" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="48" page="7" column="1">USES OF THE NOTION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" page="7" column="1">Since that time, the notion of boundary objects has enjoyed a vigorous academic career. It is referred to in various disciplines of social sciences, information sciences, management and engineering, and in particular in IT and in the “computer supported cooperative work” (CSCW) world. The notion is sometimes employed in an anecdotal manner to refer to any artefact which is involved in coordination between actors or which is at the boundary of two worlds. It is thereby relieved of its initial conceptual content and its reference to the idea of knowledge infrastructure. The Star and Griesemer article shows the complexity of information processing as well as the strategies adopted by those involved to act jointly even though their per- 4 Parks was already suggesting the role of transport and communications infrastructures as a factor of organisation (Chapoulie, 2001). <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> spectives may partially diverge. This complexity of interactions between social worlds is often forgotten to the benefit of simplified modelisation of the articulation between two worlds via a boundary object. The fact of qualifying an artefact as a boundary object would therefore appear to dispense authors of even marginally-nuanced analysis. All authors who engage in the notion of boundary object do not, however, address it in such a nominalistic manner. A lot of works have used the notion in their investigation of research fields and objects. Others work on the notion, explaining certain aspects of it or developing it to address objects and situations which move away from the seminal work of Star and Griesemer. One of the first to return to the notion was Kathryn Henderson in an an- thropology of the design activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Henderson, 1991, 1998a</xref>). She is particularly interested in visual representations – drawings and diagrams – produced to or- ganise discussions and move collective work forward. These are elements which facilitate the distributed cognitive process because they facilitate the crossover between interpretations held by the different professional groups involved in the design of a turbine. In her work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Henderson, 1998b</xref>), she explores the impact of computer-assisted design tools on visual design culture. The works of Dominique Vinck and Alain Jeantet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Vinck and Jeantet, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Jeantet, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Vinck, 1999</xref>) developed similar conclusions by monitoring intermediary actors and objects (see Vinck’s article in this paper) whose boundary objects form a sub-assembly. These different works were evoked in the ethnographical aspects of design. The works of Kathryn Henderson were re-iterated in particular by Marc <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Berg (1997, 1998)</xref> in his study on working practices in the medical field. He looked at the use of artefacts in work and power games linked to for- malisation tools. He investigated in particular at the case of the computerised medical file. He made the bridge between the works of Susan L. Star and the research fields of Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW) and par- ticipative design (the involvement of users in the design process of technological artefacts). The notion of boundary object was also revisited in the field of the sociology of design and innovation at the end of the 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Aibar and Bijker, 1997</xref>, in urban planning; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R111" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Weedman, 1998</xref>, on the participation of the customer in design; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Harvey and Chrisman, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Chrisman, 1999</xref> and MacEachren, 2001, on the social construction of geographic information systems; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Swan et al, 2002</xref>, on the role of communities of practices in the management of innovation) and then in a major series of works during the second half of the 2000s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Majchrzak et al, 2004</xref>, on the re-use of knowledge in the management of innovation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Hess, 2005</xref>, on the articulation between design and social movements; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Popham, 2005</xref>, on the introduction of forms of communication in the medical world; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Jensen, 2005</xref>, on computerised medical files; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Broom, 2005</xref>, on the impact of the inter- net on the doctor-patient relationship; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Mehalik and Gorman, 2006</xref>, on main- taining adaptive stability of socio-technical networks in the case of the design of a factory; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Hyysalo, 2006</xref>, on the role of imagination linked to professional traditions of designers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Constantinides and Barrett, 2006</xref>, on innovation in the<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> area of information technologies and large-scale communications in the health business; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Prasad, 2007</xref>, concerning the attribution of paternity in the invention of medical imaging by magnetic resonance; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Swan et al, 2007</xref>, on the role of objects in biomedical innovation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Boland et al, 2007</xref>, on the adoption of three- dimensional representation in architectural design; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Faulkner, 2007</xref>, concerning the heterogeneity of professional identities between architects and engineers in the construction field; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Dodgson et al, 2007</xref>, on simulation as a boundary object in a collaborative engineering project; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Van der Poel, 2008</xref>, on competition between professional groups in the design of new industrial facilities in the area of waste-water treatment; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Bruun and Sierla, 2008</xref>, on the distributed character of problem-solving in software development). Some of these works see in the notion of boundary objects the possibility of designing the “desirable” articulation between new social groups (customers, users, patients) or issues (sustainable development) in design processes.<marker type="block"/> Paul <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (2002, 2004)</xref> is one of the authors who was to revisit most wholeheartedly the notion of boundary object within the framework of organisation theory where he promotes a pragmatic approach, in particular in the case of the study of the processes of new product development. He seeks to shed light on the nature of knowledge produced and the boundaries which result. He distinguishes three registers of dialogue and cooperation between actors: syntax for formats and terminology; semantics for inter-understanding and mutual learning; and pragmatism, designed also to look at the development of knowledge, practices and beliefs. Attentive to concrete and localised knowledge and development practices, he emphasises the problem of boundaries which are thrown up in the area of knowledge. These boundaries can be represented and transformed by a boundary object which contributes to their differentiation and integration. The management of knowledge at the boundary would thereby entail three types of activity: • Transfer: management of formats (pipes, syntax, management of information, etc.). It corresponds to situations where the relationship is stable and where there is a shared repertoire • Translation: when it is impossible to forecast or there is change, or meanings cannot be determined (unknown, ambiguous or different); when there is interactivity (mediation, joint activity, etc.). The result is translation from one register to another, explanation and confrontation of points of view, construction of acceptable compro- mises and shared visions. The boundary object thereby becomes a “cognitive” mediator; it constitutes a transaction zone for the perspectives in attendance • Transformation: when the interests of actors diverge, there is negotiation of interests and knowledge, and construction of a compro- mise. At this point, the boundary object becomes a “social” mediator where there are issues of power and allegiances, exchanges of contributions and identity.<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> Some works, and in particular those concerning design, developed from the 2000s onwards in the field of work situation analysis and design. This was the case in particular of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Damarin (2006)</xref>, on the flexibility and structure of employ- ment in the production of websites, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Thurk and Fine (2003)</xref> on the issue of tools and the sharing of knowledge, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Bechky, 2003</xref>, on the transformation of working communities and their understanding of production processes in a production workshop. A second research field drew on the notion of boundary object from the beginning of the 1990s and in a relatively continuous manner to the present day, with, however, a peak during the second half of the 2000s with the sociology of sciences. Joan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Fujimura (1992)</xref>, who, as Susan L. Star was from the world of symbolic interactionism, shows in the case of research into cancer that cancer is a boundary object which facilitates multiple translations between the different social worlds involved (and in particular between doctors and biologists). The notion is often revisited to address scientific exchanges and collaborations: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Myers, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Wasser and Bresler, 1996</xref>, concerning interpretation zones in qualitative research; Nutch, 1996, concerning instruments; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Myers, 1996</xref>, on scientific writ- ing; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Derksen, 1997</xref>, on rhetorical demarcation in psychology; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Gunnarsdottir, 2005</xref>, on the circulation of pre-publications in the scientific world; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Akkerman et al, 2006</xref>, on learning within international scientific collaborative projects; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Milanovic, 2006</xref>, on the notion of boundary organisation in urban research; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Nersessian, 2006</xref>, on the cognitive and cultural system of a research laboratory; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Sundberg, 2007</xref>, on the relationships between researchers and modelisers in the configuration of metrological models; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Almklov, 2008</xref>, on the standardisation of data and their collaborative use by geologists and engineers working on highly singular situations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R114" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Wilson and Herndl (2007)</xref>, concerning interdisciplinary cooperation within the Los Alamos National Laboratory, reinterpret the notion of boundary objects to make it a rhetorical construction (knowledge maps) which facilitates communication between heterogeneous groups. These maps replace the habitual work of demarcation and create temporary negotiation and inter-comprehension buffer zones. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Evans (2009)</xref> also shows the benefits of the boundary object notion concerning disciplinary boundary construction processes which he studied within the framework of American sociology. It is also present when analysing the articulation between scientific actors and society’s other actors: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Kleinman, 1998</xref>, on the links between a laboratory and the market; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Lee and Roth, 2003</xref>, on links with the citizen; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Kelly, 2003</xref>, on public bioethics bodies as a boundary organisation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Cash et al, 2006</xref>, on the co-production of knowledge between researchers and decision-makers in the case of the El Niño forecasting system; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Saj et al, 2006</xref>, on the articulation between founding myths in African villages and the conservation agenda for two primate species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Cassidy, 2006</xref>, on public debate allowing scientific boundaries to be overcome in the case of popular evolutionist psychology. The notion is also reviewed in the area of scientific communications (public understanding of science), and in particular: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="108" class="deo:Reference">Ratto, 2006</xref>, on the use of metaphors in communica-<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> tions with the public in the area of genetic databases; Prior, 2007, concerning inter-comprehension between doctors and patients concerning cancer genetics; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Marres, 2007</xref>, on the involvement of the public in scientific controversies; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Lopez, 2007</xref>, on metaphorical communications on the genome; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Soneryd, 2007</xref>, on the management of controversies concerning new generations of mobile phones; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Shostak, 2007</xref>, concerning relationships between researchers, risk as- sessors and regulators on the subject of genetically modified mice; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Marie, 2008</xref>, concerning research in the area of species improvement (hens and rabbits). Other works engage the notion to explore the reconfiguration of objects and actors involved in research activities: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="117" class="deo:Reference">DeNora, 1996</xref>, on fertility control; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="118" class="deo:Reference">Shackley and Wynner, 1996</xref>, on the formation of boundaries in the area of sciences and policies concerning climate change; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Moore and Clarke, 2001</xref>, on issues of sex and gender; Prentice, 2005, concerning simulation of surgical operations where he reports on the way in which different professions are articulated; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Kwa, 2005</xref>, on the construction of an international biosphere and geosphere programme; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Glasner, 2005</xref>, explores the logistical chain from stem cells to their therapeutic use; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Sommerlund, 2006</xref>, on the coexistence of two classification systems of micro-organisms and tensions thereby generated; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Sommer, 2006</xref>, on Neanderthal as image and ‘distortion’; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Moreira, 2006</xref>, on the coexistence of two methods to measure blood pressure in neurosurgery, their interdepend- ence and mutual parasitism; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Mondada, 2007</xref>, on the practice of transcribing speeches; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Henke, 2007</xref>, on ecology. Law and Singleton (2005), on the treatment of an alcoholic liver, engage with the notion to demonstrate the complexity of the object such as designed in the STS field. They retain three approaches to the object seen as a region, a network or a fluid and suggest a fourth, fire, which addresses the discontinuity between the presence and absence of an object. A third major research field has addressed the notion of boundary objects to elucidate the subject of its enquiries: the organisation theory, including questions of organisational change, organisational learning and knowledge management. In these areas, the use of the notion comes latterly, generally at least 10 years after its publication. Amongst the first authors in the field to give visibility to this notion, the works of Etienne <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Wenger (2000)</xref> on communities of practice and the article by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Barley and Kunda (2001)</xref> which pleaded for the enrichment of organisation theory through detailed studies of work activities, are of note. Subsequent works focused on: • Issues of organisational learning: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Davenport and Bruce (2002)</xref> concerning links between the use of space and knowledge management; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Berends et al (2003)</xref> on the structuring of organisational learning; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Sydow et al (2004)</xref> on the links between project-based organisations and knowledge repertoires; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Im and Rai (2008)</xref> on the ambidextrous nature of learning in inter-organisational relationships. • Coordination within and between organisations: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R113" id="133" class="deo:Reference">White and Bradshaw (2004)</xref> on industrial logistics; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Faraj and Xiao (2006)</xref> on coordination in reactive organisations; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Kellogg et al (2006)</xref> on the<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> structuring of coordination beyond the boundaries of bureaucratic organisations; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="139" class="deo:Reference">Denis et al (2007)</xref> on pluralistic organisations. • Internal dynamics and organisational culture: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Burman (2004)</xref> on psy- cho-dynamic analysis of social groups; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Neyland (2007)</xref> on the production of a form of transparency of work in organisations; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="142" class="deo:Reference">Morrill (2008)</xref> on organisational culture; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92" id="143" class="deo:Reference">Simpson and Carroll (2008)</xref> on the notion of the role of boundary object in identity construction; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Zeiss and Groenewegen (2009)</xref> on the contribution of boundary objects to the study of organisations and management; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Schneider (2009)</xref> on the benefits of boundary organisations. • Organisational innovation: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Locke and Lowe (2007)</xref> on the introduction of ERPs in companies and the associated organisational changes in the form of a biographical accumulation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Barreteau et al (2007)</xref> on the use of simulation and games in the collective management of natural resources; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Bartel and Garud (2009)</xref> on the role of narrative in organisational innovation. The notion of boundary object is also revisited in areas such as teaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Cobb et al, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Anagnostopoulos et al, 2007</xref>, concerning the discrepancy between learning and teaching at <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R116" id="151" class="deo:Reference">University and teaching practices in front of students; Kazemi and Hubbard, 2008</xref>, on the role of artefacts in the learning of mathematics) and learning in relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87" id="152" class="deo:Reference">Ribeiro, 2007</xref>, on the work of an interpreter (Japanese to Portuguese) in the industrial field; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Handley et al, 2007</xref>, on learning in a relationship between customer and consultant). Recently, in political science literature (Halphon, 2006, on the construction of global political consensuses concerning the 1994 Cairo Conference on Population; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="154" class="deo:Reference">Hunter, 2008</xref>, on the analysis of multiple social relationships (in particular resistance and domination) established through a policy document; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="155" class="deo:Reference">Andrews et al; 2008, on deliberations on energy policy objectives; Barnett, 2008</xref>, concerning articulations between peace and development; Keller, 2008, on the pertinence and credibility of environmental policies) as well as in economic sociology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="156" class="deo:Reference">Callon, 1994</xref>, concerning the public nature of scientific production; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="157" class="deo:Reference">Jensen, 2008</xref>, concerning links between free market economics and donation economics; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="158" class="deo:Reference">Ebeling, 2008</xref>, concerning communications on financial potential and risks linked to nano-technology; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Cochoy, 2009</xref>, on the benefits of the symmetrical approach of economic actors). In the works referred to, the notion is sometimes articulated with others which gravitate around the issue of boundaries; boundary work (Gieryn), boundary negotiation and shifting boundaries (Callon), boundary blurring (transgression), boundary spanning (contacts outside the group, sharing and knowledge), bounda- ry-spanning individual and boundary organisation. Besides the few authors to whom we have given slightly more exposure, others have used the notion especially for descriptive, explanatory or even nor- mative reasons. Sometimes moving away from what the notion means from the implicit standardisation point of view, they have used it as a translation vehicle<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> between heterogeneous worlds. In the end, the notion describes any interface mechanism between knowledge or actors. It seems to have lost its original analytical momentum, i.e. the fact that certain objects or configurations – or even organisations – materialise and transport an invisible infrastructure made up of standards, categories, classifications and conventions that are specific to one or more social worlds.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50" page="8" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="51" page="8" column="1">g</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="72" page="9" column="1">h</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="73" page="9" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="84" page="10" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="85" page="10" column="1">i</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="11" column="1">j</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="111" page="11" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="137" page="12" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="138" page="12" column="1">k</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="161" page="13" column="1">l</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="162" page="13" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="164" page="13" column="1">THE CONCEPTUAL INFRASTRUCTURE OF THE BOUNDARY OBJET</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" page="13" column="1">“Interpretive flexibility without understanding of infrastructure, information needs, standards and classification is a misunderstanding” ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Star, 2007</xref>) 5 . This (re)inscription of the initial concept of boundary object in a broader range of concepts which specifically describe cooperation processes finds an echo in the way in which Star deploys it in her research work. Looking at the scientific progression of the author after this founding article of 1989, one quickly observes that the boundary object is more annexed to the initial, major issue of the role of infrastructures in communities of practices and in coordination between heterogeneous worlds. Particular interest is paid to information infrastructures, those through which individuals and groups manage knowledge: the historical construction of taxonomies and classifications in sciences or in leading public organisations (World Health Organisation), the production of position profiles in work activities (nurse), the impact of information systems on organisations, the production of categorisations (race, disease) and new knowledge management tools (NICTs), are some of the major works of the research programme that Susan L. Star is pursuing, with Geoffroy Bowker in particular. In it she deploys an ethnography which is sensitive to the way in which individuals and groups produce and manage information, including the activity’s material basis as the central mediation in the construction of knowledge. From this point of view, S. Star’s concern is substantially different – although not radically so – from a whole series of works which, along the lines of ANT, describe the genesis of innovations, the stabilisation of sociotechnical networks and the construction of translation chains which wind and unwind through the work of innovator(s). The attention given to communities’ physical and symbolic frames and the way in which they are built up as an invisible foundation to action, describes a more historical and temporal movement. From the analysis of scientific exchanges to that of innovation in information systems via and study of the compilation of a database within major public organisations (WHO), the ethnography of infrastructures builds on past elements (the construction, stabilisation<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> or on the contrary, disappearance of categorisation modes), and combines with a detailed interpretation of the way in which classifications then perform courses of action in an invisible manner. The perspective is similar to the pragmatic sociology of coordinated action, putting this essential mechanism which constitutes classification at its heart: personal classification of the researcher or of the PC (familiarity regime), to the categorisations and classifications which are shared by communities of practices or their intersection, without excluding the political and ethical dimension of infrastructures. In the grammar of coordination within the universes of action and distributed knowledge, infrastructures, standards, classifications and boundary objects appear in their relational properties, operating both as mediators in the production of knowledge and as vectors of translation in the organisation of heterogeneous worlds. The infrastructure and associated concepts thus describe the vital lead of a research programme which is deployed through the accumulation of empirical works. Beyond the identification of coordination mechanisms (classification, standards, norms), the idea is to document the way in which they are engaged, manipulated, negotiated and activated, whilst taking into account coordination constraints which are not necessarily dissociated from them. The distinction operated by Star and Strauss between “coordination work” and “articulation work” describes the potentially incomplete nature of this “pooling”, for which the actors involved in the alignment work may have to take responsibility with varying degrees of visibility in a dynamic and recurrent manner. Following this same perspective, the description of the fabric and role of these “formats” of common action, becomes, in the works of Star, a reading of what they make invisible: silencing non-categorised actors, forcing similari- ties into a standardised category, making what is not “accountable” inappro- priate for knowledge, as is the case of the silent work of infrastructures. It is then through irregularities, excesses, tensions faced with the challenges that the researcher is able to track them down. This analytical posture, which is attentive to the formatting and conditioning operated by classification operations, fundamentally refers to a methodological principle in Star’s interpretation: “the strength of fieldwork is its anthropological strangeness” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="171" class="deo:Reference">Star, 2007</xref>).</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="168" page="13" column="1">5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Star, Grenoble Conference, 2007</xref>.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="169" page="14" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="170" page="14" column="1">m</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="173" page="14" column="1">THE CONTENT OF THIS ISSUE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="186" page="14" column="1">We will open this collection by returning to one of the root sites of the notion of boundary objects, since the article by Céline Granjou and Isabelle Mauz (When the identity of the boundary object strikes its own course: the case of estimating the wolf population in France), transports us directly to the field of ecology and the coordination of scientific actors in the production of knowledge. The shared horizon here is dedicated to the production of scientific expertise based on environmental management issues, which echoes the renewal of the challenges <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> which scientific activity faces today in its involvement in the management of controversies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Callon, Lascoumes, Barthes, 2001</xref>). By following the different scientific knowledge production sequences step-by-step, the authors observe in detail the way in which certain common objects are manipulated at the intersection of the worlds. In place of birds and other natural species which contribute to the collection of natural science information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96" id="178" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer, 1989</xref>), here we are working with the wolf or rather the hairs and other natural fragments gath- ered as evidence of its presence in the Mercantour Mountains. From collection to genetic identification via probabilistic estimation, they describe first of all the different actors involved in the expert science unit working on nature management. They then take us through the reconstruction of the evidence-processing chain (hairs, excrement, etc.). Analysis shows how, through these associations to heterogeneous scientific domains, the presence index of the wolf has new qualities translated through codes and indicators attached to it. These succes- sive re-qualifications of the object characterise one of the central properties of the boundary objects i.e. its “multiplicity” (Star and Bowker, 2000). Thinking of the equipment as one of the properties of the boundary object through which the articulation to infrastructures is described is indeed another of the extensions proposed by D. Vinck (From the intermediary object to the boundary object. Moving towards the accountability of “equipment work”). As a counterpoint to this return to the notion of boundary object, he proposes more precise qualification of the properties of the “intermediary object”, a similar and often closely-attached or even embedded in the former in STS work. Through this retrospective look at the career of the concept in his own works (extended to include those of the research group around him), we see the contours of a concept which serve primarily to describe and monitor design and innovation activity through the multiplicity of intermediate “inscriptions” of the object which circulate and support collective work. What is of interest to D. Vinck and his colleagues is more the reconstitution of processes through which the pro- gressive stabilisation of facts in design or in science are constructed; hence the advantage of not distinguishing objects which circulate inside worlds from those found at the intersection, nor through registrations which have an ephemeral or incomplete status (rough), around which heterogeneous knowledge will be articulated. The scope of the intermediary object is in “mediation” rather than in articulation, in its capacity to perform the course of action rather than serve as a frame to the coordination work. This conceptual clarification clearly shows that it is around the incorporation or association with conventional supports that the conceptual meaning of the boundary object is constructed. D. Vinck then suggests that the equipment work could be the key allowing us to under- stand what is common to the intermediary objects and boundary objects of Star and Griesemer. The article by G. Tétart and D. Torny (“Sometimes it kills but it’s not danger- ous”: institutional injunction and scientific mobilisation around an emerging pathogen, Bacillus cereus) documents the setting up of a scientific programme as a vector<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> of new convergences between researchers who are initially relatively far apart, even though they are working in the same disciplinary field. The setting up of an ANR project describes the “pragmatic coming together between funda- mentalists of molecular biology and specialists of microbiological risk (applied research) around emerging biological risk incarnated by a pathogenic bacteria, the Bacillus cereus. The authors describe a whole series of investments through which we see this research group of unlikely members moving towards a “cred- ible project”: the article describes the chains of translation, the work of alignment and the operations of mediation which progressively lead to the stabilisation of this hitherto unknown scientific assembly. By then exploring an avenue already well trodden by numerous works on the sociology of innovation and the sociology of sciences, the analysis sheds particularly original light on the subject. First of all, it suggests a symmetrical treatment by the sociologists, through the reflective demonstration of their own translation and conformation activities affecting scientific arguments working towards a common project. Then not only do they look at the creation of alignments, but beyond that, at alignments “that survive the course”. Through the “pragmatism of likelihood”, the authors show that Bacillus cereus is not just “a good” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="182" class="deo:Reference">Latour, 1992</xref>), but is or becomes, as the programme unfolds, a collective construction of an emerging risk, an en- semble of distributed and exchanged collections, one or several hotly-debated taxonomic categories, i.e. a shared reference set. They demonstrate a sort of “virtuous circle” of translation work, in which initially relatively opportunistic alliances and rhetorical activities give a very novel opening to new qualifications and investigations: thus, from this boundary qualification of Bacillus therus, as an “emerging risk” which is propitious to new modelisations which can benefit from agro-foods expertise in a precautionary system. The article by Martin Rémondet (Boundary Objects on Trial: the trajectory of a group built around the DICS-X genetic therapy trials) addresses this same issue of the setting up of research collectives as part of new scientific convergences, in this case in the development of genetic therapy at the crossroads between molecular biology and biomedicine. As with the previous case, the object reveals a whole series of challenges which traverse the scientific field: the question of coordination does not or no longer only engages the issue of the association between researchers and disciplines or that of the delegation of work to amateurs, but also the integration of “concerned groups” (patient associations) and the “publicisation” of science. This case, which is subject to an empirical and detailed description and describes to us a singular end game is full of learning: first of all, through the trials and tribulations involved in the death of a patient which brings an end to clinical trials; subsequently, with the negotiation of this “crisis” by the collectivity, driven forward by this “undesirable event” in a process of justification; and finally, concerning the alliance and mobilisation of all actors, and in particular the “novice” in an understanding of the irreducibility of scientific uncertainty; an exemplary case of solidarity of a hybrid group in an arena which is both scientific and public, in place of controversies we are more used to seeing them immersed in.<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> Finally, this issue will end with the return to the Natural History Museum under the pen of Morgan Meyer (“Boundary object” or “boundary project”? Construction, (non)-utilisation and database policy). With a historical leap forward of a century and a geographical one of several thousand kilometres, we find scientists and amateurs working in a distributed manner on the setting up of a database. We can but enthuse for the fertile nature of this revisited terrain, an enterprise which is far too rare in human sciences. The description depicts innumerable micro-negotiations which milestone the setting up of a database. Certain alignment constraints immediately look like infrastructure conflicts as described by Star and Bowker: they concern IT systems in particular, which require more distribution, devolution, and personalisation to be maintained as conventional supports to coordination. However, the author also identifies other points of discord or tension: the political and sociological dimension of ownership around this collective possession which is knowledge, or indeed the invisible work of the amateur and the problem of his or her compensation. He defines a increasingly hybrid and collective representation of the amateur in the technical equipment that he / she has to integrate in order to comply with the expectations of scientists in the delegation process. Finally, the article reminds us that through the boundary object concept, Star and Griesemer were more fundamentally defending a distributed perspective which is able to account for the “non-alignment” of its actors (Akrich, 2007). As a supplement to this issue, Antoine Doré presents the work published under the direction of François Mélard in 2008. It shows the benefit of notions of objects and intermediary concepts used to clarify collective environmental action. In particular, it is situated in relation to the diversity of concepts forged in the social sciences to address objects in actions. Thus ends this first “return” to the notion of boundary object, with a collection of particularly significant texts representing the embedding of this concept in the sociology of sciences and techniques. The Revue d’Anthropologie des Connaissances should shortly be publishing a second special issue addressing the “return to the notion of boundary object”.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="175" page="15" column="1">n</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="176" page="15" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="16" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="181" page="16" column="1">o</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="184" page="17" column="1">p</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="185" page="17" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="187" page="17" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="17" column="1">Aibar E., Bijker W. (1997), “Constructing a City: The Cerda Plan for the Extension of Barcelona”, Science Technology Human Values, 22(1): 3-30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="17" column="1">Akkerman S., Admiraal W., Simons R. J., Niessen T. (2006), “Considering Diversity: Multivoicedness in International Academic Collaboration”, Culture Psychology, 12(4): 461-</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">485. Almklov P. G. (2008),” Standardized Data and Singular Situations”, Social Studies of Science, 38(6): 873-897.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="17" column="1">Anagnostopoulos D., Smith E. R., Basmadjian K. G. (2007), “Bridging the University- School Divide: Horizontal Expertise and the ‘Two-Worlds Pitfall’”, Journal of Teacher Education, 58(2): 138-152.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="18" column="1">Andrews C., Jonas H. C., Mantell N., Solomon R. (2008), “Deliberating on Statewide</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Energy Targets”, Journal of Planning Education and Research, 28(1): 6-20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="18" column="1">Barley S. R., Kunda G. (2001), B”ringing Work Back In Organization”, Science, 12(1):</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">76-95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="18" column="1">Barnett J. (2008), “Peace and Development: Towards a New Synthesis”, Journal of Peace Research, 45(1): 75-89.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="18" column="1">Barreteau O., Le Page C., Perez P. (2007), “Contribution of simulation and gaming to natural resource management issues: An introduction”, Simulation Gaming, 38(2): 185-194.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="18" column="1">Bartel C. A., Garud R. (2009), “The Role of Narratives in Sustaining Organizational Innovation”, Organization Science, 20(1): 107-117.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bechky B. A. (2003), Sharing Meaning Across Occupational Communities: The</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Transformation of Understanding on a Production Floor, Organization Science, 14(3): 312-330.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="18" column="1">Berends H., Boersma K., Weggeman M. (2003), “The Structuration of Organizational</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Learning”, Human Relations, 56(9): 1035-1056.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Berg M. (1997), “Of Forms, Containers, and the Electronic Medical Record: Some Tools</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">for a Sociology of the Formal”, Science, Technology &amp; Human Values, 22(4), p. 403-433. Berg M. (1998), “The Politics of Technology: On Bringing Social Theory into Technological</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Design”, Science Technology Human Values, 23(4): 456-490.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="18" column="1">Boland R. J., Lyytinen K., Yoo Y. (2007), “Wakes of Innovation in Project Networks: The Case of Digital 3-D Representations in Architecture, Engineering, and Construction”, Organization Science, 18(4): 631-647.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Broom A. (2005), “Medical specialists’ accounts of the impact of the Internet on the doctor/patient relationship”, Health, 9(3): 319-338.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="18" column="1">Bruun H., Sierla S. (2008), “Distributed Problem Solving in Software Development: The</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Case of an Automation Project”, Social Studies of Science, 38(1): 133-158.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" page="18" column="1">Burman E. (2004), “Boundary Objects and Group Analysis: Between Psychoanalysis and Social Theory”, Group Analysis, 37(3): 361-379.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" page="18" column="1">Callon M. (1986), « Éléments pour une sociologie de la traduction. La domestication des</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="18" column="1">coquilles Saint-Jacques et des marins-pêcheurs dans la baie de Saint-Brieuc », L’année sociologique. (36), p. 169-208.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="18" column="1">Callon M. (1994), “Is Science a Public Good? Fifth Mullins Lecture”, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 23 March 1993, Science Technology Human Values, 19(4), p. 395-424.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="18" column="1">Callon M., Lascoumes P., Barthes Y., Agir dans un monde incertain. Essai sur la démocratie technique, Paris, Seuil, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="18" column="1">Carlile P. (2002), “A Pragmatic View of Knowledge and Boundaries: Boundary Objects in</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">New Product Development”, Organization science, 13 (4), p. 442-455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="18" column="1">Carlile P. (2004), “Transferring, Translating, and Transforming: An Integrative Framework</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">for Managing Knowledge Across Boundaries”, Organization science, 15(5), p. 555-568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" page="18" column="1">Cash D. W., Borck J. C., Patt A. G. (2006), “Countering the Loading-Dock Approach to Linking Science and Decision Making: Comparative Analysis of El Nino/Southern Oscillation</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="18" column="1">(ENSO) Forecasting Systems”, Science Technology Human Values, 31(4): 465-494.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="18" column="1">Cassidy A. (2006), “Evolutionary psychology as public science and boundary work”, Public Understanding of Science, 15(2): 175-205. Chapoulie J. M. (2001), La tradition sociologique de Chicago 1892-1961, Paris, Seuil.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" page="18" column="1">Chrisman N. (1999), Trading Zones or Boundary Objects: Understanding Incomplete Translations of Technical Expertise. Paper presented at the Presented at Society for Social Studies of Science Annual Meeeting, 1999, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://faculty.washington.edu/chrisman/" id="224">http://faculty.washington.edu/chrisman/</ext-link> Present/4S99.pdf, p. 28-31.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="18" column="1">Cobb P., McClain K., de Silva Lamberg T., Dean C. (2003), “Situating Teachers’ Instructional Practices in the Institutional Setting of the School and District”, Educational Researcher, 32(6): 13-24. <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> Cochoy F. (2009), “Driving a Shopping Cart from STS to Business, and the Other Way Round: On the Introduction of Shopping Carts in American Grocery Stores (1936-- 1959)”, Organization, 16(1): 31-55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" page="19" column="1">Constantinides P., Barrett M. (2006), “Large-Scale ICT Innovation, Power, and Organizational Change: The Case of a Regional Health Information Network”, Journal of Applied Behavioral Science, 42(1): 76-90.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Damarin A. K., (2006), “Rethinking Occupational Structure: The Case of Web Site Production Work”, Work and Occupations, 33(4): 429-463.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" page="19" column="1">Davenport E., Bruce I. (2002), “Innovation, knowledge management and the use of space: questioning assumptions about non-traditional office work”, Journal of Information Science, 28(3): 225-230.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" page="19" column="1">Denis J.-L., Langley A., Rouleau L. (2007), “Strategizing in pluralistic contexts: Rethinking</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">theoretical frames”, Human Relations, 60(1): 179-215. DeNora T. (1996), “From Physiology to Feminism: Reconfiguring body, gender and</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">expertise in natural fertility control”, International Sociology, 11(3), p. 359-383.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" page="19" column="1">Derksen M. (1997), “Are We not Experimenting then?: The Rhetorical Demarcation of</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Psychology and Common Sense Theory”, Psychology, 7(4): 435-456.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" page="19" column="1">Dodgson M., Gann D. M., Salter A. (2007), “‘In Case of Fire, Please Use the Elevator’: Simulation Technology and Organization in Fire Engineering”, Organization Science, 18(5): 849-864.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" page="19" column="1">Ebeling M. F. E. (2008), “Mediating Uncertainty: Communicating the Financial Risks of</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Nanotechnologies”, Science Communication, 29(3): 335-361.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" page="19" column="1">Epstein S. (1995), “The Construction of Lay Expertise: AIDS Activism and the Forging</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">of Credibility in the Reform of Clinical Trials”, Science Technology Human Values, 20(4), p. 408-437.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" page="19" column="1">Evans M. S. (2009), “Defining the public, defining sociology: hybrid science--public relations and boundary-work in early American sociology”, Public Understanding of Science, 18(1):</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">5-22.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" page="19" column="1">Faraj S., Xiao Y. (2006), “Coordination in Fast-Response Organizations”, Management Science, 52(8): 1155-1169.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" page="19" column="1">Faulkner W. (2007), “‘Nuts and Bolts and People’: Gender-Troubled Engineering</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Identities”, Social Studies of Science, 37(3): 331-356.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" page="19" column="1">Fujimura J. (1992), “Crafting Science: Standardized Packages, Boundary Objects, and</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" page="19" column="1">‘Translation’”, p. 168-211, in Pickering A. (ed.), Science as Practice and Culture, Chicago, University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" page="19" column="1">Glasner P. (2005), “Banking on Immortality? Exploring the Stem Cell Supply Chain from Embryo to Therapeutic Application”, Current Sociology, 53(2): 355-366.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" page="19" column="1">Griesemer J. R. (1992), “The Role of Instruments in the Generative Analysis of Science”, p. 47-76, in A. Clarke and J. Fujimura (eds.), The Right Tools for the Job: At Work in Twentieth Century Life Sciences, Princeton, Princeton University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="252" page="19" column="1">Gunnarsdottir K. (2005), “Scientific Journal Publications: On the Role of Electronic</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="253" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Preprint Exchange in the Distribution of Scientific Literature”, Social Studies of Science, 35(4): 549-579.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="254" page="19" column="1">Halfon S. (2006), “The Disunity of Consensus: International Population Policy Coordination as Socio-Technical Practice”, Social Studies of Science, 36(5): 783-807.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="255" page="19" column="1">Handley K., Clark T., Fincham R., Sturdy A. (2007), “Researching Situated Learning: Participation, Identity and Practices in Client-Consultant Relationships”, Management Learning, 38(2): 173-191.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="259" page="19" column="1">Harvey F., Chrisman N. (1998), “Boundary objects and the social construction of GIS technology”, Environment and Planning A, 30, p. 1683-1694. Henderson K. (1991), “Flexible Sketches and Inflexible Data Bases: Visual Communication, Conscription Devices, and Boundary Objects in Design Engineering”, Science Technology Human Values, 16(4), p. 448-473. <marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> Henderson K. (1998a), “The Role of Material Objects in the Design Process: A Comparison of Two Design Cultures and How They Contend with Automation”, Science Technology Human Values, 23(2): 139-174.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="260" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Henderson K. (1998b), On Line and on Paper: Visual Representations, Visual Culture, and Computer Graphics in Design Engineering, MIT Press Cambridge, MA, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="261" page="20" column="1">Henke C. R. (2007), “Situation Normal? Repairing a Risky Ecology”, Social Studies of Science, 37(1): 135-142.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="262" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Hess D. J. (2005), “Technology- and Product-Oriented Movements: Approximating Social Movement Studies and Science and Technology Studies”, Science Technology Human Values, 30(4): 515-535.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="263" page="20" column="1">Hunter S. (2008), “Living documents: A feminist psychosocial approach to the relational</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="264" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">politics of policy documentation”, Critical Social Policy, 28(4): 506-528.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="265" page="20" column="1">Hyysalo S. (2006), “Representations of Use and Practice-Bound Imaginaries in Automating</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="266" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">the Safety of the Elderly”, Social Studies of Science, 36(4): 599-626.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="267" page="20" column="1">Im G., Rai A. (2008), “Knowledge Sharing Ambidexterity in Long-Term Interorganizational Relationships”, Management Science, 54(7): 1281-1296.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="268" page="20" column="1">Jeantet A. (1998), « Les objets intermédiaires dans les processus de conception des</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="269" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">produits », Sociologie du travail, (3), p. 291-316.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="270" page="20" column="1">Jensen C. B. (2005), “An Experiment in Performative History:: Electronic Patient Records</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="271" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">as a Future-Generating Device”, Social Studies of Science, 35(2): 241-267.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="272" page="20" column="1">Jensen T. E. (2008), “Experimenting with Commodities and Gifts: The Case of an Office Hotel”, Organization, 15(2): 187-209.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="273" page="20" column="1">Kazemi E., Hubbard A. (2008), “New Directions for the Design and Study of Professional Development: Attending to the Coevolution of Teachers’ Participation Across Contexts”, Journal of Teacher Education, 59(5): 428-441.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="274" page="20" column="1">Keller A. C. (2009), “Credibility and Relevance in Environmental Policy: Measuring</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="275" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Strategies and Performance among Science Assessment Organizations”, J. Public Adm. Res. Theory, February 16, 2009.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="276" page="20" column="1">Kellogg K. C., Orlikowski W. J., Yates J. (2006), “Life in the Trading Zone: Structuring Coordination Across Boundaries in Postbureaucratic Organizations”, Organization Science, 17(1): 22-44.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="277" page="20" column="1">Kelly S. E. (2003), “Public Bioethics and Publics: Consensus, Boundaries, and Participation</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="278" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">in Biomedical Science Policy”, Science Technology Human Values, 28(3): 339-364.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="279" page="20" column="1">Kleinman D. L. (1998), “Untangling Context: Understanding a University Laboratory in the Commercial World”, Science Technology Human Values, 23(3): 285-314.</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="280" page="20" column="1">Kwa C. (2005), “Local Ecologies and Global Science: Discourses and Strategies of the International Geosphere-Biosphere Programme”, Social Studies of Science, 35(6): 923- 950.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="281" page="20" column="1">Latour B. (1987), Science in action: how to follow scientists and engineers through society. Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="282" page="20" column="1">Latour B. (1992), Aramis ou l’amour des techniques, Paris, La Découverte.</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="283" page="20" column="1">Latour B., Woolgar S. (1979), Laboratory life: the social construction of scientific facts. Beverly Hills, Sage Publications. Law J., Singleton V. (2005), “Object Lessons”, Organization, 12(3): 331-355.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="284" page="20" column="1">Lee S., Roth W.-M. (2003), “Science and the ‘Good Citizen’: Community-Based Scientific Literacy”, Science Technology Human Values, 28(3): 403-424.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="285" page="20" column="1">Locke J., Lowe A. (2007), “A Biography: Fabrications in the Life of an ERP Package”, Organization, 14(6): 793-814.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="286" page="20" column="1">Lopez J. J. (2007), “Notes on Metaphors, Notes as Metaphors: The Genome as Musical Spectacle”, Science Communication, 29(1): 7-34. MacEachren A. M. (2001), “Cartography and GIS: extending collaborative tools to support virtual teams”, Progress in Human Geography, 25(3): 431-444.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="289" page="21" column="1">Majchrzak A., Cooper L. P., Neece O. E. (2004), “Knowledge Reuse for Innovation”, Management Science, 50(2): 174-188.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="290" page="21" column="1">Marie J. (2008), “For Science, Love and Money: The Social Worlds of Poultry and Rabbit Breeding in Britain, 1900-1940,” Social Studies of Science, 38(6): 919-936.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="291" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Study of Public Involvement in Controversy”, Social Studies of Science, 37(5): 759-780.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="292" page="21" column="1">Marres N. (2007), “The Issues Deserve More Credit: Pragmatist Contributions to the</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="293" page="21" column="1">Mehalik M., Gorman M. (2006), “A Framework for Strategic Network Design Assessment,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="294" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Decision Making, and Moral Imagination”, Science Technology Human Values, 31(3): 289- 308.</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="295" page="21" column="1">Milanovic F. (2006), « Travail d’articulation et organisations-frontières dans la recherche urbaine française », Social Science Information, 45(1): 109-138.</ref>
          <ref rid="R76" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="296" page="21" column="1">Mondada L. (2007), “Commentary: transcript variations and the indexicality of transcribing practices”, Discourse Studies, 9(6): 809-821.</ref>
          <ref rid="R77" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="297" page="21" column="1">Moore L. J., Clarke A. E. (2001), “The Traffic in Cyberanatomies: Sex/Gender/Sexualities in Local and Global Formations”, Body and Society, 7(1): 57-96.</ref>
          <ref rid="R78" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="298" page="21" column="1">Moreira T. (2006), “Heterogeneity and Coordination of Blood Pressure in Neurosurgery”, Social Studies of Science, 36(1): 69-97.</ref>
          <ref rid="R79" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="299" page="21" column="1">Morrill C. (2008), “Culture and Organization Theory”, The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 619(1): 15-40.</ref>
          <ref rid="R80" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="300" page="21" column="1">Myers G. (1993), “Centering: Proposals for an Interdisciplinary Research Center”, Science Technology Human Values, 18(4), p. 433-459.</ref>
          <ref rid="R81" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="301" page="21" column="1">Myers G. (1996), “Out of the Laboratory and Down to the Bay: Writing in Science and Technology Studies”, Written Communication, 13(1), p. 5-43.</ref>
          <ref rid="R82" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="302" page="21" column="1">Nersessian N. J. (2006), “The Cognitive-Cultural Systems of the Research Laboratory”, Organization Studies, 27(1): 125-145.</ref>
          <ref rid="R83" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="303" page="21" column="1">Neyland D. (2007), “Achieving Transparency: The Visible, Invisible and Divisible in Academic Accountability Networks”, Organization, 14(4): 499-516. Nutch F. (1996), “Gadgets, Gizmos, and Instruments: Science for the Tinkering”, Science Technology Human Values, 21(2), p. 214-228.</ref>
          <ref rid="R84" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="304" page="21" column="1">Popham S. L. (2005), “Forms as Boundary Genres in Medicine, Science, and Business”, Journal of Business and Technical Communication, 19(3): 279-303.</ref>
          <ref rid="R85" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="305" page="21" column="1">Prasad A. (2007), “The (amorphous) anatomy of an invention: the case of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)”, Social Studies of Science, 37(4): 533-560. Prentice R. (2005), “The Anatomy of a Surgical Simulation: The Mutual Articulation of Bodies in and through the Machine”, Social Studies of Science, 35(6): 837-866. Prior L. (2007), “Talking About the Gene for Cancer: A Study of Lay and Professional Knowledge of Cancer Genetics”, Sociology, 41(6): 985-1001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R86" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="306" page="21" column="1">Ratto M. (2006), “Foundations and profiles: splicing metaphors in genetic databases and biobanks”, Public Understanding of Science, 15(1): 31-53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R87" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="307" page="21" column="1">Ribeiro R. (2007), “The Language Barrier as an Aid to Communication”, Social Studies of Science, 37(4): 561-584.</ref>
          <ref rid="R88" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="308" page="21" column="1">Saj T. L., Mather C., Sicotte P. (2006), “Traditional taboos in biological conservation: the case of Colobus vellerosus at the Boabeng-Fiema Monkey Sanctuary, Central Ghana”, Social Science Information, 45(2): 285-310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R89" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="309" page="21" column="1">Schneider A. L., (2009), “Why do Some Boundary Organizations Result in New Ideas and Practices and Others only Meet Resistance? Examples From Juvenile Justice”, The American Review of Public Administration, 39(1): 60-79.</ref>
          <ref rid="R90" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="310" page="21" column="1">Shackley S., Wynne B. (1996), “Representing Uncertainty in Global Climate Change Science and Policy: Boundary-Ordering Devices and Authority”, Science Technology Human Values, 21(3), p. 275-302.</ref>
          <ref rid="R91" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="311" page="21" column="1">Shostak S. (2007), “Translating at Work: Genetically Modified Mouse Models and Molecularization in the Environmental Health Sciences”, Science Technology Human Values, 32(3): 315-338.</ref>
          <ref rid="R92" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="314" page="22" column="1">Simpson B., Carroll B. (2008), “Re-viewing ‘Role’ in Processes of Identity Construction”, Organization, 15(1): 29-50.</ref>
          <ref rid="R93" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="315" page="22" column="1">Sommer M. (2006), “Mirror, Mirror on the Wall: Neanderthal as Image and ‘Distortion’ in Early 20th-Century French Science and Press”, Social Studies of Science, 36(2): 207- 240.</ref>
          <ref rid="R94" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="316" page="22" column="1">Sommerlund J. (2006), “Classifying Microorganisms: The Multiplicity of Classifications and Research Practices in Molecular Microbial Ecology”, Social Studies of Science, 36(6): 909-928.</ref>
          <ref rid="R95" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="317" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Soneryd L. (2007), Deliberations on the Unknown, the Unsensed, and the Unsayable? Public Protests and the Development of Third-Generation Mobile Phones in Sweden, Science Technology Human Values, 32(3): 287-314.</ref>
          <ref rid="R96" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="318" page="22" column="1">Star S.L., Griesemer J. (1989), „Institutionnal ecology, ‘Translations’ and Boundary objects: amateurs and professionals on Berkeley’s museum of vertrebate zoologie”, Social Studies of Science. 19(3), p. 387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R97" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="319" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Star S.L. (1999), “The ethnography of infrastructure”, American Behavioral Scientist, vol.</ref>
          <ref rid="R98" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="320" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">43, no 3, p. 377-391 Star S.L. (2007), “The History and Boundaries of Boundary Objects”, Conference at the workshop “Boundary Object, Boundary work”, Grenoble University, 13 septembre 2007.</ref>
          <ref rid="R99" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="321" page="22" column="1">Strauss A., Fagerhaugh S., Suczek B., Wiener C. (1985), Social Organization of medical Work, Chicago, The University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R100" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="322" page="22" column="1">Sundberg M. (2007), “Parameterizations as Boundary Objects on the Climate Arena”, Social Studies of Science, 37(3): 473-488.</ref>
          <ref rid="R101" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="323" page="22" column="1">Swan J., Bresnen M., Newell S., Robertson M. (2007), “The object of knowledge: The role</ref>
          <ref rid="R102" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="324" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">of objects in biomedical innovation”, Human Relations, 60(12): 1809-1837.</ref>
          <ref rid="R103" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="325" page="22" column="1">Swan J., Scarbrough H., Robertson M. (2002), “The Construction of `Communities of</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="326" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Practice’ in the Management of Innovation”, Management Learning, 33(4): 477-496.</ref>
          <ref rid="R104" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="327" page="22" column="1">Sydow J., Lindkvist L., DeFillippi R. (2004), “Project-Based Organizations, Embeddedness</ref>
          <ref rid="R105" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="328" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">and Repositories of Knowledge”, Organization Studies, 25(9): 1475-1489.</ref>
          <ref rid="R106" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="329" page="22" column="1">Thurk J., Fine G. A. (2003), “The Problem of Tools: Technology and the Sharing of Knowledge”, Acta Sociologica, 46(2): 107-117.</ref>
          <ref rid="R107" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="330" page="22" column="1">Van de Poel I. (2008), “The Bugs Eat the Waste: What Else is There to Know?: Changing Professional Hegemony in the Design of Sewage Treatment Plants”, Social Studies of Science, 38(4): 605-634.</ref>
          <ref rid="R108" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="331" page="22" column="1">Vinck D. (dir.) (1999), Ingénieurs au quotidien. Ethnographie de l’activité de conception et d’innovation. Grenoble, PUG.</ref>
          <ref rid="R109" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="332" page="22" column="1">Vinck D., Jeantet A. (1995), “Mediating and Commissioning Objects in the Sociotechnical Process of Product Design: a conceptual approach”, p. 111-129 in edited by Maclean</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="333" page="22" column="1">D., Saviotti P., Vinck D. (eds), Designs, Networks and Strategies, vol. 2, COST A3 Social Sciences. Bruxelles: EC Directorate General Science R&amp;D.</ref>
          <ref rid="R110" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="334" page="22" column="1">Wasser J. D., Bresler L. (1996), “Working in the Interpretive Zone: Conceptualizing Collaboration in Qualitative Research”, Teams Educational Researcher, 25(5): 5-15.</ref>
          <ref rid="R111" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="335" page="22" column="1">Weedman J. (1998), “The Structure of Incentive: Design and Client Roles in Application- Oriented Research”, Science Technology Human Values, 23(3): 315-345.</ref>
          <ref rid="R112" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="336" page="22" column="1">Wenger E. (2000), “Communities of Practice and Social Learning Systems”, Organization, 7(2): p. 225-246.</ref>
          <ref rid="R113" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="337" page="22" column="1">White R., Bradshaw M. (2004), “Business in Action: Framing and Overflowing in the Logistics of an Australian Company”, Journal of Sociology, 40(1): 5-20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R114" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="338" page="22" column="1">Wilson G., Herndl, C. G. (2007), “Boundary Objects as Rhetorical Exigence: Knowledge Mapping and Interdisciplinary Cooperation at the Los Alamos National Laboratory”, Journal of Business and Technical Communication, 21(2), p. 129-154.</ref>
          <ref rid="R115" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="339" page="22" column="1">Zeiss R., Groenewegen P. (2009), “Engaging Boundary Objects in OMS and STS? Exploring the Subtleties of Layered Engagement”, Organization, 16(1): 81-100.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="342" page="23" column="1">Pascale TROMPETTE is a CNRS Research Director, a member of the</ref>
          <ref rid="R116" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="343" page="23" column="1">PACTE Politique - Organisations Laboratory (CNRS/Grenoble University). Her research works focus on the field of economic sociology and more particularly the sociology of markets. Today she is working on the articulation between innovation and emerging markets. She recently published a work entitled Le marché des défunts (Presses de Sciences Po, 2008).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="345" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">A DRESSE PACTE Politique - Organisations Université de Grenoble Le Patio, BP 47 38040 Grenoble cedex 9 (France). C OURRIEL <email id="344">pascale.trompette@upmf-grenoble.fr</email></ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="346" page="23" column="1">Dominique VINCK is Professor of Sociology at Grenoble University. He is</ref>
          <ref rid="R117" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="347" page="23" column="1">a member of the PACTE Politique - Organisations Laboratory (CNRS/Grenoble University) for which he heads the “Sciences – society” stream. His research concerns the sociology of sciences and innovation, particularly in the micro- and nano-technology fields. He recently published Everyday Engineering. Ethnography of Research and Innovation (MIT Press, 2003), Pratiques de l’interdisciplinarité (PUG,</ref>
          <ref rid="R118" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="348" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Grenoble, 2000) and Sciences et sociétés. Sociologie du travail scientifique (A.Colin,</ref>
          <ref rid="R119" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="349" page="23" column="1">Paris, 2007; English version, Edward Elgar, forthcoming), L’équipement de</ref>
          <ref rid="R120" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="350" page="23" column="1">l’organisation industrielle. Les ERP à l’usage (Hermes, 2008) and Les nanotechnologies</ref>
          <ref rid="R121" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="351" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">(Le Cavalier Bleu, 2009).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="353" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">A DRESSE PACTE Politique - Organisations Université de Grenoble Le Patio, BP 47 38040 Grenoble cedex 9 (France). C OURRIEL <email id="352">dominique.vinck@upmf-grenoble.fr</email></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="192" page="18" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="193" page="18" column="1">q</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="227" page="19" column="1">r</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="228" page="19" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="257" page="20" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="258" page="20" column="1">s</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="287" page="21" column="1">t</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="288" page="21" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="312" page="22" column="1">Presentation</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="313" page="22" column="1">u</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="340" page="23" column="1">v</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="341" page="23" column="1">Revue d’anthropologie des connaissances – 2009/1</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
