<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>f426f8a37f0cfa70dd28aee56b6f3da1067b759c2f5324ec4fa2453c33653444</job>
    <base_name>62ha</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1978942.1978979</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">“Pleasure is Your Birthright”: Digitally Enabled Designer Sex Toys as a Case of Third-Wave HCI</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Jeffrey Bardzell</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Shaowen Bardzell</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Indiana University School of Informatics &amp; Computing 919 E 7 Th Street Bloomington, IN, 47408 {jbardzel; <email id="6">selu}@indiana.edu</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8">In the past decade, HCI has become increasingly preoccu- pied with the deeply subjective qualities of interaction: experience, embodiment, pleasure, intimacy, and so on, an agenda sometimes grouped under the heading of “third- wave HCI.” Analytically understanding and designing for such qualities has been an ongoing challenge to the field, in part because its established theories and methodologies are comparatively weak at understanding and being responsive to human subjectivity. In this paper, we present a case study of a group of designers who have, in the past few years, revolutionized their domain—sex toys—by combining embodied pleasure, intimate experience, health and wellness, emerging technologies, high-quality design processes, and social activism. We consider the implications this case could have for researchers innovating on especially third- wave HCI design theories, methodologies, and processes.</abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">HCI, design, human sexuality, criticism, activism</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Author Keywords: Classification:</h2>
      </section>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">H.5.1.m. Information interfaces and presentation (e.g., HCI): Miscellaneous.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">General Terms</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Design, Theory</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="15" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="26" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">Digital Sexual Interaction</h2>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="33" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">Sex Toys: An Historical Overview</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" page="2" column="1">Invented by a British doctor in the 19th century, vibrators were first used by physicians to treat women with “hys- teria” [26]. Often these vibrators resembled heavy machin- ery and were hardly anything but sensually appealing. Between the 1920s and 1960s, traveling salesmen began selling vibrators not as therapeutic instruments but as aids to induce sexual pleasures, which were seen at the time as secret, unauthorized, and even morally corrupt. As a part of <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the sexual revolution of the 1960s, sex toys became a visible part of a movement that constructed sexual pleasure as a human right, rather than as a moral shame [36]. The 1970s saw a backlash against the sexual revolution, in part from feminism, which attacked many forms of sexuality, including pornography, as a form of violence against women. In the 1970s and 80s, a “sex positive” feminist movement pushed back, advocating sexual freedom, including advancing (often female-produced) pornography as well as gay, lesbian, and alternative sexual lifestyles. Around the same time, sex positive feminists began to open sex stores to offer an alternative to traditional sex shops, which were perceived as sleazy shops that were often unsafe for women. These early feminist sex shops, such as San Francisco’s Good Vibrations, which opened in 1977, featured clean, well-lit environments, trained employees, and a sex positive message: in the words of one of our interviewees, the main buyer for Good Vibrations, “We have been really positive for 32 years saying, no, no, no, it is our birthright, pleasure is your birthright, this belongs to you.” For years, however, sex-positive shops continued to sell toys designed and sold by the sex industry, lacking any alternative. Such toys, still widely available today, often have the following characteristics. Made by pioneering vibrator companies such as California Exotic Creations and Doc Johnson, many of these toys have strong ties to the adult and/or porn industries. Made of plastic and rubber, they are comparatively inexpensive (often between US$10 and $30). Unreliable, their motors often break before the product is even sold. The plastic itself often contains phthalates, which is an ester used in plastics that have been linked to allergies, asthma, endocrine disruption, and birth defects. These toys are often sold in clear plastic clamshell packaging, with an image of a female porn star printed on a cardboard insert. In short, traditional vibrators are targeted at a male buying public for use as a quasi-disposable adult novelty. In recent years, several factors have given rise to a new generation of sex toys. Sex toys have increasingly been portrayed in a favorable light in mainstream media (e.g., Sex and the City), and at the same time they have become increasingly marketed to female consumers. Simultaneous to these developments has been the rise of digital technologies, which has encouraged the sex toy industry to embrace high quality production and digital technology [37]. Exam- ples of high quality sex toy companies include Lelo, Jimmyjane, OhMiBod, We-Vibe, Je Joue, Tenga, and Nomi Tang, among others. These companies are recognized by sexologists (and, importantly, each other) as constituting a group of designers defining and inaugurating a new era in sex toys. Defining this era are toys that reflect the values of the sex positive movement, design for the sexual health and the overall wellbeing of individuals and groups—a value that resonates with what’s being proposed at the recent Wellness Informatics workshop [18], all while providing physical pleasure, supporting intimacy between partners, and contributing to fulfilling experiences.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="36" page="2" column="2">258</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="37" page="3" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="38" page="3" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="1" column="1">It might be surprising to consider that human-computer interaction, once the province of engineers and experimen- tal psychologists, would find itself on a trajectory that is converging with that of sex toys, once the province of sleazy urban sex shops and pornographers. Yet, as is well documented (e.g., [10, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="16" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]), HCI has taken a strong cultural turn, taking seriously the subjective dimensions of interaction: experience [23, 27], embodiment [15, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="17" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="18" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>, 22], pleasure [9], emotion [30, 11], and physical intimacy. Several major conferences devote themselves to such these concerns: DUX, TEI, DPPI, to name a few. The other side of this converging trajectory is the rise of</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" page="1" column="2">designer sex toys. Challenging the cheap adult novelties of the past, these new designs are digitally enabled, aestheti- cally sophisticated, high-quality consumer electronics. A typical example of these new designer toys is Jimmyjane’s Form 6 vibrator ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>), which retails for $185 USD, and features body safe materials, dual motors, a rechargeable lithium ion battery, and an elegant user interface. The OhMiBod Freestyle offers wireless connectivity to MP3 play- ers for real-time music-vibration synchronization. Nomi Tang’s Better than Chocolate has a tangible user interface to control vibration patterns and intensity. Je Joue’s SaSi has a user-programmable vibration design interface. These toys, whose function is to provide pleasurable embodied experiences, have not only revolutionized the adult toy industry, but they offer a more general vision of digitally enabled physical pleasure can be.<marker type="block"/> This vision of pleasure is timely for third-wave HCI, because it is clear that progress in many of its target areas of experience, embodiment, wellness, pleasure, and so forth has been elusive: as a community we seem to have strug- gled to develop coherently a social science methodology, linked both to an epistemology and a body of methods, for the third wave. Whatever the reason, attempts to detect and measure experience and emotion, or to design for embodied interaction, have turned out to be more difficult perhaps than the research community expected. Case studies obviously cannot generalize into a new epistemology, methodology, and collection of methods, but they can offer glimpses of what the eventual solutions could look like.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62ha.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62ha.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="24" page="1" column="2">Figure 1: JimmyJane’s Form 6</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="1" column="2">The topic of sex in HCI has seen a steady stream of work in the past decade. HCI researchers have already called attention to the significance of online porn for HCI [8]. At the same time, sexuality—a term that includes emotional inti- <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> macy, vulnerability, and experiential qualities such as ex- citement, as well as the more obvious physical dimensions of it—includes much more than individuals looking at porn. Indeed, sexual expression is a part of everyday life, from the bedroom [7] to the social media landscape, including Twittergasm, ijustmadelove.com, and Vibe Review. Pro- jects integrating HCI and performance art have explored physical intimacy that often borders on the erotic [33, 34]. Virtual worlds have been studied as sources of intimacy [31], and have become home to evolved sexual subcultures, including furries and Goreans [4, 5]. Low bandwidth technologies have been shown to provide rich interpretative mediations for couples in long distance relationships [21]. In human-robot interaction, there is the emerging field of teledildonics. Workshops have been held in recent years on sex and HCI at both CHI and NordiCHI [12, 3]. We argue that sexuality and human-computer interaction (SHCI), rather than being a marginal example of third-wave HCI, in many ways should be recognized as a paradigmatic example of the third wave, since it so powerfully inter- weaves its major themes. Lest we be misunderstood, we are not claiming that all third wave HCI is sexual in nature or that people working in third wave HCI should take up sexuality. Rather, we are observing that both HCI/sex and third wave HCI share a number of common concerns. Given the extraordinary success of recent designer sex toys in bringing together design innovation, sexual health expert and sex-positive feminist involvement, and consumer advocacy, we believe that they make a worthwhile case study for the third wave. (Note: neither our data nor our backgrounds qualify us to assess the actual public wellness benefits of this movement; we limit our own assessment of this move- ment’s “success” with reference to it as a commercially successful, innovative design movement that has earned for itself strong buy-in from sexual wellness experts.) This paper offers just such a case study, relying primarily on expert interviews to reveal the design processes and outcomes of this experience-, pleasure-, and embodiment-oriented domain of interaction design. We argue that sex toy designers are successful in two particular areas that could be emulated among third-wave HCI designers:  Critical engagement with interactions, especially one’s sensual and visceral responses, to cultivate a dense subjective understanding of specific interaction qualities.  Embedded commitment to a stakeholder community, including users and experts as well as to their values.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="28" page="1" column="2">CHI 2011, May 7–12, 2011, Vancouver, BC, Canada. Copyright 2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0267-8/11/05....$10.00.  </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="29" page="1" column="2">257</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="30" page="2" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="31" page="2" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="3" column="1">RESEARCH APPROACH</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="3" column="1">The present work introduces digitally enabled designer sex toys to the HCI and interaction design communities. The work offers a critical synthesis of over 30 hours of interviews with industry experts. Relying on the voices of the designers and sexperts at the center of this movement, the paper then offers a synthetic account of who is doing this design, what their design processes are, and how these processes relate to their values and goals both for a given design and more broadly for social change. We relate these activities to design processes and issues in HCI, including the roles of criticism, problem framing, embodied design cognition, and activism in supporting this movement. From November 2009 through May 2010, we conducted a total of 14 interviews. We spoke with some of the most privileged voices in this emerging community—the designer-inventors who have collectively initiated this new wave of high quality vibrators as well as sexual health experts and sex-positive activists on the front lines of the sexual health community. We interviewed these industry experts because they are uniquely able to highlight key design and development issues as well as to understand their perspectives on these artifacts’ design intentions, rationales, materials, and production tools and practices. The fourteen interviewees (9 female, 5 male, and including 2 participants with doctorate degrees) reside in Hong Kong, Canada, Sweden, China, and the United States, and were recruited initially through the recommendation of one of the AASECT-certified sex educators who is an advisor to this research. A snowball sample was subsequently developed from the original participants. We asked these experts to tell us about their experience designing, developing, buying, and/or curating sex toys in the industry. The open-ended questions centered on four threads:  Background: Education/industry history, motivation, day-to-day responsibilities, etc.  Perceptions of existing toys: Qualities of a good sex toys, market perspectives, what works and why, etc.  Design process: Inspirations, rationale, tools, materials, working with consumers, etc.)  Integration with technology: Their vision of the role technology plays in sex toy design in 5- and 10-years, how technology shapes the design process, etc. A total of 30 hours of interviews were recorded and tran- scribed. Participants had the choice of remaining anony- mous or supplying their identities, and all but one consented to identifying themselves. All participants received a draft of this paper months prior to publication. The authors have extensive experience with sexual interaction research [3,4,5,6] and critical textual analysis [1,2]. The data analysis was conducted through a procedure known as explication de texte, or close reading, an analyti- cal method that originated in the humanities [29] and which involves the careful examination of diction, rhetorical de- <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> vices, style, and other formal and thematic elements in a text. Both researchers involved in the study have doctoral training in the humanities and have used this approach in prior research [31]. The data analysis phase followed a process. Initially both researchers conducted their close readings independently of one another to identify her or his own set of themes. Subsequently, the researchers collaborated to combine, refine, and distinguish among themes before ar- riving at the critical synthesis of their design process, described below. The combination of these expert voices and our critical analysis should help to shed insights on successful practices in the interaction design areas emphasizing any combination of experience, embodiment, wellness, pleasure, social activism, and intimacy.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="42" page="3" column="2">DESIGNING DIGITALLY ENABLED SEX TOYS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="3" column="2">One of the hallmarks of the new class of digitally enabled designer sex toys that we have been describing is that they are the outcome of a particular engineering and design process. This process is different than that typically taught in HCI, with its emphasis on users, empirical measurement, and iterative prototyping and evaluation [17]. Thus, as we critically reflect on ways to advance third-wave HCI in light of the limitations of earlier approaches, it is useful to explore alternative approaches that are successful in their own separate, but related, domains. In the ensuing exposi- tion, we highlight areas of difference between mainstream HCI and sex toy design processes, especially where they may most influence the resulting product.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Sex Toy Designers</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="3" column="2">All of the designers we interviewed are small business. While they did not all provide us with exact numbers, most have around 10-20 employees based on our office visits and the information they did share, exclusive of manufacturing (mostly done in China). The largest company for which we have a number was Lelo, which has about 30 employees, exclusive of manufacturing. These numbers include the founders, who are themselves designer-engineers, and they also include industrial and packaging designers, marketing and sales staff, customer support staff, and accountants and lawyers. One of the most interesting findings from our interviews was that none of the designer-engineers behind these products comes from or has a significant history in the adult or sex toy industry. The designer behind Jimmyjane, for example, started in bioinformatics working on the human ge- nome, before moving into industrial design and working at Frog Design doing mainstream design work for Nike, Mo- torola, Colgate, and so forth. The couple who created the We-Vibe worked in semiconductors at Nortel, before a ca- reer change provided the impetus to take a vibrator concept through the process of invention and bringing it to market. The brothers behind Lelo were engineers at Ericsson. Oth- ers worked at Apple, in car manufacturing, at NASA, and Tyco Electronics. The trend toward high tech designers making toys is likely to grow, in the words of one of our interviewees: “there are more people coming from indus- <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> trial design and design backgrounds going, ‘I don’t want to design a new watch, I want to design a sex toy.’” We can see that these companies all have a number of simi- larities. All are small, and many are family-run, facts whose significance we will return to later. All of the founding inventors have some form of technical engineering, commonly hailing from large, high-tech companies, as a key part of their pedigree. This combination seems to offer both the entrepreneurial and technological know-how to succeed in this new market. The high standards that one expects from products from companies like Ericsson, Apple, and Frog Design has survived their departures as a commitment to high quality in the field of sex toys.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="46" page="3" column="2">259</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47" page="4" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="48" page="4" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">An Embodied Design Process</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="4" column="1">In this section, we synthesize an account of designer processes from the interviews, including many direct quotes to allow readers to hear the voice of our interviewees. Our goal is not merely to shed light on their processes, but also their attitudes, metaphors, and epistemological orientations to their problem space. We emphasize throughout the cen- trality of their own cultivated subjective experience in their design reasoning. Inspiration Most of our designer-inventor interviewees had a narrative that explained how they ended up making vibrators. As industry outsiders, it is perhaps not surprising that some of these narratives begin with a founding flash of intuition, which is later framed, researched, and prototyped, and put to market. One inventor writes, OhMiBod came about because [my husband] was traveling a lot in China and one Christmas he bought me an iPod mini and a vibrator... and I found that I was using the two together.... [After I’ve done chores] and I’ve put my kids to bed, how do you get sexy from there? So what I found, music helped to transport me easily to a different place. I could kind of get out of my own head and listen to my music and then be open to basic pleasure. With OhMiBod, a personal narrative about the inventor’s own sensual experience helped identify a particular need— “how do you get sexy from there?”—which led to the insight that music can transport us from the mundane to the sexy. From there, it’s not hard to see how music + vibrator led to the OhMiBod line of toys. It is important to note, however, that the originating goal was to serve a deeply felt subjective experience, “getting sexy,” and not an intention to build a thing, that is, an interactive technology. Another product, the We-Vibe, a small vibrator that is worn during intercourse, had a similar start. [W]e were [on] an eight hour drive ... and we were just—and sex toys were not a part of our life. We starting talking about all sorts of silly things like the Californians with their blow-up dolls [in the HOV lanes] ... [a]nd you know all these $10,000 sex ma- <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> chines.... And it was just a pretty innocent idea. We were just like, “Oh,” it was just like, “Well, I wonder if there is a sex toy that fits between people when they’re making love?” And it was that simple. And then basically got home ... and wrote it down in my little inventor’s book.... I looked ... to see what sex toys were out there..., but there was just nothing out there. So, then I went to the patent office.... Here again we see that the idea just happened fortuitously during a conversation about sexual aids. Interestingly, the speaker is clearly not only not from the adult industry, but he even here still seems to be distancing himself from sex toys, by first insisting that sex toys had never been a part of his life and by repeatedly using the word “silly” to describe the conversation (this word is used elsewhere in the same passage, not quoted here). The distancing of themselves from traditional sex toy manufacturers, who as noted earlier are commonly associated with the adult/porn industry, is a common theme with this whole group of designers. If the two narratives just cited suggest an almost uninten- tional initial inspiration, for others, inspiration came as a result of a critical engagement with existing toys. We came to one of those nice little shops in Shibuya, Tokyo. I thought that well we are a little bit in a holi- day mood, so why not try a vibrator? We were frustrated afterwards, because it did not survive the battery lifetime.... And we said, why doesn’t anyone make this kind of device better? Why is nobody caring about high quality sex toys that come in nice packaging, with a nice design, not one with a naked woman...? Maybe a little bit more modern approach towards technology? [3 years later we] brought up this whole story, and I said why is nobody caring about really nice sex toys with a sexy approach, which is not so intimidating as maybe one of those dildos or classic vibrators you find in an ordinary sex shop? Yes, this is where the idea finally was formed. I thought that well if nobody does it better why am I not doing it better? This critique does not lead to a concrete concept in and of itself. Instead, it identifies a small number of design qualities [25] that the speaker perceives that the market fails to offer: high production quality, technological currency, non- pornographic packaging, and not being too intimidating. The founder of Jimmyjane is even further removed from a random flash of insight. He writes that in 2002, “I was approached by three different people to look into products related to sex and that is what made me think, okay, something is going on because I have never been approached with this before.” Accordingly, I went to [an adult industry] trade show and ... I was personally sort of overwhelmed because I had very limited experience with these products.... I started picking products up ... and thinking of them just as product. Relatively quickly you become desensitized<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> to the stigma.... You start look at these as just products, and looking through that lens all sorts of things that would never have been acceptable to me as a designer, were present in these products.... The products were scary looking, very unapproachable, often looked like severed anatomy or you know, were ani- mals and very figurative.... They were noisy, they were smelly, and a whole host of materials.... I could tell ... if something is off gassing, if you can smell it, you know that some chemical is being released. Any- way, so it became immediately apparent that these products were made out of toxic material. They were packaged in packaging with porn stars.... It seemed to me that there was a lot that could be done. The speaker here also distances himself initially from sex toys, but his perception of them completely inverts the mo- ment he re-categorizes them from “sex toys” to “design product.” With this shift, he has a flood of critical insights about the (then) state of the art. Considering shapes, visual appearance, and smells, he infers the materials from which they are made and then immediate continues on to infer a set of design qualities as diverse as product experience, cultural positioning, and health. His criticisms in many ways echo and reinforce those of Nomi Tang, cited just above. And as with Tang, he does not immediately have an idea of the toy he will make; instead, he constructs a list of design qualities that the toys should meet: body safe, not intimidating, approachability, non-smelly, non-porno- graphic, nice packaging, etc. The designers acquire a holistic understanding of their problem space not through an early focus on users, as rec- ommended by [17], but rather by means of critical self- reflection on their own experience and/or a more systematic act of design criticism, defined in [1] as the careful, prac- ticed, and theoretically informed investigation of a cultural work or phenomenon, situated in the creative, historical, social, and semantic contexts of similar works. Our participants stress an aspect of criticism that [1]’s definition un- derstates: the role of the designer-critic’s sensual and visceral response in directing design-critical cognition. Design criticism is needed, because when helping designers build understandings of human needs in terms of the relationships among dense experiential qualities, product se- mantics, design materials, the state of the market, and broader social movements, most users are simply not able to articulate their needs. The expert eye of the designer- critic, on the other hand, is able to interrogate designs to perceive design opportunities. With the design space identi- fied, the next step is to think about it in a structured way. Problem Framing Design research—e.g., the work of Schön [35], Cross [14], and Lawson [24]—has stressed the importance of “fram- ing.” Framing refers to the designer’s identification of “ar- eas of the solution space in which they choose to explore” [14, p.102], in Schön’s words, to “set its boundaries, select particular things and relations for attention, and impose on<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the situation a coherence that guides subsequent moves” [14, p.102]. Perhaps the most fundamental example of problem framing, and on some level it is shared by all of the designers we interviewed, is the understanding of vibrators as “consumer electronics.” This particular framing has implications both for what quality toys should be and also how they should be made. One of the designer-inventors of OhMiBod puts it thus: I actually think, and it’s us together with a couple of other companies, who are actually defining what a quality type toy should be. The consumers historically don’t know.... They’re so used to buying the very cheap, the kind of jelly rubber toys ... it’s really turn- ing into a consumer electronics product as opposed to just what historically has been a kind of cheap sex toy. So there are different manufacturing protocols. We do ... tracking so if something goes wrong with a toy we can actually trace it back to a specific lot number.... The key act of framing is the shift from “cheap plastic toy” to “consumer electronic.” As soon as that occurs, every- thing else shifts as well: manufacturing protocols, quality control, and a certain understanding of “quality” itself. Problem framing goes well beyond the overall framing of the sex toy design space, however. For the founder of Jimmyjane, problem framing not only applies to a given design, but also to his brand strategy. Building a brand strategy led him to develop a model of “sexuality,” so he could ensure that his brand is not one-dimensional. He says, Jimmyjane ... is not a vibrator company, but rather a concept about extending sexiness throughout the day, about this notion that fundamentally we never feel better than when we feel sexy. So, why not have that and access that consistently throughout the day in all sorts of different ways? One way certainly is actual physical sexual contact with the body and with another, but also obviously there all sorts of other phases of sexuality that permeate our lives. It extends to how we dress, it extends to all sorts of other sort of rituals that are fundamental to our lives, grooming and so on. Here is an understanding of sexuality that is quite different than that of traditional porn-industry sex toy manufacturers, who build toys and brand experience around the California porn industry fantasy of a sex encounter episode. For Jimmyjane’s founder, overt sex acts barely register: he is talking about how aspects of sexuality “permeate our lives”—a profound and ultimately phenomenological question. His understanding is equally distinct from a scientific models or theories of human sexuality, e.g., from psychology or health sciences. His critical understanding is not only healthy from a sex positive feminist perspective—it emphasizes feeling good about yourself—but it also helps him develop his business: in addition to vibrators, Jimmyjane also offers a line of fragrances, thus connecting sexuality to grooming.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Grooming is a different type of sexual practice than body contact, and to design fragrances that will help people feel sexy, Jimmyjane’s founder decided to work with the concept of attraction as a way to structure his design reasoning: But ... as soon as I realized, okay, there are so many different types of attraction.... [The] essential elements of attraction [are the] intellectual component, the emotional component and the sexual component.... And so the fragrances then ... are Charm, Wit, and Kink.... So, in a relationship that maybe is defined by Wit and Kink is an intellectual and a physical interaction, but not really an emotional one, is one sort. I can’t think of a better word for it, but one that is emotional and physical.... You know, perhaps this overlap of all three is you know, what you might call love... Both the development and the design explanation of Jimmyjane fragrances are intertwined with an explanation of both the brand as well as attempts to think systematically not only about sexuality, but also about related concepts, including attraction and love itself. Jimmyjane’s founder is not alone in critically examining human sexuality as a resource to design reasoning. In our interview with We-Vibe, when we asked them to tell us about the qualities of a good designer sex toy, one of the designer-inventors proposes a three-dimensional understanding of the problem space: So, that’s the trick in engineering is to me is to take all of the human desires on one side from a functional point of view. And ... then the aesthetics of it to make it beautiful so it doesn’t look ugly or threatening as a second dimension. Then the third one is the engineering side of it how do you get something that’s got all of those attributes small, powerful, quality, lasts a long time, easy to use and how do you make it an ob- ject that will achieve that? And that’s the art of engineering. For We-Vibe’s designer-inventors, a good sex toy is responsive to human desires, aesthetic, and well engineered. Interestingly, when we probed about “human desires,” he responded, “but ‘human’ like how it performs: its function, its longevity, its ease of use, ease of washing you know it’s bullet proof, and lasts a long time, etc.” The inventor’s understanding of human desire here has clearly been opera- tionalized into concrete design qualities. In fact, it is difficult, based on this passage, to distinguish between the “human desire” and the “engineering” dimensions, because he has analyzed human desire into constituent parts, each of which in turn becomes a design problem space. In all of our interviews with designers, we saw time and again evidence of efforts to think systematically about the problem domain, simultaneously exploring use- and design qualities. Nomi Tang, for example, used tangible user interfaces as starting point to help her think through her design’s user interface, leading to a surprisingly (and wittily) natural<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> gesture/touch control for vibrator speed and pattern that technologically resembles the iPod trackwheel and experi- entially resembles clitoral stimulation. Research for Design Inspiration and problem framing is a form of reasoning that is largely internal to the designer. However, all of the designers we interviewed also turned outside, by conducting different forms of research for design. The most commonly reported form of research was not surprisingly user research, but our interviewees also reported the use of sexperts, that is, involving sexual health experts in the prototyping and evaluation stages of design, as well the use of published works. All of the designers we interviewed engaged in two or more forms of user research. This included standard market research, such as surveys, focus groups, and interviews with users and retailers. One designer reported reading blog- based reviews of sex toys, starting her own blog, and trying to encourage critical dialogue about toys between herself and her customers. Most of the designers told us that they got ideas and feedback from their own partners and girlfriends. Another designer-inventor went to the streets and randomly talked to passers-by: I remember standing downtown handing out surveys to government worker ladies going by and saying, “Oh, can I borrow a few minutes of your time and talk to you about sex toys?” The ones who didn’t run away of course gave me great information in terms of you know what’s your favorite toy. Then I went away and of course bought all these toys and measured what frequency they are and what rpm they do and their basic characteristics. The distance between the designers-as-researchers and their research subjects seems reduced in many of these examples. Instead of scientists behind a two-way mirror, these designer inventors are having frank, personal, and individual conversations with consumers, whether they are new ac- quaintances or their own family members. Considered as sources of empirical data, such strategies seem rife with problems, e.g., of anecdote, bias, and problems of generali- zation. Considered as conversations that sustain critical investigation of the phenomenology of human sexual experience and its relationship to design, however, it may be that intimate conversations with family members and customers may be a particularly strong strategy, because of the demanding—interpersonally, intellectually—nature of what the designers are asking. (Embodied) Prototyping Our interviewees spoke at length about their prototyping processes. We were struck at how strongly their descrip- tions of prototyping were interlaced with the language of embodiment. Obviously, an intellectual understanding of embodiment—human sexuality, anatomy, texture, safety, etc.—is central to designing sex toys. But it was clear to us that embodiment was not merely rationally understood;<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> rather, the designers’ own embodiment strongly influenced the way they approach design. For the founders of OhMiBod, 3D prototypes are transformative, so much so that they have gone to interesting lengths to obtain them: we can take a concept and throw it into a CAD and then within 24 hours get a 3D print so you can actually hold that product in your hand and feel it against your body; I think transforms the whole design process.... I won’t give any names..., but there’s a couple of guys who actually had access to a 3D printing machine with a local company here..., and they run the 3D printing lab, and so at night they sneak in there and they 3D print the vibrators for us.... The idea that these guys kind of sneak into their own lab and do vibrator prints is pretty interesting. Indeed, these prototypes seem to play some of the same roles that sketches do in traditional design in terms of thinking through experience [13], only with a more touch- oriented perspective. Embodiment influences design in other, more gendered ways, as the buyer for Good Vibrations explains: Now this is a funny story. And one of my [employees] was explaining how when she uses [a particular vibrator], when she uses this it is counterintuitive because how to turn it off and on and up and down. It is just is counterintuitive to her and [when confronted with this reaction, the designer] was like, oh right it was designed for a man to use on a woman. The designers are all men. [The sex toy company] was all men and now there are women but it was all men.... And they designed them to use on their wives or girlfriends or whomever, never thought about what would happen when a woman uses it on herself. This example illustrates a certain first-person mentality that pervades the design process. Again, viewed scientifically, this is problematic, since it suggests a certain lack of distance or objectivity on the part of the designers. At the same time, designing for experience, physical pleasure, intimacy, and so forth can hardly be done without deep recourse to one’s own personal embodied experience; this experience is not an intellectual liability in understanding human experience, but arguably its preeminent resource. We saw more unconsciously embodied reasoning in the interviews that we were able to conduct face-to-face. In explaining toys to us, our interviewees often gestured toward their own or even our bodies; these gestures were natural and unconscious. Once, a company co-founder quite un-self-consciously climbed on a table to show us a sexual position in order to explain the placement of some controls on a toy. Further, when talking about g-spot vibrators, interviewees tended to direct their attention and gaze to the female researcher, and likewise when talking about prostate vibrators, they directed their attention to the male researcher.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> An embodied understanding of vibrators goes beyond their intended uses as sexual stimulants, as well. For example, the lead engineer at Lelo was concerned about the portabil- ity of a set of prototypes, and so he “would carry these in his pocket almost all of the time and he was trying to see which device would be kind of the best that he would be most comfortable with and that is how Mia basically was chosen.” A lifestyle includes not just sex acts and feeling sexy, but even the mundane dimensions of carrying pleasure objects around in one’s pocket. Nomi Tang wanted her vibrator both to be a piece of art and also to have the ergonomic qualities associated with high quality medical equipment. She explains how she achieved this fusion of concept art and ergonomics in her design for Better Than Chocolate: I gave [the design team] a couple of references of art pieces that I ... liked and said I want to have the toy which looks more like a piece of art, which I can keep in the bedroom or in the bathroom, which blends into the environment without looking any kind of cheap or non luxurious, and [without giving] away directly that it is a vibrator.... And the design team that came up with 12 or 16 [prototypes].... They come from medical design background, which is quite interesting ... they specialized in emergency room equipment, which has to be very ergonomic to please the hand as well as the body of the patient. The resulting toy has a highly organic-looking shape—it is immediately appealing to the eye and to touch—but it does not look like any particular part of the human body—its shape is the outcome of a design process. Several designers also talked about the problem of sound. For example, the inventors of the We-Vibe explain, the perfect toy should be ... dead nut silent. And we go to a lot of effort to make this We-Vibe quiet. We actually test each motor for the noise it makes. And I’m often astounded at when you turn these things on it sounds like a washing machine or you know it’s just some of these [toys] are just so noisy it’s just gross and because part of the human intake is noise and if this thing just sounds ugly. It doesn’t matter what it looks like or what it feels like it’s just a bad thing. The diction in this passage—“astounded,” “sounds like a washing machine,” “gross,” and “sounds ugly”—is em- phatic and personal. We do not normally describe a machine sound as “gross,” which normally has organic connotations, and surely it is an exaggeration to describe the sound of a small electronic device as “like a washing machine.” Yet when such noises occur in the context of sexual intimacy, this use of such vocabulary makes sense. Designers leverage their own imaginations as sexual human beings to form judgments about what constitutes acceptable levels of sound in intimate situations and make design deci- sions accordingly.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The major themes of the third wave of HCI all engage in some way with the sensual. The designers’ own embodied and even sexual perspectives and practices position them to design for sensual pleasure: 3D sketching, developing an aesthetic vocabulary, relating to interlocutors and users, orienting UI controls, and assessing the acceptability of machine noises, among many others. As interaction design takes on increasingly intimate aspects of human experience, the field will possibly benefit from adopting a more embodied vocabulary to express its design reasoning. Evaluation When asked about evaluation, the designers described many standard mechanisms for evaluating designs: beta testers were given prototypes and they provided their reactions; the designers collected product feedback, e.g., from product returns, customer surveys, and comments from retailers. Interestingly, we also continued to see the emphasis on col- lecting critical feedback from close relations: internal employees and their families/friends evaluated products both professionally and personally: “[our designers] even ask their spouses or whatever, girlfriends.” Again, because sex toy design is governed by critical, rather than empirical, understandings of embodied pleasure and experience, accounts offered by close friends and family may be deeper, more honest, and more personally intimate than accounts acquired in more traditional scientific ways. An important aspect of the evaluation phase of these designer sex toys is how short the iteration loops are. This is possible, according to nearly all of our interviewees (including the sexual health experts and retailers), because customer feedback penetrates design companies even at the highest levels. In the words of Lelo’s co-founder and co- lead designer, And we would get numerous e-mails also regarding any feedback. Pretty much all of these e-mails are sent to [the co-founders] or to development people and we would ... take action and do something.... And that is the nice thing about being a smaller company is that ... the top people see these things and they are not fil- tered.... Everybody, not always but usually, has the same goal and is driven by the same things. That designers, senior management, and customers are on the same page affects the design in important ways. All of the designers emphasize fast product iterations and innovations possible because of consumer feedback, facilitated in part by the fact that staff and key decisionmakers alike are engaging the community together, helping the company respond quickly to criticisms and ideas.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="53" page="4" column="2">260</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54" page="5" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="5" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="58" page="5" column="2">261</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="59" page="6" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="60" page="6" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="6" column="2">262</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="7" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="7" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="68" page="7" column="2">263</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="69" page="8" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="70" page="8" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="72" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Social Activism Through Design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="8" column="1">One dynamic that gradually became visible over the course of our interviews is that stakeholders throughout the com- munity—companies making toys, sexual health experts, retailers, and consumers alike—are united in pursuing an agenda. This unity of purpose, shaped in part by ideals, creates an ecosphere of resources that we believe is ex- <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> tremely effective in advancing good sexual interaction design. And in that ecosphere, better design is not merely the outcome of work done by health experts and sex positive feminists; rather, design is also an input that contributes to this agenda in ways that seem to relate both to the HCI topics of research through design [38] and feminist HCI [2], but also more generally to feminist activist research, which likewise advocates for the integration of knowledge and action [32, 28]. The unity of purpose is evident in several ways. Chief among them may be the key role of the advocacy offered by sexual health experts and feminist sex retailers (whom we collectively refer to as “sexperts”), whose alignment not only benefits the consumer (as was intended from their very beginnings in the 1970s) but is now increasingly influenc- ing design itself. This is supported by strong lines of com- munications among all three constituencies: sexperts, designers, and consumers. We can see evidence of the tie between the sexperts and consumers through sexperts’ commitment to educating consumers, the outcome of which is apparent in this observa- tion by Good Vibrations’ buyer: “I think that people now, they want to know ingredients, they want to know materials, they, I mean just as in electronics, as in any other industry the user is a little more savvy, they have done their research online.” Sexperts in retail obviously can do more than merely educate the consumer: they also decide what to put in front of the consumer as well as what to promote, an activity that shapes demand. This demand in turn influences designers, who, thanks to their own critiques of the industry, were anticipating these needs and responding to them. In delivering high quality toys—and leveraging their skills at marketing to trumpet that quality—they not only meet demand but also make it easier for sexperts to educate consumers and promote the sexual wellness agenda. We also saw evidence of significant interaction between sexual health experts and the designers themselves. One expert describes her involvement with the design of the first OhMiBod vibrator: I met with [the company founders] ... a couple of times around different products and they are wonder- ful because they ... very much appreciate our input as experts in this field.... I met with [them] ... before [their first] product actually came out and just gave him my thoughts, and he is a manufacturer that is so, I just love him for doing this.... I sat down with him and it was just like, I love this, I don’t love this, and you have to have this, and just, my own opinions of a buyer knowing the market, and he listened, he listened. And even if some things could not be changed then, they were changed on ... the second product. By engaging Good Vibrations’ buyer in the design process, its design was influenced by a retailer-sexpert, and at the same time that sexpert began to engage in design cognition: beyond understanding toys as particular contributors to cer-<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tain experiences or forms of wellness, she now has a better understanding of sex toys as a design problem (e.g., manufacturing issues and other design constraints). We heard other examples of this kind of interaction between designers and sexperts—indeed it a part of every interviewee’s experience in one way or another. In some cases, all three groups—designers, sexperts, and consumers, come together. For example, the Center for Sexual Health, run by sexual health scholars, sometimes collaborates with Good Vibrations and San Francisco-based toy designers to host events with focus groups and even amateur sex toy design competitions. In this way, design processes about sex toys reaches out and includes consumers as well. A key to the design success of this design-advocacy- consumer ecosystem is that it serves its stakeholders well on different levels. It addresses an area of public health where people historically have been underserved. It enables all stakeholders to advance a set of ideals (including, but not limited to, a progressive sex-positive feminist agenda), and it creates a profitable market. And design companies are well aware of the market, as the co-founders of one company made clear, when we asked why their first toy was designed for couples: “Money.... [Product] is aimed specifically right dead nuts in the middle of the bell curve of the population.” Sex toys have transitioned from a topic of shame to a movement that people are increasingly proud to be a part of, which in turn motivates them to contribute to its ad- vancement, as the founder of Jimmyjane explains in a news article at AskMen.com: I was designing—it was kind of whatever clients came through the door and I was looking for something that was going to be more impactful. You know, I designed yet another cell phone, yet another toothbrush, yet another computer monitor, and all of my fellow designers in other firms are designing the same stuff. It just seemed like all we were doing was driving demand, but not actually delivering something that at the end of the day was going to make a big difference in people’s lives. Obviously, it is not always possible to design in an area where one feels that one is contributing to a good social cause—someone has to design watches, shoes, mobile phones, and productivity software. Still, it is hard to deny the motivating power of the designers’ passion to contribute to wellness—and the collaborative stakeholder configura- tions that it leads to.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="8" column="2">264</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="76" page="9" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="77" page="9" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="79" page="9" column="1">CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="9" column="1">Many of the concerns of third-wave HCI—experience, emotion, embodiment—remain secondary considerations in HCI practice. As a field, we historically have begun with a set of functional needs and/or a sense of a particular interface in mind, and we have iterated on it, before starting to evaluate it in terms of usability or user experience. Subjec- tive satisfaction is often measured in crude terms, e.g., via <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Likert scales. Often, experiential qualities are reduced to cybernetic system features: can a system infer when a user is frustrated with pressure-sensitive mice, face-recognition algorithms, or by detecting breakdowns in information seeking behaviors? Likewise, some seek to achieve aesthetic interaction by grafting psychological models of flow onto user models. In addition to placing experience in the backseat behind functionality, such approaches seem meth- odologically to alienate designers from their own vast experience with, well, experience. This case study of sex toy designers has shown an alternative: what might it look like when designers start with the objective of designing to support pleasurable, embodied, affective experiences? We have seen that in the case of designer sex toys, designers operate in a critical, rather than empirical, space. They interrogate key vocabulary, from sex to attraction to feeling sexy to love itself, dialogically, by engaging in design criticism, reasoning from their own experiences, and having intimate conversations with friends, family, colleagues, customers, and even strangers. User feedback goes directly to principle designers, unmediated by averages and models. Designers talk openly about their own sexual experiences and reflections and incorporate them into their design explanations as just another resource. Instead of developing complex analytic models, they quickly iterate through three-dimensional prototypes. They con- sult with experts, not to have domain knowledge transmitted to them, but rather to engage the experts themselves, as thinking subjects, in their cycles of iteration. It would be absurd to suggest that the specific case of high- end sex toy design could generalize to all of third-wave HCI. This case study provides one example, however, of a successful area of experience design whose processes bear little resemblance to hallowed HCI traditions, with their early empirical focus on users and predilection for validated models and methods [17]. For sex toy designers, to design for experience, emotion, and physical pleasure is to critically immerse themselves in experience, emotion, and physical pleasure, and to engage these critical immersions into a conversation involving “users” as fellow sexual beings (rather than data providers); sexual health, medical, and retail experts; and a steady stream of quickly iterating 3D prototypes. Our suggestion is not, of course, that we should abandon our past and emulate sex toy designers, but rather to reflect on cases such as these while HCI critically interrogates its own design processes during this third-wave paradigm shift. Perhaps we can develop our methodological and/or theoretical vocabulary to be responsive to aspects of this case that seem to be working well, in particular in the areas of embodied design cognition and social activist- oriented design.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="82" page="9" column="2">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" page="9" column="2">1. Bardzell, J. Interaction Criticism and Aesthetics. Proc. of CHI'09: World Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. ACM: New York. (2009).</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="10" column="1">2. Bardzell, S. Feminist HCI: Taking stock and outlining an agenda for design. Proc. of CHI’10. ACM: New York. (2010), 1301-1310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="10" column="1">3. Bardzell, J., Bardzell, S., Bertelsen, O., and Kannabiran, G. Erotic life in Human-Computer Interaction. Proc of NordiCHI’10, Reykjavík, Iceland. New York: ACM Press (2010).</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="89" page="10" column="1">4. Bardzell, J., Bardzell, S. Intimate interactions: Online representation and software of the self. Interactions. ACM: New York. (2008), 11-15.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" page="10" column="1">5. Bardzell, S., &amp; Odom, W. The experience of embodied space in virtual worlds: An ethnography of a Second Life community. Space and Culture 11, 3 (2008), 239- 259.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="91" page="10" column="1">6. Bardzell, S., &amp; Bardzell, J. Docile avatars: Aesthetics, experience, and sexual interaction in Second Life. Proc. of British HCI 2007, (2007).</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="92" page="10" column="1">7. Bertelsen, O., and Petersen, M. Erotic life as a new fron- tier in HCI. Proc. of British HCI 2007. Lancaster, UK. (2007), 7-10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="10" column="1">8. Blythe, M. and Jones M. Human Computer (Sexual) Interactions. In Interactions 11, 5 (2004), 43-46.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" page="10" column="1">9. Blythe, M., Overbeeke, K., Monk, A., and Wright, P. Funology: From usability to Enjoyment. Springer, 2003.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">10.Bødker, S. When second wave HCI meets third wave challenges. Proc. of NordiCHI’06, ACM Press (2006).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">11.Boehner, K., DePaula, R., Dourish, P., and Sengers, P. How emotion is made and measured. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies 65, Elsevier Ltd (2007), 275-291.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="97" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">12.Brewer, J., Kaye, J., Williams, A., and Wyche, S. Sexual interactions: Why we should talk about sex in HCI. Ext. Abstracts CHI 2006, ACM Press (2006).</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="98" page="10" column="1">13. Buxton, B. Sketching User Experiences: Getting the Design Right and the Right Design. Morgan Kaufmann, 2007.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="10" column="1">14. Cross, N. Designerly Ways of Knowing. Birkhäuser Architecture, 2007.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="100" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">15.Dourish, P. Where the Action is: The Foundations of Embodied Interaction. MIT Press, 2006.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="101" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">16.Fogtmann, M., Fritsch, J., Kortbek, K. Kinesthetic interaction: Revealing the bodily potential in interaction design. Proc. of OzHCI, 2008. ACM Press (2008), 89-96.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">17.Gould, J., and Lewis, C. Designing for usability: Key principles and what designers think. Communications of the ACM 28, 3(1985), 300-311.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="103" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">18.Grinter, B., Siek, K., and Grimes, A. Wellness informat- ics. Extended Abstracts, CHI’10 (2010).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="104" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">19.Harrison, S. Tatar, D. and Sengers, P. The three paradigms of HCI. Ext. Abstracts CHI 2007, ACM Press (2007).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="105" page="10" column="2">20.Hornecker, E., and Burr, J. Getting a grip on tangible interaction: A framework on physical space and social interaction. Proc. of CHI 2006. ACM Press (2006), 437-</ref>
          <ref rid="R446" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" page="10" column="2">446. 21.Kaye, J.J. I Just Clicked To Say I Love You: Rich Evaluations of Minimal Communication. CHI '06 extended abstracts on Human factors in computing systems, ACM Press (2006), 363-368. 22.Klemmer, S., Hartmann, B., Takayama, L. How bodies matter: Five themes for interaction design. Proc. of DIS</ref>
          <ref rid="R2006" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" page="10" column="2">2006. ACM Press (2006), 140-149. 23.Law. E. Preface: Meaningful measures: Valid useful user experience measurement. In Proc. of the International Workshop on Meaningful Measures. (2008), 3-4. 24.Lawson, B. How Designers Think: The Design Process Demystified. Elsevier Architectural Press, 1980. 25.Löwgren, J. and Stolterman, E. Thoughtful Interaction Design. MIT Press, 2004. 26.Maines, R. The Technology of Orgasm: Hysteria, the Vibrator, and Women’s Sexual Satisfaction. Johns Hop- kins UP: Baltimore &amp; London, 1999.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">27.McCarthy, J. and Wright, P. Technology as Experience. The MIT Press, 2004. 28.Naples, N. Feminism and Method: Ethnography, Dis-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">course Analysis, and Activist Research. Routledge,</ref>
          <ref rid="R2003" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="10" column="2">2003. 29.Ogden, C., Richards, I.A. The Meaning of Meaning.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">Mariner Books, New York, 1923. 30.Picard, P. Affective Computing. The MIT Press, 2000. 31.Pace, T., Bardzell, S., and Bardzell, J. The rogue in the</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">lovely black dress: Intimacy in World of Warcraft. Proc. of CHI’10. ACM: New York (2010), 233-242. 32.Reinharz, S. Feminist Methods in Social Research. Ox-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">ford UP, 1992.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">33.Schiphorst, T. soft(n): Toward a somaesthetics of touch. Extended Abstract of CHI’09. ACM: New York. (2009),</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="115" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">2427-2438.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="116" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">34.Schiphorst, T. exhale. An art installation. 2007. Re-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">trieved September 18, 2010.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="119" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sfu.ca/" id="118">http://www.sfu.ca/</ext-link>~tschipho/exhale/index.html 35.Schön, D. The Reflective Practitioner: How Profession- als Think In Action. Basic Books, 1984.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">36.Silverberg, C. Putting a price on pleasure: An oral history of retail sexual business and public discourse on sexual pleasure, 2009, unpublished manuscript. 37.Waxman, J. The case for intelligent design. Adult Video News. Retrieved November 2009 from avn.com. 38.Zimmerman, J., Forlizzi, J., and Evenson, S. Research through design as a method for interaction design research in HCI. Proc. of CHI’07 ACM: New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2007" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">(2007), 493-502.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84" page="9" column="2">265</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="85" page="10" column="1">CHI 2011 • Session: Sex &amp; Bodies</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="86" page="10" column="1">May 7–12, 2011 • Vancouver, BC, Canada</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="122" page="10" column="2">266</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
