<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e8578123b335c5b052465adf1d30ad1adf3c3e457576258c64dee517d505bfbb</job>
    <base_name>62rk</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1511837</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62rk.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Design Research: A Disciplined Conversation Author(s): Nigel Cross Source: Design Issues</name>
          <aff id="3">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Vol.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">No.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Design Research (Summer</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">)</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">pp. 5-10 Published by: The MIT Press Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/1511837 . Accessed: 07/10/</name>
          <aff id="9">5-10</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="10">.</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="12">Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="11">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="13">upon a wide range of and facilitate new forms</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">. JSTOR is a not-for-profit content in a trusted digital of scholarship. For more</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="16">service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="15">support@jstor.org</email>.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="17">.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="18">The MIT Press is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Design Issues.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx19">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62rk.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="20">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">DesignResearch: A Disciplined Conversation Nigel Cross</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60">Design research is alive and well, and living in an increasing numberof places.I find encouragingevidencefor this in the growth of research-based journalsin the design world over the last ten to fifteen years. For example, Design Studieswas launched in 1979; <marker type="block"/> in 1992.These are not the only ones; and therehave been others,of course, in other languages, such as Temes de Disseny(Catalanand<marker type="block"/> 1992;FormDiskurs (German), 1996. There has also been a lot of design-oriented research reportedin a wide range of journalsconcernedwith artificialintel- ligence, human-computerinteraction,and so on. Comparedwith the academicdesign scene in the 1970s,we now have a rich culture in which to grow our design researchseedlings. Eachof these design researchjournalsdraws upon scholarship paradigmsfrom the sciences or the arts.A history-basedjour- nal such as Journal of DesignHistoryclearlydraws upon paradigms of scholarshipin the artsand humanities,and an engineering-based<marker type="block"/> researchparadigmof the naturalsciences. But the importantthing is that collectively we have the possibility of adding to these other paradigmsand of developing our own design researchculture.<marker type="block"/> ResearchSociety,in 1980,BruceArchergave a generaldefinitionof research,which is that "Research is systematic inquiry,the goal of which is knowledge."'Our concernin design researchhas to be the development, articulationand communicationof designknowledge. Our axiom has to be that there are forms of knowledge peculiarto the awarenessand abilityof a designer,just as the other intellectual cultures in the sciences and the arts concentrateon the forms of knowledge peculiarto the scientistor the artist. Where do we look for this knowledge? I believe that it has threesources:people, processesand products. Design knowledge residesfirstlyin people: in designersespe- cially,but also in everyone to some extent. Designing is a natural human ability Otheranimalsdo not do it, and machines(so far)do not do it. We often overlook the fact that people are naturallyvery good at design. We should not underplayour abilitiesas designers, many of the most valued achievementsof humankindareworks of<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> design, including anonymous, vernacular design as well as the "highdesign"of professionals. One immediate subjectof design research,therefore,is the investigation of this human ability-of how people design. This suggests, for example,empiricalstudies of designerbehavior,but it also includes theoreticaldeliberationand reflectionon the natureof design ability. It also relates strongly to considerations of how people learnto design, to studies of the developmentof design ability in individuals and how that development might best be nurturedin design education. Design knowledge resides secondly in its processes: in the tacticsand strategiesof designing. A majorareaof design research is methodology:the study of the processesof design, and the devel- opmentand applicationof techniqueswhich aid the designer.Much of this researchrevolves around the study of modeling for design purposes. Traditionalmodels are the sketches and drawings of proposed design solutions, which in contemporary terms now extend to "virtualreality"models. The use of computershas stimu- lated a wealth of researchinto design processes;so has the development of new practicesin industrysuch as concurrent engineering. Thirdly,we cannot forget that design knowledge resides in products themselves:in the forms and materialsand finishes which embody design attributes.Much everyday design work entails the use of precedents or previous exemplars-not because of laziness by the designer but because the exemplarsactuallycontainknowl- edge of what the product should be. This is certainlytrue in craft- based design:traditionalcraftsarebased on the knowledge implicit within the objectitself of how best to shape, make, and use it. This is why craft-madeproducts are usually copied very literally from one example to the next, fromone generationto the next. As with the design knowledge that resides in people, we would be foolish to disregard or overlook this informal product knowledge simply because it has not been made explicityet; that is a taskfor design research. So too, is the developmentof moreformal knowledge of shape and configuration,the theoreticalstudies of design morphology. These may be concerned as much with the semantics as with the syntax of form, or may be concerned with prosaic matters of efficiency and economy, or with relationships between form and context-whether ergonomicsor environment. My own taxonomy of the field of design research would thereforefall into three main categories,based on people, process and products: * design epistemology -study of designerlyways of knowing * design praxiology -study of the practicesand processesof design * design phenomenology -study of the form and configurationof artifacts.<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> What clearly has been happening in the field of design researchin the last decade or so is that there has been a growing awarenessof the intrinsicstrengthsand appropriatenessof design thinking within its own context. Therehas been a growing acceptance of design on its own terms, a growing acknowledgmentand articulation of design as a disciplinein its own right.We have come to realize that we do not have to turn design into an imitation of science,nor do we have to treatdesign as a mysterious,ineffableart. Werecognizethat design has its own distinctintellectualculture;its own designerly "thingsto know,ways of knowing them, and ways of finding out about them." 2 This view of design as a distinct cultureis also embodied in attempts to break away from C. P. Snow's "two cultures"view of Western intellectual tradition, the two cultures of the Arts and Sciences. It has to be recognized that there is at least one other culture,which we might regardas the cultureof Design, which can be articulatedin comparisonwith the othertwo. For instance, the "things to know," the respective fields of knowledge, arethe naturalworld for science,human experiencefor art, and the artificialworld for design; the "ways of knowing,"the values of science are rationality and objectivity,those of art are reflectionand subjectivity, and those of design are imaginationand practicality.Similarly,the "ways of finding out," the intellectual skills, can be differentiated:those of science are experiment and analysis, those of art are criticism and evaluation, and those of design aremodeling and synthesis. The above categorizationsmay be rathersimple, but many researchers in the design world have been realizingthatdesign does indeed have its own strongand appropriate intellectualculture,and that we must avoid totally swamping our researchwith different cultures imported either from science or art. This does not mean that we completely ignore these other cultures. On the contrary, they have much stronger histories of inquiry, scholarship, and research than we have in design. Weneed to draw upon those histories and traditionswhere appropriate, while buildingour own intellectual culture, acceptableand defensible in the world on its own terms.We have to be able to demonstratethat standardsof rigor in our intellectualcultureat least matchthose of the others. In TheSciences of theArtificial, HerbertSimon went so far as to say that "Theproperstudy of mankindis the scienceof design."3 (Of course, the quotation is a corruption from Pope's original version, that "the proper study of mankind is man.")What Simon was suggesting was that the study of design could be a fundamen- tal, interdisciplinarystudy accessible to all those involved in the creative activity of making the artificialworld (which includes all mankind). For example, Simon wrote that "Few engineers and<marker type="block"/> about the content of each other's professional work. What I am<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> suggesting is that they can carry on such a conversation about design, can begin to perceivethe commoncreativeactivityin which they are both engaged, can begin to share their experiences of the creative,professionaldesign process." This, it seems to me, is the challenge for design research,to help constructa way of conversingabout design that is at the same time both interdisciplinary and disciplined.We do not want conversations that fail to connect across disciplines, that fail to reach commonunderstanding,and that fail to createnew knowledge and perceptionsof design. It is the paradoxicaltask of creatingan inter- disciplinarydiscipline. For some leading examples of this developing conversation, we might turn to the series of papers which, in recent years, have won the annual DesignStudiesAward for the best paper published in that journal.These examples have originatedin design research conducted in differentdomains and with differentmethodologies, but each individual contribution has had something to say to membersof the wider design researchcommunity. The Awardwas firstinstitutedin 1987,and a selectionof the winners includes: Donald Sch6n4 (Urban Planning,MIT,USA)Designing: Rules, Types and Worlds Analysis of design protocolsto identifypatternsof reasoningbased on rules derived fromtype-concepts. Jacob Burr and Myrup Andreason5(Engineering,Lyngby<marker type="block"/> Development Analysis of the propertiesof design models, leading to proposalsfor models appropriate to mechatronic productdesign. Frances Downing6 (Architecture,Texas A&amp;M University, USA) Conversations in Imagery Study of the role of memory (mental imageryof memorableplaces) in the architectural design process. RobinRoy7(Design &amp; Innovation,The Open University,UK)<marker type="block"/> creativeindividual designers to gain insight into the creativepro- cess and innovativeproductdevelopment. Gabriela Goldschmidt8 (Architecture, Technion, Haifa, Israel)<marker type="block"/> individual designer and a small team tackling the same design problem. TerryPurcell and John Gero9(Design Science, Sydney Uni-<marker type="block"/> studies of problem solving in design, aimed at understandingthe causes and effectsof fixation. Jars-Erik Janlert and ErikStolterman10 (Computing and In- formatics, Umea University, Sweden) The Character of Things A consideration of how things (hardwareand software), as well as people, can have a "character." What these examples of "best practice"in design research have in common include the following characteristics.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="25">Design Issues first appeared in 1984; the Journalof Design History in 1988; Researchin EngineeringDesign in 1989; and Languagesof Design</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">Spanish), 1986; Revue Scienceset Techniques de la Conception(French),</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="29">journal such as Researchin Engineering Design leans heavily on the</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="31">At the Design: Science: Method conference of the Design</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="32">I B. Archer, "A View of the Natureof Design Research" in R.Jacques and J. Powell, eds., Design. Science. Method, (Guildford, UK: WestburyHouse/IPC Science and Technology Press, 1981).</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="34">5</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="35">O Copyright 1999 MassachusettsInstitute of Technology Design Issues: Volume15, Number 2 Summer1999</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx36">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62rk.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="37">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="39">6</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40">Design Issues: Volume 15, Number 2 Summer 1999</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx41">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62rk.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="42">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="44">composers . . . can carry on a mutually rewarding conversation</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="45">2 B. Archer, K. Baynes,and R. Langon, Design in General Education, (London, UK: Royal Collegeof Art,1979). 3 H A. Simon, TheSciences of the Artificial, (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1969).</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="47">Design Issues: Volume15, Number 2 Summer 1999</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="48">7</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx49">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62rk.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="50">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="52">University, Denmark) Design Models in Mechatronic Product</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="54">Case Studies of Creativityin InnovativeProductDevelopmentStudies of</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="56">The Designer as a Teamof One Comparative protocol analyses of an</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="58">versity, Australia) Design and Other Types of Fixation Experimental</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="59">4 D.Sch6n, "Designing: Rules, Types and Worlds" Design Studies, 9: 3 (1988): 181-190. 5 J. Burr and M.Andreason, "Design Models in Mechatronic Product Development" Design Studies 10: 3 (1989): 155-1 62. 6 F.Downing, "Conversations inImagery" Design Studies 13:3 (1992): 291-319. 7 R.Roy, "Case Studies of Creativity in Innovative Product Development" Design Studies14:4 (1993): 423-443. 8 G.Goldschmidt, "The Designer as a Team of One" Design Studies,16:2 (1995): 189-209. 9 T.Purcell and J. Gero "Design andOther Types of Fixation" Design Studies, 17:4 (1996): 363-383. 10 L-E. Janlert andE.Stolterman "The Character of Things" Design Studies 18: 3 (1997): 297-31 7.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="61">8</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="62">DesignIssues: Volume15, Number 2 Summer1999</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx63">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62rk.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="64">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" confidence="possible">The researchis: Purposive, based on identificationof an issue or problem worthy and capableof investigation. Inquisitive, seeking to acquirenew knowledge. Informed, conductedfrom an awarenessof previous,related research. Methodical, planned and carriedout in a disciplinedmanner. Communicable, generatingand reportingresultswhich are testableand accessibleby others.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72">These characteristics are, of course,normalfeaturesof good research in any discipline.I do not thinkthat such normal,academic criteria inhibit or precluderesearch that is "designerly" in its origins and intentions. However, they would exclude works of so-called researchthat fail to communicate,and which are undisciplined or ill-informed. I think also that we should draw a distinction between works of practiceand works of research.I do not see how normal works of practicecan be regardedas works of research.The whole point of doing researchis to extractreliableknowledge from either the naturalor artificial world, and to make thatknowledgeavailable to othersin re-usableform.This does not mean thatworks of design practicemust be wholly excluded from design research, but it does mean that, to qualify as research,there must be reflectionby the practitioneron the work, and communication of some re-usable resultsfrom that reflection. The design fields coveredin the selectedpapers,above,have included architectural design, engineeringdesign, industrialdesign and software design, and the methods of inquiry underlying the research have ranged from philosophical analysis, through case studies and interviews, to protocol studies. They are examples drawn from an ongoing research "conversation"about design which is being sharedby membersof widely differingprofessions and disciplines.They draw upon the research paradigmsand methods of both the arts and the sciences,but they also contributeto the emergingparadigmsand methods of design research. One of the dangersin this new field of design research is that researchers from other,non-design,disciplineswill importmethods and approaches that are inappropriateto developing the understanding of design. Researchersfrom psychology or computer science, for example, have tended to assume that there is "nothing special" about design as an activity for investigation. However, developments such as artificial intelligence and other computer modeling in design have perhapsserved mainly to demonstratethe high-level cognitive ability of designers, and how much more research is needed to understand it. Better progress seems to be made by designer-researchers,and for this reason the recent Europeanseries of workshopsand symposia on descriptivemodel- <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> ing of design by Cross et al.,11 Akin et al.,12 Frankenburger at al.,13 featuring a younger generation of designer-researchers, has been extremely useful in developing the methodology of inquiry in design research. As design grows as a discipline with its own researchbase, so we can hope that there will be a growth in the numberof emergingdesigner-researchers. Another of the dangers is that researchersadhere to underlying paradigmsof which they are only vaguely aware.Weneed to develop this intellectualawarenesswithin our community.A good example here is the work of Kees Dourest,"4 in making an explicit analysisand comparisonof the paradigmsunderlyingthe approach of HerbertSimon,on the one hand, and Donald Schonon the other. These two scholars have been the most influential in our field, representing positivist and constructivist philosophies,respectively. Simon's positivism leads to a view of design as "rationalproblem solving," and Sch6n'sleads to a view of design as "reflectiveprac- tice." These two might appear to be in conflict,but Dross's use of the two paradigms in analyzing design activity leads him to the view that the differentparadigms have complementarystrengths for gaining an overview of the whole range of activitiesin design. We are still building the appropriateparadigm for design research. My personal"touch-stone" theory for this paradigmis that there are "designerlyways of knowing;" 15 many of the examples of design research I have referredto are contributionsto building our understanding of this concept of particular,designerly ability. I believe that building such a paradigm will be helpful, in the long run, to design practice and design education. We still know rela- tively little about the mystery of design ability,and that limits our "properstudy of mankind."This is the goal for design research.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="67">Design Issues: Volume 15, Number 2 Summer 1999</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="68">9</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62rk.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="70">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="71">11 N.Cross, H. Christiaans, and K.Dorst eds.,Analysing Design Activity, The Delft Design Protocols Workshop, (Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; SonsLtd., 1995). 12 0. Akin and G.Saglamer eds., Descriptive Models of Design, (Istanbul Technical University, Turkey: Faculty of Architecture, 1996). 13 E.Frankenburger, P.Badke-Schaub and H. Birkhofer eds., Designers-The Key to Successful Product Development, (London, UK: Springer Verlag, 1998). 14 K.Dorst, "Describing Design: A Comparison of Paradigms," Ph.D. Thesis, (Delft University of Technology, The Netherlands: Faculty of Industrial Design Engineering, 1997). 15 N.Cross, "Designerly Ways of Knowing" Design Studies, 3:4 (1982): 221-227.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="73">10</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74">Design Issues: Volume15, Number 2 Summer1999</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx75">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rk.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62rk.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="76">This content downloaded from 148.88.67.24 on Mon, 7 Oct 2013 09:28:09 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter"/>
  </article>
</pdfx>
