<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>be2b52430e9cc338a10ed861728be2b104da1eec0dd706c5d7b876a9e83fe1ca</job>
    <base_name>62ga</base_name>
    <doi>10.1057/ejis.2012.20</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">European Journal of Information Systems (2012) 21, 570–586 &amp; 2012 Operational Research Society Ltd. All rights reserved 0960-085X/12 www.palgrave-journals.com/ejis/</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">RESEARCH ARTICLE</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in information systems development</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Bill Doolin</name>
          <aff id="5">1</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Laurie McLeod</name>
          <aff id="7">1</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="8">1 Auckland University of Technology, New Zealand</footnote>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">Correspondence: Bill Doolin, AUT University Business School, Private Bag 92006, Auckland 1142, New Zealand. Tel: þ 64 9 921 9999 extn. 5807; Fax: þ 64 9 921 9876; E-mail: <email id="9">bill.doolin@aut.ac.nz</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="11">Information systems (IS) development is a complex organisational activity involving multiple stakeholders who interact with various artefacts in order to facilitate understanding and cooperation across diverse knowledge domains. A considerable body of work has analysed such artefacts as boundary objects, focusing on their interpretive flexibility across communities of practice. Increasing interest in the materiality of organisational practices directs attention to how such objects result from the performance of sociomaterial relations. This paper draws on these two strands of research to complement the analysis of project-related artefacts as boundary objects with a sociomaterial perspective on such objects and the practices within which they are constituted. The contribution of this combined approach is illustrated using the findings of a longitudinal case study of IS development. We trace the production and use of a prototype, the various people and practices with which it was associated, the multiple sociomaterial configurations that constituted it as a boundary object, and the social and material consequences of its use. The utilisation of sociomateriality as a theoretical lens enables us to further our understanding of how project-related artefacts act as boundary objects, and in doing so, constitute IS development as a sociomaterial practice. European Journal of Information Systems (2012) 21, 570–586. doi:10.1057/ejis.2012.20; published online 10 April 2012</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="12">Keywords: artefacts; boundary objects; IS development; sociomateriality</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="1" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Contemporary information systems (IS) development frequently involves the active participation of a wide range of internal and external stakeholders in cross-disciplinary and temporary project-based settings. A key challenge in this development context is representing, negotiating and integrating the diverse knowledge, viewpoints and interests of these stakeholders, in order to create a shared understanding of the development work and outcome (Arias et al, 2000; Karsten et al, 2001; Hendry, 2004; Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010). A range of project-related artefacts mediate this process, functioning as ‘boundary objects’ (Star, 2010) that enable knowledge sharing and cooperation across different social worlds or communities of practice. Boundary objects are used by multiple groups, creating a shared space for action: ‘These common objects form the boundaries between groups through flexibility and shared structure’ (Star, 2010, p. 603). Thus, such objects maintain a common identity across these intersecting commu- Received: 30 November 2009 Revised: 23 January 2011 nities, but are sufficiently flexible to meet the informational needs of each, 2nd Revision: 1 August 2011 enabling cooperation without necessarily consensus (Star &amp; Griesemer, 3rd Revision: 14 January 2012 1989; Star, 2010). Various studies have shown how different functional Accepted: 11 February 2012 groups involved in design and development activities interact and</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="15" page="2" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="16" page="2" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="17" page="2" column="1">571</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="2" column="1">communicate around a range of boundary objects, such as industry ‘roadmaps’, technical specifications, assembly drawings, computer-aided design tools and prototypes (Henderson, 1991; Karsten et al, 2001; Carlile, 2002; Bechky, 2003; Subrahmanian et al, 2003; Howard- Grenville &amp; Carlile, 2006; Gal et al, 2008). Although boundary objects can be either abstract or material, they are most commonly understood as material objects. Yet, with a few exceptions, the IS literature has tended to neglect or downplay the implications of this materiality, focusing predominantly on the interpretive flexibility of boundary objects and their boundary-spanning role across communities (Zachry, 2008; Ewenstein &amp; Whyte, 2009; Star, 2010). We argue that a consideration of both the sociality and materiality of boundary objects is needed to answer questions about why various project-related artefacts are more (or less) effective as boundary objects, how their nature and shape as objects differs with the work and informational needs of the communities involved, and how boundary objects emerge in IS development practice (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005; Zachry, 2008; Ewenstein &amp; Whyte, 2009). Recently, there has been renewed interest in the ways in which ‘everyday organizing is inextricably bound up with materiality’ (Orlikowski, 2007, p. 1435). In particular, a number of authors have drawn on the notion of ‘sociomateriality’, a posthumanist perspective in which the traditional dualism of human actors inhabiting a world of separate material things is replaced by a mutually constitutive duality between what we call the social and the material (Pickering, 1995; Barad, 2003; Orlikowski, 2007). Such a perspective privileges neither human agent nor technology, but explores how organisational practices are constituted through sociomaterial agencies (Orlikowski &amp; Scott, 2008). Sociomateriality is associated with an increasing interest in objects in contemporary social theory (e.g. Pels et al, 2002; Engestrom &amp; Blackler, 2005), and the way objects emerge as sociomaterial configurations in everyday practice with particular social and material consequences (Orlikowski, 2007; Suchman, 2007). Given their common concern with objects, we believe that sociomateriality and boundary objects are complementary perspectives. Indeed, Star’s original conceptua- lisation of a boundary object, the materiality of which ‘derives from action, not from a sense of prefabricated stuff or “thing”-ness’ (Star, 2010, p. 603), shares an ontological foundation with sociomateriality. Based on our study, we propose that bringing together the current debate on sociomateriality and the literature on boundary objects produces new and richer insights, both theoretical and practical, into our understanding of artefacts in IS development, and in IS research more generally. In particular, utilising a sociomaterial perspective allows us to describe and render visible how various artefacts are able to act as boundary objects, an ability that otherwise tends to be ‘black-boxed’ or taken for granted (cf. Introna &amp; Hayes, 2011), how different actors <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> negotiate the circumstances of the production and use of such objects, and how IS development practice takes the sociomaterial form that it does. In this paper, we review how the concept of boundary objects has been applied to study design and development in IS and related fields, before introducing sociomateriality as a complementary perspective for understanding how boundary objects are incorporated in and through organisational practices. We illustrate the value of a combined approach that draws on both these theoretical perspectives using findings from a longitudinal case study of an IS development project in a large manufacturing organisation. We outline the methods used for data collection and analysis in the case study before presenting a brief case description. We then trace how a particular project-related artefact was constituted and reconstituted as a boundary object in IS development practices across multiple sites and times, with varying consequences. Finally, we discuss the contribution made by applying a sociomaterial perspective to the analysis of boundary objects, and its theoretical and practical implications.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="20" page="2" column="2">Boundary objects in IS development</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="2" column="2">Various project-related artefacts function as boundary objects between the heterogeneous groups and diverse knowledge domains involved in IS development. These objects are shared between groups, facilitating communication and coordination while maintaining the specific purposes, viewpoints and interests of each (Østerlund, 2008; Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010). Such objects offer a common focus or reference for the translation of knowledge without necessarily enforcing a particular shared meaning among project participants (Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004; Constantinides &amp; Barrett, 2006). For example, published representations of a solution design may be used to communicate design ideas, frame problems and allow collaborative problem solving, and coordinate the actions of various participating groups (Hendry, 2004; Ewenstein &amp; Whyte, 2009). They may also perform a contractual role in the IS project, for instance in defining the problem and solution boundaries (Gasson, 1999). Other examples of boundary objects in IS development include requirements specifications (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005; Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010) and project management tools such as status reporting tools or project timelines, which facilitate the temporal coordination of divergent interpretations of project progress (Yakura, 2002; Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004). While particular artefacts may be designated as boundary objects, they only become ‘boundary objects-in-use’ when they are meaningfully and usefully incorporated into the local practices of each group (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005). Both groups need to be able to contextualise the boundary object (Lee, 2007; Lutters &amp; Ackerman, 2007), so that it maintains a common identity in a joint field of practice or endeavour (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005), while acquiring more specific meanings and uses in each <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> group’s local practices. ‘At once temporal, based in action, subject to reflection and local tailoring’ (Star, 2010, p. 603), boundary objects are not necessarily stable or static (Carlile, 2002; Boujut &amp; Blanco, 2003; Gal et al, 2008), but may evolve or change as they are modified to address internal or external contingencies (Subrahmanian et al, 2003). Boundary objects perform a range of boundary- spanning functions. They enable knowledge transfer between groups through a shared syntax or schema with which knowledge is represented (Carlile, 2002, 2004). Their common structure and adaptability to different viewpoints also make boundary objects ‘a means of translation’ between groups and their perspectives (Star &amp; Griesemer, 1989, p. 393). Through them, the interpretive or semantic differences that exist or emerge over time between groups can be translated and accommo- dated (Carlile, 2002, 2004). Further, boundary objects can be involved in the translation of different concerns and interests (Star &amp; Griesemer, 1989; Carlile, 2004), by enlisting participation in the negotiation of shared understanding (Lee, 2007), aligning interests so that particular design knowledge is legitimised and followed (Bergman et al, 2007), or enabling groups to resolve conflicting interests by negotiating and transforming their knowledge and practice (Carlile, 2002, 2004). Boundary objects do not necessarily reflect consensus (Star &amp; Griesemer, 1989) and may involve the exercise of power relations (Boland &amp; Tenkasi, 1995; Bergman et al, 2007; Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010). While much of the literature on boundary objects emphasises their facil- itative roles in knowledge sharing and the coordination of expertise, such objects do not always function consistently, or even positively, across different sites (Carlile, 2002; Zachry, 2008). Indeed, ‘their characteristics are hard to sustain as problems and people change’ (Carlile, 2002, p. 452). A boundary object may not be able to span all knowledge boundaries equally effectively, or may perform different roles in different settings or over time (Swan et al, 2007; Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010). A number of studies have drawn attention to the material implications of boundary objects (Arias et al, 2000; Howard-Grenville &amp; Carlile, 2006; Gal et al, 2008; Østerlund, 2008; Jonsson et al, 2009), often in terms of ‘affordances’ – how the material disposition of an artefact or technology shapes the range of possible ways in which it can be used (Harr  ́, 2002). An artefact’s material properties afford different possibilities for action when a particular user acts in relation to them, based on how he or she perceives those properties and on the context within which the artefact is used. Thus, the same material properties may produce multiple and different affordances across different users or different contexts of use (Hutchby, 2001; Leonardi, 2011). While a consideration of the materiality of boundary objects has shed light on how the material properties of an artefact afford certain boundary-spanning practices, treating materiality as a distinct phenomenon obscures<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ways of seeing how it is intrinsic to the practices and relations in which such objects are constituted (Orlikowski &amp; Scott, 2008). From a sociomaterial perspective, the material and the social are viewed as inseparable and co-performed in everyday organisational practices (Pels et al, 2002; Orlikowski, 2007). For example, Østerlund (2008) considers how the materiality of a patient-tracking system not only afforded certain communicative practices between groups of health professionals but also constituted part of the actional field in which communication occurred and was negotiated. Sociomateriality ‘sensitizes us to a different set of issues and influences than we have tended to focus on’ (Orlikowski, 2007, p. 1445). It provides us with a vocabulary with which to articulate the emergent and performative nature of boundary objects, their multiplicity, and how they help constitute IS development as a sociomaterial practice, with both intended and unintended consequences. Moving beyond Østerlund’s (2008) focus on the production and reproduction of communicative practices, we now outline the ontological foundations and implications of a sociomateriality of boundary objects.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22" page="2" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="23" page="3" column="1">572</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24" page="3" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="3" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="3" column="2">Sociomateriality and boundary objects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="3" column="2">From a sociomaterial perspective, distinctions between humans and artefacts are not ontologically given, but are enacted in the performance of everyday practices in particular settings, at particular times and with varying effects (Barad, 2003; Suchman, 2007; Orlikowski, 2010). The result is the constitution of humans and artefacts as sociomaterial ‘assemblages’ (Suchman, 2007), ‘entangle- ments’ (Orlikowski, 2007), or ‘mangles’ (Pickering, 1995). Such terms are an attempt to indicate the inherent inseparability of the social and the material in everyday life (Latour, 1991; Bloomfield, 1995; Law &amp; Mol, 1995). Human action is not just dependent on materiality and material artefacts, but is constituted by them. Organisational practices, such as IS development, are thus sociomaterial practices. Rather than being an attribute of either humans or their technical artefacts, agency is reconfigured as a capacity for action realised through the constitutive sociomaterial entanglement of the two (Barad, 2003; Orlikowski, 2007, 2010; Suchman, 2007). Barad (2003) uses the term ‘intra-action’ (as distinct from interaction) to describe the way that sociomaterial agency emerges from the performance of these relations. It is through the specific sociomaterial intra-actions of an ‘apparatus’ or sociomaterial practice that an observed phenomenon or ‘object’ is performed, and that the boundaries and properties of its social or material ‘components’ become determinate and meaningful. The contours of this sociomaterial agency can never be completely mapped out in advance. The entanglement of humans and artefacts is ‘temporally emergent’ (Pickering, 1995). Sociomaterial apparatuses are constantly shifting and evolving, ‘reconfigured y in the real time of <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> practice’ (Pickering, 1995, p. 20) to address obstacles encountered or solve new problems. Pickering refers to the continual revision of human intentions and the material artefact in response to resistances and opposi- tions in the achievement of intended performances as a ‘dialectic of resistance and accommodation’ (1995, p. 22). Similarly, the emphasis on the performativity of sociomaterial relations in practice (Pickering, 1995; Barad, 2003) implies that sociomaterial assemblages are (re)produced differently across different times, places and participants. Rather than fixed human–artefact relations, what results is a multiplicity of diverse assemblages, with a range of sociomaterial agencies (Suchman, 2007). We propose that sociomateriality has five implications for how we understand boundary objects. First, boundary objects do not exist independently of the sociomaterial practices in which they are located. They are ‘dynamic sociomaterial configuration[s] performed in practice’ (Orlikowski, 2010, p. 136). Object and practice are mutually constitutive, so that an object is both produced in practice and configures this practice in particular ways (Orlikowski, 2007). Second, as sociomaterial configurations or assemblages, boundary objects are not static, but dynamic and open, emerging temporally in practice. An object’s ability to span knowledge boundaries between social worlds is not determinate. Rather, the construction and use of a boundary object is an open-ended process of ‘becoming’ (Pickering, 2003), involving the possibility of future adjustments and reconfigurations as either obstacles in the integration of knowledge across different groups are encountered or new directions for extensions are explored (Pickering, 1995). Third, the usefulness of a boundary object is neither inherent in its material properties nor exclusive to the intentionality of human agency, but arises from the sociomaterial agency that is realised in the constitutive entanglement of the two. The affordances of a boundary object are the possibilities for action that result from the performance of sociomaterial relations between particular users and the materiality of an artefact. That is, affordances and ‘the material resistances of objects are inseparable from the arrangements through which they materialize in practice’ (Suchman, 2005, p. 381). Fourth, a boundary object is performed differently across different occasions, sites of use and associated practices (Suchman, 2005). Each performance represents a particular sociomaterial configuration or assemblage, involving different participants with different histories and different relations to the artefact (Suchman, 2007). These diverse assemblages produce different sociomaterial agencies that support possibilities for action, but may also subvert actors’ intentionalities (Introna &amp; Hayes, 2011), so that a boundary object performs in different ways across time and space. Different performances constitute communication, translation and knowledge sharing in particular ways, with varying consequences that are social and material, intended and unintended.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Fifth, diverse assemblages or performances of a boundary object imply a multiplicity of co-existing, related but different objects, each enacted in different ways in multiple practices comprising different contexts and sets of relations (Mol, 1999; Law &amp; Singleton, 2005). Rather than a single underlying object that is interpreted flexibly by different groups, multiple boundary objects are performed and come into being in specific sociomaterial practices. This helps to explain how a boundary object can be recognisable as a common object between different groups, while its local meaning and use are tailored within each group (Star, 2010). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> summarises key concepts drawn from the literature on boundary objects, together with the implications of sociomateriality for boundary objects outlined above. A sociomaterial perspective supports and extends our understanding of boundary objects by encouraging us to explore such objects as diverse and shifting assemblages, multiply performed in specific sociomaterial practices. While the concept of boundary objects explains the what, where and when of boundary-spanning communication and collaboration across diverse knowledge domains, we suggest that sociomateriality provides a vocabulary and theoretical apparatus that can help us to explain how and why boundary objects emerge and evolve in practice and achieve their effects in particular times and places. For example, while we know that boundary objects are capable of performing different roles in different settings (Barrett &amp; Oborn, 2010), we need to understand how a particular artefact is an effective boundary object in one setting but is less effective in another time and place, or how it can be used for knowledge sharing at one stage but as a political instrument at another (Carlile, 2002). In the next part of the paper, we illustrate the value of adding a sociomaterial perspective to the analysis of boundary objects using findings from an IS development case study. Following Suchman’s (2007) call to make sociomaterial assemblages the object of analysis, we follow the ‘life’ (Engestrom &amp; Blackler, 2005) of a particular project-related artefact, a solution prototype, through this project and its performance as a boundary object in the sociomaterial practices of IS development.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="30" page="3" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="31" page="4" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="4" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="33" page="4" column="1">573</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="37" page="4" column="2">Research method</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" page="4" column="2">The analysis presented in this paper is based on a longitudinal interpretive case study of IS development in AlphaCo (a pseudonym), a large multinational manufacturing company based in New Zealand. The project studied involved commercial package acquisition, outsourced solution development (by SoftCo, a pseudonym), and a range of internal and external stakeholders and participants. The project was followed by the second author for 2 years from June 2005 to July 2007, comprising an initial 8-month period of on-site field work with repeated follow-up visits to the company in subsequent years. During this time, she was co-located <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> with the AlphaCo project team and participated in the research setting without directly performing functional project activities. In total, 558 h were spent on site combining participant observation with semi-structured interviews and document review (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). This included ‘hands-on’ examination and operation of a prototype of the new solution created by the AlphaCo project manager, as well as observation of the prototype’s use by different individuals and groups in various project activities. The longitudinal approach enabled observation of IS development processes in action as they unfolded, while extended interaction with the project participants provided insight into local meanings, knowledge and practices (Westrup, 1993; Walsham, 1995; Nandhakumar &amp; Jones, 1997). A comprehensive thematic analysis (Braun &amp; Clarke, 2006) was conducted on the data collected from field notes, interview and meeting transcripts, emails, and various project and organisational documents. Data were read and re-read multiple times, categorised and compared across themes that emerged around aspects of the project content, particular IS development processes, the actors involved and their interactions, and contextual properties and conditions. Chronological order and temporal relativity of the data were maintained throughout the data analysis. This facilitated the identification and description of key events and activities within the project, which provided the structure for a case study narrative, which drew on the various themes identified in the data analysis and portrayed how IS development in the project studied unfolded over time (McLeod, 2008).<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The initial analysis was subsequently re-visited by both authors to understand how project-related artefacts were implicated in the IS development. In re-reading the case study narrative, we looked for instances where some kind of ‘breaking down’ was observed in project activities so that a particular artefact became visible or ‘present-at- hand’ (Winograd &amp; Flores, 1997, p. 36). Relevant data from across a range of project events, participants and sources were then re-analysed using concepts drawn from the literatures on boundary objects and sociomateriality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>). Particular attention was given to examining the material artefact in its various versions, identifying each occasion and site of its use, including the practice within which it was used and the project participants interacting with it, and analysing its material properties, the boundary-spanning functions it performed and any observable effects on project activities. The result was an account of each project-related artefact that traced its multiple performances as a boundary object over time and space and identified the sociomaterial consequences, both intended and unintended. While a range of artefacts were analysed, in this paper we focus on a particular artefact that formed a prototype of the new solution used by various internal and external project participants, in a range of activities, for multiple purposes, throughout much of the project. Prototypes are one of a range of material artefacts used with contemporary IS development as simulations to explore design possibilities, as a basis for development (where the prototype becomes the system through progressive itera- tions), or as a formal specification of future system behaviour (Grønbæk, 1990). The prototype analysed here<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> resembles the latter in that it served as a (partial or complete) representation of the ‘contractual’ description of the system being produced (Subrahmanian et al, 2003). Prototypes and their associated practices are interesting from a sociomaterial perspective as they reflect a shift from abstract specifications to ‘directly embodying the design’ (Suchman et al, 2002, p. 166) in a concrete way (Carlile, 2002). In the following section we provide a brief overview of the case study, including where the prototype was used. We then present the findings of our analysis of how the prototype was performed as a boundary object in various activities in the IS development process.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="39" page="4" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="40" page="5" column="1">574</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="5" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="5" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="43" page="5" column="1">Table 1 Boundary objects and sociomateriality</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="5">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Concept or implication</th>
                  <th class="table"> Key references</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Key concepts on boundary objects</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects facilitate cooperation between intersecting communities by maintaining a</td>
                  <td class="table"> Star (2010)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> common identity while satisfying the informational needs of each</td>
                  <td class="table"> Star &amp; Griesemer (1989)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects require a joint field and incorporation into local practice to become boundary</td>
                  <td class="table"> Levina &amp; Vaast (2005)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> objects-in-use</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects are subject to change, rather than being stable and static</td>
                  <td class="table"> Carlile (2002)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Subrahmanian et al (2003)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects enable knowledge transfer and the translation of meaning and interests, but</td>
                  <td class="table"> Carlile (2002, 2004)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> their boundary-spanning effectiveness or role may vary across settings or time</td>
                  <td class="table"> Star &amp; Griesemer (1989)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects have material aspects that afford or constrain boundary-spanning practices</td>
                  <td class="table"> Howard-Grenville &amp; Carlile (2006)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Østerlund (2008)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Implications from sociomateriality</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects are constituted in and constitute sociomaterial practices</td>
                  <td class="table"> Orlikowski (2007, 2010)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects are temporally emergent, reconfigured in practice in response to encountered</td>
                  <td class="table"> Pickering (1995)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> resistances</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> The agency of a boundary object is produced through the constitutive sociomaterial entanglement</td>
                  <td class="table"> Barad (2003)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> of actor and artefact</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> A boundary object may be performed differently across multiple sites, times, practices and</td>
                  <td class="table"> Suchman (2007)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> participants, with varying effects</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Rather than a singular boundary object, multiple boundary objects are performed in specific</td>
                  <td class="table"> Law &amp; Singleton (2005)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> sociomaterial practices</td>
                  <td class="table"> Mol (1999)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="44" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Concept or implication Key references Key concepts on boundary objects Boundary objects facilitate cooperation between intersecting communities by maintaining a Star (2010) common identity while satisfying the informational needs of each Star &amp; Griesemer (1989) Boundary objects require a joint field and incorporation into local practice to become boundary Levina &amp; Vaast (2005) objects-in-use Boundary objects are subject to change, rather than being stable and static Carlile (2002) Subrahmanian et al (2003) Boundary objects enable knowledge transfer and the translation of meaning and interests, but Carlile (2002, 2004) their boundary-spanning effectiveness or role may vary across settings or time Star &amp; Griesemer (1989) Boundary objects have material aspects that afford or constrain boundary-spanning practices Howard-Grenville &amp; Carlile (2006) Østerlund (2008) Implications from sociomateriality Boundary objects are constituted in and constitute sociomaterial practices Orlikowski (2007, 2010) Boundary objects are temporally emergent, reconfigured in practice in response to encountered Pickering (1995) resistances The agency of a boundary object is produced through the constitutive sociomaterial entanglement Barad (2003) of actor and artefact A boundary object may be performed differently across multiple sites, times, practices and Suchman (2007) participants, with varying effects Rather than a singular boundary object, multiple boundary objects are performed in specific Law &amp; Singleton (2005) sociomaterial practices Mol (1999)</region>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="49" page="5" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50" page="6" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="51" page="6" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="52" page="6" column="1">575</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="53" page="6" column="1">Table 2 Data collection methods Observation Project activities Activities were observed around project management, use of a solution prototype in the project, Request for Information (RFI) document preparation, vendor engagement and evaluation, solution development, testing and delivery, and client–developer interactions Formal meetings All but one of 37 formal meetings (47 h) were observed, including project manager interviews, vendor meetings and demonstrations, AlphaCo project team meetings, project meetings with the external developers, and development tool and solution training sessions Field notes Seven A5 notebooks (each with 200 leaves) of field notes were produced Audio recording Recordings were made (with permission) of selected project meetings, activities and informal conversations, and transcribed in part or in full</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="54" page="6" column="1">Interviews Semi-structured interviews Thirty-three interviews (totalling 24 h; average 45 min) were conducted with 16 participants, including: AlphaCo project team: external project manager, business analysts (2), IS architect, business managers (2) AlphaCo IS staff: IS Project Office (3), IS managers (2), IS analysts (2) SoftCo external development team: project manager, senior developers (2) Interview guide Interviews were structured around the interviewee’s organisational role, involvement/interest in project, perspective on organisational events and activities, and experiences of IS development in their organisation. Interviews were further customised to particular interviewees based on their role in the project, the project stage, procedural matters and issues arising Audio recording Interviews were recorded (with permission) where possible and transcribed in full (otherwise extensive field notes were taken) Document review Project-related emails Emails were available as a data source through the field researcher’s inclusion in the AlphaCo project emailing list AlphaCo project documentation Project documentation reviewed included outsourcing contract models and documents, external project manager terms of reference, a solution prototype and its documentation, RFI document, vendor RFI responses and product information, vendor evaluation reports, project deliverables (e.g. concept document, project definition, feasibility reports, project plan, closure report), monthly progress and update reports, and project self-assessment report SoftCo project documentation Review of the external developer’s project documents included project costings, project meeting agendas and minutes, task allocation plan, issues register, training manuals, solution documentation, and software license agreement AlphaCo organisational documentation Organisational documentation reviewed included IS process documents, IS project life cycle, project tracking system, IS policy framework, IS strategic and business plans, IS quality standards and governance, project management standards, organisational restructuring documents, staff intranet, company internal magazine and annual reports Public documents Over 100 articles on AlphaCo and its IS function published in newspapers, industry magazines and on the Internet were reviewed</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="6" column="2">Case description</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="6" column="2">AlphaCo relies on information technology (IT) to maintain its global competitiveness. The IS function (around 200 employees) combines IS shared services with distributed support teams in various business units. A major process improvement initiative included the creation of a digital repository of its documented IS processes. An IS Project Office provides support for IS project management processes, including an IS project life cycle. AlphaCo IS has adopted various ‘guiding principles’, which advocate, for example, the acquisition of packaged software rather than its internal development. <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> In 2004, IT infrastructure and services across AlphaCo were outsourced to a global IT provider. Ongoing evaluation and management of contract performance was performed by the IT outsourcing contract management (ITOCM) team, using ad hoc spreadsheet models they had developed to evaluate the initial contract bids. Because these models were difficult and time consuming to maintain, and did not afford the complex analysis and reporting desired, the ITOCM team proposed migrat- ing the models to a more dynamic database solution with additional functionality. In late 2004, a new IS development project was initiated to do this. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> depicts the project as a trajectory of (sometimes overlapping) episodes, and indicates the project activities in which the prototype was implicated. From the outset, the project was perceived as relatively small and well defined, with no major threats to project delivery within a planned 6-month time frame. Consis- tent with previous projects, an external project manager, Frank, was hired in May 2005. While he lacked formal project management experience, Frank had the financial analysis skills required to understand the project. The core of the AlphaCo project team comprised Frank and two ITOCM business analysts: Claire, who had developed the original spreadsheet models, and Gary, the intended main user of the new database solution (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>). In defining the requirements for the new solution, Frank constructed a prototype that rationalised the original spreadsheet models for subsequent solution development. In July 2005, an Request for Information (RFI) document was sent to six AlphaCo preferred suppliers of packaged software solutions. A copy of the prototype was also provided as part of the vendor engagement process. Only one of the vendors contacted, VendorOne (a pseudonym), had a suitable product, conducting a product demonstration in August 2005. In the absence of any alternatives, the AlphaCo project team pursued one<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> of the VendorOne products, with month-long negotiations to find an acceptable pricing option. During this time, Frank contacted an AlphaCo subsidiary using the product to ascertain their experience of it, only to discover that they were replacing it with a software application from another vendor, SoftCo, a small firm of external development and implementation consultants. Interested in providing a choice in vendors, Frank contacted SoftCo, who demonstrated their product in late September. After evaluating both products, SoftCo was hired in October 2005 to supply MDS (a pseudonym), a multi-dimensional database and online analytical processing (OLAP) tool, and develop the desired database solution. SoftCo’s main development team comprised the project manager, Marie, and two senior developers, Nancy and Ross (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>). The delays in identifying a suitable package vendor, together with an expected year-end 2005 project comple- tion date, meant that solution development proceeded within a tight time frame. Work on the solution began immediately, without the detailed project definition that SoftCo normally undertook in a project, and concur- rently with the formal project planning phase of AlphaCo’s IS project life cycle. The SoftCo developers relied on the prototype for developing an understanding of the requirements and in building the MDS solution. Solution development involved iterative cycles of building, testing and amendment to the emerging solution. Development quickly fell behind schedule, project mile- stones were revised and the prototype became implicated in negotiations around the scope of contracted project work. While a largely completed solution was available by the end of 2005, final testing was delayed due to the departure of Frank (who had only been contracted until the end of 2005 and had secured new work elsewhere) and ongoing problems within the solution and with data integrity. It was not until June 2006 that the project was<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> formally closed off with SoftCo, and a fully functional MDS solution was available for transfer to AlphaCo’s networked environment.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="58" page="6" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="59" page="7" column="1">576</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="60" page="7" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="61" page="7" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="62" page="7" column="1">Episodes Project Project Vendor commencement definition engagement Feb Jun July Nov 2005 2005 2005 2005 Prototype Vendor creation understanding Activities of project Solution Developer requirements understanding definition of requirements</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="63" page="7" column="1">Figure 1 Chronology of project episodes and activities involving the prototype.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="67" page="7" column="2">Solution development Project Solution planning implementation Dec Jan Jun 2005 2006 2006 Solution build Project work negotiations</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="70" page="7" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="71" page="8" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="72" page="8" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="73" page="8" column="1">577</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="74" page="8" column="1">Table 3</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="75" page="8" column="1">Project participants appearing in the case analysis Position Role in project</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx76">
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="3" page="8">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Organisation</th>
                  <th class="table"> Participant</th>
                  <th class="table"></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> AlphaCo</td>
                  <td class="table"> Frank</td>
                  <td class="table"> Project manager</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Claire</td>
                  <td class="table"> ITOCM business analyst</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Gary</td>
                  <td class="table"> ITOCM business analyst</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> SoftCo</td>
                  <td class="table"> Leon</td>
                  <td class="table"> Vendor representative</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Marie</td>
                  <td class="table"> Project manager</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Nancy</td>
                  <td class="table"> Senior developer</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Ross</td>
                  <td class="table"> Senior developer</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> VendorOne</td>
                  <td class="table"> Jack</td>
                  <td class="table"> Vendor representative</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="77" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Organisation Participant AlphaCo Frank Project manager Claire ITOCM business analyst Gary ITOCM business analyst SoftCo Leon Vendor representative Marie Project manager Nancy Senior developer Ross Senior developer VendorOne Jack Vendor representative</region>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="79" page="8" column="1">Case analysis</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" page="8" column="1">In presenting our analysis of the prototype, we focus on its production and performance as a boundary object in defining solution requirements, vendor understanding of the project task, the external developers’ understanding of solution requirements, building the MDS solution, and negotiating the scope of project work ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Creating a prototype The ad hoc and incremental development of the original spreadsheet models used to model the IT outsourcing contract had resulted in a large, cumbersome and complex set of around 20 Excel spreadsheet workbooks (14GB in size and containing over 1 million formulae) that lacked structure and internal consistency. Frank, the external project manager, was tasked with extracting the data from these using Visual Basic scripts, and rationalis- ing the data into a single Excel workbook (referred to by participants as ‘the database’ file) in the correct formats for uploading into a new database solution. At the same time, Frank reviewed and documented the original models, as he explained in a project progress report, in order ‘to gain understanding of how the various spread- sheets pull together to construct the outcome reports and models’. This would assist him to understand the requirements for a new solution and draft an RFI document. To facilitate his understanding and validate the extracted data against the original spreadsheet models, Frank constructed what he called a ‘prototype front-end’ in Excel. This prototype front-end ran off the database file and reproduced the calculations, reports and scenario modelling capability of an ‘evaluation’ function of the original spreadsheet models, as well as some basic calculations and summary reports for a regular ‘scorecard’ reporting function. The prototype front-end did not<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> completely replicate this latter, scorecard, function as its use was still evolving in the ITOCM team’s work and Frank assumed that additional reports could be easily added in any eventual new solution. The understanding that Frank developed in construct- ing the database file and prototype front-end was the performative outcome of a sociomaterial assemblage constituted by his extended interaction with the original spreadsheet models, his existing expertise with spreadsheet modelling and scripting languages, and the material specificity of the spreadsheet technology he was working with. Claire, the creator of the original models had spent only a short time explaining them to Frank, instead advising him that, as Frank put it, ‘the best way to learn or understand the model is to get in there and try it for yourself’. However, multiple versions of the original models had been created historically in order to model various scenarios, each with subtle differences that were not always documented. Frank worked with only one of these versions so that, as Claire noted in an interview, there were ‘elements of it that Frank was aware of, but didn’t have a full understanding of’. The spreadsheet technology Frank was using afforded him certain possibilities for prototyping, such as using spreadsheet pivot tables to simulate the data relationships in an envisaged multidimensional database solution. However, Frank was unable to simulate an additional functionality desired by the ITOCM team that would enable a new solution to dynamically reflect changes in AlphaCo’s IT environment over the life of the outsourcing contract. Frank resorted to producing a document that he later introduced to the SoftCo developers in a project meeting as containing a set of ‘rules and calculations y [that] take you through how I think it’ll work’. In this more abstract form, the ‘business rules’ were conceptual and untested rather than demonstrable in a concrete or tangible way (Carlile, 2002). Together, the database file, the prototype front-end and the business rules constituted a solution prototype – a material artefact capable of performing a range of possible futures for the new<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> solution when incorporated into particular development practices, rather than representing a complete and literal specification of the requisite functionality.<marker type="block"/> Defining solution requirements Frank circulated the prototype to members of the ITOCM team to check its accuracy and to establish that he had correctly understood the requirements for the new solution, asking them in an email, ‘Is [it] giving you the sort of information you are looking for? Anything we pick up now will help ensure that the database is constructed with the correct data relationships’. Only Claire and Gary provided any feedback to Frank, although, busy with their organisational roles, their work with the prototype was individual, cursory and partial. Claire focused on the evaluation function part of the front-end ‘very briefly to check that it looked alright’, pointing out several additional features that Frank later incorporated, while Gary was interested primarily in the scorecard function that he had used in the original models. Both Claire and Gary concluded that Frank’s prototype adequately resembled and was thus identical in content to the original models, although Gary later acknowledged that: ‘We should’ve been a little more involved. When Frank put together his version, I think possibly we should’ve run through that ourselves together’. The prototype was a ‘designated’ boundary object (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005), in the sense that Frank intended it to be used to span the semantic boundary between his understanding as the external project manager and that of the ITOCM team. It provided a common schema with which to articulate particular functionality or solution requirements. As the main users of the original models and of any future solution, Claire and Gary were intended by Frank to interact with the prototype in a particular way in order to verify his interpretation of the original models and the solution requirements. However, they did not engage to any meaningful extent in the joint practices around it that Frank proposed, suggesting that reviewing the prototype appeared to have little relevance for them at this point in the project (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005; Star, 2010). Rather than translating meaning between Frank and the ITOCM team, reviewing the prototype served a more symbolic purpose (Swan et al, 2007) as a necessary project task. From a sociomaterial perspective, the outcome of the various participants’ use of the prototype reflects the different assemblages within which it was incorporated. In each performance, the resultant sociomaterial agency was different, producing different social and material consequences for the project. That Claire and Gary did not engage with the prototype to the extent intended meant that various errors, omissions or oversights made by Frank remained undetected. Frank mentioned at one point, ‘It’s exactly the same data y same rules, same everything’. All three participants’ acceptance of the prototype as a legitimate representation of the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> original models meant that the prototype was no longer needed as a boundary object to share understanding of the solution requirements. Frank gained authority in terms of project knowledge (Bechky, 2003), becoming, in effect, an internal AlphaCo actor. The legitimacy of the prototype also introduced a new design artefact that could (and would) substitute for the original models in subsequent solution development work. As the materi- alisation of Frank’s translation of the solution requirements (Gasson, 2006), any assumptions, simplifications or deficiencies in the prototype had the potential to affect solution development through its incorporation in other sociomaterial practices in the project.<marker type="block"/> Vendor understanding of the project task Frank distributed a copy of the prototype to prospective vendors as part of the RFI process to transfer knowledge and translate understanding of the solution requirements; as Frank explained, ‘So they knew what sort of thing was expected’. The digital form of much of the prototype meant that different versions could be created; in this case, with ‘dummy data’ for the vendors. The prototype provided a more tangible and usable representation of the required data relationships specified in the written RFI document. Jack, the VendorOne representative, used the prototype to gain an understanding of what AlphaCo was trying to achieve, and in discussing aspects of the solution requirements with Frank. Jack also used it as a basis for building a simple model to demonstrate the capabilities of various VendorOne products, although Frank noted that there were discrepancies in Jack’s interpretation. According to Jack, the prototype offered him a reference point for defining the project task, as ‘replicating some of that [prototype] logic’, and the project boundaries, as ‘everything that would be in scope in that spreadsheet you’ve given us’. These definitional issues would re-emerge in SoftCo’s solution development. Leon, the lead SoftCo representative, similarly used the prototype to gain an understanding of the solution requirements and to build a simple demonstration model in MDS. During a SoftCo product demonstration he noted that, ‘That prototype in Excel ... is a really good place to start’. Leon seemed to focus on the tangible and accessible spreadsheet components of the prototype, rather than the more abstract business rules. Certainly, as he explained in another SoftCo product demonstration, he was used to ‘tak[ing] existing Excel models that people have got ... and translat[ing] them back into MDS models’. According to one of the SoftCo developers, Ross, ‘[Leon had] seen the prototype front-end, but didn’t realise that AlphaCo didn’t do the business rules functionality in there. It would have been better if [he had]’. Keen to secure AlphaCo as a new major client, Leon confidently proposed a short solution development time to the AlphaCo project team: ‘From what I saw from your prototype, y two weeks’. In doing so, he consider- ably underestimated the complexity of the project and the financial modelling involved.<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Leon’s underestimation of the task complexity suggests that his engagement with the prototype was less than fully effective in bridging the semantic knowledge boundary around understanding the solution requirements. AlphaCo’s expectations of a relatively straightforward solution development process were confirmed, and SoftCo became committed to a very tight project time frame and budget, with which the SoftCo development team subsequently struggled. Marie, the SoftCo project manager, emphasised in a project meeting: ‘I always said we could never do it in this time for the money’. From a sociomaterial perspective, these consequences were the effects of a particular performance of the prototype as a boundary object involving Leon, within the situated practices of product demonstration and making a sales pitch, and subject to the prevailing constraints of time and place, not to mention an explicit agenda in securing a new client. When reflecting on the project, Claire was sceptical that ‘a salesman [could] come in and go, “Yeah, it’ll take five minutes” ... [when] it was actually a very complex model’.<marker type="block"/> External developer understanding of the solution requirements The outsourced development of the new solution meant that SoftCo depended on knowledge sharing with the AlphaCo project team to understand the problem domain and solution requirements. Given the tight project time frame, the perceived straightforward nature of the development task, and the availability of the prototype, SoftCo did not perform a detailed project definition as they had done in other projects. Instead, solution development commenced immediately and the prototype became an important object for bridging the boundary between the AlphaCo project team’s domain- specific knowledge and the SoftCo developers’ technical knowledge of the MDS development tool and its possibilities. The familiar Excel format and functionality of the main part of the prototype, together with the calculations and rules of financial modelling, provided a common schema able to be understood by both groups, so that knowledge could be transferred. While Frank had intended the prototype to be used for discussing the solution requirements with the SoftCo developers, the tight project time frame restricted the extent to which this occurred. Instead, as Nancy, the second SoftCo developer, explained, the developers acquired much of their understanding ‘by spending a lot of time in the prototype frontend y and trying to map that back to the database file that Frank gave us’. The prototype’s material form allowed the developers to take it offsite and work independently of the AlphaCo project team. It also provided an artefact that the developers could focus on and work with in a very tangible way (Carlile, 2002). In Marie’s view, ‘If you get given an Excel sheet ... then you can follow through how things fit together y If you give me something, I can see that y It’s always best just to have it there’. While the developers<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> looked at the RFI document, the capacity of the spreadsheet-based prototype to demonstrate data relationships (compared with the RFI document) condi- tioned the developers’ understanding when the prototype was incorporated into their development practices. The SoftCo developers were more comfortable ‘mimicking’ (Bechky, 2003) the prototype than building to the specifications defined in the RFI document, which ‘in some instances, was very vague’, according to Marie. For example, the developers’ focus on the prototype meant that their understanding of the scorecard-reporting function was based on the abridged version the prototype contained, rather than the larger and more complex function anticipated by AlphaCo. The prototype provided what AlphaCo considered to be a more usable and understandable representation of the original models. According to their creator, Claire, ‘In the format that the original models were in, it would’ve made absolutely no sense to [the developers]’. The intentional deployment of the prototype for this purpose presumed a need for such an object and a role for AlphaCo in providing it to the developers. The emphasis placed on its use privileged the knowledge claims of AlphaCo (as translated by Frank) rather than the SoftCo developers, who had not conducted their usual problem definition, and reinforced the legitimacy of the representation that the prototype provided (Bechky, 2003). In fact, for a long time, the developers were unaware of the existence of the original spreadsheet models. The SoftCo developers’ understanding of the solution requirements was a productive consequence of the performance of the sociomaterial assemblage constituted by their interaction with the prototype within the constraints of time and place. According to Frank, ‘I don’t think they really had a good grasp of the model when they started developing y It’s such a tight deliverable ... they had to start developing straight away’. In addition, much of the contract terminology was unfamiliar to the developers. For example, Ross com- mented in an interview, ‘It wasn’t a normal standard accounting application y We kind of lost the week on that’. Similarly, some meanings and definitions, while tacitly known to the AlphaCo project team, were not specified in the prototype, so that the developers’ understanding was not always correct or as complete as it would have been if Frank had been involved in the assemblage; as Frank observed, ‘they just missed some of the finer points of it’. Even after completing the MDS solution, the developers did not have a full understanding of how some aspects of the data worked, so that Ross, reflecting on one aspect of the MDS solution, noted: ‘The data is in the solution and it’s sitting there y but I still don’t know what it does!’<marker type="block"/> Building the MDS solution Solution building was an iterative process involving the construction of various elements in MDS by the<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> SoftCo developers, the testing of these against the prototype by Frank and Gary to check that the developers had translated the prototype models correctly, discussion of the validity of the developers’ translation and negotiation of potential problems, followed by any necessary amendment of the emerging solution by the SoftCo developers. During this process, the prototype had sufficient common identity to both project teams to act as a reference point in coordinating the various tasks. SoftCo generally understood their work in building a solution as ‘translating’ an existing client application into MDS. In this case, the availability of the prototype reinforced this understanding of their role, so that solution development was framed by Marie as ‘decon- structing it [the prototype], interpreting it and rebuilding it in MDS’. The prototype served as an object of evaluation (Østerlund, 2008), the material focus of the developers’ attention and consideration, which they made the basis for solution development – ‘the actual model that we had to replicate’, as Marie put it. In the practice of testing the emerging MDS solution, different actors’ use of the prototype produced different sociomaterial agencies. As its creator, the agency produced by Frank’s interaction with the prototype was more effective in resolving issues arising from the developers’ translation of the prototype than when the testing was performed by Gary, who lacked familiarity with the evaluation function of the solution. Although the continual amendments to the emerging solution that resulted from the testing were frustrating for Frank and Gary, the SoftCo developers considered that these were inevitable given that aspects of the design problem and development task were, according to Ross, ‘very unstruc- tured and going to take time’. Indeed, an incremental approach involving ‘learning through doing’ (Gasson, 1999) was the developers’ preferred approach to solution development, and one they had followed in other projects. As Nancy explained, they felt that it suited the nature of the MDS tool: ‘You just build it yourself and try and learn from the thing. It’s not a very structured thing y It’s just the way it works’. Other required amendments were the result of material errors, oversights or omissions in the prototype. While the AlphaCo project team considered the prototype to be an accurate translation of the original spreadsheet models created by Claire, the SoftCo staff believed that there were ‘differences’ between the two versions. Marie, the SoftCo project manager, noted that there appeared to be ‘areas where Frank y and Claire had understood it differently’. The SoftCo developers felt that they would have developed a fuller understanding of the solution requirements and saved time if they had had direct access to the original models and their creator. According to Nancy, Claire could have highlighted ‘all the quirks and all the problems’ inherent in the historical development of the models. Thus, the artefact intended to bridge the knowledge boundary between AlphaCo and SoftCo was<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> perceived by Nancy as inhibiting boundary spanning: ‘Frank thought he was making it easier for us, however I believe it caused more problems’. The most complex part of the proposed solution was the new dynamic functionality, the intended behaviour of which Frank had defined in the business rules, but which required a substantially completed database solution before it could be tested fully. The developers worked with these rules to understand how they func- tioned and could be translated into MDS, although that knowledge was incrementally developed over time, with Ross noting that ‘We’d come to an understanding but it wasn’t quite right’. Some rules had not been fully defined or did not operate as intended, requiring Frank to re-write them or write additional rules. As a boundary object, the business rules component of the prototype was thus relatively open, being modified on several occasions to accommodate the shifting understandings of solution requirements before, in Nancy’s words, ‘actually coming to that point of everyone knowing exactly how it’s supposed to work’. The temporal emergence of the business rules component of the prototype was the result of its incorporation into joint development practices and its reconfiguration in response to the problems encountered in implementing the new functionality (Pickering, 1995).<marker type="block"/> Negotiating the scope of project work As the deadline for solution delivery approached, Marie became increasingly concerned about the extent of the changes to the emerging solution being requested by the AlphaCo team. Faced with what she saw as escalat- ing project scope and costs, Marie began classifying changes as either necessary amendments or new work. This culminated in a formal project meeting to debate whether the changes were ‘out-of-scope’ of the original project specification. As a published representation of the solution design, the prototype was used as a boundary object in these negotiations. Appeals to it reflected an acceptance and acknowledgement of its existence as a material object, a tangible resource that could be drawn upon in communicating and furthering interests in the definition of solution boundaries and legitimate project work. Although the prototype was a common reference point mobilised by both parties, its meaning was enacted differently by the two parties, particularly in relation to the project’s ‘original spec[ification]’. SoftCo staff understood their role in the project to be ‘replicating’ the prototype, which for them was the ‘original spec’, an interpretation that they relied on as a contractual reference point, with Nancy arguing in the project meeting, ‘You said exactly like the prototype, and that’s how we basically defined it’. In contrast, the AlphaCo project team understood the ‘original spec’ as the functionality required for a database solution as specified in the RFI document. As Claire countered in the project meeting, ‘That’s always been in the RFI y it’s always had the functionality’. For AlphaCo, the<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> prototype was intended primarily as an aid for development. The different interests of the two parties constituted a pragmatic boundary that needed to be bridged in order to reach an acceptable alternative understanding that allowed collaboration to continue (Carlile, 2002, 2004). In resolving these differences, the prototype was used by both parties to represent their knowledge of the solution requirements and how to achieve them, to recognise the consequences of each other’s domain- specific knowledge, and then to transform their respective knowledge to create a new joint practice that would enable them to continue to work effectively together in developing the solution (Carlile, 2004; Swan et al, 2007). This required establishing a common interest in completing the project, something both parties were aware of. Marie later reflected in an interview, ‘[Otherwise] you get nowhere. Like Claire said, we’ve all got to get to a “happy place”’. For example, completing the scorecard-reporting function in the new solution had become contentious. Rather than the relatively straightforward ‘add-on’ that SoftCo had understood from the abridged version contained in the prototype, the actual scorecard-reporting function requested by AlphaCo towards the end of the project contained a significantly increased number of reports with varying layouts and involving more complicated data manipulation. Rather than being ‘just copies of another sheet’ as initially envisaged by Gary, the main user of the scorecard function in the original models, reproducing each report actually required a large amount of code to be written by the developers. This led Marie to argue, in the project meeting held to discuss the ‘out-of- scope’ issues, that ‘With the original spec [prototype], we got a one-pager ... [Now] it’s a model in itself’. The AlphaCo project team acknowledged the negative consequences of this, with Gary pointing out to his colleagues, ‘I can see what they’re saying ... [What] we gave them last week, is a lot bigger than the original [prototype] version’. For their part, SoftCo conceded that they had misunderstood how data were fed into the scorecard reports. Both parties transformed their knowledge of the solution requirements, changing the content of the prototype to accommodate the enlarged specification of the scorecard-reporting function, and, as Marie put it, ‘com[ing] to an arrangement’ in which the cost of its development was split between the two parties. From a sociomaterial perspective, the different performances of the prototype as a boundary object produced particular understandings of the solution specifications for the SoftCo and AlphaCo project teams. Each team’s knowledge was ‘localised, embedded and invested in practice’ (Carlile, 2002, p. 445) and in their interaction with the prototype. Bridging the pragmatic boundary constituted by the conflicting interests that these different understandings under- pinned entailed both parties participating in the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> performance of a collective assemblage that involved reconfiguring the prototype to accommodate any negative consequences. The ‘political capacity of a boundary object’ (Carlile, 2002, p. 453) to resolve conflicting interests was the performative outcome of the sociomaterial relations involved in the joint transformation of shared knowledge.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="83" page="8" column="2">Contracted by AlphaCo to manage the project Requirements determination and vendor engagement Testing the emerging solution Creator and user of the original models ‘Strategic oversight’ of the project Partial user of the original models Future user of the new MDS solution Testing the emerging solution Product demonstration and contract negotiations Managing the MDS solution delivery Developing the MDS solution Developing the MDS solution Product demonstration and contract negotiations</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="85" page="8" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="86" page="9" column="1">578</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="87" page="9" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="88" page="9" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93" page="9" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94" page="10" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="95" page="10" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="96" page="10" column="1">579</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="101" page="10" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="102" page="11" column="1">580</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="11" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="104" page="11" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="108" page="11" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109" page="12" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="12" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="111" page="12" column="1">581</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="114" page="12" column="2">Discussion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" page="12" column="2">The case analysis presented in the previous section draws on the theoretical literatures of both boundary objects and sociomateriality. From the former perspective, the prototype was created as a designated boundary object and became a boundary object-in-use through its recog- nition and use as a design representation in the local practices of the various groups involved in the joint field of IS development in the project studied (Levina &amp; Vaast, 2005). These included the external project manager, the ITOCM business analysts, the vendor representatives, and the SoftCo project manager and developers. The prototype resided at, and helped form, the boundaries or shared spaces between these groups (Star, 2010). Materi- ally, it was an object of evaluation, the subject of attention and consideration by various project participants in their development activities (Østerlund, 2008). It existed in multiple versions and places, and was modified over time as aspects of the solution requirements became better known and defined (Subrahmanian et al, 2003). Incorporated into IS development practices in the project studied, it was used to span (or attempt to span) a range of knowledge boundaries between different groups (Carlile, 2002, 2004). For example, its use was implicated in transferring syntactic knowledge of the problem domain and solution requirements, translating the semantic meaning of what solution development entailed, and pragmatically resolving the consequences of conflicting interests, between the AlphaCo and SoftCo project teams. However, the prototype’s effectiveness in spanning these boundaries varied across different sites, times and participants. Adding a sociomaterial perspective to the case analysis involved conceptualising the prototype’s function as a boundary object as the multiple performances of a sociomaterial assemblage of human–artefact relations that varied over time and space (Suchman, 2007). We believe that this enables us to explain how and why the prototype became recognised and delineated as a boundary object, emerged and evolved in the project’s IS development practices, and achieved varying boundary- spanning effects across specific sites, times and participants. The findings from the case analysis reinforce the usefulness of a sociomaterial perspective, which provides five concepts that support or extend our understanding of project-related artefacts as boundary objects in IS development. These concepts and how they explain the features of boundary objects listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> and observed in our analysis are discussed below and summarised in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Table 4</xref>.<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> To become a boundary object-in-use, an artefact needs to be recognisable in a joint field between intersecting groups and meaningfully incorporated into the local practices of each. Sociomateriality extends our understanding of this aspect of boundary objects by empha- sising how a boundary object is not an independent technical object but is constituted in and emerges from the performance of situated sociomaterial practices. At the same time, a boundary object helps to constitute and configure those practices in particular ways. Sociomateriality helps us understand how such objects become materially integral to the collaboration and knowledge sharing of disparate groups engaged in cooperative activities such as IS development, ‘mak[ing] some practices and knowledge more salient and determinate than others’ (Orlikowski, 2010, p. 136). In the case study, the prototype had a recognisable identity and role in the joint field of IS development, and was locally useful in different ways to Frank, the vendors and the developers in understanding the solution requirements. Its incorporation into their practices configured those practices by defining appropriate participants, purposes, sites and times of use. For example, the prototype’s availability as a legitimate representation of the solution requirements appeared to obviate the need for SoftCo’s usual problem definition and encouraged the developers to rely on working with it to acquire their<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> understanding of the solution requirements, in turn minimising the perceived need to consult AlphaCo staff. Similarly, the prototype’s existence reinforced the ‘repli- cation’ development approach used by SoftCo in other projects, helping to define how and where the MDS solution would be built, and the role of Frank and Gary in testing the emerging solution.<marker type="block"/> Temporal emergence The concept of temporal emergence supports the idea that boundary objects are not necessarily stable or static. The temporality and local tailoring of boundary objects observed by Star (2010) is consistent with Pickering’s (1995, 2003) notion of sociomaterial assemblages as always in a process of ‘becoming’ as they are continually configured and reconfigured in practice to accommodate encountered resistances or solve new problems. Thus, boundary objects evolve and change when their intended boundary-spanning effects are problematic to achieve or when new forms of knowledge transfer and translation are required. Over the course of the project, the prototype was modified to address particular contingencies. It was not a static object but relatively open and malleable, changing over time as it became incorporated into particular practices, as problems arose or as new demands were placed on it. Different versions of the prototype were assembled, for example with ‘dummy’ data for vendor<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> engagement and actual data for solution development. At various points in the project it was modified, for example, to accommodate minor design changes sug- gested by Claire or the evolution of a more comprehensive scorecard-reporting function. In addition, problems encountered in implementing the additional dynamic solution functionality necessitated a number of revisions to the business rules component of the prototype as the understanding of how to implement that functionality was incrementally and cooperatively developed by both project teams.<marker type="block"/> Sociomaterial agency Sociomateriality extends our understanding of how the materiality of boundary objects affords certain aspects of boundary-spanning practices and constrains others. From a sociomaterial perspective, we conceptualise a boundary object as a sociomaterial assemblage rather than defining it as a material artefact, a socially con- ceived plan or the collection of uses to which it is put. Doing so implies that its associated agency is neither vested in its material specificity nor in its user as an autonomous human actor, but is sociomaterial, constituted through the ‘intra-action’ (Barad, 2003) of the two. Thus, the affordances of a boundary object are the effects of sociomaterial agency, and different sociomaterial agencies are enacted in different sociomaterial assemblages. In the case study, the different performances of sociomaterial relations between particular project participants and the prototype as a material artefact produced different possibilities for knowledge transfer and the translation of meaning. For example, Claire and Gary’s particular (limited) interaction with the prototype in defining the solution requirements meant that some errors, omissions or oversights in Frank’s translation of the original models were not identified. The SoftCo developers’ work with an early version of the prototype, which contained an abridged version of the scorecard- reporting function with various reports produced from summary data, created a misunderstanding about the level of data manipulation involved in developing that function in the MDS solution. In both examples, the consequences for the project were the result of the sociomaterial agency produced in particular performances of the boundary object as a sociomaterial assemblage.<marker type="block"/> Performativity Carlile (2004) calls for empirical research that focuses on how and why boundary objects function the way they do. If we think of boundary objects as ‘performative artifacts’ (Suchman et al, 2002), then their observed effects in collaborative work are the productive consequences of their constitution and reconstitution across particular times, participants, sites of use and associated practices. Such consequences are social and material, intended and unintended, and vary with each enactment of the assemblage constituting the boundary object. The<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> performativity of diverse sociomaterial assemblages explains how and why boundary objects do not function determinately or atemporally, but vary in their effects. As a boundary object, the prototype enabled the translation of knowledge, meaning and interests between different groups involved in the project. However, its boundary-spanning function and effectiveness varied, with the translation accomplished in any one use of the prototype being the result of the performance of a particular sociomaterial assemblage, involving participants with particular interests and experiences interacting with the artefact in specific practices and project settings, and on various occasions. For example, SoftCo’s initial underestimation of the project task complexity was an effect of Leon’s use of the prototype within practices of product demonstration and contract negotiation, and subject to time constraints and his desire to secure AlphaCo as a client. Similarly, any ambiguity or omissions encountered in working with the prototype were more of a problem for the developers than for say Frank or Claire, who had tacit knowledge of how the original models operated or of contract-specific meanings and definitions. This sort of knowledge was not embo- died in the prototype, and hence not able to be transferred through the developers’ engagement with the prototype in their development practice.<marker type="block"/> Multiplicity Boundary objects are interpretively flexible in that cooperating groups can recognise a common object, yet understand and appropriate it differently as part of their local practices. Sociomateriality helps to explain how this occurs. Multiple performances of diverse and shifting sociomaterial assemblages suggest that, instead of view- ing a boundary object as a static and autonomous singularity, we can talk about a multiplicity of boundary ‘objects-in-action’ (Suchman, 2005). The concept of multiplicity enables diverse groups to utilise and inter- pret a shared artefact in different ways, as each group enacts a different object in their performance of specific sociomaterial practices. In the project studied, the prototype was recognisable to all the participants because of its familiar form and content (e.g. financial spreadsheet models) and the participants’ shared understanding of the role of prototypes in IS development. As a boundary object, it constituted the shared space between interacting groups. However, its meaning differed between the various groups as they made sense of it in terms of the particular sociomaterial practices in which they incorporated it. For the AlphaCo project team, the prototype was distributed as a supplement to the RFI document, a rationalised representation of the original models that would transfer knowledge to potential vendors and developers in an understandable way. For the vendors, who incorporated the prototype into their situated practices of product demonstration, it was useful for defining the project scope and as a reference point for<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> demonstrating their products. For the SoftCo developers, who were used to translating existing client applications into MDS, the prototype was the object of replication in building an MDS solution. Each group used the same prototype artefact in their respective work practices, but in each case it comprised a different human–artefact relation and a different context of use, and had different sociomaterial effects. Through these multiple performances, the prototype was constituted as multiple different, yet co-existing and related, boundary objects (Mol, 1999).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="118" page="12" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="119" page="13" column="1">582</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="120" page="13" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="121" page="13" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="122" page="13" column="1">Table 4</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="123" page="13" column="1">Application of sociomaterial concepts to the analysis of boundary objects Boundary object feature observed Sociomaterial explanation</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx124">
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> Concept</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="4" page="13">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Practice</td>
                  <td class="table"> To become a boundary object-in-use, the</td>
                  <td class="table"> The prototype was not an independent technical object, but</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> prototype needed to be jointly recognisable</td>
                  <td class="table"> was constituted as a boundary object in the performance of</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> and meaningfully incorporated into the local</td>
                  <td class="table"> the sociomaterial practices of specific participants. In turn, its</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> practices of each project participant group</td>
                  <td class="table"> performance as a boundary object helped to configure those situated practices</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Temporal emergence</td>
                  <td class="table"> As a boundary object, the prototype was not</td>
                  <td class="table"> As a sociomaterial assemblage, the prototype emerged</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> static, but was subject to change during the</td>
                  <td class="table"> temporally in practice, being reconfigured over the course of</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> project</td>
                  <td class="table"> the project in response to particular contingencies</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Sociomaterial agency</td>
                  <td class="table"> The materiality of the prototype afforded</td>
                  <td class="table"> The possibilities for knowledge transfer and the translation of</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> certain aspects of boundary-spanning practices</td>
                  <td class="table"> meaning and interests between project participants using the</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> and constrained others</td>
                  <td class="table"> prototype were the effects of the sociomaterial agency produced from the constitutive entanglement of human actor and material artefact</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Performativity</td>
                  <td class="table"> The prototype’s boundary-spanning function</td>
                  <td class="table"> Diverse sociomaterial assemblages incorporating the proto-</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> and effectiveness varied across time and space</td>
                  <td class="table"> type were performed differently across different occasions, sites and participants, producing varying effects</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Multiplicity</td>
                  <td class="table"> As a boundary object, the prototype was</td>
                  <td class="table"> Each project participant group enacted the prototype as a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> interpretively flexible across the intersecting</td>
                  <td class="table"> boundary object differently in specific sociomaterial practices.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> groups involved in the project, recognisable</td>
                  <td class="table"> Thus, rather than a singular boundary object, a multiplicity of</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> by each while satisfying their different</td>
                  <td class="table"> boundary objects were performed</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> informational needs</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Practice</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="125" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Concept Practice To become a boundary object-in-use, the The prototype was not an independent technical object, but prototype needed to be jointly recognisable was constituted as a boundary object in the performance of and meaningfully incorporated into the local the sociomaterial practices of specific participants. In turn, its practices of each project participant group performance as a boundary object helped to configure those situated practices Temporal emergence As a boundary object, the prototype was not As a sociomaterial assemblage, the prototype emerged static, but was subject to change during the temporally in practice, being reconfigured over the course of project the project in response to particular contingencies Sociomaterial agency The materiality of the prototype afforded The possibilities for knowledge transfer and the translation of certain aspects of boundary-spanning practices meaning and interests between project participants using the and constrained others prototype were the effects of the sociomaterial agency produced from the constitutive entanglement of human actor and material artefact Performativity The prototype’s boundary-spanning function Diverse sociomaterial assemblages incorporating the proto- and effectiveness varied across time and space type were performed differently across different occasions, sites and participants, producing varying effects Multiplicity As a boundary object, the prototype was Each project participant group enacted the prototype as a interpretively flexible across the intersecting boundary object differently in specific sociomaterial practices. groups involved in the project, recognisable Thus, rather than a singular boundary object, a multiplicity of by each while satisfying their different boundary objects were performed informational needs</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="126" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Practice</region>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="130" page="13" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="131" page="14" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="132" page="14" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="133" page="14" column="1">583</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="139" page="14" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="140" page="15" column="1">584</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="141" page="15" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="142" page="15" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="144" page="15" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="15" column="1">In this paper, we have illustrated the value of combining a sociomaterial perspective with the analysis of boundary objects. The two perspectives share a compa- tible conceptual foundation and complement each other. Focusing on the sociomateriality of boundary objects engages with the complexity of the concept and helps unpack its ‘black-boxing’ in studies of collaborative work. Sociomateriality sensitises us to the temporally emergent nature of boundary objects as sociomaterial assemblages, the performed relations that constitute them in organisational practices, the distributed nature of agency in such practices and its productive consequences, both intended and unintended, and the multiple performances of diverse assemblages across time and space. The five concepts of practice, temporal emergence, sociomaterial agency, performativity and multiplicity, discussed in the previous section, support and extend our understanding of boundary objects, and can help future research on boundary objects in IS development by providing a theoretical vocabulary with which to explain how and why boundary objects function the way they do. While the analysis presented in the paper and used to illustrate our argument is based on one particular boundary object, a range of other project-related artefacts were analysed and produced observations consistent with those discussed here. Similarly, although our analysis is grounded in a single case study of IS development, we suggest that the sociomaterial analysis of boundary objects has applicability beyond the specific context of the case study. Sociomateriality offers a way of looking at artefacts in IS development that enhances their concep- tualisation as boundary objects. However, while it provides a theoretical vocabulary at a conceptual level, applying it in an empirical analysis can be challenging. On a practical level, it is often difficult to describe the sociomaterial relations or ‘intra-actions’ between humans and artefacts without reverting to the dualistic language traditionally employed in accounts of technology and organisation. Despite this, we hope that our study represents a useful illustration that other researchers can build on. Adding a sociomaterial perspective to the analysis of boundary objects has both theoretical and practical implications. Future research could focus on other types <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> of artefacts and development settings. For example, rather than artefacts created specifically as part of an IS development project, other studies could focus on boundary objects institutionalised as part of established organisational development or project management practices. A combined theoretical approach has much to offer research on contemporary IS development, which is often characterised by iterative and incremental, Agile development approaches, in which the system itself is temporally emergent. It is important to understand how IS development is performed as a sociomaterial practice in contexts such as open source software, outsourced or offshore development, co-development with users, and the implementation and customisation of enterprise and inter-organisational systems. In such development environments, the diverse groups involved are separated not only in terms of knowledge domains, but increasingly culturally, linguistically and geographically; the design of systems and artefacts is not solely the responsibility of IS professionals; and the boundary between development and use is blurring. A sociomaterial perspective is also relevant for IS research more generally, given the pervasiveness of information technologies and artefacts in contemporary organisations and society, and the practices they connect. Examples include virtual teams, distributed collaboration, mobile work and social networking. Our research also has practical implications for IS development. While some boundary objects emerge and gain relevance as development proceeds, others may be created purposefully as designated boundary objects. However, as the prototype analysed in this study reveals, the translation materialised in a project-related artefact may not necessarily be accurate or complete, with adverse effects on knowledge transfer and solution development. Further, the intended boundary-spanning functionality of a project-related artefact may not always be achieved. The different histories and relations that different participants or groups bring to their engagement with and enactment of project-related artefacts as boundary objects make some practices and knowledge more likely to be realised than others. Particularly in the case of prototypes, the materiality of the artefact must be engaged with by an actor in order to understand the specifications or requirements it embodies. The notion of a multiplicity of boundary objects performed in practice suggests that the use of a project- related artefact as a boundary object requires an acknowledgement of these potentially co-existing enactments, together with the range of consequences that could arise from these different performances. Similarly, the move- ment of project-related artefacts from one setting and practice to another will produce diverse performances of a boundary object, with both intended and unintended consequences. The potential for divergence in understanding between intersecting groups as performances of a boundary object multiply over time suggest the need for an awareness of this by the human actors involved<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> and for action to re-establish a shared understanding that enables cooperative work. That consequences are revealed through performance represents a challenge for managing IS development practices (Orlikowski &amp; Scott, 2008). This highlights the need to attend to boundary objects as sociomaterial assemblages in the context of specific practices, rather than focusing exclusively on the artefact or its human user. IS professionals, managers and clients need to understand that integrating project-related artefacts into IS development practices shapes those practices and influences interactions between project participants. This has implications for who is included or excluded, how responsibility and control are allocated, and how</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="147" page="15" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="148" page="16" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149" page="16" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="150" page="16" column="1">585</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="152" page="16" column="1">About the authors</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" page="16" column="1">Bill Doolin is Professor of Technology and Organisation at Auckland University of Technology, New Zealand. His research focuses on the processes that shape the adoption and use of information technologies in organisations. This has involved work on information systems in the public health sector and electronic business applications and strategies. His work has been published in international journals such as Accounting, Management and Information Technologies, Electronic Markets, Information Systems Journal, the Journal of Global Information Management and the Journal of Information Technology.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="154" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="16" column="1">A RIAS E, E DEN H, F ISCHER G, G ORMAN A and S CHARFF E (2000) Transcending the individual human mind – creating shared understanding through collaborative design. ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction 7(1), 84–113.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B ARAD K (2003) Posthumanist performativity: toward an understanding of how matter comes to matter. Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society 28(3), 801–831.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B ARRETT M and O BORN E (2010) Boundary object use in cross-cultural software development teams. Human Relations 63(8), 1199–1221.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B ECHKY BA (2003) Object lessons: workplace artifacts as representations of occupational jurisdiction. American Journal of Sociology 109(3), 720–752.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B ERGMAN M, L YYTINEN K and M ARK G (2007) Boundary objects in design: an ecological view of design artifacts. Journal of the Association for Information Systems 8(11), 546–568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B LOOMFIELD BP (1995) Power, machines and social relations: delegating to information technology in the National Health Service. Organization 2(3/4), 489–518.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B OLAND RJ and T ENKASI RV (1995) Perspective making and perspective taking in communities of knowing. Organization Science 6(4), 350–372.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B OUJUT J-F and B LANCO E (2003) Intermediary objects as a means to foster co-operation in engineering design. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 12(2), 205–219.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">B RAUN V and C LARKE V (2006) Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qualitative Research in Psychology 3(2), 77–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="16" column="2">C ARLILE PR (2002) A pragmatic view of knowledge and boundaries: boundary objects in new product development. Organization Science 13(4), 442–455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">C ARLILE PR (2004) Transferring, translating, and transforming: an integrative framework for managing knowledge across boundaries. Organization Science 15(5), 555–568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">C ONSTANTINIDES P and B ARRETT M (2006) Negotiating ICT development and use: the case of a telemedicine system in the healthcare region of Crete. Information and Organization 16(1), 27–55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">E NGESTROM Y and B LACKLER F (2005) On the life of the object. Organization 12(3), 307–330.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">E WENSTEIN B and W HYTE J (2009) Knowledge practices in design: the role of visual representations as ‘epistemic objects’. Organization Studies 30(1), 7–30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">G AL U, L YYTINEN K and Y OO Y (2008) The dynamics of IT boundary objects, information infrastructures, and organisational identities: the introduction of 3D modelling technologies into the architecture, engineering, and construction industry. European Journal of Information Systems 17(3), 290–304.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">G ASSON S (1999) A social action model of situated information systems design. The Data Base for Advances in Information Systems 30(2), 82–97.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">G ASSON S (2006) A genealogical study of boundary-spanning IS design. European Journal of Information Systems 15(1), 26–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">G R ø NB Æ K K (1990) Supporting active user involvement in prototyping. Scandinavian Journal of Information Systems 2, 3–24.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="17" column="1">H ARR E  ́ R (2002) Material objects in social worlds. Theory, Culture &amp; Society 19(5/6), 23–33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">H ENDERSON K (1991) Flexible sketches and inflexible data bases: visual communication, conscription devices, and boundary objects in design engineering. Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values 16(4), 448–473.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">H ENDRY DG (2004) Communication functions and the adaptation of design representations in interdisciplinary teams. In Proceedings of the 5th ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (B ENYON D and M OODY P, Eds), pp 123–132, Association for Computing Machinery, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">H OWARD -G RENVILLE JA and C ARLILE PR (2006) The incompatibility of knowledge regimes: consequences of the material world for cross- domain work. European Journal of Information Systems 15(5), 473–485.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">H UTCHBY I (2001) Technologies, texts and affordances. Sociology 35(2), 441–456.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">I NTRONA LD and H AYES N (2011) On sociomaterial imbrications: what plagiarism detection systems reveal and why it matters. Information and Organization 21(2), 107–122.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">J ONSSON K, H OLMSTR O  ̈ M J and L YYTINEN K (2009) Turn to the material: remote diagnostics systems and new forms of boundary-spanning. Information and Organization 19(4), 233–252.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">K ARSTEN H, L YYTINEN K, H URSKAINEN M and K OSKELAINEN T (2001) Crossing boundaries and conscripting participation: representing and integrating knowledge in a paper machinery project. European Journal of Information Systems 10(2), 89–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L ATOUR B (1991) Technology is society made durable. In A Sociology of Monsters: Essays on Power, Technology and Domination (L AW J, Ed.), pp 103–131, Routledge, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L AW J and M OL A (1995) Notes on materiality and sociality. Sociological Review 43(2), 274–294.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L AW J and S INGLETON V (2005) Object lessons. Organization 12(3), 331–355.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L EE CP (2007) Boundary negotiating artifacts: unbinding the routine of boundary objects and embracing chaos in collaborative work. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 16(3), 307–339.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L EONARDI PM (2011) When flexible routines meet flexible technologies: affordance, constraint, and the imbrication of human and material agencies. MIS Quarterly 35(1), 147–167.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L EVINA N and V AAST E (2005) The emergence of boundary spanning competence in practice: implications for implementation and use of information systems. MIS Quarterly 29(2), 335–363.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">L UTTERS WG and A CKERMAN MS (2007) Beyond boundary objects: collaborative reuse in aircraft technical support. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 16(3), 341–372.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">M CLEOD L (2008) Understanding IS development and acquisition: a process approach. Unpublished PhD thesis. [WWW document] <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://hdl.handle.net/10292/644," id="196">http://hdl.handle.net/10292/644,</ext-link> Auckland University of Technology, Auckland.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">M OL A (1999) Ontological politics. A word and some questions. In Actor Network Theory and After (L AW J and H ASSARD J, Eds), pp 74–89, Blackwell, Oxford.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="17" column="2">N ANDHAKUMAR J and J ONES M (1997) Too close for comfort? Distance and engagement in interpretive information systems research. Information Systems Journal 7(2), 109–131.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">O RLIKOWSKI WJ (2007) Sociomaterial practices: exploring technology at work. Organization Studies 28(9), 1435–1448.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">O RLIKOWSKI WJ (2010) The sociomateriality of organisational life: considering technology in management research. Cambridge Journal of Economics 34(1), 125–141.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">O RLIKOWSKI WJ and S COTT SV (2008) Sociomateriality: challenging the separation of technology, work and organization. Academy of Management Annals 2(1), 433–474.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Ø STERLUND C (2008) The materiality of communicative practices: the boundaries and objects of an emergency room genre. Scandinavian Journal of Information Systems 20(1), 7–40.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">P ELS D, H ETHERINGTON K and V ANDENBERGHE F (2002) The status of the object: performances, mediations, and techniques. Theory, Culture &amp; Society 19(5/6), 1–21.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">P ICKERING A (1995) The Mangle of Practice: Time, Agency, and Science. University of Chicago Press, Chicago.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">P ICKERING A (2003) On becoming: imagination, metaphysics, and the mangle. In Chasing Technoscience: Matrix for Materiality (I HDE D and S ELINGER E, Eds), pp 96–116, Indiana University Press, Bloomington, IN.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S APSED J and S ALTER A (2004) Postcards from the edge: local communities, global programs and boundary objects. Organization Studies 25(9), 1515–1534.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S TAR SL (2010) This is not a boundary object: reflections on the origin of a concept. Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values 35(5), 601–617.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S TAR SL and G RIESEMER JR (1989) Institutional ecology, ‘translations’ and boundary objects: amateurs and professionals in Berkeley’s Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, 1907-39. Social Studies of Science 19(3), 387–420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S UBRAHMANIAN E, M ONARCH I, K ONDA S, G RANGER H, M ILLIKEN R, W ESTERBERG A and T HE N- DIM GROUP (2003) Boundary objects and prototypes at the interfaces of engineering design. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 12(2), 185–203.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S UCHMAN L (2005) Affiliative objects. Organization 12(3), 379–399.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S UCHMAN L (2007) Human-Machine Reconfigurations: Plans and Situated Actions, 2nd edn, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S UCHMAN L, T RIGG R and B LOMBERG J (2002) Working artefacts: ethno- methods of the prototype. British Journal of Sociology 53(2), 163–179.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">S WAN J, B RESNEN M, N EWELL S and R OBERTSON M (2007) The object of knowledge: the role of objects in biomedical innovation. Human Relations 60(12), 1809–1837.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">W ALSHAM G (1995) Interpretive case studies in IS research: nature and method. European Journal of Information Systems 4(2), 74–81.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">W ESTRUP C (1993) Information systems methodologies in use. Journal of Information Technology 8(4), 267–275.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">W INOGRAD T and F LORES F (1997) Understanding Computers and Cognition: A New Foundation for Design. Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Y AKURA EK (2002) Charting time: timelines as temporal boundary objects. Academy of Management Journal 45(5), 956–970.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Z ACHRY M (2008) An interview with Susan Leigh Star. Technical Communication Quarterly 17(4), 435–454.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="164" page="16" column="2">sociomaterial assemblages might be configured to produce constructive and critical engagements with information technology (Suchman, 2007; Orlikowski, 2010).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="165" page="16" column="2">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="166" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">We gratefully acknowledge the support, encouragement and insightful comments of the Associate Editor and three anonymous reviewers, which helped to shape the resultant paper. The case study on which this research is based was funded through a Top Achiever Doctoral Scholarship by the Tertiary Education Commission of New Zealand. Preparation of this manuscript was supported by an Auckland University of Technology Post-Doctoral Fellowship.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="167" page="16" column="2">Laurie McLeod recently completed her Ph.D. at Auckland University of Technology, New Zealand. Her doctoral research focused on a process approach for understanding information systems development and acquisition. Her research has been published in various journals, including ACM Computing Surveys, Australasian Journal of Information Systems, Empirical Software Engineering, the Journal of Research and Practice in Information Technology and the Journal of Systems and Information Technology.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="177" page="16" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="178" page="17" column="1">586</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="179" page="17" column="1">Sociomateriality and boundary objects in IS development</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="17" column="1">Bill Doolin and Laurie McLeod</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="220" page="17" column="2">European Journal of Information Systems</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
