<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>b389973706d8bc569d96937e2265055bc93f296a4a55aec79aa6b379ec78b532</job>
    <base_name>62rn</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1542084.1542125</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Bringing the Television Experience to other Media in the Home: An Ethnographic Study</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="2">Emmanuel Tsekleves</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="4">Roger Whitham</name></contrib></contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Brunel University Lancaster University Kingston Lane, Uxbridge, Lancaster, UB8 3UE, UK LA1 4YW, UK <email id="5">emmanuel.tsekleves@brunel.ac.uk</email> <email id="6">r.whitham@lancaster.ac.uk</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8">In this paper we report on a study conducted in 2007 and 2008 looking at the media use habits of 27 families in the Greater London area. The project builds on previous ethnographic work studying media use within a similar group in 2006. The study investigated attitudes towards different types of media and the role Television (TV) currently plays and could play within the home environment. Following a participatory design methodology, we rapidly prototyped an experimental home media device and asked participants and use and respond to it. We explored the issues such as interactional simplicity and sharing media using a TV using the experimental device as a focal point for discussion and the generation of new ideas.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="9" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Categories and Subject Descriptors</h2>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">General Terms Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="18">Koko Kondo</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="19">Annette Hill</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" page="1" column="1">H.5.1 [Information Interfaces and Presentation]: Multimedia Information Systems - Evaluation/methodology; H.5.2 [Information Interfaces and Presentation]:User Interfaces Prototyping; J.7 [Computer Applications]: Computers in Other Systems—Consumer products.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Design, Experimentation, Human Factors.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">Interactive Television, user studies, interaction, divergent user needs, media use in the home.</region>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="1">Media consumption within the home has seen substantial change in recent years. New forms of media and associated devices have become prevalent in domestic settings, altering the types of entertainment and information-centric activities individuals engage in. With increasingly general forms of media [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="15" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>], such as the World Wide Web, come increasingly complex systems and the risk of an accompanying increase in the difficultly of using them.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. EuroITV’09, June 3–5, 2009, Leuven, Belgium. Copyright 2009 ACM 978-1-60558-340-2/09/06...$5.00.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="22" page="1" column="2">University of Westminster Northwick Park, Harrow, HA1 3TP, UK <email id="20">k.kondo@wmin.ac.uk</email> <email id="21">a.hill@wmin.ac.uk</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" page="1" column="2">Our research into media use in the home, along with that of others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="23" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="24" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="25" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>], shows that this increase in media availability and complexity has substantially different effects on different groups of users. In an exemplary and frequently documented trend, older individuals are typically less interested in, and able to interact with, the latest media devices and services. This paper documents ethnographic research looking at the interaction of diverse media in the home and the equally diverse needs of the individuals who engage with them. Comparisons are made both between and within co-residential groups. Our research is focused around television (TV) as a common denominator of entertainment and information access within the home. A family TV often offers a high quality audio and visual experience compared with other devices in the home. It is also typically situated prominently in a shared social space, such as the living room or kitchen. These typical features of TV usage, combined with the simplicity of the core TV user experience (a power button, channel and volume controls) make for a device all members of the family can understand, situated in an environment suitable for shared consumption of media. After considering related literature, this paper describes our study in two distinct parts. Firstly we describe the process of engaging with study participants and finding out about their current and ideal media use. After reporting on these results we then describe how these findings drove the design of an experimental second screen device which was taken back to study participants in the final stages of the study.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" page="1" column="2">2. PROJECT BACKGROUND</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="1" column="2">BITe (Barriers to Interactive Television) is funded by the Media and Moving Image component of WestFocus 1 , a UK Government funded (HIEF) consortia of universities in the west of London working together to promote knowledge transfer between academia and industry. It involves collaboration between Brunel University and the University of Westminster. The overall aim of the project is to develop knowledge of domestic digital media environment, including interactive Television (iTV) and suggest possible solutions based on audience/user perspectives. The project uses a combination of methods involving interviews, observation and creative tasks with several households with digital TV and broadband connections in the Greater London area.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">1 See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.westfocus.org.uk" id="29">http://www.westfocus.org.uk</ext-link> .</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="31" page="1" column="2">201</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="2" column="1">The project involves two phases. The first phase (2006-2007) investigated digital entertainment technologies in the home, exploring barriers to iTV in a household environment. This involved user reactions (likes, dislikes, frustrations, preferences) and technological issues and experiences associated with iTV services. It addressed several of these by developing a novel ‘second screen’ prototype remote control device in response to these findings and tested it with users in their own homes. The project used a combination of methods involving interviews and observations with 20 pilot households in the London area. The second phase of the project (2007-2008) followed the basic form of first phase, probing further into the use of digital entertainment technologies at home, exploring barriers to digital media engagement and the personalisation of digital media services and devices. A series of ethnographic studies were conducted involving repeated visits to 27 Greater London households with digital TV and broadband, leading in the latter phases to the development of an experimental artefact to facilitate further exploration of attitudes, expectations and barriers surrounding iTV and digital media use in the home.</region>
      <section class="deo:RelatedWork">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="33" page="2" column="1">3. RELATED WORK</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="34" page="2" column="1">3.1 Media Use in the Home</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="2" column="1">Co-resident groups of individuals are likely to make use of shared sources of information and entertainment. The home environment may contain all manner of information devices ranging from a wide-screen TV in the living room to individual laptops or mobile phones spread throughout the home. All such devices play complex social roles within the group as well as fulfilling objective information-access functions. Understanding the social context of media use in the home plays a vital role in informing the design of information devices and media forms, yet this topic is frequently overlooked [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="35" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. The literature suggests that there is still a lack of studies on the context of media use in the home, in addition to a lack of empirical data on users’ media consumption in a domestic setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="36" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. Gaunlett’s and Hill’s is one of the most related and comprehensive media study conducted in a domestic environment. It involved 500 UK participants over the course of 3 years and investigated people’s TV use in a domestic setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="37" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>]. Some key findings include the realisation that TV is a locus of attention and social interaction. It is prominently placed in the house and forms a central part of the family’s social life with other interactions taking place around it and through the watching of it. Also viewing habits (different genres of TV show and times people watch TV) differ immensely between different age groups, genders and personal interests. Other media devices such as the video recorder seemed to be integrated well into the TV environment and welcomed by most viewers. Gaunlett and Hill found also that TV programming can be divided into three types: favourite programmes, which would always be watched or recorded, non-favourite programmes, which would be watched routinely and other programmes which would be watched because they happened to be on and seemed to be interesting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="38" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>]. Several other media studies conducted in a domestic environment evaluate a particular media technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="39" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="40" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="41" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. These studies are centred solely on investigating user experience<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> (on network digital devices, specific Internet Protocol Television (IPTV) prototypes and set-top boxes respectively) or investigate how people use multiple devices in various domestic and professional contexts, particularly looking at the interactions and information exchange between and across the devices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="43" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>], instead of focusing on media use and user experiences with media. The media use studies most closely related to ours are those conducted by Obrist et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="44" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] and Bernhaupt et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="45" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. These studies investigate media consumption with TV as the focal point. Both papers report on ethnographic studies that explore user’s requirements and experiences of interactive TV within Austrian home environments, with 16 and 12 households participating in the two studies respectively. Another user study explores the use of TV and new media in the home environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="46" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. This study however focuses solely on media consumption of younger members of the household such as children and teenagers, overlooking adult, and elder household members’ media use. Another study by Seager et al. investigated the use of ‘triple-play’ services (TV, Internet, PC) in the home. They conducted a study involving 40 household in the UK and France, conducting most interviews outside of the household using user pictures of household technologies. The majority of their study considered the different devices employed in the home. Some of their key findings involve the concurrent use of PC and TV in the same room, especially in terms of performing quick checks on the Internet while watching TV (e-mails, web surfing). User preference for multiple display panels, user frustrations with DRM systems and incompatibility of devices and formats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="47" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>].</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="49" page="2" column="2">3.2 The TV User Experience</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" page="2" column="2">TV is often seen as being at the epicentre of the household media consumption. It is principally seen as an entertainment activity and part of leisure experience in the domestic environment [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="50" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="51" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="52" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="53" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. Additionally, TV is regarded as a lean-back medium with its users often ascribing a relaxing and passive attitude towards it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="54" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]. These notions of the core TV experience have, however, been altered by the advent of iTV in the home environment, allowing a traditionally passive medium to support a two-way interactive experience. Several studies have shown that interactivity in the TV domain is not always welcomed by viewers, and in some cases, may be disruptive to the core TV entertainment experience [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="55" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="56" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="57" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="58" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. This is especially likely as iTV services attempt to transform the TV from a lean-back to a lean-forward medium. The level of interactivity is not only limited by the potential of the technology, namely display mechanisms, hardware and interaction models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="59" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="60" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>] but also by the user’s willingness to interact [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="61" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. The TV user experience benefits more from an optional interaction model, where the user decides how much interaction they wish to engage in, if any. As Chorianopoulos indicates, “On one hand, a fraction of the viewers impulsively selects a program to watch, there is also a need to support familiarity with a small set of channels. As a consequence, designers should assume that most TV viewing starts with familiar content, but it might<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> continue with browsing of relevant items. As a principle, instead of information seeking, support relaxed exploration. Therefore, content navigation support should be subtle and not be enforced to the users.” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="64" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] Most of the media studies conducted on a domestic setting (see previous section) placed great emphasis on TV as the core media consumption and entertainment device in the home. TV has been the centre point of the entertainment experience with all or most household members making regular, if not always shared, use of it. It is interesting that although TV is usually controlled by a single person, it is clearly a medium that supports social activities in the domestic setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="65" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="66" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="67" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. Geerts et al. have conducted extensive research on the subject of TV and sociability. They have published findings on TV programme genres that promote social interaction by watching TV together over distances by sending annotated video clips and messages to family or friends both synchronously and asynchronously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="68" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. Their study involved 36 participants in a simulated living room environment. The most interesting findings were that news and films are the most popular genres people talked about and that TV is the most popular device for viewing long and high quality video content. Harper et al. also found that even in the more personalised medium of mobile TV, watching TV on mobile phones appears to be a social activity too [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="69" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]. Furthermore younger members of the household, despite their frequent reliance on PCs (Personal Computers) and the Internet for entertainment purposes, also make use of the TV as or in support of social activities, though their parents are often have first say in what is watched [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="70" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. The TV is also often seen as comfortable and familiar. As such it can be perceived as a less intimidating technology to individuals less used to interacting with digital media, especially when compared to modern day PCs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="71" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. For elderly people the burden of accessing the Internet through the TV is lower than buying and learning to interact with a PC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="72" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. In the contemporary Western household environment there are diverse media devices (TV, PC and the Internet, MP3 players, digital cameras, etc.) and within in each one of them there are different content sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="73" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. For example, through a typical TV one can find broadcast TV programmes, recorded programmes stored on the TV’s Personal Video Recorder (PVR) and access to the Internet. This latest trend brings into the light the issue of increasing complexity and media access in the home being opposed to the simplicity of the core TV experience. For example, in the first phase of the BITe project we found that study participants generally made limited use of the wide array of interactive features available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="74" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. Instead they concentrated on the most familiar and essential functions. The Electronic Programme Guide was a feature used by nearly all participants, while specialised interactive features unique to specific TV programmes or channels were rarely used. Finally, a recurring theme in the study's results was the desire for speed and simplicity with rapid and direct access to content. The interactive functions participants most favoured were those which facilitated rapid access to content with a minimum of fuss.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Given the social aspect and nature of TV, its familiarity amongst the community of less experienced digital media users and its synthesis of different media sources, one could take the TV paradigm and experience to other media in the home (such as photos, video-clips, music and many more). This is one of the concepts of the ideas we most prominently explored during the study described in this paper.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="2" column="2">202</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="77" page="3" column="2">3.3 Use of Second Screen Devices in the TV Domain</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="3" column="2">Although the focus of our research and this paper is not on the design and development of a portable second screen device, but rather on the concepts behind it, we still believe it appropriate to offer a brief section on this. The concept of employing secondary screen devices in the TV environment is not a new one. In fact several researchers have designed and developed portable secondary systems for the control of TV content by more than one users simultaneously. These can be divided into two distinct categories, depending on the main motive behind their design. The first category includes secondary systems, which are mainly employed towards the control of TV programmes and services. In 1996 Robertson et al conducted a study employing a Personal Digital Assistant (PDA) in conjunction with a TV and set-top box to demonstrate an estate agency service [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="78" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>]. Also Karanastasi et al developed a prototype system that enables people to use mobile phones and PDAs to personalise and interact with a TV guide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="79" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. In their study Park et al made use of sketch-based conceptual design to investigate the control of TV in a multi-user context with mobile phones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="80" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>]. There are also studies investigate the use of secondary devices beyond the control of TV. More precisely, commercial solutions such as MiXTV employ mobile messaging (both text-SMS and multimedia messaging-MMS) to interact with TV services, such as quizzes, game and voting and enrich the regular TV programming by displaying the messages and photos sent by viewers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="81" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>]. Cesar et al have also contribute considerably in this area by developing a secondary system that enables viewers to enrich, author TV programme content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="82" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>] and share it with family and friends [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="83" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]. The introduction of a secondary screen in the TV domain has several advantages. Some of them are summarised below: • It offers the opportunity to remove the need to show graphical navigation elements on the main Television screen. This allows viewers to continue enjoying the broadcast experience, even when the TV guide or an interactive service is viewed by another person in the household, by displaying the graphics and programme info on the secondary screen. • It also offers the opportunity to extend the model of TV operation by offering a far richer interaction mechanism than conventional remote control devices.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">• It allows for the dynamic reconfiguration of the user interface to reflect a user’s personal needs and desires. This could be used to allow for personalisation of both</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="86" page="3" column="2">203</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">graphical elements as well as personalisation of media and TV content.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="88" page="4" column="1">4. STUDY METHODOLOGY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" page="4" column="1">27 households in the Greater London area, each access to digital TV and broadband, participated in the primary study on which this paper reports. This provided a total of 70 people aged 8- 50+, containing a balance of gender, and socio-economic status (ABC1, C2DE) [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="89" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>]. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> provides an overview of the selected participants in the study.<marker type="block"/> The study involved a total of four visits to participants’ homes by researchers. The first visit took place between February and August 2007. This included 10 households who had participated in the first phase of the project in 2006 along with 17 new households. The aim of the first visit was to establish trust between the participants and the researchers and to gather information about general media use in the households. A second visit took place between August to October 2007. It included all 27 households and aimed at gather information on participants’ likes and dislikes, preferences and experiences with media in the home. A third visit was carried out between November 2007 to January 2008. This visit aimed at collecting information on participant’s use of media devices, media content, media device personalisation and multiplatform media. A final, fourth visit was carried out between February to March 2008. The aim of the last visit was to investigate and evaluate the concepts of interactional simplicity, customisation, privacy and security. This was effected with the use of an experimental home media device, developed as a response to user feedback from previous visits, as a vehicle for further discussion and generation of new ideas. The ethnographic observations made during the four visits to participant’s homes were augmented with three multiple-choice questionnaires (visit 1: general media use, visit 3: use of media devices, media content, media device customisation, visit 4:<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> privacy and security, media customisation, media interaction and sharing). Audio from 108 interviews was recorded for later analysis. In this paper we first discuss the outcomes of the first three visits (section 5). We then turn to the design of an experimental home media device used in the fourth and final visit, describing how the outcomes of the first three visits informed the design of the device, and the responses of participants to the device in the final visit (section 6).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="92" page="4" column="1">Table 1. Overview of participating people in the study</caption>
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> Age Gender Occupation Income</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="4">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Age Range</th>
                  <th class="table"> No</th>
                  <th class="table"> %</th>
                  <th class="table"> Male Female</th>
                  <th class="table"> Range</th>
                  <th class="table"> No</th>
                  <th class="table"> %</th>
                  <th class="table"> Range</th>
                  <th class="table"> No</th>
                  <th class="table"> %</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 8-12</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10.0</td>
                  <td class="table"> 32 (46%) 38 (54%)</td>
                  <td class="table"> A</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11</td>
                  <td class="table"> 15.7</td>
                  <td class="table"> less 5000 than</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 13-17</td>
                  <td class="table"> 13</td>
                  <td class="table"> 18.6</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> B</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7.1</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5-10K</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 18-25</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8.6</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> C1</td>
                  <td class="table"> 17</td>
                  <td class="table"> 24.3</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10-15k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 26-35</td>
                  <td class="table"> 17</td>
                  <td class="table"> 30.0</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> C2</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11.4</td>
                  <td class="table"> 15-20k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11.4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 36-45</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8.6</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> D</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.8</td>
                  <td class="table"> 20-25k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 14</td>
                  <td class="table"> 20.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 46+</td>
                  <td class="table"> 21</td>
                  <td class="table"> 24.3</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> pupils students &amp;</td>
                  <td class="table"> 23</td>
                  <td class="table"> 32.9</td>
                  <td class="table"> 25-30k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10.0</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> retired</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.9</td>
                  <td class="table"> 25-30k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> 30-35k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> more than 35k</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7.1</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> don’t know</td>
                  <td class="table"> 23</td>
                  <td class="table"> 32.9</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
              <tfoot>
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Total</th>
                  <th class="table"> 70</th>
                  <th class="table"> 100.0</th>
                  <th class="table"> 70 (100%)</th>
                  <th class="table"></th>
                  <th class="table"> 70</th>
                  <th class="table"> 100</th>
                  <th class="table"> 70</th>
                  <th class="table"></th>
                  <th class="table"> 100</th>
                </tr>
              </tfoot>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="93" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Age Gender Occupation Income Age Range No % Male Female Range No % Range No % 8-12 7 10.0 32 38 A 11 15.7 less than 3 4.3 (46%) (54%) 5000 13-17 13 18.6 B 5 7.1 5-10K 3 4.3 18-25 6 8.6 C1 17 24.3 10-15k 3 4.3 26-35 17 30.0 C2 8 11.4 15-20k 8 11.4 36-45 6 8.6 D 4 5.8 20-25k 14 20.0 46+ 21 24.3 pupils &amp; 23 32.9 25-30k 7 10.0 students retired 2 2.9 25-30k 1 1.4 30-35k 3 4.3 more than 5 7.1 35k don’t 23 32.9 know Total 70 100.0 70 (100%) 70 100 70 100</region>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="96" page="4" column="2">5. INITIAL RESULTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="4" column="2">Exploring the role of the TV in the domestic context formed our key research priority. The feedback gathered from the participant responses informed us about user needs and directed our response in the creation of an experimental artefact device. This paper does not provide sufficient space to report on all of the ideas we explored with participants. As such we report on some of the more interesting areas of dialogue which arose during the study.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="98" page="4" column="2">5.1 The Core Experience of TV</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" page="4" column="2">Studies from both the first and second phases of the project share similar perspectives to those of the literature (see 3.2) in that TV is associated with relaxation and the safety and comfort of one’s home: "...to watch TV is you must be comfortable and basically be at home" (Andrew) TV is also closely associated with familiarity and ease of use for all age groups and especially for older adults. “It comes back to the fact, we are certain age, and for us, TV is familiar, so we like watching Television, but don’t play around with interactive Television” (Linda and Tom, middle aged couple) The limited choice of options in addition to the provision of visual feedback seems to also form core parts of the TV experience that further contribute to ease of use. “I think TV is a good idea cause, it doesn’t seem to be complicated and the choice is really easy to make and you have a visual, you know, impact or knowledge of what is going on.” (Mike) Furthermore, the instant access to content with the simplicity of the TV interaction model renders it the dominant entertainment medium in the home, as the following user responses illustrate. “because the good thing with this is everyone can use it even young kids, just look at it, you are already on it, you don’t have to show them, that’s how easy it is” (Leon) “for someone like me that is not into the computer in any sense of the words the telly is simplifying everything for me” (Kate) The role of the TV is often contrasted with other media related activities in the household which require a more active user role, such as using a PC. “TV is more like when I have bad day, and it’s more like relaxation, internet requires you [to make] more actions. You have to engage with it”. (Lynn) <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> It is also interesting that the same views on the differences between the role of the TV and PC are shared among most members of the household, despite their age and differing motivations. This is exemplified in a family discussion regarding the different experiences between using the Internet and watching TV: 14 year-old daughter: “...because I thing with internet, coz you need to absorb information as such whereas with TV so much visual television, you can tell what’s going on without listening such, or, so definitely I say internet requires more concentration whereas television is more relaxing. If I am ill or something, I wouldn’t go on the Internet. I would sit and watch telly.” Mother: “That’s true. With Internet, you are more, you are involved, doing with a mouse, aren’t you? Keyboard as well. Whereas [with TV] you just probably watch a programme for half hour or hour and Internet you are doing other thing.” Father: “You can’t fall asleep on the internet, can you?" The universal access and simplicity of use of the TV has a positive impact on how people perceive it, particularly as the cognitive cost of interacting with the underlying technology is fairly low, while at the same time offering high quality content. Interaction costs are low, especially when compared to a PC. In this context a highly appreciated feature of the TV medium is its optional interaction model. The following quotes are typical of viewer experiences with a set of features they can interact with, but only if they wish to and at their own convenience. “I know, it’s going further [interactive TV], if you are interested in something, and you can go further to find out more information, but I don’t use it so often.” (Diana) “I don’t really use them [interactive TV services]. I think the player camera became better, I don’t know; and different commentators and things. But normally when I am watching football, I just watch football I don’t really care if it is interactive or not.” (Andy) This is especially true with optional interactive functions, such as the ‘information function’, which offer the viewer more information about programmes. “we use it [information function] a lot. Lots of shows, Simpsons or Star Trek, I have seen them all, and then I press ‘i’ to see which episode it is, and I can decide if I watch it or not.” (Kathrin)</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="100" page="4" column="2">204</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="102" page="5" column="1">5.2 TV as a Shared Resource</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" page="5" column="1">In addition to the association of relaxed interaction within the TV, participants also associated social activities with the medium. For them TV is a shared experience. It usually takes a prominent place in the social space of the living room. It enables a common entertainment activity within the domestic environment, which encourages social interaction among household members during the content viewing experience and afterwards. “It is a family thing isn’t it. You can interrupt because you can talk about what’s going up and down and everything, which is <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> funnier isn’t it. Come on burn it down or something like that” (Daisy) The social aspect of the TV is especially emphasised when participants contrast it with the PC and Internet activities. The PC is seen as a solitary activity, which by its design discourages social interaction and media sharing in the household. “it’s quite difficult, back stretching to see over his shoulder it’s better to share it over the TV” (Kate) “...she does drama and singing and they’ve got a MySpace page and every now and then you might get a clip or Kate on the computer singing. And how many evening have we been sitting down here and heard her laughing and we’ve all had to run upstairs in that little room and have a look” (Katie) In contrast, watching TV is regarded as a more sociable activity that allows sharing of media among the household members and particularly among family members, as a mother explains: “linking the computer with the TV is a good idea cause it would make it possible for Andrew to share her stuff with all of us, so it open’s it up a bit, it’s more communicative” (Connie)</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="105" page="5" column="2">5.3 TV and Multi-platform Media</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" page="5" column="2">Today, several devices such as mobile phones, portable game consoles (e.g. Nintendo DS), pocket PCs can perform multiple media-related tasks. Several participants expressed a positive view on multi-platform media. For adults having different media sources is very good, including old media such as magazines and radio especially for news and information gathering, as well as catching up on missed TV programmes. Mother: “I just recently downloaded iPlayer BBC iPlayer, because I missed something.” Daughter: “and if you miss the something on channel four, you can watch on channel four website.” <marker type="block"/> Teenagers and children tend to use multi-platform media mostly for playing games from relevant websites, such as the Cartoon network or Disney channel, where they can relate with the characters in the games.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Despite the positive view on multi-platform media, users do not often access a wide range of media from portable media devices, such as accessing the Internet from their mobile phones, and other portable media devices. This is due to device complexity and the limited number of websites that are being specifically designed to run on a mobile device (scaling, design and performance). When asked whether they use multiple devices at the same time most participants responded positively with 86% of them saying they perform multiple media-related tasks simultaneously, such as phoning and watching TV, using a PC and watching TV at the same time and several more. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> indicates that TV accounts for four out of the five most popular simultaneous media device uses, with 64% of the respondents watching TV while performing other media-related tasks. In this study we also explored the use of other non-TV-related media such as photos and videos, particularly in the context of the PC and the Internet. In a series of questionnaires we gathered that 86% of the households view photos on the Internet and 78% of them also watch video clips online. Although nearly eight out of ten households consume photos and videos online, only half of them share or upload photos on the Internet and even fewer, approximately three in every ten households, upload or share video clips online. Following the social and shared aspect of the TV experience, we explored the consumption or access of other media, this time on participants’ TV sets. Our studies indicated a new tendency of households sharing some media content through their TV set. More technical savvy households connect their digital cameras to share their pictures with other family members as well as friends. “that’s what we tend to do, don’t we, cause we’ve been doing it straight off your camera onto the TV and looking at them with friends which is quite fun to do” (Jane)</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="107" page="5" column="2">Table 2. Simultaneous use of media devices in the home</caption>
            <content>
              <h1 class="table"> Media devices used at the same time Percentage</h1>
              <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="5">
                <thead class="table"/>
                <tbody>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> TV and PC</td>
                    <td class="table"> 21%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> TV and mobile phone</td>
                    <td class="table"> 21%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> PC and mobile phone</td>
                    <td class="table"> 20%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> TV and PMP (personal media player)</td>
                    <td class="table"> 11%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> TV, PC and mobile phone</td>
                    <td class="table"> 10%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> PC and PMP</td>
                    <td class="table"> 7%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Mobile phone and PMP</td>
                    <td class="table"> 5%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Mobile phone and game console</td>
                    <td class="table"> 3%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> Game console and PMP</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1%</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr class="table">
                    <td class="table"> TV, PC, mobile phone and PMP</td>
                    <td class="table"> 1%</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </content>
            <region class="TableInfo" id="108" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">Media devices used at the same time Percentage TV and PC 21% TV and mobile phone 21% PC and mobile phone 20% TV and PMP (personal media player) 11% TV, PC and mobile phone 10% PC and PMP 7% Mobile phone and PMP 5% Mobile phone and game console 3% Game console and PMP 1% TV, PC, mobile phone and PMP 1%</region>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="110" page="5" column="2">205</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rn.page_006.image_01.png" thmb="62rn.page_006.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="112" page="6" column="1">Figure 1. The Experimental artefact: TV as a portal to other media.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">“I like the idea of being able to see them on the telly, it’s nice when you come back from holidays you sit down and all look at the photos together, especially if you had a really good party and there is some funny photos of everybody getting all round together” (Kate)</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="116" page="6" column="2">6. THE EXPERIMENTAL ARTEFACT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" page="6" column="2">For the fourth and final visit to study participant’s homes we developed an experimental home media device. This became the focus of the final visit, responding to and making concrete many of the ideas we had discussed with participants in the previous visits.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="118" page="6" column="2">6.1 Our Design Response</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="124" page="6" column="2">Our design response was strongly influenced by study participant’s views on the core TV experience. Our aim in the experimental artefact design was the maintenance of the core TV experience (instant access, simplicity, familiarity, low interaction cost, high quality, optional access to additional content). The very positive response of households to sharing media on the TV, preferences for accessing multiple media types from a single device and the use of several media-related devices at the same time created new opportunities for media convergence. This led us in the design and development of a second screen experimental artefact, aimed at making interaction more intuitive and less intrusive, especially for those individuals who see TV solely as a relaxing activity. The resultant experimental artefact is intended to realise the following ideas: • The core TV experience as a counterpoint to modern digital media experiences. • TV as a social activity: the shared experience of the TV is ideal for other non-TV-related media sharing, such as photos, videos and music <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> • TV as a common denominator: all members of the family can understand TV content and the basic interaction of the technology. Our experimental touch screen device uses the TV as a portal to access, use and share different media types. This included the viewing and sharing of photos and videos from YouTube and other online sources.<marker type="block"/> In this study we were more interested in participant responses to the ideas and concepts behind the experimental artefact rather than the artefact itself and user interface employed. Our main interest was in revealing households’ opinions after making use of the artefact and in generating discussion as to where this could lead or be extended to. The experimental artefact was used as a focal point and catalyst for discussion. As such we do not include an evaluation of the usability and user experience of the experimental artefact in this paper.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="120" page="6" column="2">206</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rn.page_007.image_02.png" thmb="62rn.page_007.image_02-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="123" page="7" column="1">Figure 2. Bringing different media to the TV.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="125" page="7" column="1">6.2 The Device</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" page="7" column="1">The experimental device used in this study was design to provide a realistic experience for study participants in their own homes. The device connected wirelessly to a laptop, which was in turn connected to participant’s TVs. This allowed actions performed on the second screen device to be instantly reflected on the TV within participant’s normal viewing environment. The device allowed control over the TV channel showing and allowed participant’s to display photos on the TV screen. The second screen device itself was created using a Samsung Q1 Ultra running Microsoft Windows XP. The device’s dimensions are approximately 23 x 12 x 23cm, with a 7 inch screen. The user interface (UI) displayed on the device was implemented using Adobe Flash connected wirelessly to a Java application running on a separate laptop, also running Microsoft Windows XP. The UI itself was controlled entirely with the touch screen. The buttons visible to the right and left of the device’s screen in figures 1, 2, 3 and 4 were not used in the study. Most actions were performed by touching regions of the screen, for example touching channel logos to change channels, or TV programmes to view information about a specific show. Scrolling of lists and panes was performed with a dragging gesture.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="127" page="7" column="2">6.3 Participant Responses</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="7" column="2">Using the experimental artefact as a focal point, we generated discussion on whether and how households would employ similar devices in sharing media between household members. The experimental artefact included a number of personalised photos and videos that the user could either view privately on their on the device itself or display to the main TV for everyone to see. Here we present several of the user responses, suggestions and discussion generated. Overall people showed positive attitudes towards accessing different media from the experimental artefact and projecting the contents to the TV. 96% of participants liked the idea of being able to access a range of media (TV, photos, video) and 91% expressed the wish to share photos and videos with family and friends. “you could be in the same room and enjoy different media, that would be great, wouldn’t it?” (Carole) “I think if you gonna go for the full mouthy, that’s probably what the future means to everybody, going forward and incorporating all different presentations of media, having everything all in one place seems to be the thing, doesn’t it?” (Kelly) When asked which type of media they would expect to share the most, the user responses varied depending on the devices involved. 43% responded they would mostly share the photos, followed by TV shows with 25%, 15% other videos (e.g. YouTube) and 12% films, provided they used the second screen device itself. Interestingly, in the case of media shown on the TV screen, participants indicated that then TV shows would be the most popular media they would share (49%), followed by photos (28%), films (17%) and then videos (6%) , as opposed to the responses above.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="129" page="7" column="2">6.3.1 Sharing Photos</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" page="7" column="2">Most participants greatly appreciated the photo-sharing concept. Participants wanted to share photos with other family members, friends and even party guests. “the photos is good and to be able to share it and very easily...with this I think it will cut the process of doing the complicated stuff, you know, of transferring, connecting, etc...[with this] you will not lose a lot of time” (Mark) “I’d have put it in a photo album I’d have prepared it and it’s great for when friends come round the same with you tube to watch clips which are funny as part as, you know, a party a conversation” (Garry) Seager et al. also found in their study that users favoured services which make use of the social nature of the space, such as photo sharing, especially with family and friends [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="130" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>].<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Another participant suggested that the idea behind the experimental artefact enables an activity which was lost when domestic photo technologies became primarily digital, making possible again activities surrounding sharing pictures with other people. “I like the photo idea, cause I always thought it was very sad when everybody when to digital cameras, whereas in the old days you had a film developed and you had something to look at, print and you don’t tend with the digital camera to look at your pictures as often as you would if you had them in an album or whatever, but if you have them on here it would be quite easy to get to them it would make it a lot more accessible” (Jacky) One participant saw a conceptual distinction between the situations and tasks of sharing photos and viewing them individually, suggesting the benefit of having a socialising activity whilst maintaining privacy. “you come back from holiday where you’ve took a lot of pictures and you do a slideshow and invite friends then you project them on the TV...here is more like when I am by myself and I am like let me see my memories from holiday.” (Carol)<marker type="block"/> In this context, one young participant described how the experimental artefact could support privacy when watching video media too. “say if you’ve got something personal like a video rather than it just coming up on the TV straightaway you can skip it, you don’t give anyone a chance to see it, that’s for you on private use and<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> you just touch something else and you see something else on the screen, yeah that is a good idea” (Trevor) An interesting observation was that the photo sharing idea appealed mostly on adults, parents and young children. Younger individuals such as teenagers, who do not take photos very often, did not show much interest in sharing photos. For them this is more of a private activity which they would mainly undertake with a few friends and peers around a PC. For some younger participants the sharing of photos in the experimental artefact was seen as making the viewing of photos easier for their parents.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="132" page="7" column="2">207</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rn.page_008.image_03.png" thmb="62rn.page_008.image_03-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="134" page="8" column="1">Figure 3. Browsing photos on the experimental artefact.</caption>
            </region>
            <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
              <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rn.page_008.image_04.png" thmb="62rn.page_008.image_04-thumb.png"/>
              <caption class="deo:Caption" id="137" page="8" column="1">Figure 4. Projecting photos from the experimental artefact to the TV.</caption>
            </region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="140" page="8" column="2">6.3.2 Sharing Videos</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" page="8" column="2">The idea of sharing of videos either streamed or downloaded from the Internet by projecting them on the TV appealed mostly to younger adults and especially teenagers. Parents preferred the idea of sharing photos to that of sharing online video clips. “YouTube, yeah if you’d just found a funny clip and wanted to show the family. It’ll be like oh look at this I show that today just bang that out, click on it and you can just show to everyone and have few giggles maybe” (Simon – 27 years) “it would be to see videos on here that you would upload, then you would end up with your own private You tube” (Jeff – 14 years) One participant expressed the desire to expand the range of online video sources available on the experimental artefact to cater for a wider range of video content. “I’d probably use the video if it was somewhere you could access stuff like people on Facebook, if you got access to that sort of stuff and you can see peoples’ videos, like You Tube I guess that would be interesting” (Trevor – 16 years)</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="142" page="8" column="2">6.3.3 Further User Suggestions</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" page="8" column="2">The discussion generated from the use of the experimental artefact lead us to several further suggestions. Generally households responded very positively to the concept of accessing similar media on their TV. When asked directly whether they would want similar access to media on their existing TV, 80% responded ‘yes’, 8% responded ‘no’ and 12% responded ‘don’t know’. Most study participants suggested the expansion of the media-sharing concept to incorporate music and Internet related media. Participants indicated that the social activities supported by the experimental artefact could also include the media from the audio/music genre. This idea was popular among younger age groups and was mainly expressed as a new means of sharing music content with people outside of the household, such as friends. “like your iPod, it could be incorporated into it so you’ve got all your favourite music in there, then you play it on the telly instead of your iPod...oh yeah that would be cool” (Roger – 15 years) “you could create your own playlist and when you have your friends around instead of switching the channels to find something you like you just have it on there and just play all of them” (Ann – 16 years) <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> A new theme that emerged from the discussion was that of ‘quick Internet checks’. Interestingly several participants expressed the desire of having Internet access on the experimental artefact in addition to their own PCs. According to respondents, Internet access from the experimental artefact should be a simple way of enabling them to perform quick web- related activities, such as finding favourite videos over YouTube, accessing email and Facebook accounts. “I use a for lots of Internet things and I’d rather use that if I could cause it’s touch screen it just makes it so much easier, I’ve got a laptop and it’s always clicking, touch would be a really good function, you know reading deleting e-mails and stuff, it would be much user friendly than using a mouse” (Susan) “It depends on your Internet usage; to check your e-mails quickly this would be perfect even the You Tube...that’s good because it’s mild very low intense Internet usage you don’t have to do a lot of typing. For me when I go on the Internet I’ll be doing a lot of typing so my preference is to use the laptop, but for small scale stuff it would be pretty useful but definitely useful if it has the equivalent little buttons to go directly to or directly to hotmail or something like that so it’s kind of controlled Internet usage.” (Garry) Interestingly, when households were asked whether they would use the experimental artefact to share media from the Internet with others the majority responded positively. 74% of participants suggested they would do so with their family in contrast to 83% who would prefer to do this with their friends. When asked, participants would often suggest that the more other devices they could remotely control with the experimental artefact the better. Participants particularly wanted to use the experimental artefact to gain access to other media devices such as DVD players, Music Stereo, iPod and camcorders. When we posed the question of whether this might compromise the ease of using the core functions, some participants showed concern while others didn’t see this as an issue.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144" page="8" column="2">208</outsider>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="146" page="9" column="1">7. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="148" page="9" column="1">In this paper we presented the results of our ethnographic study on the use of different types of media and the role TV currently plays in modern households. Based on the user feedback we developed an experimental artefact to investigate further the concept of the core TV experience as a counterpoint to modern digital media experiences. The experimental artefact proved useful as a means of presenting new concepts and ideas and more importantly in generating further discussion. Themes emerging from our research include the continuing importance of the core TV experience, negative feelings towards iTV services and the desirability of devices and services specialised for specific online activities such as email and social networks. In this study we also explored issues such as personalisation, privacy and security with study participants using a experimental artefact to ground and focus discussion. We are currently still in the process of analysing the data collected, however our initial results suggest that the wider range of media forms within the home today is indicative of the very different <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> information and entertainment needs of household members. This is especially true in the TV domain, where the type of programmes and viewing behaviours differ depending on peoples’ age and social circumstances. This divergence in the groups of TV users suggests a great need for personalisation. Security is also seen as an important concern in the development of new kinds of interactive media services for the home. We want to test the pay-as-you-go concept found on other e- commerce systems on the TV domain as well.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="149" page="9" column="2">8. REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="9" column="2">[1] Seager, W., Knoche, H., Sasse, M. A. TV (2007) TV- centricity - Requirements gathering for triple play services. In Interactive TV: A Shared Experience TICSP Adjunct Proceedings of EuroITV 2007 (eds) Lugmayr, A. &amp; Golebiowski, 24-25 May, Amsterdam, The Netherlands, pp 274-8.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="9" column="2">[2] Geerts, D., Cesar, P., and Bulterman, D. 2008. The implications of program genres for the design of social television systems. In Proceeding of the 1st international Conference on Designing interactive User Experiences For TV and Video (Silicon Valley, California, USA, October 2008). UXTV '08, vol. 291. ACM, 71-80. DOI= <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1453805.1453822" id="151">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1453805.1453822</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="9" column="2">[3] Harper, R., Regan, T., and Rouncefield, M. 2006. Taking hold of TV: learning from the literature. In Proceedings of the 18th Australia Conference on Computer-Human interaction: Design: Activities, Artefacts and Environments (Sydney, Australia, November 2006). J. Kjeldskov and J. Paay, Eds. OZCHI '06, vol. 206. ACM. 79-86. DOI= <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1228175.1228192" id="153">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1228175.1228192</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="9" column="2">[4] Haines, V., Mitchell, V., Cooper, C., Maguire, M. 2007. Probing user values in the home environment within: A technology driven Smart Home project. Personal and Ubiquitous Computing. 11, 5, 349–359. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00779-006-0075-6" id="155">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00779-006-0075-6</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" page="9" column="2">[5] Obrist, M., Bernhaupt, R., Tscheligi, M. 2008. Interactive television for the home: An ethnographic study on users requirements and experiences. International Journal of Human-Computer Interaction. 24,2. Taylor &amp; Francis. 174 - 196. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10447310701821541" id="157">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10447310701821541</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="9" column="2">[6] Gauntlett, D and Hill, A. (1999) TV Living: Television, Culture and Everyday Life. Routledge, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="9" column="2">[7] Bly, S., Schilit, B., McDonald, D.W., Rosario, B. and Saint-Hilarie, Y. 2006. Broken Expectations in the Digital Home. Ext. Abstracts CHI 2006, ACM Press (2006), April 22-27, 2006, Montréal, Canada. 568 – 573. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1125451.1125571" id="160">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1125451.1125571</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="9" column="2">[8] Vyas, D., van der Veer, G.C.2006. Rich Evaluations of Entertainment Experience: Bridging the Interpretational Gap. Proceedings of ECCE-13, Zurich, Switzerland, ACM Press. 137–144. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1274892.1274921" id="162">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1274892.1274921</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="9" column="2">[9] O’Brien, J., Rodden, T., Rouncefield, M.J., AND Hughes, J. 1999. At home with the technology: An in-home computing and ethnographic study of a set-top-box trial. <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ACM Trans. Computer-Human Interaction. 6, 3. 282-308. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/329693.329698" id="166">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/329693.329698</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="10" column="1">[10] Dearman, D and Pierce, J. 2008. "It's on my other computer!": Computing with Multiple Devices. Proceeding of the twenty-sixth annual SIGCHI conference on Human factors in computing systems. Florence, Italy. ACM Press. 767-776. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1357054.1357177" id="168">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1357054.1357177</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="10" column="1">[11] Bernhaupt, R. Obrist, M. Weiss, A. Beck, E., Tscheligi, E. 2008. Trends in the living room and beyond: results from ethnographic studies using creative and playful probing. ACM Computer Entertainment. 6, 1. 1-23. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1350843.1350848" id="170">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1350843.1350848</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="10" column="1">[12] Svoen, B. 2007. Consumers, Participants, and Creators: Young People’s Diverse Use of Television and New Media. ACM Computers in Entertainment. 5, 2. 1-15. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1279540.1279545" id="172">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1279540.1279545</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="10" column="1">[13] Chorianopoulos, K. (2008) User Interface Design Principles for Interactive Television Applications. International Journal of Human-Computer Interaction. 24, 6. Taylor &amp; Francis. 556 - 573. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10447310802205750" id="174">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10447310802205750</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="10" column="1">[14] Chorianopoulos, K. and Spinellis, D. 2006. User interface evaluation of interactive TV: a media studies perspective. Journal of Universal Access in the Information Society. 6, 2. Springer-Verlag. 209-218. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10209-006-0032-1" id="176">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10209-006-0032-1</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="10" column="1">[15] Keeling, K., Macaulay, L.A. &amp; McGoldrick, P.J. 2007. DiTV and e-commerce among disadvantaged community groups. Journal of Behaviour and Information Technology. 26, 6. Taylor &amp; Francis. 545-560. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01449290600709137" id="178">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01449290600709137</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="10" column="1">[16] Gawlinski, M. (2003). Interactive television production. Oxford, Focal Press</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="10" column="1">[17] Cruickshank, L., Tsekleves, E., Whitham, R., Hill, A., Kondo, K.2007.Making interactive TV easier to use: Interface design for a second screen approach. The Design Journal. 10, 3. Ashgate. 41-53</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="10" column="1">[18] Baker, K. and Hulsen, P. 2003. Multi-service models for interactive television. IEEE International Conference on Consumer Electronics. June 2003. Los Angeles, USA. IEEE. 88 - 89. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/ICCE.2003.1218822" id="182">http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/ICCE.2003.1218822</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="10" column="2">[19] England, E. and Finney, A. 2002. Managing Multimedia: Project Management for Web and Convergent Media, Book 2: Technical Issues. London, Addison-Wesley</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="10" column="2">[20] Eronen, L., and Vuorimaa, P. 2000. User Interfaces for Digital Television: a Navigator Case Study. Proceedings of conference on Advanced visual interfaces. Palermo, Italy. ACM Press. 276-279. DOI = <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/345513.345346" id="185">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/345513.345346</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="10" column="2">[21] Robertson, S., Wharton, C., Ashworth, C. &amp; Franzke, M. (1996). ‘Dual device user interface design: PDAs and interactive television’. Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems CHI 1996, Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human Factors in computing systems: common ground, Vancouver, Canada, 13-18 April 1996, pp.79-86. New York, ACM DOI= <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/238386.238408" id="187">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/238386.238408</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="10" column="2">[22] Karanastasi, A., Kazasis, F.G., Christodoulakis, S.(2005) A natural language model for managing TV-anytime information in mobile environments. Personal and Ubiquitous Computing 9, 262–272</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="10" column="2">[23] Park, J., Blythe, M., Monk, A. &amp; Grayson, D. (2006). ‘Sharable digital TV: relating ethnography to design through un-useless product suggestions’. Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems CHI 2006, Montreal, Canada, 22-27 April 2006, pp.1199–1204. New York, ACM Press. DOI= <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1125451.1125676" id="190">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1125451.1125676</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="10" column="2">[24] Miller, S. 2005. Taking on the masses with mobile messaging TV. Comput. Entertain. 3, 2 (Apr. 2005), 6-6. DOI= <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1063723.1063738" id="192">http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1063723.1063738</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="10" column="2">[25] Cesar, P Bulterman, D and Jansen A (2008) Usages of the Secondary Screen in an Interactive Television Environment: Control, Enrich, Share, and Transfer Television Content. In M. Tscheligi, M. Obrist, and A. Lugmayr (Eds.): EuroITV 2008, LNCS 5066, pp. 168–177, 2008. Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2008</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="10" column="2">[26] Cesar, P., Bulterman, D., Jansen, A.(2007) Social sharing of television content: An architecture. In: Proceedings of the IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (Workshops), pp. 145–150</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="10" column="2">[27] Bocock, R. 1993. Consumption (Key Ideas). London: Routledge</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="165" page="9" column="2">209</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="197" page="10" column="2">210</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
