<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>c1b245da3fd7a39922e2dd3b3c2a25dc91d27e91541d3bea0ae086b477cff9f3</job>
    <base_name>62sq</base_name>
    <doi>10.1287/opre.1060.0310</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">informs ®</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">O PERATIONS R ESEARCH Vol. 55, No. 1, January–February 2007, pp. 1–13</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">issn 0030-364X eissn 1526-5463 07 5501 0001 OR CHRONICLE</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="4">Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Maurice W. Kirby</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7" confidence="possible">Department of Economics, The Management School, Lancaster University, Lancaster, LA1 4YX, United Kingdom, <email id="6">m.kirby@lancaster.ac.uk</email> From the 1970s onwards, the OR community in Britain engaged in ongoing debate on the future of the discipline, the product of an emerging “crisis of confidence” engendered in part by the end of the “golden age of western economic growth” and the associated downsizing, or abolition, of practitioner groups in the corporate industrial sector. In addition, reservations were expressed concerning the increasing “mathematization” of academic OR in the context of the established “hard” or “classical” paradigm. In this respect, British operations researchers, aided and abetted by a number of American colleagues (notably Ackoff, Churchman, and Miser), engaged in a fundamental reappraisal of the OR methodological repertoire and its client base. Thus, in Britain, a new phase in the history of OR was inaugurated whereby the “positivist/scientist” approach bequeathed by the wartime pioneers was subject to challenge and qualification. Whilst some elements in the American OR community empathized with the emergent British critique, the response (notwithstanding Ackoff et al.) was, on the whole, relatively muted. This conservative American response provides one part of the rationale for this paper. The key issue here is to compare and contrast the tone and content of the Anglo-American debate on the future of OR after 1970: In simple terms, why did British OR practitioners and academics (especially the latter) respond so vigorously to the post-1970 OR critique in marked contrast to their American counterparts? In explaining the differential response, the paper will emphasize the interplay among an array of political, intellectual, and economic factors. Subject classification: OR/MS philosophy. Area of review: OR Chronicle. History: Received July 2004; revision received May 2005; accepted November 2005.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="1" column="1">Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">In 2000, I published a paper ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2000</xref>) that provided contrasts and comparisons between the development of operations research (OR) in Britain and the USA in the so-called “golden age”—the 30 years after 1940 when dif- fusion into the military sector was followed by the incor- poration of OR into an increasingly wide range of civilian organizations in the public and private sectors. In addi- tion, the period was notable for the dissemination of an expanding repertoire of American-derived methodological techniques that proved capable of delivering substantial efficiency gains to the organizations to which they were applied. The techniques themselves proved to be eminently teachable, so that by 1970 OR, both in Britain and the USA, was viewed as an entirely legitimate subject for academic discourse and enquiry in the university sector. This positive trajectory underpinned the agenda for my research mono- graph on the history of OR in Britain (from the 1930s to 1970), published in 2003 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="10" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003a</xref>). However, notwith- standing the substantial achievements of the “golden age,” the book could not fail to end without a postscript on the “crisis” that began to afflict the British OR community in the 1970s, and subsequently its American counterpart in the 1980s and 1990s. I am now writing a second volume that will cover the period from 1970 to 2000. Inevitably,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the book begins where volume one concluded—with an analysis of the critical debates after 1970 and their inter- face with comparative developments in the USA. In that context, the purpose of this paper is threefold. In the first instance, it identifies the essential features of the original “crisis” debate in Britain as a prelude to a more detailed analysis of the intellectual stance of the “reformist” and “revolutionary” critics of the American-driven “hard” or “classical” paradigm. Section two argues that the notion of “crisis” was fundamentally misconceived insofar as it emanated from a minority of British academic operations researchers who presented a distorted, if not ill-informed, view of OR in practice. It also highlights the intellectual and cultural, as well as the political and economic, factors that motivated the critics of the hard paradigm, emphasiz- ing that significant aspects of their critique were rooted in time-specific historical circumstances. The purpose of the final substantive section is to relate these developments to American experience after 1980.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="12" page="1" column="2">doi 10.1287/opre.1060.0310 © 2007 INFORMS</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" page="1" column="2">The “Crisis” in British Operations Research, and the Critical Response</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="1" column="2">Whilst the notion of “crisis” in OR emerged first in Britain, one of the most intelligent and succinct summaries of its <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> primary reasons (as they subsequently appeared in the USA) was provided by the American operations researcher, Pierre <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="19" class="deo:Reference">Hansen, in an article published in 1989</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Hansen 1989</xref>). Whilst Hansen was writing for a predominantly European and British audience in advance of the post-1990 American debate on the role and future of OR, he suc- ceeded in identifying the following commonly encountered explanations: (a) OR now concentrates on techniques and ignores managerial needs (this we might call the perversion theory). (b) OR techniques have already been used wherever they were needed (the obsolescence theory). (c) Management needs have evolved and are more com- plex than those which OR caters for (the inadequacy theory). (d) OR’s practice has been misguided and has under- mined the confidence managers had in it (the counterper- formance theory). Of the above possible reasons, the only one that requires elaboration at this point is the “counterperformance” the- ory. The critical issue here is the extent to which failures in OR practice contributed to the emergent crisis by under- mining managerial confidence in the discipline. In Britain, the best recorded example of this is the fate of OR in British Petroleum (BP), a multinational corporation that during the course of the 1960s had modelled its global operations on the basis of increasingly complex linear programming models. All of this was dispensed with in the wake of the 1973–1974 oil crisis which, in the view of senior BP execu- tives, served to undermine their confidence in deterministic modelling of the kind devised by its OR Division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003a</xref>). Although personality clashes and perceptions of “empire building” on the part of the division’s head played significant roles in the downgrading of OR, Hansen’s obser- vation that the “gigantism” of OR models applied to corpo- rate planning in the later 1960s was characterised, in some cases, by “[f]requent absence of validation and of critical discussion of what could be effectively predicted,” seems particularly appropriate in the case of BP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Hansen 1989</xref>). Further insights into the OR “crisis,” at least as it was portrayed in Britain by academic operations researchers, were provided by Dando and Bennett, writing in the early 1980s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Dando and Bennett 1981</xref>). In invoking the theme of a “Kuhnian” crisis in British OR—in the sense that “the dominant framework of assumptions appears to fail in relation to important problems”—the authors began by identifying a threefold classification of the methodology of OR as it had evolved from its inception in the later 1930s up to the 1970s. The first variant was the long-established “classical” or “positivist/quantitative” paradigm, rooted in the established “methods of science.” The second variant was the new “reformist school,” supposedly represented by the American operations researcher, Russell Ackoff, whilst the third variant was the “revolutionary” critique of both the classical paradigm and the reformist school devel- oped by a minority of British academic OR scientists in the 1970s. In an earlier paper, I analyzed Ackoff’s intellec-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> tual trajectory given his original status as an apostle of OR, his ultimate apostasy, and his long-established points of contact with the British OR community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003b</xref>). In highlighting the evolution of Ackoff’s thought I identified three “way stations” in his changing stance on the theory and practice of OR. Thus, in the early 1970s he devel- oped insights into the interaction between systems thinking and human behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff and Emery 1972</xref>): If indi- vidual systems are “purposive,” it follows that knowledge and understanding of their aims can only be obtained by taking into account the mechanisms of social, cultural, and psychological systems. According to Ackoff, these systems were undergoing radical change as the “Machine Age” gave way to the “Systems Age.” The Machine Age, the prod- uct of industrialisation, was supported by two interrelated concepts—“reductionism,” in the sense that everything can be decomposed into indivisible parts—and “mechanism,” embracing cause-and-effect relationships. For Ackoff, the beginning of the end of the Machine Age was signalled in the 1940s when philosophers, mathematicians, and biolo- gists collectively defined the intellectual framework of the new systems approach, whereby A system is more than the sum of its parts; it is an indivisible whole. It loses its essential properties when it is taken apart. The elements of a system may themselves be systems, and every system may be part of a larger system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1973</xref>, p. 664). The post-1945 onset of the systems age gave rise to new forms of engineering practice and new sciences of manage- ment, including OR, cybernetics, systems engineering, and the communications sciences. To the extent that these inter- related developments were conducive to interdisciplinary research, mankind’s ability to understand mounting com- plexity and volatility would be enhanced. According to Ackoff, however, the promise remained unfilled principally because the three postwar decades were characterised by increasing introversion, giving rise to “jurisdictional dis- putes between disciplines.” In this light, it was Ackoff’s perception that by the early 1970s a narrow and increas- ingly inward-looking OR community was insufficiently broadbased to define a research agenda relevant to the enhancement of the human condition. For Ackoff, the most pressing problems confronting humanity included discrimi- nation, inequality, and the inefficiency of public services. In these contexts, Machine Age thinking was seriously com- promised because it could not comprehend the “messes” of unstructured reality: traditional OR models were self- limiting, if only because they were rooted in excessively complicated mathematics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1973</xref>). Ackoff’s second “way station” offered a further con- demnation of OR in theory and practice. In two papers published in 1977 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1977a</xref>, b), he argued that OR’s unrelenting focus on “optimization” and “objectivity” encouraged “opt-out,” or a withdrawal from reality. In an increasingly turbulent economic and political environment,<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> “it is silly to look for an optimal solution to a mess.” As for “objectivity,” Ackoff rejected the view that it could only be achieved by excluding the moral and ethical values held by the researchers involved. Ackoff therefore argued that objectivity cannot be the absence of value judgements in purposeful behaviour—because purposeful behaviour can- not be value free: In his own words, “there is no concept as value loaded as objectivity, and no activity more value-full than science.” Ackoff’s final and most controversial way station was described in two papers delivered to the British Operational Research Society’s annual conference in 1978 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1979a</xref>, b). Here, he set out his highly personal interpreta- tion of the reasons for the OR “crisis” fully in conformity with Hansen’s later analysis. Significantly, he took the view that whilst American OR both in academia and practice was beyond redemption, British OR was capable of resuscita- tion in view of an established tradition of inquiry into non- corporate “social” issues dating back to the early 1960s. In the light of his first and second way stations, Ackoff there- fore called for a new OR paradigm designed to encompass a holistic systems approach that would serve to marginalize the malign influence of the inexorable trend towards “math- ematisation” in OR. As he had stated earlier, “the ‘messes’ of unstructured reality were being murdered by reducing them to problems, which were then murdered by reducing them to models, which in turn were murdered by excessive mathematics” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1973</xref>). In the later 1980s, Ackoff provided further insights into the reasons for his apostasy, arguing that the classical OR paradigm was wholly redundant in view of its irrel- evance to the resolution of problems of choice in the post-“golden age” era of intensifying competition, both at home and abroad (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1987</xref>). Unable to explain “pur- poseful choices,” operations researchers were increasingly downgraded in corporate manufacturing as top management engaged with marketing rather than the production-led problems characteristic of the “golden age.” Ackoff’s solu- tion to the OR “crisis,” therefore, was to proclaim the need for operations researchers to collaborate with managerial decision makers in order to remove or resolve conflict in such a way as to serve the interests of all stakeholders in an organization—bearing in mind that the “organization” may be far removed from the corporate boardroom. There was, in effect, a moral responsibility on operations researchers to advocate, either directly or indirectly, the concerns of all stakeholders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1977a</xref>, b; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Churchman and Schainblatt 1965</xref> and Muller-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Merbach 1988</xref>). As an alleged reformer, Ackoff had his contemporary and earlier British counterparts with a record of practical work and associated publications dating back to the 1960s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Stringer 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Friend and Jessop 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Friend et al. 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Eden et al. 1979</xref>). Borrowing from the methodology of “social science,” the early British reformers were certainly conver- sant with Ackoff’s approach insofar as they were intent upon applying OR to the needs of “multiorganizations” such as<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> local government and the National Health Service. More to the point—and in conformity with Ackoff’s emergent methodology—they placed particular emphasis on “action research.” In practice this meant that a social science approach was adopted “almost by osmosis” in the negotia- tion and management of change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Stringer 1967</xref>). Within the British OR community, one of the most well- known reformers and critic of the universal applicability of the classical paradigm, was Peter Checkland, Professor of Systems at the University of Lancaster from 1969 until his retirement in 1997. In developing his critique of “classical” OR, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Checkland (1981)</xref> noted that its essential methodologi- cal basis was rooted in model building, whereby a surrogate of the real world could be manipulated to conduct experi- ments and the results transferred to the real world. In this context, he noted Patrick Blackett’s wartime view that this was achievable because of the long-term stability of many of the variables involved in operations so that the aggregate results were relatively constant. Thus, the early pioneers of OR developed a methodology based upon model building of the logic of the situation: Experimentation on the model could indicate the solution that best achieves the objectives in hand as a prelude to implementation of the solution. For Checkland, the fact that Blackett had identified “the logic of situations” was an important intellectual breakthrough, in that A number of these situations were identified and algorithms developed. Because they were teachable [they] passed through into university courses. Because it was more attractive to research algorithms than to conduct action re- search in organisations, OR research became mathematical in nature. Thus, researchers concentrating on a class of log- ical situations became separated intellectually from practi- tioners who had to deal with unique idiosyncratic situations affected by chance events and individual personalities, as noted by Blackett (R. Ormerod to M. W. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Kirby, 2005</xref>). From the early 1980s onwards, Checkland, building on the work of earlier British reformers, emerged as a lead- ing exponent of “soft systems methodology” (SSM) as a response to the alleged limitations of the classical paradigm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Checkland 1981</xref>). Checkland’s publications at this time were notable for their acknowledgement of his debt not only to Ackoff, but also to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Vickers, writing in 1965</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Vickers 1965</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Churchman in 1971</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Churchman 1971</xref>). All three developed a “systems” approach to the res- olution of managerial problems, which could be deemed to be “wicked” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Rittel and Webber 1973</xref>) or “messes” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1975</xref>). Checkland’s espousal of SSM was justified by its relevance to the resolution of “management situations in which objectives were problematical and the engineer- ing/optimizing of the approaches developed in the 1950s and 1960s could not be used unchanged.” Thus, the crit- ical difference between the classical paradigm and SSM was the manner in which they deployed systems ideas. As Checkland observed, The soft approaches do not assume that systemicity lies in the world. Their assumption is that whatever the real world<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> consists of (on which they are neutral), the process of inquiry into the world can be organized as a learning system. Thus in SSM the system is the process of inquiry itself—though SSM also happens to make use of systems models of pur- poseful activity, though these are not would-be descriptions of anything in the world, only devices to structure the debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Checkland 2001</xref>, p. 769; italics in original). It is important to note, however, that in his capacity as a reformer Checkland was concerned to emphasize that the classical paradigm and SSM were complementary to each other to the extent that they were “powerful” in combina- tion. This does, of course, stand in complete contrast to Ackoff’s comprehensive rejection of the classical paradigm, and to that extent it raises a critical issue concerning Dando and Bennetts’ definition of reformist thought. Tak- ing Ackoff’s long-term “intellectual trajectory,” it is evident that he could be more accurately classified as a “conserva- tive revolutionary” rather than as a reformist. This is par- ticularly evident when his views are judged in relation to Dando and Bennet’s third classification of OR methodol- ogy, namely, the Marxist-inspired “revolutionary” critique as set out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Thunhurst (1982)</xref>. The Marxist-inspired “revolutionaries” began to formu- late their critique of the classical paradigm in the early 1970s. In this respect, there was a highly distinctive British contribution emanating from a number of university depart- ments of OR. The revolutionaries’ stance can be well illus- trated by their critical response to Ackoff’s dismissal of the classical paradigm in the wake of increasing economic and political turbulence after 1970. Whilst the revolution- aries endorsed Ackoff’s interpretation of the limitations of the classical paradigm, both in terms of its mathemat- ical bias and preoccupation with the needs of corporate industry and government, they wholly rejected his advo- cacy of “socially responsible” OR epitomised in his advo- cacy of participatory and interactive planning. Given the fact that much of the critical response was rooted in a Marxist perception of economy and society that by defini- tion was directly at odds with Ackoff’s consensual stance, it is not surprising that there were some sharp exchanges in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Chesterton et al. 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Rees 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead 1976</xref>). One of the most polemical contributions—in the sense that it deployed explicit Marxist terminology—stemmed from Rosenhead and Thunhurst. To the historian of OR, the relevant article, published in the early 1980s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Thunhurst 1982</xref>), makes fas- cinating, if not humorous, reading at this distance in time in the light of the rightwards shift in British politics inau- gurated by Margaret Thatcher after 1979 and its dramatic impact on the Labour Party in opposition before its re- election to government in 1997. In this setting, it is instruc- tive to quote selectively from Rosenhead and Thunhurst’s article: From the earliest days [of capitalism], the organized workforce has resisted [management exploitation] in fierce<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and sometimes locally successful struggles. But in the strug- gle between management (who act in this respect as agents of capital) and labour, the initiative has lain with manage- ment. On its behalf theories have been developed and tech- niques introduced in steady succession. The result has been the battery of sciences on which management now relies for the design and control of the work-process and the con- trol of the workforce. These include time-and-motion study, production engineering and ergonomics (also called human engineering), as well as the various schools of industrial psy- chology, industrial sociology and organization theory. This proliferation of specialisms can be seen simultaneously as elements in a Taylorist offensive, and as managerial tactics aiming to head-off the workers’ passive or active response. Operational research is one of these management sciences. And both these tendencies—to control the workplace and to control the response—are present within it. It is part of the forces of production the resources and knowledge at the disposition of society to make use of nature which under capitalism are the means by which the work-force is more efficiently exploited; and it is part of the ideological super- structure, the dominant system of ideas which dictate that the workers must accept the conditions of their exploitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Thunhurst 1982</xref>, p. 115; italics added). Thus, classical OR was profoundly ideological because it “suppresses open discussion and consideration of ends and values in favour of a technical selection of efficient means. It trades on the label ‘scientific’ to justify partic- ular, instrumental values” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Mingers 1992</xref>). For Rosenhead and Thunhurst and their fellow Marxist sympathisers, it was self-evident that Ackoff’s approach—and by implica- tion, Checkland’s SSM—was unable to comprehend the inevitable power struggles that afflict hierarchical orga- nizations. Ackoff’s advocacy of consensual interactive planning, where all stakeholders subscribe to a shared com- munity of interests, could therefore be viewed as naïve if only because “some issues never reach the agenda for debate,” whilst some groups can be duped by “false con- sciousness” leading to the marginalizing of their concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Flood and Jackson 1991</xref>). Somewhat predictably, the revo- lutionaries called for the British OR community to replace its overwhelming commitment to the corporate boardroom and the controlling mechanisms of the capitalist (corpo- rate) state in order to serve the needs of the exploited workforce—in effect replacing “management science” with a nascent “workers’ science” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Thunhurst 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Hales 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Chesterton et al. 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead 1976</xref>). In terms of its longevity, the historical record confirms that in its British setting, the challenge to the classi- cal paradigm was sustained not by the revolutionaries or, indeed, by Ackoff, but by the reformers. This is in con- formity with the predictions of Dando and Bennett, who concluded that the reformist position “will probably be far easier for the OR community to understand and accept than the revolutionary paradigm which is so far from their nor- mal modes of thought” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Dando and Bennett 1981</xref>; italics in original). Indeed, as the 1980s gave way to the 1990s,<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> increased sophistication in reformist thought was evident within the British OR community, most notably within the university sector. This was the product of cross fertiliza- tion of ideas in the literature, conference presentations, and working together on group projects. Thus, by 2000, it was possible to refer to “problem structuring methods” (PSMs) as a recognized complement to the classical paradigm. Designed to deal with decision-making procedures where there was profound “complexity” and “uncertainty,” PSMs accept as a fact that the most demanding and troubling task in formative decision systems is to decide what the prob- lem is. There are too many factors; many of the relation- ships between them are unclear or are in dispute; the most important do not reduce naturally to quantified form; dif- ferent stakeholders have different priorities. Problem struc- turing methods use models (often in the plural and with little or no quantification) to help mostly group decision- making—since it is rare for such issues to be resolved by single decision makers. The model representations are used to provide enough structure that those who must take respon- sibility for the consequences of the choices which are made, do so on a coherent basis and with sufficient confidence to make the necessary commitments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>, p. 1). From this it follows that PSMs realize their potential most fully in use with groups in work-shop format, That is, meeting without formal agenda or chairing but with a shared commitment to making progress to the issue at hand. Indeed, PSMs have been called “wide-band group decision support systems,” where “wide- band” indicates their ability to handle problems that have not been pre-formulated and may have quite diverse structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>, p. 13). Somewhat ironically, the first attempt to produce a coher- ent volume to describe and advocate PSMs was under- taken by one of the original revolutionaries, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead in 1989</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead 1989</xref>). The impact of this edited book was reflected in the fact that a former editor of the Jour- nal of the Operational Research Society (JORS) could claim in 2000 that, in his experience, Rational Analy- sis for a Problematic World was “probably the most ref- erenced book by JORS editors over the last ten years” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Ranyard 2000</xref>). A second edition was published in 2001 by Rosenhead, as the original editor in collaboration with Mingers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>). The methods identified were as follows: Strategic Options Development and Analysis (SODA), together with its Journey-Making variant and its technical component of cognitive mapping; Soft Systems Methodology; Strategic Choice Approach; Robustness Analysis; Drama Theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>). Whilst this did not exhaust the repertoire of PSMs, the above list was commended “on grounds of transparency,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> activation of judgement, a focus on commitment, and prac- tical applicability.” In terms of their relevance to decision making in the post-golden age, Rosenhead and Mingers highlighted the relevance of PSMs to several institutional settings within and beyond Britain. These included support for community groups in the London Borough of Tower Hamlets in resisting hospital closure, the organizational restructuring of a division of the Shell Petroleum Com- pany, the application of “community” OR in favour of an ex-coalminers’ council housing estate, the devising of a national system for the transport of hazardous waste on behalf of the Netherlands Government, and the develop- ment of an IT strategy for Sainbury’s as a major player in the British retail supermarket sector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>, Table 1.1, p. 10). In overall terms, this “alternative” paradigm for OR could be distinguished from its classical counterpart in terms of “subjectivity” versus “objectivity”—in effect, a methodological response to the uncertainties ushered in by the end of the “golden age.” It can be argued that the inclusion of Checkland’s SSM within the approved method- ological repertoire, together with chapters addressing the needs of corporate enterprise, is indicative of the matu- rity of the alternative paradigm following the post-1990 rapprochement between the so-called reformers and the upholders of the classical paradigm. Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers (2001)</xref> were as keen as Checkland to empha- size the complementarity between the alternative paradigm and the traditional modelling techniques bequeathed by the Blackett-inspired pioneers of OR. Thus, at the begin- ning of the 21st century, in spite of the Ackoff-driven cri- tique and the original depradations of the university-based revolutionaries, the classical paradigm remains a key OR tool in that it continues to provide well-founded solutions to a myriad of complex problems confronting “financial institutions, extractive and manufacturing industry, airlines and rail companies-and society as a whole” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Mingers 2001</xref>). Moreover, as the following section will demonstrate, classical OR in practice—in marked con- trast to the reservations expressed by a limited number of high-profile academic operations researchers—proved suf- ficiently flexible to assimilate elements of soft OR method- ology as part of an expanding “toolkit” of techniques. This is verified by the post-1965 contents lists of the major British journals, and also by the delivery of academic and practitioner-based papers at the principal national and inter- national conferences in the discipline. It is also the case that whilst there has been a decline in the number of corporate “in-house” OR groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Fildes and Ranyard 1997</xref>), this has been offset substantially by “A new model of highly spe- cific investigations and developments conducted by external specialist firms and management consultancies” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1999</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1998</xref>). In all of these respects, the practitioner-turned-academic operations researcher, Richard Ormerod, has commented appositely that notwithstanding</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="16" page="1" column="2">1</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="17" page="2" column="1">2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18" page="2" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="31" page="3" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="32" page="3" column="1">3</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="55" page="4" column="1">4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="56" page="4" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="74" page="5" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="5" column="1">5</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91" page="6" column="1">6</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92" page="6" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">the agonizing debates of the 1970s and early 1980s, Blackett’s child is alive and well. In some sense it has reached and passed its maturity. This should be no surprise 50 years on. The [OR] profession was for a time the centre of managerial attention. It had its golden era. It is now a small professional grouping that has found its niche. Few people realise that [OR] lies behind many every day events, providing the algorithms for airline reservations, checking the creditworthiness of loan applicants and calculating the replenishment quantities required by supermarkets. Despite its important role in today’s society [OR] lacks pomposity, it includes many, diverse interests and has demonstrated a certain capacity for survival. We would all wish as much for our own children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1999</xref>, p. 20).</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="95" page="6" column="1">Paradigm Change After 1970: Background Factors</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" page="6" column="1">Clearly, the period after 1970 witnessed a mounting critique of the classical paradigm in Britain, on the part of both reformers and revolutionaries. However, the essential ele- ments of the paradigm have survived, largely intact. More- over, a continuous process of refinement and enhancement of the methodological repertoire has been of substantial benefit to practitioners and academics alike. In this sec- tion, I wish to highlight some possible reasons for this. The discussion is informed by three reflective papers in JORS, the first by Ormerod ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1996</xref>), the second by Munro and Mingers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Munro and Mingers 2002</xref>), and the third by Brockelsby (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Brockelsby 1995</xref>). The section is also informed by the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Operational Research Society itself in the form of a sponsored report on the future of OR, published in 1986</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Operational Research Society 1986</xref>). I conclude the section by utilizing my perspective as an economic historian of modern Britain. I shall argue that in a fundamental sense, the critics of the classical paradigm, the revolutionaries in particular, were creatures of time- specific circumstances in a period of exceptional economic and political turbulence. In addition, I shall argue that the post-1970 interventions of the reformers and revolution- aries were compromised by preexisting developments in practical “soft” OR. Ormerod’s (1996) paper provides a retrospective inter- pretation of the broad influences that underpinned the con- troversies of the 1970s and 1980s. In the first instance, he follows Checkland in drawing attention to the post-1970 debate on the validity of OR’s aspirations to “scientific” status. For the original pioneers, this was an article of faith insofar as their approach to the subject was rooted in an “inductive-deductive” methodology as dictated by the accepted canons of scientific inquiry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003a</xref>). Notwithstanding the continuing claims that OR was/is a science-based discipline, Ormerod commented as follows: The assumption that the scientific world makes progress through the diligent use of an inductive-deductive<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> method has been under sustained attack by those inter- ested in the nature of science, including both scientists them- selves and philosophers of science. Some argue for changes to the logical underpinnings of the scientific method, oth- ers recognize that the scientific method requires explanation as a social and historical rather than a purely logical pro- cess. The social and historic accounts of the logic of science served to cast doubt on the rational-empirical claims of sci- ence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1996</xref>, p. 2). Whilst operations researchers of the stature of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Ravetz (1971)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Miser (1991)</xref> continued to defend OR’s scien- tific status, the assault on the nature of “science” gave pause for thought in the British OR community, especially on the part of academic members of the discipline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Keys 1989</xref>, 1998). In a second section, Ormerod summarized the view, extant in the 1970s (and providing the basis for Ackoff’s critique), that OR had become technique oriented to the extent that operations researchers were increasingly down- graded in managerial hierarchies in their limited capacity as technicians. This is a well-rehearsed theme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Eilon 1977</xref>, 1980), and my earlier comments have set it in a long-term historical perspective. More interesting for this section of the paper is Ormerod’s focus on the links between OR and the social sciences. As he commented of the 1960s, At the same time as the nature of science was being rede- fined, social scientists were questioning the applicability of the methods of natural science to social questions. The concerns here were as much instrumental as philosophical. Could the methods of natural science be applied to social situations without trivializing the very object of inquiry, the human element? The approach of science was found to be wanting when it came to capturing the subtleties of a situ- ation where different meanings could be attached to social actions, not least by the subjects themselves. Attempts to use the methods of science to define social attributes and the relationship between them could only give a partial picture and in the eyes of many a very inadequate one (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="108" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1996</xref>, p. 4). Thus, the “increasingly coherent development of the social sciences” fulfilled an important role in fuelling the critique of the classical paradigm because it provided an essential underpinning for the advocates of the alternative paradigm and its associated “soft” methodology. Although Ormerod was concerned with drawing atten- tion to the broad influences that had helped to undermine the validity of OR’s historic claim to scientific status, he was equally determined to correct the view—expounded in the revolutionary literature and reinforced by some of the reformers—that OR in practice was singularly based upon the optimization inherent in American-derived math- ematical models. Thus, Ormerod drew on his accumulated expertise as a former member of the most successful OR practitioner group in British industry to emphasize that in his experience OR practice was never as unthinkingly con- ducted as the reformers and revolutionaries implied. As he has stated with respect to his experience in the Operational<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Research Executive within the nationalized coal industry in the 1970s, the amount of optimization going on was vanishingly small. The main technique used was simulation but even that was dominated by investigations that didn’t involve techniques. Part of the problem in understanding the practice of OR lies in the “mathematical masturbation” of some academics and a desire to provide a social science critique [on the part] of others (R. Ormerod to M. W. Kirby 2004b; italics added). Support for this view of British OR in practice is sub- stantial. For example, in his presidential speech to the Oper- ational Research Society’s annual conference in 1978, the practitioner-turned-academic, Mike Simpson, commented as follows: Standard mathematical techniques or their immediate exten- sion are rarely applicable [in practice] This is borne out by surveys among past students, the majority of whom, even several years after graduation, have never used queuing theory, linear programming or the rest The techniques themselves reflect and embody the underlying structures of commonly occurring processes. Quite apart from [oper- ations researchers] being aware both of the potential and limitations of formal mathematical ways of handling prob- lems of a given structure, I believe that a thorough apprecia- tion of the techniques enables one much better to understand (or even to recognize) the existence of the underlying form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Simpson 1978</xref>, p. 518). It is a supreme irony that Simpson’s hymn of praise to methodological pragmatism was delivered to the same conference at which Ackoff had chosen to present a gross caricature of the OR community, whereby enhanced math- ematical virtuosity went hand in hand with increasing prac- tical irrelevance (see above). A powerful and objectively based vindication of Simp- son’s message was provided by the Operational Research Society itself in the form of a commissioned report “On the Future Practice of Operational Research,” published in 1986 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Operational Research Society 1986</xref>). The rationale for the report was provided by the ongoing notion of “cri- sis” in OR, but more especially by the downsizing or clo- sure of some in-house corporate groups that followed in the wake of the economic recession of the early 1980s. Thus, the main concern of the report was to sustain and support the practitioner community “in meeting the chal- lenges of the last fifteen years of the twentieth century.” In relation to the theme of this paper, the most pertinent com- ments are contained in the section entitled “Methodology of O.R. in Practice.” It is worthwhile to quote selectively from this section: The Commission found that most practitioners subscribe to the view that O.R. in practice uses, or seeks to use, method- ology of a kind which would be endorsed by the scientific community Phrases like “logical analysis,” “develop- ing understanding through modelling” and “basing belief on factual evidence” were frequently used by practitioners to describe O.R.’s methodology. Beyond these generalities and the frequent use of statistical methods, the Commis-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> sion found little by way of a definable uniform methodology (p. 842). The Commission therefore rejected the caricature of OR in practice as presented by the reformers and revolutionaries alike. More to the point, The Commission also found little explicit use of those math- ematical techniques which are most commonly associated with O.R. (for example, mathematical programming and queuing theory). These and the insights they offer, along with many other technical devices, help constitute a tool-kit of methods from which the practitioner may draw as need dictates. From time to time some potentially widely appli- cable tool is developed, either in the O.R. community or elsewhere, which many practitioners decide to add to their kit (p. 842). In this light, the Commission concluded that the “main methodological drive” in the practitioner community was “pragmatism:” Subject to a regard for the wider dictates of scientific probity, practitioners use the methodology and the tools, or meth- ods, which meet the needs of the case as quickly as pos- sible. These needs often include that the methodology and the tools should be understood by, and otherwise be accept- able to the client. The means by which these needs are met usually entail working closely with the client or his repre- sentative, and almost continuous negotiation, stage by stage, of how the work should be moving. Only rarely does O.R. move straight from problem to solution (p. 842). In relation to the methodological stance of OR and its implications for practice, the Commission therefore found that “change is endemic,” implying that practitioners needed to be “adaptive, opportunistic, articulate and sen- sitive to the political and social environment around him or her” (p. 842). In turn, the Commission identified a widespread view among practitioners that the practice of OR called for communication, social, and political skills in greater measure than most other comparable activities. In all of these respects, “The O.R. worker is a change agent, and the changes in question are often to deep- seated values or practices.” This conclusion resonated pow- erfully with a 1980 paper published by senior operations researchers at British Airways (BA), the then state-owned airline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Tobin et al. 1980</xref>, p. 280). The relevant OR group was influential within the Operational Research Society on account of its size and long practitioner experience, dat- ing back to the 1950s. The article addressed, in part, the issues raised by Ackoff in his recent conference papers. Thus, the group acknowledged the increasing complexity of the real world—and hence the limitations of the classical paradigm—especially as applied to the solution of “whole problems,” but also argued that for many OR practitioners their role had been transformed from that of “expert” to “change-agent,” whereby “the O.R. man (sic) is asked to help in changing the decision-making process through bet- ter tools, information or organization without becoming a surrogate decision maker.”<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> In highlighting the intellectual debate on the respective merits of the classical paradigm versus SSM and PSMs, a necessary complement is an assessment of the impact on OR practice of the alternative, “soft” paradigm. This section of the paper is therefore informed by Munro and Minger’s recent survey of the use of hard and soft method- ologies in Britain in the three decades after 1970 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Munro and Mingers 2002</xref>). In invoking the concept of “multi- methodology” the authors were concerned to analyse the extent to which the availability of hard and soft meth- ods had been conducive to a pluralistic methodological approach rooted in pragmatism. Notwithstanding their con- clusion that the application of “multimethodology” has been a “common occurrence”—to the extent that “SSM is distinctive in that it appears to be the predominant method- ology used as part of multimethodology, in combination with other [traditional] techniques,” the authors emphasized that their survey of OR in practice indicated that “There are few combinations of hard and soft together” (p. 378). Furthermore, in response to a critical comment by Ormerod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 2004a</xref>), Munro and Mingers confirmed that their original survey of OR practitioners had revealed that only 10% had used SSM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Munro and Mingers 2004</xref>). More to the point, they emphasized that their survey was consistent with the conclusion that the use of SSMs was largely con- fined to the academic community, albeit in a consultancy capacity, whereas practitioners “tended to use simulation, statistical analysis, mathematical modelling and forecasting most frequently in combination” (p. 94). Taking all of this into account, Ormerod has observed that We are twenty years into these [soft] methods. It is difficult to believe that they are going to penetrate now. The impact has been remarkably slight. A pity, I think, because they are useful and I advocate their use. But there it is: OR prac- tice manages its problem structuring, intervention approach and relationships with the client largely without the help of soft approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 2004b</xref>). Brockelsby’s paper was an appeal for “methodological complementarism”—“the idea of combining hard, soft and critical methodologies in systems research” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Brockelsby 1995</xref>). Like Ormerod, he too provided insights into the “crisis” debate—in his case, by adopting a cultural per- spective. He began with a reminder of the implications of the fundamental paradigm change advocated by Ackoff and Checkland: the transition from hard to soft systems thinking triggers fundamental changes in both the content and the style of the intervention. The primary task switches from problem solv- ing to problem structuring; system optimisation is replaced by iterative learning, engineering consensus and system “improvement”; the interest domain shifts from objective “facts” to subjectivities and multiple rationalities; the dis- cipline base shifts from mathematics to the social sciences, models of perceptions replace models of real world entities; implied metaphors are political system and culture instead of machine and organism (p. 1290).<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Insofar as paradigm change on this scale would require “changes at the level of beliefs and assumptions, as well as at the artefact level,” the fundamental difficulties are read- ily apparent. Ingrained habits and entrenched patterns of thought must be laid aside. Indeed, an entire belief system may require abolition, and presumably, sooner rather than later. Such changes have occurred, albeit extremely rarely, but as Brockelsby observed, “long-held basic assumptions, ‘root’ metaphors and values, have a habit of retaining their sub-conscious influence even under circumstances in which they have been publically repudiated” (p. 1290). To put it bluntly, paradigm change can be extremely painful if long- held beliefs and assumptions are to be surrendered. It fol- lows, therefore, that such action will not be taken lightly. Brockelsby’s remarks provide interesting insights into the muted, if not hostile reception, given to Ackoff’s controver- sial papers of the late 1970s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Ackoff 1979a</xref>, b). His inter- pretation of the “crisis” is consistent with the view that the alternative paradigm was bound to have limited impact on the theory and practice of OR in view of the considerable vested interests in sustaining the classical paradigm. In concluding this section, I wish to draw attention to the time-specific political and economic factors that gave special poignancy to the emergent critique of the classi- cal paradigm in Britain. In this respect, I quote from a paper already cited—Rosenhead and Thunhurst’s “revolu- tionary” appeal for OR to embrace the concept of a “work- ers’ science:” Capitalism is in crisis. Rampant inflation, long dole queues, cuts in public expenditure and social services, factory shut- downs and layoffs, shrinkage of capital investment and of profit margins, and the chaos of the last ten and especially five years in the arrangements for financing world trade are all symptoms of different stages of the world-wide crisis. But the boom-slump mechanism is an integral part of the process by which capitalism periodically rejuvenates itself— bypassing, transcending or crushing obstacles to its further development. Whether the current crisis will follow this pattern, or will threaten the very existence of capitalism, can still only be a matter of speculation. But the crisis is clearly of unusual length and severity and is world-wide in scope. Alongside the economic crisis there is also a crisis of legitimation—an unwillingness among large sectors of the population to accept passively the conditions of their labour and their social existence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Rosenhead and Thunhurst 1982</xref>, p. 120). This article was published in 1982, but the main focus of its temporal coverage relates to macro and microeconomic events in the previous decade which played a crucial role in precipitating the “crisis” debate. As an economic historian of post-1900 Britain, I can elaborate on the Rosenhead- Thunhurst agenda by placing the decade of the 1970s in its appropriate historical context. In Britain, the main features of the decade can be summarized as follows: 1. The slowest rate of economic growth since the early 1900s and exceptionally poor growth performance in rela- tion to the leading developed economies.<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 2. A period that witnessed the loss of more than 2 mil- lion jobs in the manufacturing sector, giving rise to a major debate on the causes and consequences of “deindustrialisa- tion.” 3. The bankruptcy of “flagship”/prestigious firms in the manufacturing sector and their takeover by the state (notably, Rolls Royce in 1971 and British Leyland in 1975). 4. Exceptional turbulence in industrial relations, focussing on the nationalized coal industry where there were strikes in 1972–1973 and 1973–1974, the latter result- ing in the electoral defeat of the governing Conservative Party. 5. Failures in macroeconomic policy intensifying an ex- isting “boom and bust” cycle, the product of unprecedented growth in the money supply, and the public-sector borrow- ing requirement. 6. A major exchange-rate crisis in 1976 when the gov- ernment of the day was obliged to seek the support of the IMF on terms which were viewed as “humiliating” and cer- tainly consistent with the IMF’s policy of responding to the monetary needs of “third-world” countries. 7. A governing party (Labour after 1974) that conceded considerable political influence to the trade union move- ment at the same time as a substantial proportion of the parliamentary party moved decisively to the left in its eco- nomic and social policy stance. 8. The inflationary consequences of the OPEC-admin- istered oil-price hike in 1973–1974, bearing in mind that the British inflation rate in the mid-1970s was by far the highest among OECD countries. 9. A sense of mounting political concern about the future of the British state itself (reflected in journal and newspaper articles on the theme, “Is Britain becoming ungovernable?”) in view of the rise of trade union militancy and nationalist political parties in the Welsh and Scottish “Celtic” fringe. The endemic problem of Northern Ireland was also at its height. 10. The collapse of the post-1945 consensus on eco- nomic policy, whereby the maintenance of full employment was replaced by the control of inflation as the overriding policy objective. For Britain, therefore, the “golden age” of western eco- nomic growth ended with a vengeance, and it is the above circumstances that provide the broad background to the emergence not only of the revolutionary critique, but also Checkland’s reformist agenda. In retrospect, however, the 1970s appear to be an aber- ration in British economic history. In that decade there was widespread concern that the British economy, and even the state itself (defined in terms of the “United Kingdom”), were in terminal decline for the reasons stated. The fact remains, however, that the prognostications of the pessimists, both reformers and revolutionaries, were not realized. The international economy and its institutions survived the oil crisis with relative ease compared to the world depression of the 1930s. Unemployment in Britain<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> in the 1980s was at a historic postwar high, and the rate of deindustrialization accelerated, but as I write this paper in October 2005, the British economy, as defined by the level of gross domestic product, is the fourth largest in the world. In the Western European context, the rates of unem- ployment and inflation have been at historic lows since the early 1950s, and as the Chancellor of the Exchequer keeps reminding us, during the last eight years the British econ- omy has enjoyed an unprecedented period of macroeco- nomic stability and enhanced economic growth. Compared to the 1970s, the trade union movement is virtually invisi- ble as a sectional interest, and economic policy across the political divide has achieved a post-Keynesian, postmone- tarist consensus. Far from the alternative paradigm taking over the OR methodological agenda, it has been absorbed into the OR “cultural” mainstream, albeit with limited prac- tical impact. It is also worth emphasising that even as the “crisis” debate was inaugurated after 1970, OR was mak- ing major advances in penetrating the machinery of civil government. The critical development here was the for- mation in 1968 of a separate Civil Service Department, carved out from the Treasury, and with a remit to secure the diffusion of OR throughout the full range of White- hall ministries. This had been substantially accomplished by the mid-1970s following the formation of strong OR groups in the Ministry of Transport, the Department of Health and Social Security and the National Health Service, the Department of Industry, and the Treasury itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003a</xref>). In addition, OR had already begun to penetrate local civil government in the 1960s, a trend that continued into the following decade. In this context, a key role was fulfilled by the Institute for Operational Research (IOR), formed in 1963 and incorporated within the Tavistock Insti- tute of Human Relations. As a joint OR Society-Tavistock initiative, the remit of the IOR was to engage in “active partnership with social scientists, since their discipline was concerned with whole organisations, and seeks policies which are best for the whole rather than for the individual parts of an organisation” (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2003a</xref>; italics in the original). As indicated earlier (see above, p. 3), the early British reformers located in the IOR, pre-dating Checkland, but with the support of Ackoff, proved to be among the earliest advocates of “soft” OR approaches. The point to be made here is that even before the “crisis” debates of the 1970s, British OR had begun to diversify its methodolog- ical foundations beyond the classical paradigm. This fact in itself provides a further, and plausible, insight into the muted reaction to the post-1970 reformers and revolution- aries alike.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="110" page="7" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="111" page="7" column="1">7</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="117" page="8" column="1">8</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="118" page="8" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="128" page="9" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="129" page="9" column="1">9</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="134" page="9" column="2">The American Experience</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" page="9" column="2">I can do no better in this section of the paper than to begin with an assessment of the American reaction to Ackoff’s rejection of the classical paradigm, bearing in mind that he was the leading American advocate of “soft” OR. In the <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> paper that I delivered to the INFORMS conference in 1998, I presented comparisons and contrasts between the differ- ing trajectories of OR in Britain and America in the period 1945–1990 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Kirby 2000</xref>). Inevitably, I touched on the “cri- sis” debate in both countries as it emerged after 1970, pay- ing particular attention to the relevant journal literature. In the United States there was certainly some sympathy for particular elements of Ackoff’s critique of the state of OR in the 1970s and 1980s—notably the trend towards “mathema- tisation,” and hence OR’s increasing irrelevance to the needs of managerial decision makers. Corbett and Van Wassen- hove (1993), for example, identified the phenomenon of “natural drift,” as did <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="139" class="deo:Reference">Reisman and Kirschnick (1994)</xref>, thereby lending support to Ackoff’s argument that OR was being “devolved” and downgraded in managerial structures. Insofar as these authors were, like Ackoff, concerned with challenging the ongoing trend towards “mathematisation” in OR, their worries conformed to critical elements in Abbott’s (1988) thesis of “professional regression.” In a wide-ranging analysis of “the expert division of labour” with reference to the modern professions, Abbott argued that the preem- inence of the mathematical paradigm was both inevitable and irreversible in view of the existence of “a small but very elite core” enjoying “intellectual control over a much wider jurisdiction” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Abbott 1988</xref>). This was of direct relevance to the OR community because “the elite core” responsible for “mathematisation” was concentrated in the American university sector, which, like its British counterpart, repre- sented OR to the outside world in terms of its content and supposed relevance to practical human affairs. It is signif- icant, however, that even amongst those who empathised with Ackoff’s critique and ultimate apostasy, few Amer- ican academics, and still fewer practitioners, agreed with his remedies in the form either of participatory or interac- tive planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Kirby and Rosenhead 2005</xref>). In this respect, the point should be made that in the Anglo-American con- text, the development of the alternative “soft” paradigm by reformers and revolutionaries was very much a British phenomenon. Why was this? From my perspective, I think that there were a number of interrelated factors that help to explain why American operations researchers, both in academia and practice, remained relatively immune from the academic-generated “turbulence” that afflicted British OR in the 1970s and 1980s. In the first instance, we can refer back to Brockelsby’s emphasis on the cultural obstacles to paradigm change. If anything, these obstacles were even more pronounced in the United States than in Britain because it was the American community of opera- tions researchers that had driven forward the methodological basis of the traditional paradigm. Moreover, as in Britain, the repertoire of OR methods was subject to constant change and refinement as new problems and opportunities in busi- ness, industry, and government appeared. In these respects, the rapidly advancing frontier of computer technology was of decisive importance (Abdel-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="142" class="deo:Reference">Malek et al. 1999</xref>). If proof<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> were needed of the extent of computer-assisted methodolog- ical innovation, it is only necessary to trace the record of the highly regarded Edelman finalist papers published under the auspices of Interfaces, a journal which, over the years, developed an increasing editorial preference in favour of the publication of articles with a practitioner, rather than an academic orientation. Indeed, the purpose of the Edel- man papers was to encourage the diffusion of best OR prac- tice throughout the practitioner community. Secondly, the “revolutionary” British critique of the classical paradigm was notable for its complete absence in America. As sug- gested already, Rosenhead and Thunhurst’s (1982) “materi- alist analysis” would, in all likelihood, have failed the edi- torial test if it had been submitted to the Journal of the Operational Research Society from the mid-1980s onwards. It is virtually certain that if their article had been submitted to an established American OR journal at any time, it would have received very short shrift. Thirdly, I have drawn atten- tion to the time-specific economic and political problems that afflicted Britain in the 1970s: For comparative experi- ence in the United States, the general consensus is that the country remained relatively insulated from the macro and microeconomic turbulence of the 1970s. Deindustrialization was certainly underway as a consequence of enhanced for- eign competition in manufacturing both at home and abroad, but at a much slower rate than in Britain. Put simply, the destabilizing forces that encouraged the emergence of the alternative paradigm were less forceful and compelling in the United States. I believe that it is deeply significant that Ackoff chose to launch his assault on the classical paradigm, not in the United States, but in Britain at the end of a decade of sustained economic failure and political upheaval. Returning to my INFORMS paper, I am acutely aware that there is a missing dimension that resonates in the Anglo-American context, namely, the post-1970 trend towards the closure of in-house OR groups, principally within the corporate industrial sector. To the extent that the development of OR in practice had been propelled by this particular organisational form—in effect, internal consultancies—its contraction was bound to fuel concerns about the future of OR in both countries. In Britain, the widely publicised closure of some well-known in-house OR groups after 1990 prompted the OR Society to launch a research project on “The Success and Survival of OR (SSOR) Groups” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Fildes and Ranyard 1997</xref>). Whilst the resulting report, published in 1997, noted that the closure of in-house groups was clearly related to managerial down- sizing arising from the onset of economic recession in the early 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s, it also pointed to the fol- lowing broader influences: 1. Deindustrialisation as a long-term trend was bound to have an adverse impact on the number of OR groups in corporate manufacturing. 2. The increasing standardisation of modelling lan- guages and the development of standard PC packages undermined the role of OR groups as “gatekeepers to solv- ing problems dependent on the IT function.”<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 3. Post-1970 managerial style and culture became in- creasingly antipathetic to “rational analysis,” favouring a postmodern holistic response to a problem rather than one based on decomposition and the explicit analysis of alter- native options. 4. The abandonment of “normative models of rational- ity” could well be “a reflection of an increasingly widespread belief that a coherent corporate ideology focused on the organization’s mission is more valuable than the question- ing methods of decision rationality.” 5. The failure of OR groups to respond positively to changes in management culture—as represented by the “Quality Movement” and “Business-Process Re- engineering”—led to the penetration of “alternative consul- tants, internal or external.” 6. One of the key functions of a central OR group is to reconcile “conflicting objectives across different busi- nesses and functional areas.” To the extent that this was consistent with “top-down management of a portfolio of businesses,” the mounting scepticism of the value added by centrally provided services resulted in the dispersal of OR leading to the loss of “professional identity” and “critical mass.” There is some, albeit limited, evidence that a number of these influences were at work in the United States after 1970. For example, Geoffrion (1992, p. 425), writing in the early 1990s, noted that the obvious term to describe the pro- cess of OR in industry was “dispersed” in the sense that the “long-term net decentralization and disbanding of MS/OR groups” from the late 1960s onwards meant that OR in practice was conducted mainly “by individuals in myriad types of staff groups and functional areas.” In explaining the demise of internal OR groups, Geoffrion identified the following interrelated factors: 1. OR/MS groups are susceptible to cost cutting in response to “lack of functional responsibility,” especially if senior management champions move on. 2. The move towards “leaner staffs in headquarters, flat- ter organizational structures and greater decentralization” had resulted in the dispersion of central OR/MS groups. 3. Standard OR/MS techniques had diffused into other disciplines and professions, notably “actuarial science, applied mathematics, computer science, finance, industrial and other kinds of engineering, logistics, marketing and operations management.” This had undermined the unique- ness of central groups, thereby encouraging the use of OR/MS ideas by other professionals. 4. The diffusion of OR/MS computer software had aug- mented the above process. 5. In its early days OR/MS had enjoyed a “bandwagon effect,” which had dissipated. This meant that it was increasingly unlikely that OR/MS was going to attract the attention of senior managers. 6. Although OR/MS groups had enjoyed “strategic impact,” too much of their work was conducted at the tac- tical level, leading to a decline in managerial interest.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> 7. Some OR/MS practitioners had harmed their cause as a result of arrogance, poor communication skills, and ineffective marketing of their skills. There is clearly an interface between Geoffrion’s obser- vations and the findings of the OR Society’s SSOR project. However, in both cases, the current state and future of OR was defined exclusively in relation to the ongoing demise of central OR groups in corporate industry. As indicated above, this was guaranteed to raise concerns about the future state of OR in the world of practice. However, it can be argued with equal veracity that a focus on the fate of internal OR groups did not present an accurate portrait of the contemporary state of the practitioner community in both America and Britain. In this respect, there are two critical points. In the first instance, both Geoffrion and the authors of the SSOR project pointed to the “democrati- sation” of OR as a result of the widespread diffusion of OR/MS-based computer software, leading to the loss of “uniqueness” of central OR groups. It is a point well taken that this process served to exacerbate “the lack of brand- ing” of the OR profession. As Randy Robinson has pointed out, at the beginning of the 21st century, OR is in fact undertaken under a blizzard of different names. They include synonyms and near-synonyms (e.g., management science, decision technology, operations anal- ysis, analytics), names of OR specialties in particular appli- cations (e.g., financial engineering, marketing engineering, operations management) While the medical profession guarantees that all their practitioners regardless of speciality are recognized to be doctors, within the umbrella medical profession, OR lacks assured identification of practitioners with its umbrella profession (R. Robinson to M. W. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Kirby, October 2005</xref>) In this light, investigation of the state of OR in prac- tice is bound to be compromised by the “embarrassment of riches in names” leading to substantial underestimates of the true numbers of practitioners. The second point, strongly articulated by Ormerod, and applicable to both British and American experience, is that the movement away from internal groups in favour of external consul- tancy and dispersed practitioners has been the product of changes in the pattern of work. This can be explained by the application of transactions cost economics and agency theory. In borrowing from the literature of applied eco- nomics, Ormerod has commented as follows: In choosing whether to maintain an internal OR group or whether to use external agencies, an organisation has to determine whether the purchase and transaction costs of using external services (for instance, the costs of buying, selling and managing the contract) outweigh the production and agency costs of maintaining an internal group of relevant expertise. At the same time they have to take into account the quality of the internal and external services as they see them. They also have to weigh up the merits of using inter- nal advisors with employment contracts, with the loyalty and goal alignment that it is assumed this ensures, against the<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> merits of using external providers controlled through explicit principal agent relationships and contracts. As these factors are not easily quantified, the choices have to be made on the basis of subjective views (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 1998</xref>, p. 422). As Ormerod has stated in his most recent contribution on this theme, these developments in favour of “the more com- mercially oriented service providers and consultants is an uncomfortable one for many members of the [OR] profes- sion,” bearing in mind that “Some, mainly academics, want OR to hold true to higher, non-commercial ideals” whereby the vagaries of the market are tempered by “rational pol- icy analysis” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="154" class="deo:Reference">Ormerod 2002</xref>, p. 475). This does, of course, serve as a reminder of the Rosenhead-inspired “revolution- ary” agenda of the 1970s, but as Ormerod concludes, the continuing and primary function of OR “is to support and enable change agendas set by others, usually the powerful elite within organisations.”</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="136" page="10" column="1">10</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="137" page="10" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="146" page="11" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="147" page="11" column="1">11</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="151" page="12" column="1">12</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="152" page="12" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="156" page="12" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" page="12" column="1">This paper has presented a survey of the post-1970 debates on the future trajectory of OR in the specifically British context, whilst drawing points of contrast and compari- son with experience in the United States. Its main thrust has been to identify the standpoint of the mainly aca- demic reformist and revolutionary challengers to the con- tinuing relevance of the classical paradigm. This served as a precursor to an evaluation of their perception of OR in practice. As the paper has argued, the more extreme critics were guilty of portraying a distorted view of OR in practice because the intellectual basis of their critique was rooted in time-specific circumstances. For the British reformers and advocates of “soft” OR, there were criticisms of the classical paradigm, but there was always recognition of their essential complementarity. This stands in marked contrast to Ackoff’s comprehensive rejection of the classi- cal paradigm. However, notwithstanding the views of the British reformers, survey evidence points to the fact that although their methodological approach made headway in academic OR, the impact on the practitioner community was, and remains, limited. As for the contrasts and compar- isons with contemporary American experience, the paper has emphasized that there was nothing comparable in the United States to the British revolutionaries: Concerns were certainly expressed about the limited practical relevance of the classical paradigm, but in overall terms, the impact of soft OR both on academia and practice was even less noticeable than in Britain.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="158" page="12" column="1">Acknowledgments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="159" page="12" column="1">The author is grateful to George Mitchell, Richard Ormerod, Jonathan Rosenhead, Frederic Murphy, Randy Robinson, and an anonymous referee for their advice and encouragement in the preparation of this paper. Barbara Kirby provided research assistance. Errors of fact and/or interpretation are the sole responsibility of the author.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="160" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="12" column="2">Abbott, A. 1988. The System of Professions: An Essay on the Expert Division of Labor. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, IL.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="12" column="2">Abdel-Malek, L., C. Wolf, F. Johnson, T. Spencer III. 1999. OR prac- tice: Survey results and reflections of practising INFORMS members. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 50 994–1003.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1973. Science in the systems age: Beyond IE, OR and MS. Oper. Res. 21 661–671.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1975. A reply to the comments of Keith Chesterton, Robert Goodsman, Jonathan Rosenhead and Colin Thunhurst. Oper. Res. Quart. 26 96–99.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1977a. Optimization + objectivity = opt out. Eur. J. Oper. Res. 1 1–7.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1977b. National development planning revisited. Oper. Res. 25 207–218.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1979a. The future of operational research is past. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 30 93–103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1979b. Resurrecting the future of operational research. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 30 189–199.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L. 1987. President’s symposium: OR, a post mortem. Oper. Res. 35 471–474.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="12" column="2">Ackoff, R. L., F. E. Emery. 1972. On Purposeful Systems. Tavistock, London, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="12" column="2">Brockelsby, J. 1995. Intervening in the cultural constitution of systems— Methodological complementarism and other visions for systems research. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 46 1285–1298.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="12" column="2">Checkland, P. B. 1981. Systems Thinking, Systems Practice. John Wiley, Chichester, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="12" column="2">Checkland, P. B. 2001. Soft systems methodology. S. I. Gass, C. M. Harris, eds. Encyclopedia of Operations Research and Management Science. Kluwer, Boston, MA, 767–770.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="12" column="2">Chesterton, K., R. Goodsman, J. Rosenhead, C. Thunhurst. 1975. A com- ment on Ackoff’s “the social responsibility of operational research.” Oper. Res. Quart. 26 91–95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Churchman, C. W. 1971. The Design of Inquiring Systems. Basic Books, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Churchman, C. W., J. H. Schainblatt. 1965. The researcher and the man- ager: A dialectic of implementation. Management Sci. 12 B40–B42.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="12" column="2">Corbett, C. J., G. W. Van Wassenhove. 1993. The natural drift: What happened to operations research? Oper. Res. 41 625–640.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="12" column="2">Dando, M. R., P. G. Bennett. 1981. A Kuhnian crisis in management science? J. Oper. Res. Soc. 32 939–942.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="12" column="2">Eden, C., S. Jones, D. Sims. 1979. Thinking in Organizations. Macmillan, London, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="12" column="2">Eilon, S. 1977. Technician or adviser? Omega 5 1–6.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="12" column="2">Eilon, S. 1980. The role of management science. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 31 253–265.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="12" column="2">Fildes, R., J. Ranyard. 1997. Success and survival of operational research groups. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 48 336–360.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Flood, R. L., M. C. Jackson. 1991. Creative Problem Solving: Total Sys- tems Intervention. John Wiley, Chichester, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="12" column="2">Friend, J. K., N. Jessop. 1969. Local Government and Strategic Choice: An Operational Research Approach to the Problem of Strategic Plan- ning. Pergamon, Oxford, UK (second ed., 1977).</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="12" column="2">Friend, J. K., M. E. Norris, J. Stringer. 1988. The Institute for Operational Research: An initiative to extend the scope of operational research. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 39 205–213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="12" column="2">Geoffrion, A. M. 1992. Forces, trends, and opportunities in MS/OR. Oper. Res. 40 423–445.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Hales, M. 1974. Management science and the second industrial revolution. Radical Sci. J. 1 5–28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="12" column="2">Hansen, P. 1989. A short discussion of the OR crisis. Eur. J. Oper. Res. 38 277–281.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Keys, P. 1989. OR as technology: Some issues and implications. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 40 753–759.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="13" column="1">Keys, P. 1998. OR as technology revisited. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 49 99–108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="13" column="1">Kirby, M. W. 2000. Operations research trajectories: The Anglo-American experience from the 1930s to 1990. Oper. Res. 48 661–670.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="13" column="1">Kirby, M. W. 2003a. Operational Research in War and Peace: The British Experience from the 1930s to 1970. Imperial College Press, London, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="13" column="1">Kirby, M. W. 2003b. The intellectual journey of Russell Ackoff: From OR apostle to OR apostate. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 54 1127–1140.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="13" column="1">Kirby, M. W., J. Rosenhead. 2005. IFORS’ operational research hall of fame: Russell L. Ackoff. Internat. Trans. Oper. Res. 12 129–134.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="13" column="1">Mingers, J. 1992. Recent developments in management science. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 43 1–10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Miser, H. 1991. Comment on “OR as technology.” J. Oper. Res. Soc. 42 429–431.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="13" column="1">Muller-Merbach, H. 1988. Mutual understanding revisited after nearly 25 years. Systems Practice 1 385–397.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="13" column="1">Munro, I., J. Mingers. 2002. The use of multimethodology in practice— Results of a survey of practitioners. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 53 369–378.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="13" column="1">Munro, I., J. Mingers. 2004. Response to Richard Ormerod. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 55 90–94.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Operational Research Society. 1986. Report of the commission on the future practice of operational research. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 37 829–866.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="13" column="1">Ormerod, R. 1996. On the nature of OR—Entering the fray. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 47 1–17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="13" column="1">Ormerod, R. 1998. Beyond internal OR groups. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 49 420–429.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="13" column="1">Ormerod, R. 1999. Blackett, the father of OR. OR Insight 12 14–20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="13" column="1">Ormerod, R. 2002. On the nature of OR: Taking stock. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 53 475–491.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="13" column="1">Ormerod, R. 2004a. The practice of UK OR practitioners. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 55 90.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="13" column="2">Ormerod, R. 2004b. Communication with M. W. Kirby.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="13" column="2">Ormerod, R. 2005. Communication with M. W. Kirby.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="13" column="2">Ranyard, J. 2000. Commentary on Checkland: Achieving desirable and feasible change: An application of soft systems methodology. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 51 1347–1348.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="13" column="2">Ravetz, J. R. 1971. Scientific Knowledge and Its Social Problems. Oxford University Press, Oxford, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">Rees, R. A. 1976. On the “social responsibility” of operational research. Oper. Res. Quart. 17 265–266.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" page="13" column="2">Reisman, A., F. Kirschnik. 1994. The devolution of OR/MS: Implications from a statistical content analysis of papers in flagship journals. Oper. Res. 42 577–588.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="13" column="2">Rittel, H. J. W., M. M. Webber. 1973. Dilemmas in a general theory of planning. Policy Sci. 4 155–169.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="13" column="2">Robinson, R. 2005. Communication with M. W. Kirby.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="13" column="2">Rosenhead, J. 1976. Some further comments on the social responsibility of operational research. Oper. Res. Quart. 27 266–272.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="13" column="2">Rosenhead, J., ed. 1989. Rational Analysis for a Problematic World: Prob- lem Structuring Methods for Complexity, Uncertainty and Conflict. John Wiley, Chichester, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" page="13" column="2">Rosenhead, J., J. Mingers, eds. 2001. Rational Analysis for a Problem- atic World Revisited: Problem Structuring Methods for Complexity, Uncertainty and Conflict. John Wiley, Chichester, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="13" column="2">Rosenhead, J., C. Thunhurst. 1982. A materialist analysis of operational research. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 33 111–122.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="13" column="2">Simpson, M. G. 1978. Those who can’t. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 24 517–522.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">Stringer, J. 1967. Operational research for “multi-organizations.” Oper. Res. Quart. 18 105–120.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">Thunhurst, C. 1973. Who does operational research operate for? Paper presented at the Annual Conference of Operational Research Society, Torquay, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="13" column="2">Tobin, M. R., K. Rapley, W. Teather. 1980. The changing role of OR. J. Oper. Res. Soc. 31 279–288.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="13" column="2">Vickers, G. 1965. The Art of Judgement. Chapman and Hall, London, UK.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="190" page="13" column="1">Kirby: Paradigm Change in Operations Research: Thirty Years of Debate Operations Research 55(1), pp. 1–13, © 2007 INFORMS</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="191" page="13" column="1">13</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
