<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>dafa50fecd4417bf1c094e35f55868ce9010046eb5dc88c63ab56c9b9fd8f7d7</job>
    <base_name>62dg</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-84628-733-6_14">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0956-7143(94)90019-1</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library] On: 14 February</name>
          <aff id="2">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">At: 09:41 Publisher: Taylor</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Francis Informa Ltd Registered in England</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered office: Mortimer House</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Mortimer Street</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">London W1T 3JH</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">UK</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="9" confidence="possible">CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="10">in</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="11">and</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx12">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dg.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62dg.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="14">Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20" id="13">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20</ext-link> The construction of fictional space participatory design practice a Christian Dindler a Centre for Digital Urban Living, Department of Information Media Studies, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark Version of record first published: 06 Sep 2010.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="15">167-182</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">To cite design To link to</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">this article: Christian Dindler (2010): The construction of fictional space in participatory practice, CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts, 6:3, this article: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2010.493941" id="17">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2010.493941</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19">PLEASE</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="20">SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="21">Full</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="22">This</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="24">terms and conditions of use: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-" id="23">http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-</ext-link> conditions article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial or systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, or distribution in any form to anyone is expressly forbidden.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="25">The that the</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="26">sources. demand,</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="27" confidence="possible">publisher does not give any warranty express or implied or make any representation contents will be complete or accurate or up to date. The accuracy of any instructions, formulae, and drug doses should be independently verified with primary The publisher shall not be liable for any loss, actions, claims, proceedings, or costs or damages whatsoever or howsoever caused arising directly or indirectly in connection with or arising out of the use of this material.</abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28">CoDesign Vol. 6, No. 3, September 2010, 167–182</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible">The construction of fictional space in participatory design practice Christian Dindler* Centre for Digital Urban Living, Department of Information and Media Studies, Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark (Received 7 December 2009; final version received 10 May 2010) This paper explores the creation of fictional space in participatory design and relates the notion of fictional space to the more general conception of design space as a space created through the situated practices of participants. The notion of fictional space provides insights for understanding the process through which participants in participatory design create a design space in which established conventions of everyday practice are altered or suspended. With inspiration from literary theory, it is argued that the production of fictional space may be understood in terms of participants practicing games of make-believe mediated by props. The motivation for discussing fictional space is traced through ongoing work on designing new exhibition spaces for museums. Through a case study from a participatory design session, it is explored how games of make-believe progress and the role of props in this process. Keywords: fictional space; games of make-believe; props; participatory design</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="2" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="2" column="1">A central tenet of Participatory Design (PD) is how new technologies may grow from the direct involvement of stakeholders and in particular future users in the design process ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Schuler and Namioka 1993</xref>). The aim of these endeavours is to create technologies and environments that in some sense are more responsive to the people who are to inhabit them, and to give these people a voice in the design process. Early PD projects provided central insights into both the techniques and practices that might provide the scaffolding for user participation and into the theoretical constructions that enabled PD researchers to understand and build the practice of participatory design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Greenbaum and Kyng 1991</xref>). Of particular interest to PD is the meeting between at least two different communities of practice (users and designers) and how the creation of new technologies and structures might grow from this meeting. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Ehn (1988)</xref>, PD may be conceptualised as a mutual learning process where designers step into the world of use and users learn about the opportunities offered by technology. As much as PD concerns learning about what is ‘already there’, it is certainly also about stepping into the unknown and exploring new forms of practice and meaning that transcend what exists. Techniques such as prototyping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Bødker and Grønbæk 1991</xref>), metaphorical design (Kensing and<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Halskov 1991</xref>), and future workshop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Kensing and Halskov 1991</xref>) grew out of the Scandinavian projects as ways of exploring first hand the potential and impact of new ideas. More recent contributions to PD have begun to explore the potential of the approach within a broad variety of domains stretching from business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Kensing et al. 1996</xref>) to health care (Sjo  ̈ berg and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Timpka 1998</xref>) and museums (Taxe  ́ n 2004). Moreover, PD has engaged with ubiquitous- and web 2.0 technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Hornecker et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Clement et al. 2008</xref>) as their design material. Common to these approaches and to PD in general is an emphasis on designing with users as a situated phenomenon; a practice that takes place in particular settings, with particular people, and under particular circumstances and that these fundamentally shape what is envisioned and designed in the cooperation between designers and users. The focus of this paper is on viewing the design space that is developed in PD work as a fictional space. Briefly, this is taken to mean in what sense the design space develops as a field of work distant from the user’s current practice. Fictional space is a hybrid construction where elements from established practices are drawn together with elements that have been made up to form a new constellation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren 1985</xref>). As proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Iser (1993)</xref>, the act of fictionalising is free play; it is an act of crossing boundaries by overstepping what is and thus is an act of distancing. Yet, the act of fictionalising does not annihilate existing practices; rather, aspects of these are selected and conflated into novel constellations thus re-actualising that which has been abandoned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Kambourov 2000</xref>). Based on the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref>, I will argue that fictional space is constructed by participants practicing games of make-believe mediated by props. Props play a central role as they give mandate to particular imaginings and thus mediate the creation of fictional space. However, as will be illustrated from the case study, props are the subject of continuous negotiation regarding their meaning and significance and fictional space is thus created through ongoing transactions. These ideas are explored through three connected arguments. First, the notion of design space as an emergent phenomenon is traced through the literature. Second, it is explored how the design space may be regarded as a fictional space in the sense that it is not tightly tied to the structures of everyday practice. Third, a perspective is provided on how fictional space is continuously created by participants through games of make-believe mediated by props. In particular, inspiration is found in literary theory in order to account for the role of props in supporting imagination. Based on a case study, the creation of fictional space and the use of props in a particular PD session are explored. Before embarking on this line of argument, the following paragraph will briefly introduce the research activities that have motivated this inquiry into the issue of fictional space in PD.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="37" page="2" column="1">*Email: <email id="36">imvcdi@hum.au.dk</email> ISSN 1571-0882 print/ISSN 1745-3755 online Ó 2010 Taylor &amp; Francis</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="39" page="2" column="1">DOI: 10.1080/15710882.2010.493941 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.informaworld.com" id="38">http://www.informaworld.com</ext-link></outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="40" page="3" column="1">168</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="3" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" page="3" column="1">2. Motivating fictional space in Participatory Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" page="3" column="1">The motivation for discussing fiction here is to explore the types of design practices that create design spaces that are significantly distant from the everyday practice of participants. This line of inquiry derives from ongoing work within the Digital Urban Living research centre in the domain of museums, science centers and elementary schools. Although the challenges of course differ within these domains, a common focus for our work across these domains has been to explore alternative ways of knowledge communication and participation. Generally, our work has involved a broad spectrum of stakeholders including teachers, pupils, museum professionals, and visitors that have been brought together to explore new practices <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> in the respective institutions. The specific focus here will be on the domain of cultural heritage museums. The museum is a relatively well-established institution in society. It has developed significantly since the days of the cabinets of curiosity towards an institution concerned with maintaining collections and conducting rigorous studies into the artefacts. The fact that the museum is a relatively well-established institution means that particular forms of practice are connected with a visit. People know what it means to visit a museum, how to behave, and certainly how not to behave. Moreover, many museums have established practices for how exhibitions are designed that build on more or less explicit ideas of how people are expected to engage with the exhibitions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Falk and Dierking 1992</xref>). There is of course great variety among museums and numerous examples of museums that deliberately break with the classical assumptions about what a museum is and how it is appreciated. In the fields concerned with the design and understanding of technology, a substantial body of literature has explored the role of technology in shaping the visitor experience. Within CSCW, studies have explored such issues as participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Heath and Lehn 2008</xref>) and social interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Heath et al. 2005</xref>) in exhibition spaces and within HCI and interaction design, studies have explored the potential of novel technologies in the form of augmented reality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Woods et al. 2004</xref>), context aware guides (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Raptis et al. 2005</xref> for overview), and mixed reality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Sparacino 2004</xref>). More generally, these studies reflect efforts to explore novel relationships between visitors and museums – a concern that has also been voiced from within the field of museology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Vergo 1989</xref>). Our work with interaction design and museums departs from the proposition that there is a potential in envisioning other roles of museums and new styles of communication. Our aim is to explore alternative ways for visitors to engage with and participate in museum exhibitions and to open up the museum to encompass diverse interpretations. In operationalising this aim, we have adopted a PD approach in order to provide not only museums but also their current and potential visitors a voice in the process of exploring future exhibition spaces. As our aim has been to provide alternative paths for visitor engagement and appreciation, we have seen a need in our PD inquiries for breaking free from or suspending some of the conventions and expectations that are embodied in the museum in order to allow for novel conceptions of what an exhibition might be. The notion of fictional space is a materialisation of this approach in relation to design inquiries; it brings attention to how the suspension of established conventions and expectation is accomplished within PD practice. I have previously in collaboration with colleagues, explored the staging of events that employ fictional elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Dindler and Iversen 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Brodersen et al. 2008</xref>). Here, however, the focus is on the process by which fictional space is created. The ways in which this can be understood conceptually and practically relating to PD practice is the subject of the following sections. Returning to the line of argument, the following paragraph traces the concept of design space as an imagined field of work to provide a basis for further elaborating on the notion of fictional space.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="4" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="56" page="4" column="1">169</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="67" page="4" column="1">3. Design space</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="4" column="1">In his influential work, Donald Scho  ̈ n showed how design develops as fluctuations between problem setting and problem solving. Scho  ̈ n (1987) presented a critique of <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> technical rationality, and of particular interest concerning design, Scho  ̈ n provides an alternative to Herbert Simon’s (1969) idea of design as a ‘science of the artificial’, where the design problem delimits a specific problem space and the designer searches among solutions in a general solution space. In this view, there is a relatively clear distinction between the analysis implied in the problem formulation and the synthesis needed to navigate the solution space. To a large extent, the work of Simon has been associated with a rational approach that formulates design as a problem- solving activity that adheres to information processing. The perspective offered by Scho  ̈ n highlights an alternative view, where problem and solution are co-emerging properties that grow out of the designer’s engagement in the situation. It may be the case that the differences between the work of Simon and Scho  ̈ n are not as dichotomically distinct as often found in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Chua Soo Meng 2008</xref>) and that in fact, as proposed by Heape (2007), design activity may display characteristics of both the rational searching based on criteria highlighted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Simon (1969)</xref> and the reflective conversation argued by Scho  ̈ n (1987). A central notion in these approaches is the nature of design problems. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Dorst (2003)</xref>, Simon’s (1969) original formulation of a science of design presupposes that a design problem can be adequately formulated from the outset of the process; that the problem space can be determined. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Rittel and Webber (1973)</xref> termed this ‘tame problem solving’ in that it is assumed that the problem can be understood, alternative solutions found, tested, and modified. However, the problems faced by design are typically of a ‘wicked’ nature, in that they cannot be adequately formulated and that every formulation is in itself a solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Rittel and Webber 1973</xref>). Faced with this situation, one strategy is of course to recast a wicked problem as a tame problem. This, however, neglects the fundamental uniqueness of wicked problems as they to not oblige to the same logic as tame problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Nelson and Stolterman 2003</xref>). In later works, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Simon (1973)</xref> also addressed the issue of ‘ill-structured’ problems, maintaining, however, a commitment to a rational paradigm. As formulated by Hallna  ̈ ss and Redstro  ̈ m (2005), the issue here concerns what is ‘given’ from the outset, and how this is transformed through the process. As they argue, what is given from the outset, however vague or ill-defined, is changed through the process. Design is thus always design of something given, but what that given is depends on what is designed. From a rational point of view, this state of affairs seems at best circular, at worst logically paradoxical. However, this very much serves to underline the difference between the approaches that have been, albeit somewhat simplified, laid out here. The formulation by Hallna  ̈ s and Redstro  ̈ m (2005) echoes Jones’ (1992) classical assertion that designers in a sense have to work backwards in time, predicting a future state that will only be realised if their predictions are correct. This has basic consequences for how design work is achieved, as the field of work is not directly open for empirical studies. As noted by Hallna  ̈ s and Redstro  ̈ m (2005), ‘users’ and ‘use’ are logical constructs that are defined in the process of design – not something that can be studied explicitly. The conclusion drawn from this line of reasoning is not that there is nothing gained from working with the people who may at some point become users and that one should not indulge in exploring user needs. Rather, it points to the central notion that design always entails the creation of a field of work that is imagined or, as will be our focus here, fictional. This notion of constructing a field of work is similar to Scho  ̈ n’s notion of design as world- making, where designers:<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> In this paper, the term ‘design space’ is used to denote this field of work that is constructed by the practice of participants in design and in which they move. The term ‘space’ is thus not used in the perhaps more common sense of a physical locale or three-dimensional Euclidian space (although these may certainly inform a notion of space), but in the sense of a conceptual space. Several authors have further explored the design space as the imagined field of work created in which designers move. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Heape (2007)</xref> argues that the design process may be regarded as the construction, exploration, and expansion of a conceptual space – the design space. Telier (forthcoming) provides a detailed discussion of the notion of design space and shows the connection between the situated practices of design students and the design space produced. Telier (forthcoming) makes the case that the notion of design space, interpreted through the work of Scho  ̈ n, may be regarded as the imagined field of work (or ‘as-if’ worlds) created through the designer’s engagement with the design situation. The space is imagined in the sense that it is created from images that derive from the designer’s transactions with the materials of the design situation; the mutual effect between designer and situation. Similar to these contributions, the perspective pursued here is one where the design space develops as a function of the situated actions of the people involved in design. However, the aim here is to explore this space as a fictional space within the scope of PD.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="69" page="5" column="1">170</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="70" page="5" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="79" page="6" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="6" column="1">171</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="81" page="6" column="1">(. . .) construct the meanings of their situations, materials, and messages, but also the ontologies on which these meanings depend. Every procedure, every problem formulation, depends on such an ontology: a construction of the totality of things and relations that the designer takes as the reality of the world in which he or she designs. (Scho  ̈ n 1992, p. 138).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="84" page="6" column="1">4. Fictional space in Participatory Design</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" page="6" column="1">The perspective explored so far is that the design space emerges from the designer’s transactions with the design situation. In this perspective, the design space denotes an imagined field of work as it is composed of images created through participants’ engagement with the materials of the situation. The exploration of the concept of fictional space may be framed within Ehn’s (1988) assertion that design is always caught in the tension between tradition and transcendence; between what already exists and what could exist in the future. What could come to exist through design calls upon imaginative skills. Imagination, however, is a very broad concept concerning the human ability to form images. Imagination is called upon in remembering, in describing what is present and in creating images of something in the future. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Nelson and Stolterman (2003)</xref>, the key capacity of design is the anticipatory image formation; the ability to form images about the future. Stating that the design space (in the sense defined above) is imagined, is in a strict sense only an assertion about the fact that it is composed of formed images. However, it is not in itself a statement about the nature of these images and what qualities these give to the design space. The notion of ‘fictional’ on the other hand, denotes (as it will be used here) a quality of being distant from everyday practice. In relation to Ehn’s notions of tradition and transcendence, fiction is a departure from the structures, conventions, and expectations of tradition. Not in the sense that these are completely annihilated; rather, that elements from existing practices are drawn together and reshaped to form new hybrid constellations. Ideas of fictional space may be found throughout<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> the design literature. In discussing the role of performances in design, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Iacucci et al. (2002)</xref> (see also Telier (forthcoming)) propose, similar to the approach pursued here, that a design space in some cases may be viewed as a fictional space that is created ‘by imagines that are free from the rules of reality and conventions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Iacucci et al. 2002</xref>, p. 174). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Lerdahl (2002)</xref> presents a study on the use of fantasy story writing used as a basis for creating product ideas. Lerdahl argues that the use of fantasy worlds allows participants to step out of, or put parenthesis around, reality. The assumption made by Lerdahl is that an important part of product development is the ability to break the bounds of tradition by enlarging the solution space – a concern that is analogous to the motivation discussed in section 2. Relating to PD, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Ehn (1988)</xref> speculates that the theatrical ‘Verfremdungseffect’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Ehn 1988</xref>, p. 70) (effect of alienation/distancing) may serve to highlight untried possibilities as it ‘re-casts’ what is already known in a new light. A similar notion is developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Bell et al. (2005)</xref> in their work on domestic technologies. They argue that the home is such a familiar setting that it is necessary to ‘defamiliarise’ it in order to open up the design space. Using the term ‘fiction’ here specifically brings attention to the sense in which the design space is distant from users’ current practice. So not only is the design space imagined, it is a step aside from the norms and conventions of everyday practice. However, continuing the view presented above, we cannot as such ‘place’ a design space wherever we want, as the design space is something that emerges from situated practice and thus depends on the participants in design. However, as designers we can scaffold the creation of fictional space in PD in terms of how design work is staged. So the challenge remains here to provide an account of how we can, through what we provide in terms of props, assignments, narratives etc. in participatory design work, scaffold the creation of fictional space. To this end, inspiration is found in literary theory that provides insights into the production of fictional space.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="87" page="7" column="1">172</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="88" page="7" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="96" page="7" column="1">5. Scaffolding the creation of fictional space</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="7" column="1">The issue of fictional space has been a natural focus of literary theory (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Eagleton (2008)</xref> for introduction). In particular, I will turn my attention to the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren (1985)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref>, who provide accounts dedicated to exploring how fictional space is created and how people engage with and create these spaces from their imagination. In discussing fictional space in the American novel, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren (1985)</xref> suggests that every fiction (in the sense of ‘a literary work of fiction’) creates a ‘fictional world’ that conflates elements from the empirical world, understood as ‘the contingent world as it presents itself in prosaic events, commonplace objects, and ordinary people’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren 1985</xref>, p. 16) with elements that have been made up. A fictional world is thus an addition to the empirical world, but at the same time they also intersect in some form of relation. Fictional worlds may be more or less mimetic depending on the extent of their departure from the empirical world. My proposition here is that Malmgren’s notion of fictional worlds can inform the idea of fictional space in design. Malmgren draws a simple diagram to illustrate the trajectory and intersection of the empirical and fictional world (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). The angle between the two trajectories describes the level of mimesis. The model provides a simple way of illustrating the fact that a fictional world may display varying degrees of autonomy; it may be more or less closely tied to the empirical world. Malmgren’s model shows this as the angle of the trajectory. Similar to the conceptualisation of fiction as denoting a kind of distance, Malmgren argues<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> that fictional worlds that have a steep trajectory (i.e. that are more autonomous) are typically instantiated by the attainment of a degree of ‘remoteness’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren 1985</xref>, p. 17). Of particular interest in relation to design is how fictional space is created through the practices of participants in design. As the subject of Malmgren’s study is literature, his explorations concern the relationship between author, text, and reader. Malmgren proposes that a fictional world is not a stable construct but a process; one that is re-created by the reader in the practice of reading. In a similar vein, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Worth (2004)</xref> argues that engaging in fiction is not a matter of suspending our critical faculties, but rather an exercise of our creative faculties. Two things in particular may be noted based on Malmgren and Worth. First of all, that fictional space intersects with the empirical world and conflates elements from both. Secondly, that fictional space is created from the practices of the reader. Yet the reader engages with what is provided in the form of the work of fiction. By analogy, participants in design engage with what is provided in the places where design is practiced. For a closer inquiry into this process, I turn to the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref> and his conceptualisation of how fictional space is created through the use of props. Walton is concerned with representational works of art, and argues that these representations work as props in games of make-believe similar to the games children play with toys. Indeed, Walton suggests that ‘In order to understand paintings, plays, films, and novels, we must look first at dolls, hobbyhorses, toy trucks, and teddy bears’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Walton 1990</xref>, p. 11). Fictional worlds are created through the use of props in practicing games of make-believe. Fictional worlds are thus imagined worlds. But the imagination is not an act of free or unassociated play. Props mandate particular forms of imagining in games of make-believe. In general, Walton identifies three functions that props may serve in games of make-believe and thus in the construction of fictional worlds. Props may act as prompters of imagination, e.g. when I look at the coffee cup placed next to my computer mouse I might imagine a new interaction device for my computer; if I rotated the cup I could browse through the content of my computer and when drinking the coffee I would free up space on my hard-drive. In this sense, props may prompt certain imaginings. In another sense, props may be the objects of imagination. In the example of the coffee cup, the cup is both the object of my imagination and the prompter of my imagination. However, it is not always the case that props are both object and prompter. The third function of props is that they may generate fictional truths and it is this function of props that will concern us most here, as this concerns the creation of fictional space. When we mockup a new device using paper and cardboard, the fact that we can press the buttons and that this device can use, for<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> example, internet services is a fictional truth in that it is true in the fictional world that is imagined. When we accept that this is the case, we may accordingly imagine a variety of things: that the cardboard device could in fact be used by several users, or that it could take on an entirely different shape. In short, the role of fictional truths is that they provide mandate to certain kinds of imaginings. In Walton’s terms, these activities are games of make-believe by which fictional worlds are constructed. Ehn and Kyng’s (1991) discussion on the use of mockups in PD illustrates this point in relation to design. They show how a cardboard box with a label saying ‘desktop laser printer’ works very well in the design game of envisioning the future work of typographers and journalists. What is stressed here is that these are, in the words of Walton, games of make-believe that create fictional worlds; worlds that are collections of the fictional truths (e.g. that the box is a laser printer). These worlds are not stable constructs, but subject to change as new fictional truths are created or changed. The creation of the worlds is thus a balance between people in some sense enacting what is given on the one hand (e.g. the work of the author or the staging of an event by the designer) and on the other hand the malleability as people change the structures of the worlds and contribute with new imaginings. Importantly, in relation to PD, the games of make-believe that Walton discusses are potentially shared among several participants. In this context, props assist in coordinating the imaginings of the participants. This point is exemplified and elaborated in the case study. So what is the picture created when these ideas are bridged to the world of design? Most critical to the motivation regarding design for museums (cf. section 2) and for the notion of fictional space is the issue of remoteness or distance, and, moreover, that fictional space intersects with what Malmgren terms the empirical world. In this sense, fictional worlds are both autonomous and at the same time related to the empirical world. Walton’s arguments about the creation of fictional space resonates with Jones’ (1970) assertion that designers are bound to treat as real that which only exists in an imagined future. The excursion to literary studies here has informed the notion of fictional space in several ways. First of all, it has highlighted the issue of fictional space as remote yet with connections to the empirical world and, when combining the ideas of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren (1985)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref>, that this remoteness may be instilled through the use of props. These props may serve to coordinate imagination among participants. What is imagined and how the fictional space develops has both aspects of people enacting what is afforded by the materials provided (props) and people bringing to the table novel insights or perhaps changing the very structure of the fictional truths that make up the fictional space. When we think of props in relation to design, we of course think of cardboard models and sketches. However, similar to Walton, we may also think of such things as narrative structures as representations and thus as props in games of make-believe. To further explore how these ideas may inform the exploration of the creation of fictional space in PD, I turn now to the case study. The focus here will not so much be on the particular design ideas that were developed during the session but on the imagined field of work, i.e. the design space as a fictional space, that was developed during the session. Keeping with the arguments from the previous sections, we may see the creation of fictional space as games of make-believe. In particular, the role of various props in this process is illustrated. The view presented here on the development of the design space is not exclusive, of course; many other aspects might influence the design space, such as: resources,<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> political issues, deadlines, etc. Moreover, it could be reasonably argued that the design space is best understood as developing constantly in the duration of the entire project. The insights provided here do not cover exhaustively the development of the design space over time in a given project. The goal here is more modest, namely to illustrate that the perspective of fictional space is valuable in understanding how the design space may develop as an imagined field of work that is in some respects distant from everyday practice.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="104" page="8" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="105" page="8" column="1">173</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dg.page_008.image_02.png" thmb="62dg.page_008.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="108" page="8" column="1">Figure 1. Trajectory and intersection between empirical and fictional world (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren 1985</xref>).</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="114" page="9" column="1">174</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="115" page="9" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="119" page="10" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="120" page="10" column="1">175</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="122" page="10" column="1">6. Case study: future museum spaces</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" page="10" column="1">The context of this case is recent years’ work where my colleagues and I have been involved in exploring the staging of PD events with the particular aim of facilitating the rethinking of existing practices within institutions. Our case derives from ongoing work with Moesga  ̊ rd Museum, which recently received funding to build a new museum by 2013 entailing the creation of completely new exhibition spaces. Our research efforts have been aimed at exploring new ways for the museum to involve visitors in the exhibitions and to rethink the museum experience in terms of communication, participation, and the museum’s relation to the community. The example here derives from the first workshop where museum staff, storytellers, technology providers, communication consultants, architects and design researchers were invited to collaboratively explore concepts for cultural heritage communication. The aim of the workshop was to create ideas for concrete installations that would act as springboards for the remainder of the project and as materialisations of new ways of thinking about cultural heritage communication. The workshop was initially structured around a fictional design task: participants were informed during the introduction that the sarcophagus of Tutankhamun was coming to the museum and that they had to design the exhibition. However, the participants were given five obstructions 1 that they had to incorporate in their proposal for the exhibition. The obstructions were meant to force participants to rethink existing practices of the museum. The obstructions were that (1) the exhibition should involve interactive technologies (not just ‘re-active’ technology), (2) that a significant part of the exhibition should use a counter-factual style of communication, (3) that the exhibition should revitalise the role of the body in exhibition spaces, (4) that a significant part of the content in the exhibition should be generated by the visitors, and finally (5) that parts of the exhibition should be located in the space of the city. The task for the groups of participants was to propose concrete exhibition concepts within this framework provided. Here, I will provide some insights into how this particular framing of the workshop provided the grounds for the creation of fictional space. In particular, the focus will be on one of the groups from the workshop. Having received the instructions, the group began working with the assignment. This process was characterised by at least two types of activities, the first being the exploration of possible strategies and subjects relating to how Tutankhamun would be exhibited. For example, one of the participants, a museum curator, proposed that Tutankhamun’s masks could be a central theme in the exhibition and could be related to the issue of ‘wearing masks’ in general and even that visitors themselves could be equipped with masks. Another activity was the exploration of the obstructions. One of the groups initially spent some time discussing one of the <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> obstructions in particular. The group was comprised of an architect, a professional storyteller and three curators. During their initial discussions the architect (architect) explicitly addresses the obstructions in the beginning of the session. Excerpt 1: Architect: The obstruction about being active [referring to obstruction nr. 1] is for me very much about creating one’s own content – not just about receiving (. . .) I mean, all the facts that can be told; relating this to one’s own experience I think would be very beautiful; for example relating one’s own body to the stature of the Tutankhamun; how big was he? How was it to be in the tomb?<marker type="block"/> Here there is an explicit interpretation of the first obstruction that was provided; that the issue about interactive is actually about ‘creating one’s own content’. In the terms of Walton, we can view the activity here as part of the game of make-believe. The participants invest effort in interpreting the props that were provided in the form of obstructions. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref>, props mandate particular forms of imagining as they mediate the generation of fictional truths. In the section above, we see a glimpse of the ongoing development of the fictional truths. The first obstruction is a prop that is used to generate a fictional truth: that in this game of make-believe one area of focus is imagining things that relate to people creating their own content. Of course, the interpretation provided by the architect is one of many and what is termed fictional truth is a concept that is negotiated and changed through the session as other participants suggest other interpretations. It does, however, illustrate how the props are used to mandate particular forms of imagining. The participants proceeded (from the example quoted above) to discuss how they could imagine the notion of ‘creating one’s own content’ might be realised in the exhibition space. In fact, the group’s work concluded with the development of a design concept where visitors tell their own stories into a mask (the masks of Tutankhamun). There are of course many other fictional truths at play here. The fact that Tutankhamun is to be exhibited at Moesga  ̊ rd Museum works as an underlying proposition. It does in the same sense mandate particular forms of imagining. The architect continues: Excerpt 2: Architect: And the other part of the story about Tutankhamun is the massive media coverage; that people would die when doing the excavation. There was a lot of hype around the whole excavation; I think that would be interesting to work in (. . .)<marker type="block"/> Here the architect draws attention to the media coverage that was associated with the original excavation and that this might have some role to play in the exhibition. Tutankhamun here works to mandate this particular line of imagining. Moreover, this second example illustrates the point made by Malmgren, that fictional spaces conflate elements from everyday practice and elements that have been made up. The fact that Tutankhamun is coming to Moesga  ̊ rd Museum is of course made up and exists in the session as a fictional truth. However, the media hype in relation to the excavation of Tutankhamun is not fictional. So the fictional space that emerges from this group’s work is a space that draws on both fictional elements and elements derived from non-fiction. This exemplifies Malmgren’s (1985) point, that fictional spaces most often draw on non-fictional elements and that they in fact intersect. Fictional spaces may be to a large extent autonomous, but they maintain links to non-fiction. This is the case both regarding how Tutankhamun works as a prop that<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> prompts particular imaginings, but also in the sense that the participants in the session initially held on to established ideas from their own practice; e.g. one of the museum curators (curator) suggested after having discussed ways of creating the exhibition: Excerpt 3: Curator: (. . .) but I think it would really be a shame not to tell all the wonderful stories about Tutankhamun; I mean, there is so much to work with. The architect comments after a brief exchange: Architect: (. . .) yeah, but I think that providing people with a way of creating their own content could be sort of a way into it [referring to telling stories about Tutankhamun]; I mean, the stories would be in a way discovered by relating to one’s own experience as a starting point.<marker type="block"/> The curator very much holds on to established practices within museums about telling stories related to the exhibited item. The architect, however, refers again to his former interpretation (see excerpt 1) about the fact that the first obstruction might be about allowing people to create something for themselves. In the group, this issue was discussed at length in particular between the architect and the curator. In the end, the groups decided to compromise and tried to incorporate ideas of ‘creating one’s own content’ as well as maintain a commitment to telling stories in a more conventional sense. What seems at stake in excerpt 3 is negotiating the fictional truths of their game of make-believe; what can be done and in what way in this game. It also shows that the fictional space being created here is not only one where the participants are to create an exhibition about a new thing (Tutankhamun) using traditional practices, but as the architect suggests, they may also explore new kinds of practices, e.g. by initially letting visitors and not the museum professionals tell the stories. The fact that the group ended up with a compromise exemplifies that the creation of fictional space is not a complete annihilation of existing practices; rather, these are re-shaped and put into new constellations. In this group’s work the new constellation led to a concept where visitors’ own contributions would be related to the stories provided by the museum. Relating to the issue of fictional space in terms of distance, we see here not only distance in the form of exhibiting a new item but also a distance in relation to the practices of creating the exhibition. This distance is initiated by the props provided in the form of narratives and obstructions, but it is in the particular game of make-believe played by the participants that the particular meaning of these props is constructed and the distance is created. The examples drawn from this session show how we may understand the activity of the participants as a game of make-believe where a range of props is used. Tutankhamun works to mandate particular imaginings about the exhibition theme. The obstructions on the other hand give mandate to the ways in which the exhibition is to be made. Yet the obstructions do not in themselves make up the design space for the groups. Rather, as shown from the example, the participants use the obstructions as props and continuously negotiate the meaning and significance of the obstructions. The props were provided with the intention of creating an imagined field of work where participants would break free from existing conventions and explore new ways of creating exhibition spaces. This, however, was accomplished by the groups using the props in their games of make-believe. This game intersected with other parts of the Tutankhamun story and with existing practices of creating<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> exhibitions. The props work here both as prompters of imagination, e.g. imagining things about Tutankhamun and, in the sense of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="136" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren (1985)</xref>, to generate fictional truths that become central in the space created by the groups, e.g. ‘that Tutankhamun is coming to Moesga  ̊ rd museum’ and ‘that interactive may actually mean creating one’s own content’. The props described in the examples so far have been of a somewhat non- physical nature. The obstructions were of course present on paper but did not have the physical qualities of, for example, a cardboard model. I will briefly provide a last example from the same workshop to illustrate the use of more physical props. I shall not attempt to define any inherent qualities of physical props but rather illustrate that these work in similar ways as the obstructions. As the last part of the workshop, the groups had to mock-up their design concepts using whatever materials they could find in the building including cardboard, paper, chairs, whiteboards, etc., and enact a scenario that illustrated a visit to the exhibition. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> (right) shows the work of the group from excerpt 1 to excerpt 3. The groups used props in the form of mobile boards along with Post-it Notes and other materials found in the room to illustrate their concepts. In terms of make-believe, the physical materials function as props and in this game one has to imagine that Post it Notes are digital displays and the blackboards are walls of the exhibition space. Contrary to the first examples, the group was free to choose any props that they might need – in the first example, the obstructions were, in a sense, mandatory props. So one aspect of the enacted scenario was that the group used props to illustrate their concept. However, even though the props were freely chosen, they still served the purpose of mandating particular forms of imagining. When the group worked on their scenario, they came across a video camera that had been left in one of the rooms. Based on this, the group decided to imagine that the video camera was a kind of inspection tool that visitors could use to closely inspect exhibited items (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>, left). The video camera prompted the imagination of the group to create an examining room where visitors could act as archeologists and inspect the items on display. Thus, the video camera was used as a prop in their story. But as they began to use the camera, it also mandated particular imaginings about the inspection room; the functions (buttons, dials, and lens) of the camera were incorporated into the scenario and provided new aspects to the idea of the inspection room. In this sense, the prop had a transactional nature in relation to the imagination of the groups; the group ‘created’ the meaning of the camera in their game of make-believe, but the camera also mandated particular imaginings that in</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="124" page="11" column="1">176</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="125" page="11" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="130" page="12" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="131" page="12" column="1">177</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="134" page="13" column="1">178</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="135" page="13" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62dg.page_013.image_03.png" thmb="62dg.page_013.image_03-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="141" page="13" column="1">Figure 2.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Left: one of the group members showing how the camera would work as an inspection tool. Right: the group using props to illustrate part of their final concept.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="143" page="14" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144" page="14" column="1">179</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" page="14" column="1">term shaped the outcome. Moreover, the use of the camera illustrates how props may be used to coordinate imagination among several participants, as it becomes a shared prop in their game. There were of course a wealth of props besides the camera and the blackboards, but only a fraction of these were deliberately brought into the game of make-believe. So in this example the physical props work in many respects similarly to the obstructions from the first example in that they both mandate imaginings, but also that the meaning and significance of these props is interpreted and negotiated. These examples show how the continuous use of props mandate particular imaginings. Yet they also illustrate the complexity of how fictional space is created through the games of make-believe; props are re-interpreted and given new meaning and fictional and non-fictional elements are drawn together in new configuration. The case illustrates how fiction in terms of distance is created as new configurations are established that break with some of the conventions of the everyday practices of the museum.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="146" page="14" column="1">7. Discussion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" page="14" column="1">The preceding paragraphs have provided a theoretical account as well as concrete examples of the continuous creation of fictional space in participatory design practice as participants engage in games of make-believe. Central to the notion of fictional space is the dynamic use of props and how these fundamentally shape the outcome of the design session. Relating to PD practice, there are several aspects to consider regarding props. In choosing particular props for design sessions, designers scaffold the creation of fictional space. These issues of staging are not foreign to PD. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Muller (2003)</xref> has provided a comprehensive account of the parameters, practices and props used in terms of creating hybridity in PD work. Muller addresses hybridity as the in-between regions that share attributes of both users’ and designers’ space leading to new interpretations and ideas. In many respects, the perspective of fictional space also marks hybridity in the sense of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Muller (2003)</xref>. The perspective offered here, however, reflects a particular concern for the process in which participants create fictional space. Based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Malmgren (1985)</xref>, I have described this process as practicing games of make-believe. Describing this process in terms of games implies that there are rules that structure the activity; that the imaginations of the participants are not free but mediated by props. As argued by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="151" class="deo:Reference">Walton (1990)</xref>, participants in games of make-believe create rules in the form of fictional truths that give mandate to certain imaginings. Excerpt 3 in the case illustrated how the interpretation of one of the obstructions created legitimacy for particular imaginings, namely those associated with ‘creating one’s own content’. The examples show how these rules are created by participants in the process, but also that these rules are continuously negotiated. In terms of fictional space as emerging from games of make-believe, it may be noted here how the rules of the game are emergent and open to interpretation as participants create new fictional truths that give mandate to particular imaginings. This does not mean that ‘anything goes’, but that the rules are created as transactions between props and participants. Moreover, it may be noted that the games of make-believe are not completely autonomous; rather, they conflate elements from everyday practice with elements that have been made up into new configurations. This was illustrated in the case by the groups using both fictional and non-fictional elements about Tutankhamun and<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> by some participants attempting to hold on to particular established practices within museum practice while breaking others. A first conclusion drawn from this is the importance of the props employed in design sessions. Yet even with the most meticulous planning, participants bring new interpretations to the table and alter the meanings. However, for PD practice this is a desirable outcome, as the voices and interpretations of participants are at the very core of PD practice. What has been provided in this paper are concepts for designers and researchers to gain a more nuanced understanding of the creation of fictional space in design practice as a foundation for staging and reflecting on design work. The perspective of fictional space does not prescribe a particular method or form of design inquiry. Rather, I suggest that the perspective enables reflection on three aspects of design inquiries. First, it provides concepts for reflecting on how design inquiries are staged in terms of the props chosen and how these are intended to promote particular avenues for participants to pursue. Second, the perspective provides concepts for reflection in action as design inquiries unfold by highlighting the dynamic processes in which fictional truths are created and negotiated among participants. Third, the perspective provides means for reflecting on the outcomes of design inquiries in terms of understanding how participants create new constellations by conflating elements from existing practices with novel conceptions. This third aspect enables reflection on how particular design concepts or ideas developed by participants are products of re-thinking existing practices.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="153" page="15" column="1">180</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="154" page="15" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="156" page="15" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">This research has been supported by the Danish Council for Strategic Research, grant 09- 063245 (Digital Urban Living). I thank my colleagues at centre for Digital Urban Living and the participants in the cultural heritage project.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="158" page="15" column="1">Note</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="160" page="15" column="1">1. The idea of ‘obstructions’ was adopted from the movie ‘The Five Obstructions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Von Trier and Leth 2003</xref>).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="161" page="15" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="15" column="1">Bell, G., Blythe, M., and Sengers, P., 2005. Making by making strange: defamiliarization and the design of domestic technologies. ACM Transactions on Computer–Human Interaction, 12 (2), 149–173.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="15" column="1">Brodersen, C., Dindler, C., and Iversen, O.S., 2008. Staging imaginative places for participatory prototyping. CoDesign, 4 (1), 19–30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="15" column="1">Bødker, S. and Grønbæk, K., 1991. Design in action: from prototyping by demonstration to cooperative prototyping. In: J. Greenbaum and M. Kyng, eds. Design at work: cooperative design of computer systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Publishing.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="15" column="1">Chua Soo Meng, J., 2008. Donald Scho  ̈ n, Herbert Simon and the sciences of the artificial. Design Studies, 30 (1), 60–68.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="15" column="1">Clement, A., Costantino, T., Kurtz, D., and Tissenbaum, M., 2008. Participatory Design and Web 2.0: the case of PIPWatch, the collaborative privacy toolbar. In: Proceedings of PDC 2008, Bloomington, Indiana, New York: ACM Press, 51–60.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="15" column="1">Dindler, C. and Iversen, O.S., 2007. Fictional inquiry – design collaboration in a shared narrative space. CoDesign, 3 (4), 213–234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="15" column="1">Dorst, K., 2003. The problem of design problems. Design thinking research symposium. University of Technology, Sydney.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="15" column="1">Eagleton, T., 2008. Literary theory: an introduction. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="16" column="1">Ehn, P., 1988. Work-oriented design of computer artifacts. Falko  ̈ ping, Sweden, Arbetslivscentrum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="16" column="1">Ehn, P. and Kyng, M., 1991. Cardboard computers: mocking-it-up or hands-on the future. In: J. Greenbaum and M. Kyng, eds. Design at work: cooperative design of computer systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Publishing.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="16" column="1">Falk, J. and Dierking, L., 1992. The Museum Experience. Washington, DC: Whalesback Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="16" column="1">Greenbaum, J. and Kyng, M., eds. 1991. Design at work: cooperative design of computer systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Publishing.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Hallna  ̈ s, L. and Redstro  ̈ m, J., 2006. Interaction design. Foundations. Experiments. Interactive Institute University College of Bora  ̊ s.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="16" column="1">Heape, C.R.A., 2007. The design space – the design process as the construction, exploration and expansion of a conceptual space. PhD Dissertation, Sønderborg, Denmark.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="16" column="1">Heath, C. and Lehn, D.V., 2008. Configuring ‘interactivity’: enhancing engagement in science centres and museums. Social Studies of Science, 38 (1), 63–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="16" column="1">Heath, C., Lehn, D.V., and Osborne, J., 2005. Interaction and interactives: collaboration and participation with computer-based exhibits. Public Understanding of Science, 14 (1), 91–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="16" column="1">Hornecker, E., Halloran, J., Fitzpatrick, G., Weal, M., Millard, D., Michaelides, D., Cruickshank, D., and De Roure, D., 2006. UbiComp in opportunity spaces: challenges for participatory design. In: Proceedings of PDC 2006, Trento, Italy, New York: ACM Press, 47–56.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="16" column="1">Iacucci, G., Iacucci, C., and Kuutti, K., 2002. Imagining and experiencing in design, the role of performances. In: Proceedings of NordiCHI 2002, Aarhus, Denmark, New York: ACM Press, 167–176.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="16" column="1">Iser, W., 1993. The fictive and the imaginary: charting literary anthropology. Baltimore, MD: John Hopkins Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="16" column="1">Jones, J.C., 1970. Design methods – seeds of human futures. London: John Wiley and Sons.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="16" column="1">Kambourov, D., 2000. When trapped, W. Iser’s literature obliterates its tale: The Fictive Imaginary and the Real-liart of Language. E-magazine LiterNet, 2 (3).</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="16" column="1">Kensing, F. and Halskov, K., 1991. Generating visions: future workshops and metaphorical design. In: J. Greenbaum and M. Kyng, eds. Design at work: cooperative design of computer systems. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Publishing.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="16" column="1">Kensing, F., Simonsen, J., and Bødker, K., 1996. MUST – a method for participatory design. In: Proceedings of PDC 1996, Cambridge, MA. New York: ACM Press, 129–140.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="16" column="1">Lerdahl, E., 2002. Using fantasy story writing and acting for developing product ideas. In: Proceedings of EURAM. European Academy of Management.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="16" column="1">Malmgren, C.D., 1985. Fictional space in the modernist and postmodernist American novel. Lewisberg, PA: Backnell University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="16" column="1">Muller, M.J., 2003. Participatory design: the third space in HCI. In: J. Jacko and A. Sears, eds. Handbook of HCI. Mahway, NJ: Erlbaum.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" page="16" column="1">Nelson, H. and Stolterman, E., 2003. The design way – intentional change in an unpredictable world. Eaglewood Cliffs, NJ: Educational Technology Publications.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="16" column="1">Raptis, D., Tselios, N., and Avouris, N., 2005. Context-based design of mobile applications for museums: a survey of existing practices. In: Proceedings of Mobile HCI, Salzburg, Austria.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="16" column="1">Rittel, H.W.J. and Webber, M.M., 1973. Dilemmas in a general theory of planning. Policy Sciences, 4 (1), 155–169.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="16" column="1">Schuler, D. and Namioka, A., eds. 1993. Participatory design– principles and practices. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="16" column="1">Scho  ̈ n, D., 1987. Educating the reflective practitioner. San Fransisco, CA: Jossey-Bass Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Scho  ̈ n, D., 1992. Designing as reflective conversation with the materials of the design situation. Research in Engineering Design, 3 (3), 131–147.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="16" column="1">Simon, H.A., 1969. The sciences of the artificial. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="16" column="1">Simon, H.A., 1973. The structure of ill structured problems. Artificial Intelligence, 4 (4), 181– 201.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="16" column="1">Sjo  ̈ berg, C. and Timpka, T., 1998. Participatory design of information systems in health care. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 5 (2), 177–183.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="17" column="1">Sparacino, F., 2004. Scenographies of the past and museums of the future: from the wunderkammer to body-driven interactive narrative spaces. In: Proceedings of the 12th annual ACM international conference on Multimedia. New York: ACM Press, 72–79.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Taxe  ́ n, G., 2004. Introducing participatory design in museums. In: Proceedings of DIS 2004, Toronto, Canada. New York: ACM Press, 204–213.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Telier, A.. ed. forthcoming. Design Things. MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="17" column="1">Vergo, P., 1989. The new museology. London: Reaktion Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="17" column="1">Von Trier, L and Leth, J., 2003. The five obstructions. Zentropa Real.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="17" column="1">Walton, K.L., 1990. Mimesis as make-believe. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="17" column="1">Woods, E., Billingshurst, M., Aldridge, G., and Garrie, B., 2004. Augmenting the science centre and museum experience. In: Proceedings of International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, Singapore, New York: ACM Press, 230–236.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Worth, S.E., 2004. Fictional spaces. The Philosophical Forum, 35 (4), 439–455.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="170" page="16" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="171" page="16" column="1">181</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="199" page="17" column="1">182</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="200" page="17" column="1">C. Dindler</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
