<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>93e2ab94d66b95e2f17df6a4b7446cf8ca21faefd444ddd5e5ff5c034b5e161f</job>
    <base_name>62k1</base_name>
    <doi>10.1016/S0263-7863(03)00047-4</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams: an empirical study of the processes and their dynamic interrelationships</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Patrick S.W. Fong</name>
          <aff id="4">*</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="14" page="1" column="1">* Tel.: +852-2766-5801; fax: +852-2764-5131. E-mail address: <email id="13">bspafong@polyu.edu.hk</email> (P.S.W. Fong).</footnote>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">Department of Building &amp; Real Estate, Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong Received 15 January 2002; received in revised form 20 September 2002; accepted 28 March 2003</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6">This paper reviews key literature on team processes and knowledge creation. Specifically, it assesses and synthesises relevant theories and thoughts to develop a conceptual model of the knowledge creation process. Empirical evidence, collected from two projects—an infrastructure development project and a residential development project—is also exploited as a means of building a conceptual model of knowledge creation. This paper explains the processes of knowledge creation within the context of multidisciplinary project teams. It also considers the dynamic interrelationships between the proposed processes. The paper provides a framework not only for future research to systematically examine and test knowledge creation processes within different team situations, but also to allow management to continuously anticipate knowledge creation activities within their own organisations. This research contributes to studies of organisational knowledge and knowledge creation by providing an explorative account that synthesises the existing literature with empirical evidence. Secondly, this research contributes to the theoretical development of knowledge creation by focusing on its processes rather than just on its outcomes and implications, which have been the main con- cern of other researchers. Finally, the development of a multidisciplinary knowledge creation theory contributes to the consolida- tion of the various dimensions of knowledge-related activities that have in the past been treated in isolation. # 2003 Elsevier Ltd and IPMA. All rights reserved. Keywords: Knowledge creation; Multidisciplinary project teams; Processes; Dynamic interrelationships</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="1" column="1">1.1. Knowledge as an important resource</h2>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="2" column="1">1.2. Knowledge creation and new product development teams</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="2" column="1">Several researchers have described new product development as a knowledge-intensive activity [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="29" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. New product development often involves cross-functional linkages, where different participants join a team with differing viewpoints. Such teams are often characterised according to the risk and synergy resulting from their interaction with other team members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="30" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. Morrison and Kennedy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="31" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] suggest that this interaction brings in the need to organise, integrate, filter, condense and anno- tate the collaborative data and other relevant information that these team members contribute. Creating new knowledge and perspectives is funda- mental to new product development. A new product can be considered as ‘‘a package of features and benefits, each of which must be conceived, articulated, designed and ‘operationalised’, or brought into existence’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="32" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>], p. 425). The development of a constructed facility can be viewed as a new product development, with customers or end-users purchasing or using the facility. They would assess their own needs and affordability before they purchase. The development of a new product entails the application of knowledge to new problem- oriented situations, thus requiring uncertainty reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="33" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>]. The same applies to construction projects, with each project unique in itself in terms of design and construction. With the many constraints the construction industry faces (due to limited space, increasing project complexity, limited budgets, tight programmes and the constant demand for facility innovation), project teams are faced with challenges to utilise diverse knowledge and create new knowledge in order to meet stringent requirements and fulfil ever-changing needs. Project team members have to incorporate new information into their understanding in order to solve the technical challenges they face. Thus, learning is inherent in the work they do [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="34" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]. A number of researchers investigating product innovation have emphasised the importance of a team approach in successful product development (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="35" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]). Project team members with diverse skills, knowledge and experiences are required to work together to resolve<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the issues or problems encountered in a project. Though there is extensive literature covering teams (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="37" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]) and the benefits they can bring to organisations (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="38" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]), a focus on the processes of knowledge creation from a multidisciplinary project team perspective is compelling as research specifically addressing this issue appears to be very limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="39" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>]. Senge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="40" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] suggests that creating knowledge at the team level is essential for long-term team effectiveness, innovation and pro- ductivity. In addition, a team can be viewed as a socially constructed phenomenon or linking mechanism that integrates individuals and organisations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="41" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. For con- sistency reasons, no distinction has been made between the term ‘team’ or ‘group’. Instead, both words are used interchangeably throughout the paper.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="1">The increasing importance of knowledge has been proposed as a central feature of post-industrial societies [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="9" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>], with knowledge considered as a primary economic resource. Knowledge is one of the most important resources to an organisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="10" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], and may be ‘‘the only meaningful resource’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="11" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>], p. 42). Intellectual or knowl- edge-based assets have been distinguished from the more traditional factors of production, such as land, labour and machinery. Unlike traditional factors of production, knowledge is intangible, residing within individuals. As a result, it may be more difficult to locate and harness, and may be easily lost. In order to compete in knowledge-intensive indus- tries, an organisation must continuously create, utilise<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and disseminate new knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="16" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. D’Aveni [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="17" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] rea- soned that given the dynamic environments faced by most organisations, those capable of producing a continuous stream of new knowledge are best positioned to achieve competitive advantage. In order to compete, firms must acquire, retain and integrate knowledge, and be able to facilitate the creation of knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="18" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>]. Nonaka et al. ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="19" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>], p. 2) suggest that the reason for a firm’s existence is to ‘‘continuously create knowledge’’. Attempting to develop and sustain competitive advantage so as to survive intensive competition, organisations are focusing their resources and processes on generating unique knowledge embodied in new and innovative products or services. Although many organisations are beginning to seek more sophisticated organisational structures, or train personnel in many managerial, creative or teamwork skills, many are still likely to have difficulty in being continuously innovative. They may be highly effective in exploiting existing knowledge in the short term, but there is likely to be relatively little long-term learning and knowledge<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> creation, particularly if individuals and knowledge are isolated and fragmented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="24" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>]. Bringing the collective knowledge of members in teams to bear on serving customers or clients is practically important because knowledge is a source of competitive advantage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="25" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. Knowledge-creating skills in particular are important as they are required to create new products or processes, or to enhance existing ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="26" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]. Learning must be integrated with current tasks, not only to meet present goals, but also to develop and retain knowledge for future organisational needs.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="2">www.elsevier.com/locate/ijproman</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21" page="1" column="2">0263-7863/03/$30.00 # 2003 Elsevier Ltd and IPMA. All rights reserved. doi:10.1016/S0263-7863(03)00047-4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="22" page="2" column="1">480</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23" page="2" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="2" column="2">2. Conceptual framework</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="2" column="2">In this section, key issues identified in the literature review are summarised and synthesised in order to identify theoretical gaps, leading to the identification of major research questions to be explored in this paper. The current research examines the underlying processes and their interrelationships in knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams. The issue of knowledge has been debated for several centuries [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="44" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. Knowledge has only recently been viewed as a collective phenomenon in organisational contexts. Two conflicting theoretical perspectives about knowledge have emerged during the course of this research. The first perspective, as highlighted by Wernerfelt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="45" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>], focuses on the resource-based view, where knowledge is professed as a set of strategically important commod- ities that exist independent of their creators and are context-independent, i.e. the firm’s primary role is as knowledge applicator. The second perspective, from Berger and Luckmann [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="46" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>], perceives knowledge as a set of shared beliefs that are constructed through social interactions and embedded within the social contexts in which knowledge is created, i.e. the firm’s primary role is as knowledge creator. This view of knowledge elabo- rates the social construction perspective held by this study of trying to understand knowledge creation processes and investigate the phenomenon of knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams. The literature on knowledge creation at team levels is rather limited, particularly in relation to multidisciplinary project teams. Recognition of this fact has led this research to emphasise the multidisciplinary team context in order to fill a theoretical gap. The present framework for examining the knowledge creation processes within multidisciplinary project teams is based on Nonaka and Takeuchi’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="47" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] organisational knowledge creation theory. Nonaka and Takeuchi’s theory is utilised because it is one of the few<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> knowledge creation theories available that examines the interrelationships between explicit and tacit knowledge. Furthermore, Nonaka and Takeuchi’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="51" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] theory was inductively developed using case studies of product development projects, so the focus on technical knowledge creation is appropriate for this study. As illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>, the processes of organisational knowledge creation give rise to cycles that feed off each other. How organisations view knowledge creation seems to be dependent on their organisational culture. Nonaka and Takeuchi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="53" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] explain that the superiority of the Japanese continuous innovation has been due to their strong emphasis on socialisation, i.e. sharing tacit knowledge directly, and internalisation, i.e. individuals’ own participation in learning-by-doing. In contrast, the Western focus is more on externalisation, i.e. heavily emphasising explicit knowledge and combination. This is due to the epistemological difference whereby ‘‘Westerners tend to emphasise explicit knowledge and the Japanese tend to stress tacit knowledge’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="54" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], p. 243). Moreover, in Japanese society, knowledge is mainly created on a group level through dialogue, whereas in Western organisations the link between individual learning and organisational learning is less obvious. This stems from the ontological difference between their focus on individual and group, whereby ‘‘Westerners are more focused on individuals, while the Japanese are more group-oriented’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="55" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], p. 243). They add that in the West, work at group-level is devoted to carrying out pre-defined tasks rather than maintaining dialogue through which tasks are newly defined and further developed. Conversely, Japanese firms are less adapted to managing large complex systems, requiring extensive articulation and transfer of knowledge to the environment through products, patents and people.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> However, Nonaka and Takeuchi’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="60" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] knowledge creation model has some limitations that lessen its suitability for the study of knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams. Their primary distinction between tacit and explicit knowledge is pro- blematic, as tacit or unarticulated knowledge is always a precondition for explicit knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="61" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>]. Tuomi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="62" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>] also criticises the model for taking culture and language for granted. The difficulty of discussing the role of language as a ‘‘repository of culturally shared meaning’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="63" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>], p. 340), critical for any knowledge creation theory, may make its use difficult for multidisciplinary project teams. It is also not clear what happens when the knowledge-creating spiral expands outside a team: is knowledge still created in the same way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="64" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]? As Tuomi points out ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="65" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>], p. 328), ‘‘there is no model of social activity within the [knowledge creation] model—the motives for knowledge creation, and their relations to individual or organisational needs, remain obscure. Why some knowledge is created, and why some knowledge is not, remains an open question’’. Furthermore, Tuomi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="66" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>] finds that though Nonaka and Takeuchi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="67" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] stress that the process of knowledge creation is ‘social’, their underlying focus is on individual and intra-personal knowledge. He adds that ‘‘as their concept of knowledge is intra-personal, truth becomes a necessary aspect of knowledge, grounding intra-personal knowledge into interpersonal reality’’ ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="68" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>], p. 333). In order to overcome some of the shortcomings in Nonaka and Takeuchi’s knowledge creation model, if one accepts the social construction perspective of knowledge as a set of shared beliefs constructed through social interaction amidst certain social circumstances, then both individual and social levels require acknowl- edgement and integration. Specifically, by adding the social construction and communication elements to Nonaka and Takeuchi’s model, we have distinguished three modes of knowledge creation. They are ‘knowl- edge-sharing’, ‘knowledge integration’ and ‘collective project learning’. In this study, we regard knowledge- sharing as a multitude of processes taking place directly without language (socialisation) and with language (externalisation). Designing a facility requires collaborative interaction of individuals from different professional backgrounds. Their diverse expertise represents different interests and issues. Those different experiences, mental models and motivations can be expressed only partly in explicit language. Thus, socialisation is a valuable mode of sharing knowledge in teams without language through imitation, observation and sharing experiences face-to-face. Nonaka [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="69" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>] emphasises that socialisation is also an important way to further trust between partners. Saint-Onge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="70" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>] refers to socialisation as a way of creating a sufficient level of congruence to enable individuals to understand each<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> other and work together towards their common goals from different perspectives. Besides sharing without language, sharing work-related expertise requires the use of language. Social constructionists regard language as coordination of action [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="74" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>] and therefore a funda- mental tool in knowledge creation. The commonly employed tool in externalisation is dialogue. Dialogue triggers the unconscious elements of knowing and not- knowing, as well as revealing gaps in knowledge com- pared to what the community knows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="75" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>]. An important aspect of knowledge integration is the willingness to combine knowledge from within and outside the team. The more differentiated the knowledge inputs needed in a task, the higher the knowledge diversity and the greater the scope for knowledge integration. Design, involving art, engineering, finance and business, is a process of knowledge integration, and a facility’s design emerges from the collaboration of project participants and stakeholders. Leonard-Barton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="76" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>] views creation of new knowledge by combining previously unconnected elements or by developing ways of combining elements previously associated. Innovation teams are likely to engage in effective knowledge-sharing and integration to achieve their pre- defined goals, but do their processes include activities to ensure the future creation of knowledge as well? Nonaka and Takeuchi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="77" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] claim that large Western organisations are not good at internalising learning from their activities at the team level. There is a strong emphasis on converting tacit knowledge to explicit knowledge, but less is done to support the further generation of tacit knowledge. Learning usually has a more open-ended and long-term focus.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="49" page="3" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="50" page="3" column="1">481</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62k1.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62k1.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="59" page="3" column="1">Fig. 1. Knowledge conversion processes (adapted from Nonaka and Konno, 1998; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="58" class="deo:Reference">35</xref>]).</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="72" page="4" column="1">482</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="73" page="4" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="79" page="4" column="1">3. Research method</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="4" column="1">The main focus of this research is to explore the underlying processes of knowledge creation in a multidisciplinary project team setting, while determining the interrelationships between these processes. Taking into account the explorative nature of the study and the complexity of the issues, a more holistic approach has been adopted towards the study of specific phenomena. As a result, two in-depth case studies were used to obtain as thorough a picture as possible of the attributes and practices affecting knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams. An explorative case study would enable the researcher to examine assumptions in the literature while remaining open to new explanations and evidence. It is ‘‘an explicit attempt to interpret the narrative but also to link emerging conceptual and theoretical ideas inductively derived from the case both to stronger analytical themes within the case and wider theoretical debates in the literature’’ ([ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="80" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>], p. 280).<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The choice of the construction and real estate sectors for a study on knowledge creation was influenced by their huge effect on the local economy. Two project teams—infrastructural and residential—with diverse design concepts, discipline and knowledge bases, skills and possibly attitudes towards knowledge creation, were considered. Both cases shared common involve- ment in the construction of two large-scale projects on a ‘green field’ site. In addition, the nature of the work is information and knowledge intensive, requiring the teams to develop new or utilise existing technologies, techniques and processes to achieve their work goals. The nature of project team at work is both intellectual and interactive. It is intellectual in that it requires the team to find novel or hidden solutions to complex problems, and it is interactive as it requires constant co- operation between all participants in the design development process. However, these two projects differed in many respects. The nature of the tasks was different, as were the personnel involved and the ways in which design knowledge was created. The selection of the cases hoped to gain further insight into the multiple and divergent phenomena fuelling the different modes of knowledge creation during design development. All the while, the study views knowledge as a dynamic phenomenon. The selection of the residential development project recognises the large reservoir of idiosyncratic knowledge developed by the case organisation over the years. It also recognises the crucial innovating dynamics behind the need to compete on the market with other residential developments. The infrastructure project presented alternative opportunities for knowledge creation and learning, unique in several respects. Firstly, it was a complex operation, distinguished by an extraordinary multiplicity of consultants being employed. Secondly it was rare to find such a project, usually managed by government, in private hands. Finally, the technical challenges presented in this project made it an interest- ing arena for knowledge creation and absorption within the team. Evidence for the case studies relied on three main sources collected over a 14-month period—documenta- tion and organisational records, interviews, and finally direct observation.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="83" page="4" column="2">4. Knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" page="4" column="2">Beyond modifying Nonaka and Takeuchi’s [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="84" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] model of knowledge conversion processes, a major and sig- nificant finding is that the collaborative nature of multidisciplinary project teams is essential in creating new knowledge. With a traditional focus on professional specialisation, many facility projects may be managed<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> with tasks being executed in parallel or in sequence, or by certain project team members in isolation. This is often counter-productive when projects are so designed that the success of creating new knowledge among diverse disciplines may suffer, with optimal value possibly not achieved. The first process in knowledge creation involves boundary crossing, with two types of boundary identified as affecting the progress and success of multidisciplinary knowledge creation. The importance of boundary crossing is reflected in solving the boundary paradox’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="88" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>], where team members are able to exchange and combine knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="89" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]. The interactions across these boundaries can either foster or hinder knowledge creation. The first boundary identified was between team members of different disciplines. The second boundary existed between client, consultant and contractor. The expertise boundaries could be crossed, not only through knowledge redundancy among team members, but also through boundary objects. The most prominent project boundary objects were drawings and personal conversations among team members. The second hierarchical boundaries could be crossed through team members consciously breaking down any barriers by valuing the expertise of others. The example set by the project managers was also helpful in this regard. It must be stressed that crossing boundaries does not necessarily guarantee the creation of knowledge. It is seen, however, as a pre-requisite for the four remaining processes to occur. The second process relates to knowledge-sharing, with project team members of differing knowledge domains more likely to discuss their uniquely distinct information and knowledge than those who possess information in common. It seemed to be an advantage to have a diverse pool of knowledge for team members to access and share in discussion. Despite the existence of little competition among team members, external competition could act as a double-edged sword in the knowledge-sharing process. Sharing important market or design knowledge could lead to imitation by competitors, possibly even resulting in project poaching. In addition, the type of communication appeared more influential in the transfer of tacit knowledge than in that of explicit knowledge. For tacit knowledge to be effec- tively transmitted, interpersonal communication seemed of the utmost importance. The third process to be considered is that of knowledge generation, in which teams create knowledge by generating new or ‘emergent’ knowledge through interaction and communication. New or emergent knowledge, not possessed before discussion, can develop through group discussion and interaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="90" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>]. The development of emergent knowledge is vital for creativ- ity and innovation. It is generated through various means, including those of social networks, printed sources, and customer and competitor feedback.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Social networks were identified as the most important vehicle for information and knowledge exchange, with team members heavily reliant upon colleagues, friends and ex-colleagues as rich resources for generating design knowledge. The use of printed data in the design process appeared to be limited, viewed as time-consuming and used mainly to cross-check solutions offered. Social networks tended to recommend published materials, helping to reduce research time and enhance usability. However, they could potentially restrict the generation of new knowledge, improving on existing situations or learning from projects, as team members might resort to antecedent project approaches or activities. Compre- hension of customer needs, insight into competitor products and an inspection of completed facilities all seemed to stimulate knowledge generation. Fourth is knowledge integration, realised by marrying the differing perspectives and knowledge of various disciplines in the design decision-making process. It enables different stakeholder views to be incorporated so that they can be considered and integrated. Facilities design requires multidisciplinary skills and knowledge input. Various team members brought different sets of assumptions about optimal ways to proceed, prioritising different values and perspectives to ultimately best meet stakeholder requirements as well as arrive at satisfac- tory design solutions. Project documentation, as well as various design objects, were used as tools to integrate the range of knowledge input from project participants. The fifth process involves collective project learning, in which professionals with extensive experience in self- directed learning learn from the projects they are engaged in. Project team members had to constantly absorb new technology and techniques in order to remain competitive. Experts in self-directed learning, they created an environment maximising opportunities for individual inquiry and learning. Problem-solving being central to their work, they also recognised that failure was an opportunity for learning and understanding. Understanding failure is a primary mechanism in learning how new technology and systems operate, optimally avoiding repetitive mistakes. Therefore, con- siderable effort should be made to support an indivi- dual’s critical problem-solving and reflection processes. Individuals then develop personal strategies based on their own thinking and learning preferences. The project teams themselves encouraged team learning activities, independent of any directives. Small sub- teams typically pooled their resources for learning, acquiring the necessary skills and knowledge to solve problems in an open and permissive environment. Individuals shared their information-seeking strategies so that the sub-team might learn in as many different ways as possible. The larger project teams followed more formal processes and procedures for sharing and inter- acting. The smaller teams contributed directly to the<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> work of the larger project teams, but they were not for- mally recognised in the organisational structure of the projects. They spontaneously grouped and regrouped, navigated by the team members themselves. Most for- mations were temporary, lasting only until the immedi- ate goals were accomplished. Inter-project learning can be seen as gaining knowledge from a project and transferring it directly or indir- ectly to other subsequent or concurrent projects. It can happen both concurrently or sequentially. In concurrent transfer, a project transfers knowledge to another project before the tasks of the current project are completed. Sequential transfer occurs when knowledge and experience from a completed project are transferred to a subsequent project. This transfer is not identified from interviews but from direct observation in team meetings. Once knowledge and experience are gained from a completed project, they become part of the team members’ knowledge and expertise and are hard to identify separately. Central to inter-project learning is a certain degree of repetitiveness between projects, whe- ther they are task similarities or the principles are the same. The most widely observed strategy in inter-project learning occurred in team members engaged in multiple projects rather than where knowledge was codified in any format. Now that the major findings of the research have been discussed, their integration is attempted. This results in a new model specific to the multidisciplinary project team setting and is presented in the next section.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="86" page="5" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="87" page="5" column="1">483</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="93" page="6" column="1">484</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94" page="6" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="96" page="6" column="1">Fig. 2. The interrelationships between multidisciplinary knowledge creation processes.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="97" page="6" column="2">5. Interrelationships between the five processes of knowledge creation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" page="6" column="2">Knowledge creation in multidisciplinary project teams starts with the pre-requisite boundary-crossing process, which then leads to the three knowledge processes of knowledge-sharing, knowledge generation and knowledge integration. Collective project learning is central to the three knowledge processes. This shows that the knowledge creation processes within multidisciplinary teams are not linear. Instead, they are interwoven, occurring throughout the projects, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>. It was found in both cases that the project teams needed to cross boundaries imposed both by the range of diverse professional disciplines and also by the hierarchical divisions of client, consultant and contractor before genuine work, problem-solving or pertinent knowledge creation could occur. Without boundary- crossing, team members could focus simply on their own disciplinary work without due regard for or collaboration with other disciplines. In crossing these two boundaries, they could initiate the three knowledge processes through joint problem-solving. Once the design issues and problems influencing several disciplines have been identified, knowledge can be shared using their own experience and perspectives. This shared knowledge could include both positive as well as nega- tive experiences. In this process, they might also examine various issues like assumptions, constraints, etc. If the team members possess insufficient knowledge to resolve the situation, or if the situation is not familiar,<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> they can then proceed to the next circular process of knowledge generation, where knowledge from various sources is elicited to fill the knowledge gaps. This happens frequently in design situations, where team members may not have the necessary expertise or experience to generate the pertinent knowledge. Individuals draw on their own resources to generate new knowledge. Once the required knowledge is elicited, knowledge integration will happen by combining all knowledge. In this respect, the knowledge-sharing and generation processes are repetitive until sufficient knowledge is found to solve the issue at hand. In some situations where the design problems are familiar, team members can re-use existing knowledge. This implies that generation of new knowledge is not necessary. However, due to changing customer needs, unique design inputs, and new technologies or regulations, continuous improvements and initiatives may often be required to generate new knowledge rather than re-use existing knowledge. Once team members have sourced new or emergent knowledge, they need to integrate their collective knowledge. This involves combining, modifying and negotiating among team members so that not only their needs but also those of stakeholders are fulfilled. Drawing this balance is in fact an intricate process, requiring full appreciation of the multiple perspectives held by all stakeholders, including project team members. The knowledge creation process does not stop here. Through the processes of knowledge-sharing, generation and integration, a lot of the emergent knowledge accessed by individual team members or the team as a whole will be learnt, absorbed and turned into valuable experience that may be utilised again in the future. Collective project learning is the nucleus of all three knowledge processes (i.e. sharing, generation and integration). In addition, collective project learning can occur within individuals and teams, as well as at inter- project levels.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100" page="7" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="101" page="7" column="1">485</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="103" page="7" column="1">6. Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="7" column="1">This research has arrived at a new model of knowledge creation within multidisciplinary project teams, differing from the organisational knowledge creation theory developed by Nonaka and Takeuchi [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="104" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. It places primary emphasis on the processes rather than the outcomes of multidisciplinary knowledge creation as put forward by previous researchers. A new model of knowledge creation within multidisciplinary project teams is proposed and illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>. In the model, the five processes of knowledge creation are identified, including the processes of boundary-crossing, knowledge-sharing, knowledge generation, knowledge integration and collective project learning. The interrelationships of these five processes<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> are elaborated to enable a thorough understanding of them. It must be stressed that these knowledge creation processes within multidisciplinary teams are not linear. Instead they are interwoven, occurring throughout projects. Through these interwoven processes, new or emergent knowledge is created within the project team, or existing knowledge is combined to form new insights. This model provides a critical comparison with existing organisational knowledge creation model and has tried to embrace past literature related to team processes and knowledge creation.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="7" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" page="7" column="2">[1] Bell D. The coming of post-industrial society: a venture in social forecasting. New York: Basic Books; 1973.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="110" page="7" column="2">[2] Nonaka I, Takeuchi H. The knowledge-creating company: how Japanese companies create the dynamics of innovation. Oxford University PressOxford; 1995.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="111" page="7" column="2">[3] Drucker PF. Post-capitalist society. Oxford: Butterworth-Heine- mann; 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="112" page="7" column="2">[4] Dougherty D. Interpretive barriers to successful product innovation in large firms. Organization Science 1992;3(2):179–202.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="113" page="7" column="2">[5] D’Aveni RA. Hypercompetition. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster; 1994.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="114" page="7" column="2">[6] Nonaka I, Ichijo K. Creating knowledge in the process organization: a comment on Denison’s chapter. Advances in Strategic Management 1997;14:45–52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="115" page="7" column="2">[7] Nonaka I, Toyama R, Nagata A. A firm as a knowledge-creating entity: a new perspective on the theory of the firm. Industrial and Corporate Change 2000;9:1–20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="116" page="7" column="2">[8] Dachler HP. Management and leadership as relational phenomena. In von Cranach M, Doise W, Mugny G, editors. Social representations and the social bases of knowledge. Swiss Mono- graphs in Psychology, vol. 1; 1992: 169–178.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="117" page="7" column="2">[9] Prahalad CK, Hamel G. The core competence of the corporation. Harvard Business Review 1990;68(3):79–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="118" page="7" column="2">[10] Leonard-Barton D. Wellsprings of knowledge: building and sus- taining the sources of innovation. Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press; 1995.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="119" page="7" column="2">[11] Iansiti M, MacCormack A. Developing products on Internet time. Harvard Business Review 1997;75(5):108–17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" page="7" column="2">[12] Jassawalla AR, Sashittal HC. An examination of collaboration in high-technology new product development processes. Journal of Product Innovation Management 1998;15(3):237–54.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" page="7" column="2">[13] Morrison R, Kennedy J. Advances in databases. Paper presented at the 14th British National Conference on Databases, Edin- burgh, Scotland; 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" page="7" column="2">[14] Dougherty D. Organizing for innovation. In: Clegg SR, Hardy C, Nord WR, editors. Handbook of organization studies. London: Sage; 1996. p. 424–39.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="123" page="7" column="2">[15] Cyert R, March J. A behavioral theory of the firm. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall; 1963.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="124" page="7" column="2">[16] Mohrman SA, Mohrman Jr AM, Cohen SG. Organizing knowledge work system. In: Beyerlein MM, Johnson DA, Beyerlein ST, editors. Advances in interdisciplinary studies of work teams. Greenwich, CT: JAI Press; 1995. p. 61–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" page="7" column="2">[17] Clark K, Fujimoto T. Product development performance: Strat- egy, organisation, and management in the world auto industry. Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press; 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="126" page="7" column="2">[18] Cohen SG, Bailey D. What makes teams work: group effectiveness research from the shop floor to the executive suite. Journal of Management 1997;23(3):239–90.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="7" column="2">[19] Ancona DG, Caldwell DF. Bridging the boundary: external <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> activity and performance in organizational teams. Administrative Science Quarterly 1992;37:634–65.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="8" column="1">[20] Newell S, Swan J. Trust and inter-organizational networking. Human Relations 2000;53(10):1287–328.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="8" column="1">[21] Senge PM. The fifth discipline: the art and practice of the learning organization. New York: Currency Doubleday; 1990.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="8" column="1">[22] Horvath L, Callahan JL, Croswell C, Mukri G. Team sensemak- ing: an imperative for individual and organizational learning. Paper presented at the Academy of Human Resource Develop- ment Conference; 1996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="134" page="8" column="1">[23] Wernerfelt B. A resource-based view of the firm. Strategic Management Journal 1984;5(2):171–80.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="8" column="1">[24] Berger PL, Luckmann T. The social construction of reality: A treatise in the sociology of knowledge. Garden City, NY: Doubleday; 1966.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" page="8" column="1">[25] Polanyi M. The tacit dimension. New York: Doubleday; 1962.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="8" column="1">[26] Tuomi I. Corporate knowledge—theory and practice of intelli- gent organizations. Helsinki: Metaxis; 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" page="8" column="1">[27] Nonaka I. A dynamic theory of organizational knowledge creation. Organization Science 1994;5(1):14–37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="8" column="2">[28] Saint-Onge H. Tacit knowledge: the key to the strategic alignment of intellectual capital. Planning Review 1996;24(2): 10–14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="8" column="2">[29] Burr V. An introduction to social constructionism. London: Routledge; 1995.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="8" column="2">[30] Ayas K. Design for learning and innovation. Long Range Planning 1996;29(6):898–901.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="8" column="2">[31] Pettigrew AM. Longitudinal field research on change: theory and practice. Organization Science 1990;1(3):267–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="8" column="2">[32] Quintas P, Lefrere P, Jones G. Knowledge management: a strategic agenda. Long Range Planning 1997;30(3):385–91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="8" column="2">[33] Nahapiet J, Ghoshal S. Social capital, intellectual capital, and the organizational advantage. Academy of Management Review 1998;23(2):242–66.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="8" column="2">[34] Kogut B, Zander U. Knowledge of the firm, combinative cap- abilities, and the replication of technology. Organization Science 1992;3(3):383–97.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="8" column="2">[35] Nonaka I, Konno N. The concept of Ba: Building a foundation for knowledge creation. California Management Review 1998; 40(3):40–54.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="128" page="8" column="1">486</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="129" page="8" column="1">P.S.W. Fong / International Journal of Project Management 21 (2003) 479–486</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
