<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>fc05ec10cd44a1e0ae5256a7900158e681012597eee00ea28f5f523aa6adf5ba</job>
    <base_name>62kh</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1578475</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="unknown" id="1">THEORETICAL PERSPECTIVES</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Jonathan Fish</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Stephen Scrivener</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5" confidence="possible">Althoughnewtechnology widely used fordetailed design imagemanipulation, its use inthe earlystages of visual invention muchless common, one reason beingthatthe denotation systems usedinpaper-and-pencil sketching assist creativity in waysthatare poorly understood. Leonardo da Vinci advocated the use of untidy is fluctuating in imagination. indeterminacies for working out In contrast, computer-aided composition, because he believed 'flood fill' colouring requires a tion.Recent thattheystimulated research visual in cognitive inven- precisely drawn, closed bound- psychology suggests a mental- ary in which the smallest gap imagery model thatexpands Leo- spells disaster. Before new sys- nardo's theory andprovides evi- tems and media can be de- denceforcognitive mechanisms thatclarify the function of familiar veloped that allow artists to sketchattributes. Sketchesmay manipulate the incomplete im- mediate mental translation between ages characteristic of early spatially depictive andstructurally sketches, the system designer descriptive modes of visual repre- needs an understanding of the sentation. Evidence for a hybrid percept-image theory of ordinary cognitive functions performed papersketching is briefly outlined. by ordinary 'back of an envel- Someimplications of thistheory ope' pencil and paint sketch- the development of improved coming. How do scribbled lines or puter sketching systems arebriefly discussed. washes of colour support and stimulate visual invention? What inferences can be made about the cognitive processes and representations with which they are interacting?</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">FROM DESCRIPTION TO DEPICTION: A CONTINUUM OF VISUAL REPRESENTATION</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Jonathan Fish (educator, scientist, artist), 21 College Road, Cheltenham, Gloucestershire, GL53 7HX, U.K. Stephen Scrivener (computer scientist, artist), Department of Computing, University of Technology, Loughborough, Leicestershire, U.K. Received 4 December 1987.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">S ketching, or the production of untidy images to assist in the development of visual ideas, is one of the oldest and most familiar activities of artists and designers. It is therefore surprising to find that little has been published about the mental processes that contribute to it. Within the last 20 years, the emergence of the computer, together with its associated technology, as a medium of considerable promise for the manipulation and storage of visual imagery has provided a new urgency to the study of the invisible mental processes that result in the visible activity of sketching. Despite their power and beauty, existing computer- aided sketching systems fail to assistvisual invention as much as they should; yet the increasing capacity of computer systems to record and rapidly manipulate visual images in time and space suggests that they have enormous potential to amplify invention in visual art. In order to design improved systems that are more compatible with the objectives and institutions of artists,it is necessary to analyse and model the functions performed by traditional working methods. These are the premises that led us to write this article. It became apparent to us that no sound decisions could be made, either about the design of new sketching systems or about the appropriate use of existing ones, until a plausible theory of the functions performed by traditional methods could be framed. While the theory we outline here was motivated by a desire to improve computer systems, it will also, if found correct, have implications for the use of any The necessity to sketch arises from the need to foresee the representational system that develops or refines concrete results of the synthesis or manipulation of objects without visual structure from vague ideas or abstract premises. actually executing such operations. The use of words, pic- Typically, visual design starts with a number of vague, tures or models to stand for objects, scenes or events not half-formed ideas. Sketching is conducted both to clarify physically present enormously increases the mind's ability existing ideas and to develop new ones. In the early stages, to visualise. The importance of such a system of repre- the artist may wish to preserve many visual options, restrict- sentation in creative thought increases in proportion to (1) ing his or her imagery to global structures, or using notes the degree of abstraction or generality of the manipulation and signs that implicate multiple alternatives. Paper sketch- involved and (2) the degree of time, difficulty or expense in ing uses denotation systems that include tolerances and manipulating the object itself. Both these factors demand a indeterminacies in ways that can amplify the artist's ability system for representing the object with something easily to perceive or imagine many options. Computer systems that stored and manipulated, a sign system or modelling me- fail to represent in their data storage the implicit structure dium that amplifies and is compatible with the mental or categorical meaning of an image may force the artist to representations used to predict the visual consequences of provide precise or detailed information too early in the corresponding manipulations in the world of real objects creative process. This can lead to premature decisions that and materials. Unfortunately, the two factors demand differ- are harmful to invention because they limit the ability to ent types of representational systems. To represent classes discover unexpected or original solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="8" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>]. In addition, the predictability of many computer sketching functions inhibits unnecessarily the serendipity that may accompany the vagaries of conventional media. For example, in visual composition it is frequently helpful to use indeterminate washes of colour whilst the boundary of an associated form</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">ABSTRACT</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="11">is and</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="12">is</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="13">for</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="14">? 1990 ISAST Pergamon Press plc. Printedin Great Britain. 0024-094X/90 $3.00+0.00</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="15">LEONARDO, Vol. 23, No. 1, pp. 117-126, 1990</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16">of objects or properties of objects, we use a descriptive system such as a language, which must have arbitrary, learned rules of interpretation linking the sign system to the represented objects. In the literature on 'knowledge representation', such systems are commonly termed 'propositional', since they can be represented in terms of propositions (functions with arguments that can be true or false). Prop- ositions are more basic than verbal statements. For example, 'a cat is on the mat', 'on the mat there is a cat', 'un chat est sur la natte' and 'on (cat, mat)' (as</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" confidence="possible">Table1. Acontinuum of visual representation. Acrucial component of the early stagesof designorvisual composi- tionis the one-to-many translation fromcategorical description (represented as abstract ideas or de- signconstraints) to visually spe- cificspatial depiction. Sketches anddrawings are the percept half of a hybrid percept-mental- imagethatamplifies the mind's capacity to makedescriptive-to- depictive translations. By failing to represent the important mental component of earlysketches, many computer systems havea detrimental effect onthe growth of mental imagery ininexperienced students. The answer lies notina rejection of computer-assisted sketching but inthe radical re- designof sketching software as a mind-machine synergism.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">Abstract and Categorical</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" confidence="possible">| Abstract Signs | | Verbal Description</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" confidence="possible">| Mathematical Description |</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible">| Diagrams| | Icons |</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" confidence="possible">I Maps | | Sketches</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">Illustrations 1</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" confidence="possible">Photographs |</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible">SolidModels</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" confidence="possible">| Film</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" confidence="possible">|</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible">| Moving Three-Dimensional Models |</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="29">Concrete and Spatially Specific</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx30">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62kh.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83">in the computer language PROLOG) are different expressions of the same <marker type="block"/> Descriptive representations have the advantage not only of representing whole classes of information, such as cats, but also of allowing us to separate important from unimportant informa- tion-for example, to specify the rela- tionship 'on' without specifying position, or to specify the type of animal without specifying its size or colour. Descriptive representation is a natural category, but is not easily defined and is loosely associated with a number of other attributes. For example, descriptions are commonly amodal (not specific to a single sense organ). The information in a description is extrinsic, meaning that it only exists by being associated with externally defined rules of interpretation. In contrast, depictive representation (sometimes termed analog representation) is not dependent on externally defined rules of interpretation, be-<marker type="block"/> to that associated with the object, scene or event represented. The colour of a cat may be described by the words 'pale ginger' or depicted by a paint sample that evokes a colour sensation similar to that of the cat. Depictions represent spatial structure in a two- or three- dimensional spatial medium in which there are correspondences between the spatial position in the medium and the spatial position in the thing represented. Much of the information in a depiction is intrinsic,meaning that it is not represented explicitly but can be extracted without rules of interpretation by inspection (e.g. relative size and direction). Depictions are commonly modal (associated with specific modes of perception). Apart from being necessary to represent detailed, concrete spatial information (e.g. the shape of a cat), depictions have the important advantage that they facilitate the search for novel visual relationships not easy to represent descriptively or not easy to find because they are not explicit. Although the distinction between description and depiction is commonly represented as a dichotomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="35" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" hidden="1" id="36" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="37" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>], it is better conceived as a continuum in which most visual representations are intermediate between the two theoretical ideals of pure description and pure depiction. Between the extremes of pure mathematical theory and life-size working models lie abstract and concrete words, diagrams, maps, drawings, pictures, photographs, sculptures, film<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> and so on (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>). In order to understand sketching, it is necessary to study not only the familiar visible words and pictures used by our culture but also the representational structures used by the brain to classify, store and manipulate visual experience. We posit that sketches have the important function of assisting the mind to translate descriptive propositional information into depiction. This depictive information may then be scanned by atten- tional processes to extract new and per- haps original descriptive information, which in turn can lead to new depiction. The descriptive-to-depictive translation process is a one-to-many map- ping intrinsic to inventive thought. If it is possible to understand how pencil marks on paper can amplify such mental processes, then it should be possible to design greatly improved computer systems. Although the nature of cognitive representation is still an active subject of controversy and debate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="40" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" hidden="1" id="41" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" hidden="1" id="42" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" hidden="1" id="43" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="44" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], there is converging evidence that this fuzzy descriptive/depictive distinction characteristic of external human sign systems has analogies in the internal representations used by the brain for perceiving, recognising, imagining and<marker type="block"/> Since the time of Leonardo da Vinci (1452-1519), the familiar attributes of sketches-hurried or untidy lines of pen or crayon on small pieces of paper, tenuous washes of watercolour, rough cross hatching-have remained little changed. It is helpful to reexamine these attributes, however, according to the clues they provide to underlying mental processes. 1. Sketches use abbreviated two- dimensional sign systems to represent three-dimensional visual experience. They do this in two ways. First, lines used in drawing have a variety of descriptive meanings that are (partly, at least) culturally acquired [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="48" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" hidden="1" id="49" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="50" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. These sign systems are frequently sup- plemented with written notes. Second, sketches are depictive in the sense that they provoke visual experience resem- bling that associated with the objects or scene represented. Aspects of such pictorial denotation systems have been widely discussed elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="51" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" hidden="1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" hidden="1" id="53" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="54" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]. Sketch denotational systems have as their source a stage of information pro-<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> ternscontain the results of these mental analyses and recognition processes. Sketches emphasise those struicttures and features most useful to the latei stages of vision. It is possible that such high-level denotation systems facilitate access to attentive levels of visual imagery. For example, it has been shown that, despite the much smaller amount of information they contain, simple line drawings of objects are recognised at least as quickly as detailed colour photographs of the same objects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="82" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>]. The important point is that what we are conscious of when we perceive sketches or real objects is not a static array of luminances and colours but a briefly stored, highly processed mental representation that is continually up- dated by the integration of meaningful fragments from a flow of directed glances.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="32">proposition.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="34">cause it causes visual experience similar</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="46">reasoning.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="47">THE SPECIALATTRIBUTES OF SKETCHES</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="56">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="57">1 18</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="67">cessing in the mind that is far removed '' from the pattern of light on the retina or that represented in photographs. They typically contain a mixture of descriptive and depictive sign systems which suggests that one of their functions is to assist the mental translation | between two modes of visual representation. For example, the lines used in drawing contours of objects have curva- ture and direction that are clearly depictive (i.e. there is a correspondence of the kind that exists between the shape of a footprint and the shape of a foot). On the other hand, the line has a thickness that does not correspond to any part of the object represented but . has a descriptive meaning analogous to the sign systems used in the maps. 2. Sketches contain selective and fragmentary information. They use rep- F resentational formats that must be compatible with those available to attention. The nature of attention, which is linked to consciousness, is still the subject of active research and controversy. There is evidence that vision includes a fast low-resolution mechanism that can search a visual scene for limited regions worthy of more detailed analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="58" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. Information that may be only implicit in an image must then be extracted and made available for other mental processes, such as verbal thought, or for feeding a program of motor commands controlling the hand holding a pencil. ?i Ulric Neisser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="59" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>] used the term 'focal :' ' attention' to distinguish such limited- . capacity sequential inspection processes from other 'preattentive' processes. His research suggested that 'preattentive' processes occur in parallel and provide information that can be used to direct a serial attentive search [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="60" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>]. There is evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="61" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" hidden="1" id="62" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="63" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>] that focal attention provides a limited-capacity visual processing 'window' that can 1Fig 2. Leonardo da Vinci, 1504. (Windsor Castle, Royal Library. Copyright 8 Her Majesty The Queen.) According to the theory submitted, the multiple contours scan larger internal representations and confused indeterminacies in Leonardo's sketches elicit mental imagery because auto- just as the saccadic movements of our mati ic mental recognition mechanisms attempt to complete the missing parts and match eyes record in sequence limited regions perc cepts to memory images in a continual sequence of percept-memory hybrid images. of high resolution in a larger external The tidy 'flood-fills' encouraged by most existing computer sketching systems inhibit the visual field. Psychologists distinguish sket tching process, yet this need not be, since the computer has great capacity to enhance overt attention (which directs eye dyn amic imagery. movements to parts of the external world) from covert attention (which can be directed without eye movements to different regions of an internal percept or mental image) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="64" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>]. Triesman and Gelade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="65" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>] have shown that focal attention is necessary to detect conjunc- tions of two or more object attributes at the same location, and they have made this the basis of their feature-integra- tion theory of attention. Sagi andJulesz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="66" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>], on the other hand, have stressed</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62kh.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="69">Fig. 1. Henri Matisse, Nude, Semi-Abstract, 1901-1903. (Copyright ? 1990 ARS N.Y./ Suci cession H. Matisse) Though not strictly a sketch, this drawing illustrates superbly the delil berate omission of contour lines, which is a characteristic of the sketch. How can the n be so strong with so few explicit lines? The text offers an explanation that may pro- vd vide *a new approach to the design of computer systems for artists.</caption>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="70">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="71">119</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="72">Fig. 3. Mental rotation of shapes. This</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="80">the association of parallel preattention sent global structure without specifying with the detection of spatial location detail prematurely. and the association of focal attention According to Gombrich [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="73" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>], it was with serial object or feature identifi- Leonardo da Vinci who first described cation. This makes an important and and advocated the deliberate use of plausible link between attention and such untidy indeterminacies to stimu- two parallel visual the brain late invention, pointing out that "con- that have been shown to separate the fused things rouse the mind to new processing of spatial location from that inventions". Amongst his examples of object identification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="74" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]. We postu- Gombrich cites an untidy sketch for the late that sketches are records of a se- Battle of Anghiari, which provoked the quence of attentive acts combining in- idea for a quite different work, a study formation from our eyes with images of Neptune rising from the sea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>). generated from memory. It is necessary Leonardo used his sketches as he used to distinguish here between sketching the marks on crumbling walls, to help from nature (i.e. from a model) and his inventiveness regardless of the sub- sketching entirely from imagination, al- ject. Five hundred years later an analysis though we shall argue that the differ- of the mechanism of his method and its ence is not as great as might be sup- implications for the role of mental im- posed. agery in art is overdue. 3. Sketches contain deliberate or accidental indeterminacies that are important to their function. Amongst the SKETCHING AND THE indeterminacies commonly found are MULTIPLE STAGES OF blank spaces where the drawing fades away,multiple alternative contour lines VISUAL PROCESSING (pentimenti), missing contour lines When we look at objects or sketches, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>), wobbly lines, mysterious dark the information arriving at the retina shadows (sfumati), suggestive scribbles consists of a tiny pattern of light re- and smudges, energetic cross-hatching, flected by three-dimensional objects blots, accidental flow patterns of paint and flattened by the laws of projected and even scratch marks. As already perspective. The visual experience of mentioned, one reason for such inde- meaningful three-dimensional scenes terminacies is the need to preserve segmented into figures and parts is the alternatives. Because the parts of a result of many complex processes that composition are visually interdepend- extract from and add to the informa- ent, an artist may invent signs to repre- tion presented to the eyes. In his influential model of human vision, David Marr [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="77" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>] postulated that the early stages of vision extract contours and the illustrates an influential series of experi- distance, slant and colour of surfaces ments that did much to revive the serious study of mental imagery. The time taken and lead to a representation he termed by subjects to decide whether two such the 21/2-D sketch. Depth and volume shapes were the same or different was are represented, but only as if seen found to be linearly related to the angle from a particular viewpoint. through which one of the shapes would It is this internal, heavily pre- have to be rotated to bring it into con- processed image that is available to the gruence with the other. Implicit in most explanations of this fact is the idea that the window of attention, to drive hand and brain must represent mental images in a eye in the act of sketching. Our eyes format similar to percepts and use a move in a series of glances at 1/4-second 'template'-like comparison process. intervals, and only a very small region (Reproduced by permission; from Ref. of our field of view is sharply detailed. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="78" class="deo:Reference">41</xref>], p. 21. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2.1" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2.1</xref>.) The brain must perform complex com- putations to correct for the movements of the eye, head and body and must somehow 'glue' these numerous well- resolved fragments together and pro- I I~ vide the stable percept we experience. Since we recognise the objects that we see, part of this meaningful structure must be derived from a long-term store containing representations of meaningful objects and categories. Sketches PAIR A PAIR B differ from more detailed images such "SAME" "DIFFERENT" as photographs in that their sign sys-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx81">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62kh.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="84">SKETCHING FROM</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible">OBSERVATION AND</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="86">SKETCHING FROM MEMORY</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89">The distinction referred to earlier between sketching directly by observation from a model and sketching from memory or imagination is that in the first mode the selected information can be continually refreshed by overt attention to vivid perceptual 'snapshots', whilst in the second the source material must be generated and manipulated as much less distinct mental images refreshed by covert attention that appears to mimic real perception. The more vivid percepts, however, cannot be manipulated and recombined like mental images, and they must be integrated by the use of short-term memory. Moreover, it has been widely argued that when we perceive a natural scene our percepts are modified and completed by unconscious expectations (memory) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="87" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="88" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>]. Therefore, when artists sketch, rather than draw, modification of the percept by mental manipulation is always involved. In other words, the visible marks made will generate mental images that in turn may influence the sketch. This follows from the way we have defined sketching as the making of images used to assist in the design of something else. Purely objective drawing, with no mental manipulation, would not count as sketching. Thus in both modes of sketching, perception and mental imagery in partnership are the key cognitive processes.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="90">120</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="91">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="92">THE STRUCTURE AND FORMAT OF MENTAL IMAGES</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99" confidence="possible">Unlike the stable, vivid images of perception, mental images are obtained, not from objects physically stimulating the eyes, but by mentally manipulating remembered representations of features, objects, scenes and events. Ex- cept when one is hallucinating or dreaming, such internally derived images are vaguer and less stable than percepts. In the last 10 years a debate in cognitive psychology has centred around how visual images are represented by the mind [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="93" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>]. Despite controversy, there is now growing and convergent evidence for at least two types of image representation. The evidence on one type, recognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="94" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="95" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>], suggests that the mind has access to categorical representations of visual experience as symbolic structural descriptions. Such representations, sometimes termed 'propositional' because they can be written as a collection of formal propositions, are necessary to explain the fact that object recognition is invariant for size, position, contrast and angle of view. Some such representation must also be postulated to explain the ability to generalise or to recognise the category to which a novel percept belongs. A plausible proposal is that the mind stores visual structures as a top-down hierarchy passing from general shape to the relationships between parts down to the detailed features of individual parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="96" class="deo:Reference">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="97" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>]. Such a description is consistent with evidence that suggests that in some circumstances we recognise overall shape before constituent parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="98" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>]. It has also been widely inferred that such hierar- chical descriptions of objects must be linked in turn to 'schemata', larger stored hierarchies or networks of the contextual and semantic information, which have been shown to play an important role in pictorial recognition</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="102"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="100" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="101" class="deo:Reference">39</xref>].</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106">The other type of representation, the analog or spatially depictive type, is more controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="103" class="deo:Reference">40</xref>], but it is be- coming increasingly plausible thanks to the work of Roger Shepard [41 ], Steven Pinker, Ronald Finke, Martha Farah and especially Stephen Kosslyn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="104" class="deo:Reference">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="105" class="deo:Reference">43</xref>], and their co-workers. Kosslyn proposes that the mental images that resemble percepts are 'quasi-pictorial' spatially depictive maps in which the size, shape and relative distance of a visual element</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx107">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62kh.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" confidence="possible">A'??!?</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="110"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 4</xref>. Jean-Francois Millet (1814-1875), The Trees,black crayon, 195 x 300 mm, date unknown. (Photo: Musee Nationaux-Paris) According to the proposed model, the incomplete and selective lines representing trees act as a skeletal framework onto which rapidly fading and changing mental images are superimposed in spatial register. This avoids the necessity of mentally regenerating the image skeleton but does not interfere with manipulative processes in the visual buffer. This amplifies the capacity of the brain's mental imagery system.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="111">A4 7-Y H",</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="112">"A2 2 vsl :Ta s a</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="113">I.... ........</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="114">Fig. 5. Jean-Francois Millet (1814-1875), A Heath, pen and brown ink over black crayon sketch, 209 x 278 mm, date unknown. (Photo: Musee Nationaux-Paris) The artist's hand- written notations (in English translation): "Cleared patches, tillage, rye on the heights, roughly cleared land, most of the stones set up on top of each other, broom, green rushes, green, cleared and ploughed lands having a thoroughly Celtic look." The use of words in early sketches illustrates the need to translate categorical information into depictive information by successive refinement. Note the concentration on concrete (image-generating) words.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="115">XSN</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="116">Fish and Srivener,Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="117">121</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="118">Box A</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" confidence="possible">15 + Z = 91</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="120">Box B</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="121">589 +734</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156">are implicit in its position in a matrix of neural elements. Conscious percepts and mental images may share this depictive viewer-centred but three-dimensional format. According to Kosslyn, mental images are generated from propositional descriptions in long-term memory into a grainy, spatial medium, the 'visual buffer', where objects and their features can be independently recombined, moved, rotated and re- scaled at high speed. Moreover, mental images can be scanned and 'inspected' internally, and parts can be magnified, revealing more detail, as in a computer- graphics zoom function. The evidence for this theoretical model for imagery is based not just on introspective reports but also on a wealth of subtle detection, discrimination and reaction- time experiments. For example, in an early experiment subjects were shown <marker type="block"/> shapes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="125" class="deo:Reference">44</xref>]. It was found that the time taken to determine whether the two shapes were identical was linearly related to the angle through which one of the shapes would have to be rotated to bring it into congruence with the other. This is consistent with subjects' introspective reports of mental image rotation. In another experiment, Kosslyn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="126" class="deo:Reference">45</xref>] asked his subjects to memorise a map of an island on which seven objects were located in such away that the distances between any pair of objects was different. He then asked them to form a mental image of the map, focusing on one named object, and to then scan to another one and report whether the named object pos- sessed a certain feature. He found that the time taken to scan between two parts of the mental image was directly related to the distance between them in the actual map. This finding has been extended to three dimensions by Pinker and Finke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="127" class="deo:Reference">46</xref>], suggesting that the medium of mental imagery must be<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> three-dimensional. It has also been shown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="130" class="deo:Reference">47</xref>] that it takes longer to form a detailed image than to form a simple outline and that images can be constructed mentally from separately memorised parts. Moreover, there is evidence that mental images are generated from stored parts that are structured in agreement with the way they are structured in perception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="131" class="deo:Reference">48</xref>]. Thus there is objective evidence that spatially depictive images generated from memory have many of the properties needed to explain the ability of artists and designers to generate, manipulate, combine and inspect in imagination nonexistent visual objects. Mental images may resemble percepts because they have evolved to assist us to anticipate real percepts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="132" class="deo:Reference">49</xref>] and to solve problems by visual simulation of possible events. It is likely that mental images also have the natural function of completing, from memory, incomplete percepts from brief, low-con- trastor otherwise impoverished stimuli. The question that has not been an- swered (and has been little discussed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="133" class="deo:Reference">50</xref>]) is, How do the depictive marks, suggestive scribbles and indeterminacies of the sketch amplify and assist the manipulation of mental images and (as Leonardo's theory suggests) provoke the generation of new ones?<marker type="block"/> There is ample evidence that percepts and mental images compete for the same modality-processing capacity in the brain (e.g. visual, auditory, tactile, verbal). For example, Brooks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="136" class="deo:Reference">51</xref>] found that a visual pointing response interfered more with a visual imagery task than with a verbal response and, conversely, that a spoken response interfered more with an auditory imagery task than with a visual response. Simi- larly, Segal and Fusella [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="137" class="deo:Reference">52</xref>] found that subjects instructed to form visual images made more errors in detecting a small but unrelated visual target than if instructed to form auditory images, and vice versa. There is also evidence that visual percepts and images have a similar structure and format. For example, the size and shape of the field that can be inspected mentally is the same as the field of view in normal fixated vision. Moreover, like the visual field, the corresponding image field has high resolution at the centre and declines in<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> resolution to the same extent in both the horizontal and the vertical dimensions. It has also been shown that in certain circumstances visual images and low-contrast percepts may be confused. Perky [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="139" class="deo:Reference">53</xref>] asked subjects to form mental images of familiar objects against a two-waymirror. Unknown to them, she then gradually projected from behind a faint actual image of the same object. None of her subjects noticed that a real image was present, and all attributed characteristics of the real image to their mental images. Segal and Nathan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="140" class="deo:Reference">54</xref>], using more controls, confirmed this finding. They also provided evidence for assimilation of the percept into the image. For example, when subjects were asked to form a mental image of a city skyline but were shown a tomato (subjects were inside a hood with a concealed projector), sev- eral described the skyline with a round sun behind it setting in a red sky. Segal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="141" class="deo:Reference">55</xref>] interprets these and other results as evidence that percepts can be fused with images and even that the image may be constructed around an unde- tected physical signal. It has also been demonstrated that images can facilitate percepts. Farah [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="142" class="deo:Reference">56</xref>] asked subjects to memorise and then mentally image either an uppercase Hor an uppercase 7T. Whilst doing this with eyes fixed, they were given a forced-choice detection task of similar H's or 7T'sin random order. Farah found that the detection rate for either letter was facilitated if the same letter had been imaged and that this facilita- tion was dependent on the image and the stimulus letters being in the same position in the visual field. Farah interprets this result as proving that images and percepts share the same representational medium. Support for the shared representation hypothesis comes from the study of unilateral visual neglect, a type of visual problem that results from stroke damage to a part of the parietal cortex known to be associated with visual attention and spatial perception. The left half of the visual field is known to be mapped in the right hemisphere of the brain, and vice versa. If the damage is in the right side of the brain only, the patient has difficulty attending to objects in the left half of the visual field, even though it can be shown that isolated objects can still be seen in the left visual field. Bisiach and Luzzatti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="143" class="deo:Reference">57</xref>] showed in two patients that unilateral visual neglect was also accompanied by a matching neglect for the left half of a memory image.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Thus if images and percepts share the same visual processes and have a shared neural medium, and if images facilitate percepts, it seems plausible that percepts arising from sketches can facilitate and amplify mental imagery. Since the history of sketching is too recent to make it likely that it has af- fected the evolution of the human visual system, it is also probable that the sketch exploits imagery processes that evolved for a different ecological function. Part of this may have been the completion from memory of fragmentary percepts. Because objects in the natural environment are so frequently partlyobscured by other objects or seen incompletely in momentary glances, the visual system has evolved a recognition system that is able to reconstruct images of whole objects from perceived parts and fragments. Hoffman and Richards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="147" class="deo:Reference">58</xref>] have proposed a system of segmentation of object contours at regions of concavity for part recognition that helps to explain the effective- ness of incomplete contours (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 1</xref>) and pentimenti in sketches. Biederman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="149" class="deo:Reference">59</xref>] has suggested a related recognition scheme based on a lexicon of 36 canonical volumes. Like the ink blots in the Rorschach test, other types of sketch indeterminacy may trigger innate recognition search mechanisms into generating a stream of imagery useful to invention.<marker type="block"/> PERCEPT-IMAGE HYBRIDS For solving complex visual problems, mental images have an advantage over percepts, even computer-generated ones, in the speed and flexibility with which they can be manipulated. Their disadvantage lies in their haziness and brevity. There is convergent evidence that the visual medium in working memory available to attention has a low spatial capacity and short duration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="151" class="deo:Reference">60</xref>]. According to Kosslyn's 1980 model of mental imagery, images fade quickly and must be continually re- generated from long-term memory. This disadvantage may be lessened, however, when they are superimposed over a real perceived scene to anticipate the visual results of some physical manipulation. A familiar example is that of looking at one's room and visually imagining the rearrangement of the furniture. Whilst it is clearly a help to be able to look at the room while doing this, it is also a common experience that part of the room percept, such as other<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> furniture, may hinder rather than assist the formation of the required image. As already mentioned, it has been shown that images can be generated from separately encoded parts, and chronometric studies suggest that an outline skeletal structure is imaged before the addition of parts and detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="154" class="deo:Reference">61</xref>]. It is reasonable to assume that many sketches-e.g. Picasso's studies for Les demoiselles d'Avignon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="155" class="deo:Reference">62</xref>]-are skeletal structures that substitute a percept for the stable part of an image-per- cept hybrid and by reducing the amount of image regeneration necessary enable the imagery-transform processes greater speed and scope. It is therefore necessary for an imagery theory of sketching to determine how the sketch-denotation percepts are best able to facilitate the rapid manipulation of superimposed imagery without also limiting or hindering it. Surprisingly, little research seems to have been done on the role of such hybrid images in art. Relevant data, however, can be obtained from research into the use of imagery in chess. Here the board and pieces have a function analogous to the sketch percept. In</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="123">perspective views of pairs of geometric</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx129">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62kh.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="135">SKETCHES AS PERCEPTS THAT FACILITATE IMAGERY</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="145">122</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="146">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx153">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62kh.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="157">Fig. 6. Robert Welch, Sketch for Covered Bowl, 1981. (Reproduced courtesy Robert Welch) This sketch design was the earliest idea submitted in competi- tion with four other designers for a commission for a serving collection of polished stainless steel. It illustrates the use of notes and the need to represent alternatives in the early</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="158">,?3 ^ ^ * (-</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="159">stages of design. Sketching amplifies the mind's ability to translate abstract proposi- tional/descriptive information into concrete visual/ depictive information.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="160">i i-</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="161">;,.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" confidence="possible">__:- .:'"""% .._</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="163">:g'</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="166">their study of the factors determining chess ability, Chase and Simon con- clude that "the capacity to construct an image combining perceptual structures from internal memory with sensory features from external memory is probably one of the very basic cognitive processes" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="164" class="deo:Reference">63</xref>]. Even more pertinent to the hybrid- image theory is an experimental study byJohn Hayes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="165" class="deo:Reference">64</xref>] on visual imagery in elementary mathematics. Visual imagery is important not only to geometri- cal problem solving but to algebraic problem solving as well. In one study, Hayes gave his subjects cards containing diagrams of elementary mathematical problems; they had to solve them and then report any imagery that they used. Seventeen out of 19 subjects reported that they used imagery to solve problems, and most reported that the images were superimposed on the cards in the same plane as the stimulus symbols. In solving the problem on one card (see Box A), three subjects complained that the line drawn around the symbols interfered with their imagery. One said that he had to mentally re- move the 'bars' to move the symbols,</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="167">* \.... ?? ? ? .-.5 V **, _ -' X .*^ i-.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" confidence="possible">~~</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="169">,p,,_s"s ??r?? 1^ ~ ~~I-' ; I t/:? ... . .</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="170">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="171">123</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="191">and two others felt constrained to move tially depictive hybrid images that we the symbols as if they were tiles in a propose here. But the evidence for the frame. Another card (see Box B) equivalence of visual and mental im- caused even more trouble. Subjects agery [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="172" class="deo:Reference">65</xref>], for the spatial format of complained that there was not room on mental images and for the usefulness of the card to place (mentally) their an- percept-image hybrids in other prob- swer. One subject reported that to solve lem-solving processes make the spatial- the problem he mentally taped a piece hybrid theory of sketching attractive. of paper underneath on which to write According to this, sketches are incom- the answer. plete visual structures that amplify the These reports agree with the subjec- inventive and problem-solving uses of tive experience that in sketching it is mental imagery by three mechanisms. important to omit denotational marks First, they use denotation systems that may hinder imagery movement that provide a framework to facilitate and that it is necessary to leave space and refresh spatially superimposed within the sketch for its imagery com- mental image manipulation, in a ponents. Millet's The Curtain of Trees percept-image hybrid. Faint or vague (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="173" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 4</xref>) is a good example of a sketch marks may become assimilated into the that generates imagery as much by what image. The image may modify the it omits as by the skeletal marks it con- percept. tains. In another study, Hayes obtained Second, they provide ambiguous or objective evidence that hybrid percept indeterminate signs that can provoke images really are generated in spatial innate, unconscious recognition mech- register with the supporting stimulus. anisms to generate a stream of imagery. He noticed that European-trained sub- The theory of recognition by comple- jects found that a division problem was tion from parts fits this hypothesis. more difficult when the two-digit divi- There is evidence that novel or prob- sor was placed to the left of the three- lematic stimuli elicit the most vivid im- digit dividend (as is usual in the U.S. agery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="174" class="deo:Reference">66</xref>]. and the U.K., e.g. 15 1673), I because Third, sketches facilitate the transla- they had been trained to place the divi- tion between different modes of visual sor on the right (e.g. 6731 15). Hayes representation. The act of drawing usu- considered two models of the solution ally involves translating from a categori- process. In the first, the subject gener- cal description to one of many possible ates an image in the familiar format and spatial depictions. In addition, sketches then solves the problem using the gen- use sign systems and (often) written erated (but not hybrid) image by the notes that access long-term memory usual manipulation. In the second, the and stimulate the mental translation of subject might solve the problem with a descriptive to spatially depictive im- hybrid image correcting the unfamiliar agery. This is well illustrated by Millet's to the familiar format digit by digit. sketch A Heath (Fig. 5) and by Robert Thus the effects of the unfamiliar ver- Welch's sketch for a commission to de- sus the familiar format would, if the first sign stainless steel tableware (Fig. 6). model is correct, be expected to be The latter contains not only written limited to the first stage of the solution notes but also a bifurcating diagram process, whilst the second model pre- indicating alternative types of polished dicts that the effects would be distrib- grooves. (There is evidence for the ver- uted digit by digit throughout the solu- bal elicitation of visual imagery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="175" class="deo:Reference">67</xref>].) tion process. He tested this prediction The reverse translation may be stimu- with a group of three European and lated by incomplete recognition cues nine American subjects, each of whom provided by Leonardo-type indetermi- was given 12 familiar and 12 unfamiliar nacies. two-digit-into-three-digit division problems. The differences in the means of the times that subjects required to com- COMPUTER-ASSISTED pute successive digits of the answers in the familiar and the unfamiliar formats SKETCHING were distributed throughout the solu- Despite the astonishing flexibility of tion process, confirming the hybrid paper-and-pencil sketching, its capacity model. to generate and amplify mental im- It is possible that Leonardo da Vin- agery is limited in usefulness by the ci's use of indeterminacies to stimulate short duration and small spatial capac- invention could be explained by invok- ity of working memory. In addition, ing propositional or descriptive recog- traditional media do not record or use nition mechanisms rather than the spa- the temporal information intrinsic to<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the flow of visual thought, and they make it difficult to represent and manipulate three-dimensional structure. Computers have great potential to over- come these limitations, provided depictive mental imagery and semantic knowledge underlying sketch surface structure can be represented and passed between mind and machine. Ex- isting computer sketching systems usually represent the image as a list of numbers, or bit-map, representing the colour and brightness of tiny square picture elements called pixels. These are mapped electronically by a raster display system via a colour look-up table onto the red, green and blue phos- phors of a video monitor. The resolution or grain of the image depends on the number of pixels, and the quality of the colour depends on the number of binary digits used to represent each pixel in the bit-map. Raster graphics software allows the user to directly manipulate the bit-map corresponding to this image. Although there are many advantages to such systems over paper and paint, neither perceived structure nor mental imagery is represented, and so neither can be directly manipulated. Objects to be coloured or moved must be precisely drawn to indicate their position and shape. The suggestive indeterminacies of sketches, so useful for mental processing, thus constitute one of the hardest denotation systems to manipulate in the typical raster graphics paint box system. Thus whilst painting systems resemble traditional media, they offer little scope for ampli- fying the art-and-design process. Another type of computer-aided design system stores visual objects as lists of numerical coordinates that are joined, using fast built-in procedures, by straight or curved lines, in order to be mapped onto the bit-map for raster display or to be used to control a me- chanical pen. This way of representing and manipulating images is known as vector graphics, and it allows the struc- turing of an image into contours, parts and objects. Moreover, the shape of an object can be represented in three- dimensional coordinates and then mapped by perspective projection onto the screen or pen plotter as it would be seen from any particular viewpoint. A great deal of computing ingenuity and mathematical skill has been devoted to such 'wire-frame'and 'solid modelling' systems, often with the apparent objective of achieving a detailed photographic realism. Despite their value as visual model-<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ling tools, such systems have little room for the indeterminacies and other image-supporting structures implicit in the Leonardo method of sketching, and they are rarely used in the early stages of design. The precision and realism of the image generated by such systems may inhibit the formation of the percept-image hybrids so important in the early stages of problem solving. Negroponte [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="181" class="deo:Reference">68</xref>] has characterised the design of many computer-assisted design (CAD) systems as conforming to a 'partitioned idiot slave' paradigm, in which no attempt is made to pass information about the user's mental processes to the machine nor to inform the user about transparent data structures used by the machine to construct the visible image. Artists who work with commercially available computer software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="182" class="deo:Reference">69</xref>] usually accept the limitations and treat the system as a new medium, adapting their style and imagery to the machine's capability. The ability to perform rapid colour fills, cut and paste, rescale, zoom in on detail, and animate and generate perspective views of detailed solid objects provides ample opportunity for experiment and invention. They would probably argue that there is no need to sketch, because direct and detailed manipulation of the medium is an im- provement on the vagueness of early sketches. This is a natural way of working similar to that used by many paint- ers who manipulate paint on canvas directly with little if any preliminary study. Other artists find the available software restrictiveand acquire (usually by self-education) the skills necessary to write their own [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="183" class="deo:Reference">70</xref>]. Here the individu- ality and original style characteristic of contemporary art becomes as much an attribute of the software as of the images generated. Particularly interesting in this re- spect is the recent work of Harold Cohen, who in 1968, already a suc- cessful abstract artist, studied programming and artificial intelligence with Edward Feingenbaum at Stan- ford University [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="184" class="deo:Reference">71</xref>]. Cohen's program AARON, which he has been developing for over 15 years in order to research the nature of visual representation, pro- duces endlessly varied drawings on pen plotters from a hierarchically structured set of rules or 'strategies' (Fig. 7). This way of working is not sketching, but AARON's procedures have some of the characteristics of sketching, and Cohen treated a number of AARON's products as if they were sketches, using<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> them to make large hand-coloured murals. But there are probably many artistswho are not prepared to espouse the individual program approach, because they demand a more immediate interaction with a visual medium (Cohen's program is noninteractive). For these artists, existing systems, with their photographic realism, detailed precision and limited scope for serendipity, may have little advantage over traditional sketching media. Despite the inappropriate design of existing software, computer systems offer enormous potential advantages over paper and pencil. We cannot safely specify or design improved systems, nor replace old ways of working, until we understand the subtle mental images that our media extend. Exactly how such new sketching systems should be designed is the subject of current research.<marker type="block"/> CONCLUSION Despite scholarly arguments for a greater emphasis on visual modes of thought [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="189" class="deo:Reference">72</xref>], Western culture and education are still dominated by verbal/ propositional reasoning and information storage. New evidence of the importance of mental imagery in memory, reasoning and invention, and research that reveals the awesome proportion of the brain that is dedicated to vision, emphasise the need to redress the im- balance. The evidence from cognitive<marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> science suggests that the mind uses imagery and verbal processes for comple- mentary and interdependent purposes. This suggests that it may be an error to separate, as we tend to do, visual or depictive from propositional modes of education. Information technology has a growing capacity to store and manipulate pictorial information much more dynamically than has hitherto been possible. In order to harness this capacity, the designers of improved computer systems for artistsmust attempt to understand the internal as well as the external representations and processes used by artists for visual invention. We hope that this approach will lead to computer software that is more compatible with visual cognition. It would be helpful if such expanded computer systems could also contribute to the solution of the problem of translation between differing modes of thought, which remains a ghostly barrier to pro- gress in education and culture.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx177">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62kh.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="179">124</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="180">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62kh.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="187">Fig. 7. Harold Cohen, untitled, India ink on paper, 22 x 30 in, 1987. One of hundreds of drawings produced at the Tate Gallery, London, by an 'expert system' written by Cohen. Although this is not a sketch, the production of many drawings non-interactively by computer may replace some of the functions of sketching. Few artists, however, have Cohen's programming skills.</caption>
      </region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="192" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">References and Notes</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">1. N. Negroponte, "On Being Creative with Computer Aided Design", Information Processing 77 (1977) pp. 695-704.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">2. A. Paivio, Imagery and Verbal Processes (New York: Holt, 1971).</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">3. S. E. Palmer, "Visual Perception and World Knowledge: Notes on a Model of Sensory-Cognitive Interaction", in D. A. Norman, D. E. Rumelhart and LNR Research Group, eds., Explorations in Cognition (San Francisco: Freeman, 1975).</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">4. S. E. Palmer, "HierarchicalStructure in Percep- tual Representation", Cognitive Psychology 9 (1977) pp. 441-474.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">5. Paivio [2].</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">6. Palrner [3].</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">7. Palmer [4].</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">8. S. E. Palmer, "Fundamental Aspects of Cognitive Representation", in E. Rosch and B. Lloyd, eds., Cognition and Categorization (Hillsdale, NY: Law- rence Erlbaum Associates, 1978).</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">9. S. M. Kosslyn, Ghosts in theMind'sMachine(New York:Norton, 1983) pp. 32-37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">10. E. H. Gombrich, Art and Illusion (London: Phaidon Press, 1962.)</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">11. Rudolf Arnheim, Artand VisualPerception (New Version)(Berkeley, CA: University of California Press, 1974).</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">12. J. B. Deregowski, Illusions,Patternsand Pictures (New York:Academic Press, 1970).</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">13. John Willats, "DrawingSystems Revisited: The Role of Denotation Systems in Children's Figure Drawings",in N. H. Freeman and M. V. Cox, eds., VisualOrder: The Natureand Development of Pictorial Representation (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1985).</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">14. Gombrich [10] Chaps. 2, 5 and 10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">15. Arnheim [11] Chaps. 4 and 5.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">16. Margaret A. Hagen, Varieties of Realism:Geome- triesof Representational Art (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1986).</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">17. B. G. Breitmeyer and L. Ganz, "Implicationsof Sustained and Transient Channels for Theories of Visual Pattern Masking, Saccadic Suppression and Information Processing", Psychological Reviewi 83 (1976) pp. 1-36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">18. Ulric Neisser, CognitivePsychology (New York: Appleton-Century Crofts, 1967).</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">19. BelaJulesz, "Preconscious and Conscious Processes in Vision", in C. Chargas et al., eds., Pattern Recognition Mechanisms (New York:Springer-Verlag, 1985).</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">20. G. Sperling, "The Information Available in Brief Visual Presentations", PsychologicalMono- graphs74, No. 498 (1960).</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">21. John Jonides, "Voluntary Versus Automatic Control over the Mind's Eye Movement", inJ. Long and A. Baddeley, eds., Attentionand Performance IX (Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum, 1981).</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">22. M. I. Posner, "Orienting of Attention", Quar- terly Journal of Experimental Psychology 32 (1980) pp. 3-25.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">23. Posner [22].</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">24. A. M. Triesman and G. Gelade, "A Feature- Integration Theory of Attention", Cognitive Psychol- ogy12 (1980) pp. 97-136.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">25. D. Sagi and B. Julesz, "'Where' and 'What' in Vision", Science228 (1985) pp. 1217-1219.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">26. L. G. Ungerleider, "The Corticocortical Path- ways for Object Recognition and Spatial Perception", in Chagas, et al., eds. [19].</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">27. E. H. Gombrich, "Leonardo's Method for Working Out Compositions", in Norm and Form: Studiesin theArtof theRenaissance(Oxford: Phaidon Press, 1966).</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">28. David Marr, Vision:A Computational Approach (San Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1982).</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">29. Irving Biederman, "Recognition by Compo-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="225" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">nents: A Theory of Human Image Understanding" Psychological Review 94, No. 2, 115-147 (1987).</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">30. Irving Biederman, "On the Semantics of a Glance at a Scene", in M. KubovyandJ. R. Pomer- antz, eds., PerceptualOrganization(Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum, 1981).</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">31. Jerome S. Bruner, "On Perceptual Readiness", Psychological Review 64 (1957) pp. 123-152.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">32. Steven Pinker and S. M. Kosslyn, 'Theories of Mental Imagery", in A. A. Sheik, ed., Imagery: Theory, Research and Application(New York: Wiley, 1983).</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">33. N. S. Sutherland, "Outline of a Theory of Visual Pattern Recognition in Animals and Man",Pro- ceedings of theRoyalSociety, Series B. (1968) pp. 171,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">297-317.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">34. S. K. Reed, Psychological Processes in PatternRec- ognition(New York:Academic Press, 1973).</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">35. Palmer [4].</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="233" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">36. G. E. Hinton and L. M. Parsons, "Frames of Reference and Mental Imagery",inJ. Long and A. Baddeley, Attentionand Performance IX (Hillsdale, NJ: Erlbaum, 1981).</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">37. D. Navon, "Forest Before Trees: The Prece- dence of Global Features in Visual Perception", Cognitive Psychology 9 (1977) pp. 353-383.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="235" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">38. Palmer [3].</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">39. Biederman [29].</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">40. Zenon W. Pylyshyn,"TheImagery Debate: Ana- logue Media Versus Tacit Knowledge", Psychological Review 88, No. 1, 16-45 (1981).</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">41. Roger N. Shepard and Lynn A. Cooper, Mental Imagesand TheirTransformations (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1982).</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">42. Stephen Michael Kosslyn, Image and Mind (Cambridge, MA:MIT Press, 1980).</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">43. Kosslyn [9].</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">44. R. N. Shepard andJ. Metzler, "MentalRotation of Three-Dimensional Objects" Science171 (1971)</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">pp. 701-703.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">45. S. M. Kosslyn, T. M. Ball and B.J. Reiser, "Visual Images Preserve Metric Spatial Information: Evidence from Studies of Image Scanning",Journal ofExperimental Psychology: Human Perception and Performance 4 (1979) pp. 47-60.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">46. Steven Pinker and Ronald A. Finke, "Emergent Two-Dirnmensional Patterns in Images Rotated in Depth", Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception and Performance 6, No. 2,244-264 (1980).</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">47. S. M. Kosslyn,B.J. Reiser, M.J. Farah and S. L. Fliegel, "Generating Visual Images", Journal of Ex- penrimentalPsychology Gen. 112 (1985) pp. 278-303.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="246" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">48. S. K Reed, "Structural Descriptions and the Limitations of Visual Images", Memory and Cognition</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">2 (1974) pp. 329-336.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">49. U. Neisser, "Anticipations, Images and Intro- spections", Cognition 6 (1978) pp. 169-174.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">50. Martin S. Lindauer, "Imageryand the Arts",in Sheik [32].</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">51. L. Brooks, "Spatialand Verbal Components of the Act of Recall", CanadianJournalof Psychology 22 (1968) pp. 349-368.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">52. S.J. Segal and V. Fusella, "Influence of Imaged Pictures and Sounds on Detection of Visual and</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="252" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">AuiditorySignals",journal oj Experimental Psycholo&lt;g</ref>
          <ref rid="R83" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="253" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">83 (1970) pp. 458-464.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="254" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">53. C. W. Perky, "AnExperimental Study of Imagi- nation", AmericanJournal of Psychology 21 (1910) pp. 422-425.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="255" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">54. S.J. Segal and S. Nathan, 'The Perky Effect: Incorporation of an External Stimtilus into an Imagery Experience Under Placebo and Control Con- ditions", Perceptual Motor Skills 18 (1964) pp. 385- 395.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="256" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">55. S.J. Segal, "Processing of the Stimulus in Imagery and Perception", in S.J. Segal, ed., Imagery: CurrentCognitiveApproaches (New York:Academic Press, 1971).</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="257" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">56. MarthaJ.Farah, "The Psychophysical Evidence for a Shared Representational Medium for Mental Images and Percepts",Journal of Experimental Psychology 114, No. 1, 91-103 (1985).</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="258" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">57. E. Bisiach and G. R. Luzzatti, "Unilateral Neg- lect of Representational Space", Cortex14 (1978) pp. 129-133.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="259" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">58. D. D. Hoffman and M. Richards, "Partsof Recognition", Cognition18 (1984) pp. 65-96.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="260" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">59. Biederman [29].</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="261" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">60. W. A. Phillips, "On the Distinction between Sensory Storage and Short-Term Visual Memory", Perceptionand Psychophysics 16, No. 2, 283-290 (1974).</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="262" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">61. Kosslyn et al. [47].</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="263" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">62. A. Glimcher and M. Glimcher, Je suis le cahier: TheSketchbooks of Picasso,exh. cat. (London: Royal Academy of Arts, 1986).</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="264" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">63. W. G. Chase and H. A. Simon, 'The Mind's Eye in Chess", in W. G. Chase, ed., Visual Information Processing (London: Academic Press, 1973).</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="265" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">64. John R. Hayes, "On the Function of Visual Imagery in Elementary Mathematics", in Chase [63].</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="266" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">65. R. A. Finke, "Levelsof Equivalence in Imagery and Perception", PsychologicalReview 87 (1980) pp. 113-132.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="267" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">66. Peter W. Sheehan, "A Functional Analysis of the Role of Visual Imagery in Unexpected Recall", in P. W. Sheehan, ed., TheFunction and Nature of Imagery (New York:Academic Press, 1972).</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="268" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">67. Paivio [2]. 68. Negroponte [1].</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="269" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">69. John Lansdown, Martin Reiser and Graham Howard, Introduction to Art and Computers, exh. cat. (Cleveland, Middlesborough, U.K.: Cleveland Gallery, 1988). This catalog also contains interesting statements by artistswho use computers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="270" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">70. William Latham and Stephen Todd, "Vistialisa- tion of Sculpture" (paper given at British Computer Society conference "Realism and Vistualisa- tion", London, 1987). Latham is a sctulptorwho</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="271" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">works with IBM and writes his own software, which generates detailed, textured, abstractsolid models.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="272" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">71. Harold Cohen, Introduction to Harold Cohen, exh. cat. (London: Tate Gallery Ptublications, 1983).</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="273" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">72. Rudolf Arnheim, VisualThinking(London: Faber and Faber, 1970).</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="198" page="9" column="3">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="199" page="9" column="3">125</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx224">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62kh.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62kh.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="274" page="10" column="3">126</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="275" page="10" column="3">Fish and Scrivener, Amplifying the Mind's Eye: Sketching and Visual Cognition</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
