<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>33fa5bd7dc03f4e5365474b532cd7716fe804b4e14b6e8bf242e1600ee85fcc1</job>
    <base_name>62lg</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1287/orsc.11.4.404.14600</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62lg.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Using Technology</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Constituting Structures: A Practice Lens for Studying Technology in Organizations Author(s): Wanda J. Orlikowski Source: Organization Science</name>
          <aff id="4">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Vol.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">No. 4 (Jul. - Aug.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">)</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">pp. 404-428 Published by: INFORMS Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/2640412 . Accessed: 22/08/</name>
          <aff id="9">404-428</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="11" confidence="possible">Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="10">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="12">.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible">JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="13">support@jstor.org</email>.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="15">.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="16">.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17">INFORMS is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Organization Science.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx18">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62lg.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="20"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="19">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="21">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">Using Technology and Constituting Structures: A Practice Lens or Studying Technology n Organizations</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">Wanda J. Orlikowski</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible">Sloan School of Management, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 50 Memorial Drive, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, <email id="24">wanda@mit.edu</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" confidence="possible">his essay advancesthe view thatstructuresare not locatedin organizationsor in technology,but are enactedby users. It offers a fluid view of structure that buildson and extendsearlierworkon</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">T structuration.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28">Abstract</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38">As both technologies and organizationsundergo dramatic changes in form and function,organizational researchers are increasingly turning to conceptsof innovation, emergence, and improvisation to help explainthe new ways of organizing and using technologyevident in practice.With a similarintent,I proposean extensionto the structurational perspective on technology thatdevelopsa practicelens to examinehow people,as they interact with a technologyin theirongoingpractices, enact structures which shapetheiremergentand situateduse of that technology.Viewing the use of technologyas a processof enactment enables a deeperunderstanding of the constitutive role of social practicesin the ongoinguse and changeof technologies in the workplace.After developingthis lens, I offer an exampleof its use in research,and then suggest some impli- cationsfor the studyof technologyin organizations. (Information Technology; Organization; Structuration Theory; WorkPractices) <marker type="block"/> Technology-and its relationship to organizational structures, processes, and outcomes-has long been of interest to organizational researchers. Over the years, different research perspectives on technology have developed in parallel with research perspectives on organizations-for example, contingency theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Woodward 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Galbraith 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Carter 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Daft and Lengel 1986</xref>), strategic choice models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Child 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Buchanan and Boddy 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Davis and Taylor 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Zuboff 1988</xref>), Marxist studies</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx39">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62lg.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" confidence="possible">M. ScottPoole</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155">( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Braverman 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Edwards 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Shaiken 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Perrolle 1986</xref>), symbolic interactionist approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Kling 1991, Prasad 1993</xref>), transaction-cost economics (Malone et al. 1987, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Ciborra 1993</xref>); network analyses (Barley 1990, Burkhardtand <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Brass 1990</xref>, Rice and Aydin 1991), practice theories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Suchman 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Button 1993</xref>, Hutchins 1995, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Orr 1996</xref>), and structurational models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Barley 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="53" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis and Poole 1994</xref>).l Today, both technologies and organizations are under- going dramatic changes in form and function, and new and unprecedentedforms and functions are becoming evident. In response, organizational researchershave applied notions of innovation, learning, and improvisation to account for such dynamic and emerging patterns of organizing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid 1991</xref>, Weick 1993, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Hutchins 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Eisenhardt 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Hedberg et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Barrett 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Hatch 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Lant 1999</xref>). Similarly, researchers of technology have also begun to use the notions of innovation, learning, and improvisation to understand the organizational implications of new technologies (Ciborra 1996, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Cook and Brown 1999</xref>, Orlikowski 1996, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Tushman et al. 1997</xref>). This paper continues the development of concepts that address the role of emergence and improvisation in technology and technology use, and in particular, seeks to extend the structurational perspective in this direction. The past decade has seen the development of a number of structurationalmodels of technology which have generated numerous insights into the role and influence of technologies in organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Barley 1986</xref>, Poole and<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="69" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis 1990</xref>, 1992, Orlikowski and Robey 1991, Walsham and Han 1991, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Walsham 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="72" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis and Poole 1994</xref>). These models posit technology as embodying structures(built in by designers during technology development), which are then appropriated by users during their use of the technology. Human action is a central aspect of these models, in particular,the actions associated with embedding structureswithin a technology during its development, and the actions associated with appropriatingthose structures during use of technology. A number of commentators have urged further theo- retical development of a structurationalperspective on technology, suggesting that it may have considerable analytic advantages in explaining the consequences associated with the use of new and reconfigurableinformation technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Sproull and Goodman 1990</xref>, Weick 1990, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Roberts and Grabowski 1995</xref>). Because a structurational perspective is inherently dynamic and grounded in ongoing human action, it indeed has the potential to explain emergence and change in technologies and use. However, realizing this potential will require augmenting the current structurationalperspective on technology-specifi- cally the notions of embodied structure and user appropriation. While these notions have been extremely valuable in explaining the various outcomes associated with the use of given technologies in different contexts, they are less able to account effectively for ongoing changes in both technologies and their use. This insuffi- ciency is particularly acute in the context of internetworked and reconfigurable technology (such as groupware and the Web), the use of which is becoming increasingly prevalent in organizations today. In this paper, I extend the structurationalperspective on technology by proposing a practice-oriented understanding of the recursive interaction between people, technologies, and social action. I believe such a practice orientation can better explain emergence and change in both technologies and their use. It does so by comple- menting the notion of embodied structure with that of emergent structure, and the notion of appropriationwith that of enactment.<marker type="block"/> Embodied and Emergent Structures In their understanding of technologies, structurational models of technology have been strongly influenced by the intellectual tradition of social constructivism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="76" class="deo:Reference">MacKenzie and Wajcman 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Bijker et al. 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Woolgar 1991</xref>, Bijker and Law 1992). Using rich case studies of technological invention and development, social constructivist research examines how interpretations, social interests, and disciplinary conflicts shape the production of a technology through shaping its cultural<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> meanings and the social interactions among relevant social groups. This research also examines how the produced technology achieves "stabilization" through processes of negotiation, persuasion, and debate aimed at achieving rhetorical closure and community consensus. Further work in this tradition focuses more specifically on how dominant interests are reflected in the form and functioning of the technology, a process referred to as "inscription" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Latour 1992</xref>). Akrich (1992, p. 208), for example, writes:<marker type="block"/> Drawing on the ideas of social shaping and inscription, structurationalmodels have posited that technology is developed through a social-political process which results in structures(rules and resources) being embedded within the technology. For example, Orlikowski (1992, p. 410) writes:<marker type="block"/> Similarly, "adaptive structurationtheory" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="86" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis and Poole 1994</xref>, Poole et al. 1998) focuses on the structures built into such technologies as group decision support systems. For example, DeSanctis and Poole (1994, p.125) note:<marker type="block"/> The development of a structurationalperspective on technology has benefited considerably from social constructivist ideas, particularlyin the absence of any explicit treatment of technology in Giddens' (1984) theory of structuration.However, the adoption of social constructivist conceptions has also created some difficulties, primarily with respect to two propositions: that technologies become "stabilized" after development; and that they "embody" structures which (re)present various social rules and political interests. The first proposition-that technologies become "stabilized' '-neglects the empirical evidence that people<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> can (and do) redefine and modify the meaning, properties, and applications of technology after development. As<marker type="block"/> of stabilization admits social construction only during development, and "[t]hereafter, technological determinism is allowed, on the basis that beyond the point of stabilization there is little disagreement about what the technology can do." Existing structurationalmodels of technology, because they posit flexibility in how structures are appropriated,avoid such strong technological determinism. However, their presumption that technologies embody specific stable structures is nevertheless problematic because it depicts technologies as static and set- tled artifacts with built-in arraysof fixed and determinate structuresthat are (always and readily) available to users. Such assumptions of technological stability, completeness, and predictability break down in the face of empirical research that shows people modifying technologies and their conceptions of technology long after design and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Rice and Rogers 1980</xref>, von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Hippel 1988</xref>, Ciborra and Lanzara 1991). Such assumptions are also inappropriatein the context of the dynamically reconfigurable, user-programmable, and highly internetworked technologies being developed and used today. The second proposition-that technologies "embody" social structures-is problematic from a structurational perspective, because it situates structures within technological artifacts. This is a departurefrom Giddens' (1984) view of structuresas having only a virtual existence, that is, as having "no reality except as they are instantiated in activity" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Whittington 1992</xref>, p.696). Seeing structures as embodied in artifacts thus ascribes a material existence to structures which Giddens explicitly denies (1989, p.256):<marker type="block"/> Structure is here understood as the set of rules and resources instantiatedin recurrentsocial practice. Elements of technology (such as voting procedures, stored data, and public display screens), once they have been built into a technology, are external to human action. As inscribed properties of a technology, they constitute neither rules nor resources, and thus cannot be seen to be structures.It is only when such technological elements as voting procedures, stored data, and public display screens are routinely mobilized in use that we can say that they "structure" human action, and in this way they become<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> implicated as rules and resources in the constitution of a particularrecurrentsocial practice. For example, consider the myriad software packages, network tools, and data files installed on countless desktop computers and corporate mainframes worldwide. Until such time as these are actually used in some ongoing human action-and thus become part of a process of structuring-they are, at best, potential structuringelements, and at worst, unex- plored, forgotten, or rejected bits of program code and data cluttering up hard drives everywhere. We are unaccustomed to conceiving of rules and resources as only existing "in and through the activities of human agents," largely because of our conventional views of them as either external entities (e.g., corporate policy, traffic regulations, land, factories, money) or internal schemas (e.g., rules of thumb, expertise, judgment). From a structurationalperspective, however, external entities and internal schemas are only constituted as rules and resources when they are implicated in recurrentsocial action (pace <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Sewell 1992</xref>). Our conventional view of rules and resources as external entities suffers from what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Taylor (1993)</xref> refers to as an "objectivist reification," while the view of rules and resources as internal schemas suffers from a "subjectivist reduction." Commenting on rules, Taylor (1993, pp.57-58, emphasis added) writes:<marker type="block"/> Similarly, Giddens (1979, p. 65) writes that "rules and practices only exist in conjunction with one another." In the same way, resources too, are inextricably linked to practice. Giddens observes (1984, p. 33, emphasis added):<marker type="block"/> While a technology can be seen to embody particular symbol and material properties, it does not embody structures because those are only instantiated in practice. When humans interact regularly with a technology, they engage with (some or all of) the material and symbol properties of the technology. Through such repeated interaction, certain of the technology's properties become<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> implicated in an ongoing process of structuration. The resulting recurrent social practice produces and reproduces a particular structure of technology use. Thus, structures of technology use are constituted recursively as humans regularly interact with certain properties of a technology and thus shape the set of rules and resources that serve to shape their interaction. Seen through a practice lens, technology structuresare emergent, not embodied. A practice lens more easily accommodates people' s situated use of dynamic technologies because it makes no assumptions about the stability, predictability, or relative completeness of the technologies. Instead, the focus is on what structuresemerge as people interactrecurrentlywith whatever properties of the technology are at hand, whether these were built in, added on, modified, or invented on the fly.<marker type="block"/> Appropriation and Enactment of Structures Existing structurational models of technology examine what people do with technologies in use, positing such use as an appropriationof the "structures" inscribed in the technologies. Such appropriationoccurs when "people actively select how technology structures are used" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="115" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis and Poole 1994</xref>, p.129). DeSanctis and Poole (1994, p. 130) distinguish between "faithful" and "un- faithful" appropriations of the technology structures, highlighting the degree to which use of technology cor- responds to the structures embedded in the technology, and then relating such correspondence to expected outcomes. Their analysis identifies different types of appropriation moves which preserve, substitute for, combine, enlarge, contrast, constrain, affirm, or negate the structures provided by the technology (1994, p. 135). While the notion of appropriationcaptures well the importance of human action in shaping the situated use of technology, it nevertheless frames such human agency in terms of interaction with the structuresembedded within technology. Thus, DeSanctis and Poole (1994, p.133) rec- ommend "appropriation analysis [which] tries to document exactly how technology structures are being in- voked for use in a specific context" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="116" class="deo:Reference">DeSanctis and Poole 1994</xref>, p.133), and Orlikowski and Robey (1991, p.148), while not using the term "appropriation analysis," suggest analyzing how the structureinscribed in information technology "shapes action by facilitating certain outcomes and constraining others." These views start with the structurespresumed to be embedded within technology, and then analyze how those structuresare used, mis- used, or not used by people in various contexts. If, however, we focus on emergent ratherthan embodied structures (as I have suggested above), an alternative<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> view of technology use becomes possible-a view which allows us to frame what users do with technologies not as appropriation but as enactment.2 Thus, rather than starting with the technology and examining how actors appropriateits embodied structures, this view starts with human action and examines how it enacts emergent structures through recurrentinteraction with the technology at hand. Focusing attention on how structures are constituted and reconstituted in recurrent social practices ac- knowledges that while users can and do use technologies as they were designed, they also can and do circumvent inscribed ways of using the technologies-either ignoring certain properties of the technology, working around them, or inventing new ones that may go beyond or even contradict designers' expectations and inscriptions. For example, many of us use such powerful software tools as word processing, spreadsheets, and presentation graphics in our daily lives. In our regular use of these tools, most of us typically utilize, at best, 25 percent of these tools' functionality, focusing on those elements we need to get our task done and ignoring the rest. Or consider the World Wide Web technology which was developed in 1989 as a hypertext networked system for sharing research in the European high-energy physics community. No one, least of all its inventor (Berners-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="119" class="deo:Reference">Lee 1996</xref>), anticipated the ex- plosion of innovation and reinvention that has accompa- nied use of this technology since then and that continues to transform it into an extensive global infrastructurefor business, government, entertainment, and all manner of social, political, professional, and personal communities. Together, the notions of emergent structureand enactment afford a practice-based extension to existing structurationalmodels of technology. This practice lens posits humans as constituting structuresin their recurrentuse of technology. Through their regularized engagement with a particular technology (and some or all of its inscribed properties) in particular ways in particular conditions, users repeatedly enact a set of rules and resources which structurestheir ongoing interactions with that technology. Users' interaction with a technology is thus recursive- in their recurrent practices, users shape the technology structurethat shapes their use. Technology structuresare thus not external or independent of human agency; they are not "out there," embodied in technologies simply waiting to be appropriated.Ratherthey are virtual,emerg- ing from people's repeated and situated interaction with particulartechnologies. These enacted structuresof technology use, which I term technologies-in-practice, are the sets of rules and resources that are (re)constituted in people' s recurrentengagement with the technologies at hand. After developing this practice lens further,I provide an example of its application by drawing on some empirical<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> studies of the use of a particular technology in different organizations. I end by discussing some of the research implications entailed by adopting a practice lens to study technology and its use in organizations.<marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Lave (1988)</xref> has argued for the value of focusing on "cognition in practice" rather than "cognition in the head." Similarly, the practice lens I am proposing here focuses on emergent technology structures enacted in practice rather than embodied structures fixed in technologies. This practice lens furtherrecognizes that in both research and practice we often conflate two aspects of technology: the technology as artifact3 (the bundle of material and symbol properties packaged in some socially recognizable form, e.g., hardware, software, techniques); and the use of technology, or what people actually do with the technological artifact in their recurrent,situated practices. Artifact and Use The distinction between the use of a technology and its artifactual character is an analytic, not an ontological one.4 This distinction may be elaborated by considering a discussion offered by Lave (1988, pp.150-151) in her study of arithmeticproblem-solving within supermarkets:<marker type="block"/> Lave' s point may be similarly made for technologies, that is: technology is, on the one hand, an identifiable, relatively durable entity, a physically, economically, politically, and socially organized phenomenon in space-time. It has material and cultural properties that transcend the experience of individuals and particular settings. In this aspect, it is what we may call a technological artifact, which appears in our lives as a specific machine, technique, appliance, device, or gadget. At the same time, use of the technology involves a repeatedly experienced, personally ordered and edited version of the technological artifact, being experienced differently by different individuals and differently by the same individuals depending on the time or circumstance. In this aspect it may be<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> termed a technology-in-practice, to refer to the specific structure routinely enacted as we use the specific machine, technique, appliance, device, or gadget in recurrent ways in our everyday situated activities. Some properties provided by the artifact do not exist for us as part of our technology-in-practice, while other properties are rich in detailed possibilities. While a technology5 can be seen to have been con- structed with particular materials and inscribed with developers' assumptions and knowledge about the world at a point in time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Noble 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Perrow 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Winner 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="136" class="deo:Reference">Thomas 1994</xref>), it is only when this technology is used in recurrent social practices that it can be said to structure users' actions. That is, it is only when repeatedly drawn on in use that technological propertiesbecome constituted by users as particularrules and resources that shape their action. For example, thousands of Americans annually use tax preparationsoftware to complete their tax returns. Knowledge of computers, the U.S. federal tax code, arith- metic, and the content and layout of various tax forms informed the design of this technology, as did the software programminglanguage and database structuresused to construct it. When people routinely use the tax prep- aration software, they draw on its inscribed propertiesand embedded information content, their own experiences with technology, as well as their understanding of their rights and obligations as tax payers, to enact a set of tax reporting rules and resources with the software.6 For example, interaction with the " 1040 Form" enables the entry of particular kinds of information and facilitates the calculation of various totals, while also prohibiting the creation of alternative tax reporting representations (say a "999 Form"), or figuring the totals in a more "crea- tive" way. When users choose to use a technology, they are also choosing how to interact with that technology. Thus they may, deliberately or inadvertently, use it in ways not anticipated by the developers. For example, users may use the tax preparationsoftware to print out blank forms and then complete the tax return manually, or they may use the software incorrectly, or they may use it to learn about the current tax code, or to study the software's interface design. Users may also choose not to use a technology even if it is available, as happens, for example, with tax preparationsoftware which is typically ignored for most of the year. In this case, even though the technology exists (typically installed on users' computer desktops), it is not implicated in any recurrent social practice, and thus no rules and resources (i.e., no technology-in-practice) are enacted with the tax preparationtechnology, because it is not used. Of course, this scenario typically changes quite dramatically a few weeks before April 15, when users are<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> motivated by the tax filing deadline to use their tax prep- aration software in a flurry of repeated activity and anxi- ety, and thereby enact a particulartechnology-in-practice. From the point of view of users, technologies come with a set of properties crafted by designers and developers. These technological properties may be examined to identify the typical or expected range of activities com- monly associated with use of the technology. However, how these properties will actually be used in any instance is not inherent or predetermined; rather it depends on what people actually do with them in particularinstances. And as numerous studies have shown, users can, and do, choose to use technologies in ways unanticipated by inventors and designers. Whether through error (misper- ception, lack of understanding, slippage) or intent (sab- otage, inertia, innovation), users often ignore, alter, or work around the inscribed technological properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="142" class="deo:Reference">Gasser 1986</xref>, Kraut et al. 1986, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="143" class="deo:Reference">Mackay 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Grudin 1989</xref>, Bullen and Bennett 1991, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Ciborra and Lanzara 1991, Button 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Clement 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Markus 1994</xref>, Suchman 1996). Furthermore,users often add to or modify the technological properties on hand (e.g., installing new software, peripherals, or adding data, etc.), thus, actively shaping or crafting the artifact to fit their particular re- quirements or interests. The identification of technological properties and common activities associated with our conventional understanding of a technological artifact,its inscriptions, or the intentions of its designers, cannot circumscribe the ways in which people may use it.7 Use of technology is not a choice among a closed set of predefined possibilities, but a situated and recursive process of constitution, which- while it may often invoke intended activities or replicate familiar uses-may also and at any time ignore such conventional uses or invent new ones. As Bazerman (1994, p.88) reminds us:<marker type="block"/> Having recognized this, however, it is important to keep in mind that the recurrentuse of a technology is not infinitely malleable. Saying that use is situated and not confined to predefined options does not mean that it is totally open to any and all possibilities. The physical properties of artifacts ensure that there are always bound- ary conditions on how we use them. Conceptual artifacts (such as techniques or methodologies expressed in language) are more likely to be associated with a wider range of uses than software-based artifacts, which, in turn, are<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> more likely to be associated with a wider range of uses than hard-wired machines. Similarly, the more a particular technological artifact is integrated into a larger system, network, or technological configuration, the nar- rower the range of alternative uses that may be crafted with it. Thus, the use of a stand-alone personal computer in my home is likely to be more malleable than the use of a workstation by an air traffic controller. While it is expected that more and more of the artifacts deployed in future workplaces will be software-based, user-programmable, even user-configurable (and hence, their use may be more malleable), it is also likely that the increased complexity and internetworking accompanying the growth in global infrastructures will requirethese artifacts to be more standardized, interconnected, and interde- pendent (and hence, their use may be less malleable). Use of technology is strongly influenced by users' understandings of the properties and functionality of a technology, and these are strongly influenced by the images, descriptions, rhetorics, ideologies, and demonstrations presented by intermediaries such as vendors, journalists, consultants, champions, trainers,managers, and "power'" users (Orlikowski et al. 1995). As Woolgar (1996, p.92) notes, such intermediaries "intervene in the interpretation ('reading') of the technology by the user through their comments on the product's nature, capacity, use, and value." Because some of the claims made in these com- mentaries are quite persuasive, they tend to be believed without concrete evidence to support them. Kling, for example, has found that the powerful narrativesconstructed during attempts to advocate computerization often continue to shape users' perceptions even "when computer systems are built, installed, and used in ways that differ significantly from early expectations" (1992, p.352).<marker type="block"/> Giddens (1979, 1984) proposed the notion of structure (or structuralproperties of social systems) as the set of enacted rules and resources that mediate social action through three dimensions or modalities: facilities, norms, and interpretive schemes. In social life, actors do not enact structuresin a vacuum. In their recurrentsocial practices, they draw on their (tacit and explicit) knowledge of their prior action and the situation at hand, the facilities available to them (e.g., land, buildings, technology), and the norms that inform their ongoing practices, and in this way, apply such knowledge, facilities, and habits of the mind and body to "structure" their current action (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="154" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). In doing so, they recursively instantiate and thus reconstitute the rules and resources that structure their social action. Because technology-in-practice is a kind of structure,</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="65">1047-7039/00/1 104/0404/$05.00 1526-5455 electronic ISSN</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE, C) 2000 INFORMS Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000, pp. 404-428</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="67">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="68">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx80">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62lg.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="83">Designers thus define actors with specific tastes, competences, motives, aspirations, political prejudices, and the rest, and they assume that morality, technology, science, and economy will evolve in particularways, A large part of the work of innovators is that of "inscribing" this vision of (or prediction about) the world in the technical content of the new object.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="85">[H]uman agents build into technology certain interpretive schemes (rules reflecting knowledge of the work being automated), certain facilities (resources to accomplish that work), and certain norms (rules that define the organizationally sanctioned way of executing that work).</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="88">[S]tructures are found in institutions such as reporting hierarchies, organizational knowledge, and standard operating procedures. Designers incorporate some of these structuresinto the technology ... Once complete, the technology presents an array of social structures for possible use in interpersonal interaction, including rules (e.g., voting procedures) and resources (e.g., stored data, public display screens).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="90">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="91">405</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="92">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="95">Woolgarand Grint(1991, p.370) argue,the proposition</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="100">... a position I want to avoid, in terms of which structure appears as something 'outside' or 'external' to human action. In my usage, structure is what gives forn and shape to social life, but is not itself that form and shape-nor should 'give' be understood in an active sense here, because structure only exists in and through the activities of human agents.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx102">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62lg.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="106">In its operation, the rule exists in the practice it "guides." . . . the practice not only fulfills the rules, but also gives it concrete shape in particular situations.... In fact, what this reciprocity shows is that the "rule" lies essentially in the practice. The rule is what is animating the practice at any given time, not some formulation behind it, inscribed in our thoughts or our brains or our genes or whatever. That is why the rule is, at any given time, what the practice has made it.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="108">Some forms of allocative resources (e.g. land, raw materials etc.) might seem to have a real existence. In the sense of having a "time-space" presence this is obviously the case. But their "materiality" does not affect the fact that such phenomena become resources ... only when incorporated within processes of structuration.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="110">406</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="112">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="113">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx118">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62lg.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="121">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 1 1, No. 4, July-August</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="122">2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="123">407</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="124">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="125">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="127">A Practice Lens for Studying Use of Technology</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="130">The supermarket, for instance, is in some respects a public and durable entity. It is a physically, economically, politically, and socially organized space-in-time. In this aspect it may be called an "arena" within which activity takes place. . . . At the same time, for individual shoppers, the supermarket is a repeatedly experienced, personally ordered and edited version of the arena. In this aspect it may be termed a "setting" for activity. Some aisles in the supermarket do not exist for a given shopper as part of her setting, while other aisles are rich in detailed possibilities.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx132">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62lg.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="138">408</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="139">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="140">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="141">ORLIKOWSKI. Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="149">... no matter how rigorous the typifications that guide the enactment at any single moment may be, the dynamics of the moment grant new meaning and life to the typifications, and we must look to the dynamics of the moment to understand what is happening.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx151">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62lg.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="153">Structuringof Technologies-in-Practice</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="156">ORGANIZATION SCIENCENVol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="157">409</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="158">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="160">Figure 1</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="161">(1)</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="162" page="8" column="1">I I (rules and resources instantiated in practice)</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="163" page="8" column="1">Enactment of Structures in Practice r ?-?Structural Properties of Social Systems |</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="164" page="8" column="1">I</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="165" page="8" column="1">i Facilities</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="166" page="8" column="1">Norms</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="167" page="8" column="1">Interpretive Schemes</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="168" page="8" column="1">e.g., land, e.g., codes of buildings, conduct, e.g., categories, technology etiquette assumptions</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="169" page="8" column="1">| Ongoing, Situated Human Action l</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="170" page="8" column="1">(Adapted from Giddens 1984)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" page="8" column="1">the same recursive constitution applies here too (see Figure 2). When people use a technology, they draw on the properties comprising the technological artifact-those provided by its constituent materiality, those inscribed by the designers, and those added on by users through previous interactions (e.g., specific data content, customized features, or expanded software/hardware accessories). People also draw on their skills, power, knowledge, assumptions, and expectations about the technology and its use, influenced typically by training, communication, and previous experiences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="171" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Gash 1994</xref>). These</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="173" page="8" column="1">Figure 2</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="174" page="8" column="1">Enactment of Technologies-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="175" page="8" column="1">CD</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="176" page="8" column="1">r I _J - - _ - - _ - - - _ - - _ - _ _ _ _ - _ - - _ - - _ - - -- I</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="177" page="8" column="1">m -</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="178" page="8" column="1">Technologies-in-Practice.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="179" page="8" column="1">(rules and resources instantiated in use of technology) Otherstructures enactedin the use of technology</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="180" page="8" column="1">-*--*-- --- - '-'--'-*-- *-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="181" page="8" column="1">- --*--__. _. - ...</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="182" page="8" column="1">Facilities l</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="183" page="8" column="1">Norms Interpretive</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">~~~~~~~Schemes emes i</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="185" page="8" column="1">e.g., e.g., hardware protocols e.g., software etiquette assumptions knowledge</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="186" page="8" column="1">Ongoing, Situated Use of Technology</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="187" page="8" column="1">i . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx188">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_008.image_09.png" thmb="62lg.page_008.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="260" page="8" column="2">include the meanings and attachments-emotional and intellectual-that users associate with particulartechnologies and their uses, shaped by their experiences with various technologies and their participation in a range of social and political communities.8 Users also draw on their knowledge of and experiences with the institutional contexts in which they live and work, and the social and cultural conventions associated with participatingin such contexts. In this way, people' s use of technology becomes structured by these experiences, knowledge, meanings, habits, power relations, norms, and the technological artifacts at hand. Such structuring enacts a specific set of rules and resources in practice that then serves to structure future use as people continue to interact with the technology in their recurrentpractices. Thus, over time, people constitute and reconstitute a structure of technology use, that is, they enact a distinctive technology-in- practice. Human interaction with technologies is typically recurrent, so that even as users constitute a technology-in- practice through their present use of a technology, their actions are at the same time shaped by the previous technologies-in-practice they have enacted in the past. Ongoing enactment of a technology-in-practice reinforces it, so that it becomes regularized and routinized, an expedient and habitual response to repeated use of a technology within the daily exigencies of organizational life. That is, a technology-in-practice serves essentially as a "behavioral and interpretive template" (Barley 1988, p. 49) for people's situated use of the technology. Continued habitual use of a technology will tend to reen- act the same technology-in-practice, thus further reinforcing it over time so that it becomes taken for granted. For example, most of us who drive cars have developed a familiar pattern of interacting with automobiles on the roads-repeatedly enacting a particular and typically shared technology-in-practice that we now take for granted. While regular interactions with the same technology tend to reproduce the technology-in-practice being enacted, such reinforcement is not assured. Consider the automobile example again. We happily take our (and our fellow drivers') customary enactment of a routine technology-in-practice for granted-that is, until we travel abroad and encounter different artifacts (foreign automobile models, cars with drivers' seats on different sides, road signs in foreign languages, different measuring units for indicating distance or gas (a.k.a. petrol) con- sumption), and different driving conventions and habits (including driving on the opposite side of the road). All of a sudden, the set of rules and resources we had so <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> habitually enacted with our own automobiles on well- known roads in familiar contexts is no longer effective, and we have think and act differently, thus enacting a somewhat different set of rules and resources to guide our interaction with different automobiles on different roads. On our returnhome, we will (hopefully) revert to enacting our previously effective technology-in-practice. A community of users engaged in similar work practices typically enacts similar technologies-in-practice, where through common training sessions, shared social- ization, comparable on-the-job experiences, and mutual coordination and storytelling, users come to engage with a technology in similar ways. Over time, throughrepeated reinforcement by the community of users, such technologies-in-practice may become reified and institutionalized, at which point they become treated as predetermined and firm prescriptions for social action, and as such, may impede change. For example, in a study of process technologies, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="194" class="deo:Reference">Tyre and Orlikowski (1994)</xref> found that initial patterns of using the technologies congealed quickly, becoming resistant to change despite ongoing operational problems in the use and performance of the technologies. This rapid establishment of relatively fixed technologies-in-practice was influenced by corporate pressure to improve productivity, unavailability of technical support staff, and users' expectations of and pref- erences for stable and predictable technologies. Because the enactment of a technology-in-practice is situated within a number of nested and overlapping social systems, people's interactionwith technology will always enact other social structures along with the technology- in-practice, for example, a hierarchicalauthoritystructure within a large bureaucracy, a cooperative culture within a participative workgroup, the normative structure of a religious or professional community, or the dominant status of English as the primary language of the Internet. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> shows that people's situated and recurrent use of technology simultaneously enacts multiple structures along with a technology-in-practice. In this paper, I elab- orate the notion of technologies-in-practice-the particular structures of technology use that users enact when engaging recurrently with a technology. Consequently, the other structures enacted at the same time will not be as central here. In any structurationalanalysis, one must foreground some structures and background others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="196" class="deo:Reference">Giddens, 1979</xref>). My limited discussion of the other structures here should not be taken to mean that they are less importantor more fixed than technologies-in-practice. All structuresare virtual, and continually enacted through actors' recurrent practices. However, in this discussion, I have chosen to focus on the particularstructuresof technology use which I have labeled technologies-in-practice.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> In their recurrentand situated action, actors thus draw on structures that have been previously enacted (both technologies-in-practice and other structures),and in such action reconstitute those structures. Such reconstitution may be either deliberate, or, as is more usual, inadvertent. Also, it may occur in one of two forms: reinforcement, where actors enact essentially the same structureswith no noticeable changes; or transformation,where actors enact changed structures, where the changes may range from the modest to the substantial. Changes in Technologies-in-Practice Users always have the potential to change their habits of use, and in this way change the structures they enact in their recurrentpractices. As Cassell (1993, p.13), writing about rules, puts it:<marker type="block"/> Technologies-in-practice can be and are changed as actors experience changes in awareness, knowledge, power, motivations, time, circumstances, and the technology. They are changed through the same process that all social structures are changed-through human action. People may change their technologies-in-practice by deliberately modifying the properties of their technology and thus how they interactwith it. For example, people may down- load software "plug-ins" to improve the performance of their Web browser tools, or they may override the parameters of a new scheduling system to replicate the operation of a previous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="201" class="deo:Reference">Saetnan 1991</xref>). Even when a technology appears to have stabilized, with the discourse around its properties and functionality apparentlyhaving reached "closure" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="202" class="deo:Reference">Bijker 1995, Pinch and Bijker 1984</xref>), or some industry-wide "dominant design" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="203" class="deo:Reference">Tushman et al. 1997</xref>) has been established, the stability of the technology and its applications is only provisional. It is provisional because different elements continue to be developed, existing functions fail and are fixed, new materials are invented, new standardsare set, and users modify the artifact and/or its content for new and different uses. Technologies are thus never fully stabilized or "complete," even though we may choose to treatthem as fixed, black boxes for a period of time. By temporarily brack- eting the dynamic nature of technology, we assign a "stabilized-for-now" status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="204" class="deo:Reference">Schryer 1993</xref>) to our technological artifacts. This is an analytic and practical con- venience only, because technologies continue to evolve, are tinkeredwith (e.g., by users, designers, regulators,and<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> hackers), modified, improved, damaged, rebuilt, etc. Typ- ically, such change is not predetermined or predictable, but implemented by people influenced by competitive, technological, political, cultural, and environmentalinflu- ences (e.g., feature wars with competitors, technological innovations, safety improvements, security violations, privacy legislation, climatic conditions, earthquakes,poor maintenance, etc.). Users may also choose to enact different technologies- in-practice because they have become more knowledgeable about using their technology (through attending a training class or watching a colleague's use) or because they have changed jobs and now need to use technology differently in their new work community (say, to share files with coworkers). People may adjust their technologies-in-practice intentionally, as when users respond to new safety regulations by beginning to engage safety mechanisms during machine operation, or when they respond to the unreliability of computer networks by backing up their files at the end of every session or executing system maintenance utilities. Modifications to patterns of use may also result from inadvertent slippage or breakdown, when, either through inattention or error, users fall into a different form of use, such as forgetting to attach safety guards, or discontinuing use of a faulty or complicated element. People may also change their technologies-in-practice by improvising, that is, generating situated innovations in response to unexpected opportunities or challenges, such as when a temporary machine workaroundbecomes the preferredpractice because it turns out to be more effective than the original practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="210" class="deo:Reference">Tyre and Orlikowski 1994</xref>). As people enact modified technologies-in-practice they also change the facilities, norms, and interpretive schemes used in their use of the technology (as shown with the two-way arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="211" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>). For example, through adding downloaded "plug-ins" to a personal computer, or customizing the parameters of a software application, or adding new data to the databases, the technological artifact is altered. At the same time, users' knowledge of what technological properties are available to them may be updated or made obsolete, as with the meanings, expectations, associations, and conventions they attach to the technology and its use. For example, users of electronic mail within a community may evolve a set of communication norms about effective or sanctioned electronic mail use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82" id="212" class="deo:Reference">Yates et al. 1999</xref>). Similarly, a company's new policy for use of machine safety features is likely to alter people's views and understandings of the appropriateways of using technology in that company.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> To the extent that people enact a multiplicity of structures (including other technologies-in-practice as well as other normative and authoritative structures) in their recurrent practices, they increase the likelihood that they will enact altered or alternative technologies-in-practice associated with their use of particulartechnologies. That is, by enacting various interpenetrating(and perhapseven contradictory) structures, actors experience a range of rules and resources that may generate knowledge of different structures and awareness of the possibilities for structural change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="215" class="deo:Reference">Sewell 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="216" class="deo:Reference">Tenkasi and Boland 1993</xref>). For example, participation in professional or industry conferences often allows people to exchange ideas and stories about their work practices, including how they use technology in their everyday practices. Such awareness of alternative ways of using technology may moti- vate people to make changes in their technology and/or their use of it. It may also prompt them to make changes in the other structures that they constitute in their work practices-for example, using electronic mail to enact a less hierarchical communication structure which by- passes conventional channels for interacting with senior executives. If this change is sustained over time and shared by other users within their community who similarly begin to use e-mail technology to bypass hierarchical communication channels, then a significant shift in organizational communication structuremay be possible. The practice lens elaborated here recognizes that even as technologies-in-practice may become institutionalized over time, this is only a stabilization for now. Every engagement with a technology is temporally and contextu- ally provisional, and thus there is, in every use, always the possibility of a different structure being enacted. In acknowledging this open-endedness, the practice lens augments existing structurationallenses that have tended to focus on a stable technology (with its fixed array of embodied structures) and the various situated ways in which it is appropriated.The practice lens proposed here focuses on human agency and the open-ended set of emergent structures that may be enacted through recurrent use of a technology. Such a practice lens recognizes that emergence and impermanence are inherent in social structures-that while habitual, routinized, and institutionalized patterns of using a technology may be evident, these are always ongoing accomplishments, and thus there can be no single, invariant, or final technology-in- practice, just multiple, recurrent,and situated enactments. Users have the option, at any moment and within existing conditions and materials, to "choose to do otherwise" (Giddens 1993) with the technology at hand. In such possibilities to do otherwise lies the potential for innovation, learning, and change.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The use of a practice lens to study technology use in organizations focuses attention on what people actually do with particular technologies in their ongoing and situated activity. This can be illustratedwith some empirical examples,9 which highlight how a number of user groups enacted different technologies-in-practice with a particular kind of technology. The technologies-in-practice discussed for each of the three sites below should not be seen as exhaustively characterizing what people did with the technology in those sites. These are just the technologies-in-practice I identified with the exposure I had to certain people at certain times and using particular research tools. Given the situated and emergent nature of technologies-in-practice, we can be sure that other technologies-in-practice were being enacted in these sites at the same time, and that, over time, the technologies- in-practice identified here will have evolved and changed, and new ones will have emerged. Before turning to these examples, a brief description of the technological artifact I studied may be helpful. Background: The Notes Technology The technology considered here is the Notes software product, released to the market in 1989 by Lotus Development Corporation, and subsequently sold to thousands of companies worldwide. Notes represents a class of software programs known as "groupware," which are designed to facilitate the working together of individuals by providing support for distributed electronic interaction over time. This group-oriented type of computing is grounded in research that was started by computer and social scientists in the mid- 1980s, and which became known as "computer-supported cooperative work" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="223" class="deo:Reference">Greif 1988</xref>). As represented by its manufacturer,the Notes technology consists of software modules to support communication via electronic mail and shared discussion databases, as well as programming tools to build new applications within the Notes system (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="224" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>). Phys- ically, Notes consists of both "clients" -the software installed on users' personal computers, which mediates interaction with the Notes system-and "servers"- the software installed on network computers which facilitates communication among the users and supportstheir access to shared databases maintained locally and remotely within the Notes system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="225" class="deo:Reference">DeJean and DeJean 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="226" class="deo:Reference">Chalstrom 1993</xref>). While there is some general "rhetorical closure" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Pinch and Bijker 1984</xref>) on the properties represented by the Notes product, such "closure" refers only to the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Notes technological artifact and its descriptions in training manuals, marketing ads, and press reports. The technologies-in-practice enacted with Notes, because they are constituted in use, cannot attain such closure. And as we will see below, multiple, different technologies-in- practice were enacted by different user groups-one by Iris developers, three within Alpha, and two by Zeta customer support staff.<marker type="block"/> Iris While the Notes technology is currently manufacturedby the Lotus Development Corporation (now owned by IBM), it was conceived and designed by Ray Ozzie, founder of Iris Associates. Ozzie traces his vision for Notes to the Plato system, a mainframe-basedcomputing environment at the University of Illinois in Urbana- Champaign. Ozzie used this system as a computer science student in the seventies, and observed "people who had no knowledge of computers using this tool to collaborate on projects." This left such a big impression on Ozzie that after working in the software industry for a number of years, he returnedto these early experiences:<marker type="block"/> With financing from the Lotus Development Corporation, Ozzie founded Iris Associates in 1984 and hired four former colleagues. The five Iris developers spent the next four years designing, building, and testing the Notes product. The knowledge and techniques used to construct the Notes technology came from Ozzie's Plato-inspired vision of collaborative computing and the various personal computing and networking environments the five developers had been exposed to over the years, such as client server architecture,graphic user interface, and public key cryptography. Additional influences on the construction of Notes were the ideals about work shared by the developers:<marker type="block"/> As a result, the Notes technology has a highly distributed architecture which supports collaboration among a variety of distributed users. In addition, it allows users to<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> customize their interface with the technology and provides them with the tools to develop their own applications within the Notes system. Ozzie explained that the capability to "build" applications was extended to all users in conformance with the Iris philosophy of decen- tralized control:<marker type="block"/> As is common in many software development projects, the Iris developers used the technology they were building to support their own development activities, using its features of electronic mail, discussion databases, text entry, text edit, text search, and tool design to create and share repositories of software documentation and modules. So, the first technology-in-practice to be constituted with the Notes technology was the one enacted recurrently by members of the Iris development team. It was a structure of collaboration, which both shaped and was shaped by the ongoing Iris software development process. It was influenced by the Iris developers' strong views about distributed control and individual empowerment,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> their participative culture and limited hierarchy, their en- ergy and motivation to create a computer tool to support collaboration, as well as the properties of the emerging Notes technology that Iris developers were inscribing into the artifact. Their enactment of a collaborative technology-in-practice thus modified aspects of the technology itself (through the addition or improvement of various properties), strengthened the Iris developers' be- lief in the value (both for themselves and more generally) of computer-supportedcollaboration, and reinforced their distributed and collegial work practices and norms (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="259" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>). Different technologies-in-practice with the Notes technology were enacted in other settings. Example of Enactment: Three Technologies-in- Practice Within Alpha Alpha (a pseudonym) is a large, multinational consulting firm with offices in hundreds of cities around the world, employing thousands of consultants who work on project engagements to deliver professional services to clients. While consultants work in engagement teams, their work relations and practices are strongly influenced by the "up or out" career structure which regulates progress of all consultants via four primary career milestones: junior consultant, senior consultant, manager, and partner. In the late eighties, a chief information officer (CIO) position was created with responsibility for Alpha's global use of information technology. Having recently</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="190" page="8" column="2">410</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="191" page="8" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCENVol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="192" page="8" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="193" page="9" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx198">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_009.image_10.png" thmb="62lg.page_009.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="200" page="9" column="2">Because agents draw on rules in the enactment of social practices, the capacity to modify the 'rule' that is drawn on in any action is an ever-present possibility. Men and women may, for example, transform the traditional 'rules' which have structured their past interaction by eschewing sexist norms. At each point of structuralreproduction there is also the potential for change.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="206" page="9" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCENVol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="207" page="9" column="2">411</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="208" page="9" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="209" page="10" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx214">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_010.image_11.png" thmb="62lg.page_010.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="218" page="10" column="2">412</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="219" page="10" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="220" page="10" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="221" page="11" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="222" page="11" column="1">Enacting Technologies-in-Practice: Empirical Examples</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx229">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_011.image_12.png" thmb="62lg.page_011.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="231" page="11" column="2">Example of Enactment: CollaborativeTechnology- in-Practice Within</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="233" page="11" column="2">In the early eighties I was working in spreadsheets, but spreadsheets didn't turn me on. So my mind turned to Plato and what I had experienced there-collaboration and communication. I wanted to start my own company to develop those things.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="235" page="11" column="2">As a group of individuals we share the same beliefs about how we'd like to see people work-the Iris values. [And so], we implemented a very different software development methodol- ogy here that relies on distributed management, distributed security, and distributed development.... Distribution is a value that pervades our philosophy. So technically and architecturally the product embraced distribution.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="237" page="11" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="238" page="11" column="2">413</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="239" page="11" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="240" page="12" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="241" page="12" column="1">Table 1</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="242" page="12" column="1">Properties of the Notes Technological Artifact</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx243">
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="12">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> ELEMENTS</td>
                  <td class="table"> TECHNOLOGICAL PROPERTIES</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Electronic</td>
                  <td class="table"> Electronic messaging to geographically dispersed community via e-mail</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Communication</td>
                  <td class="table"> Announcements and responses on widely distributed electronic bulletin boards</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Importing of newsfeeds from external services</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Electronic mail gateways to transfer Notes e-mail messages to other systems</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Text Editing</td>
                  <td class="table"> Creation and editing of documents that include multiple field types and formats with an emphasis on free-form</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> textual information</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Importing of text, tables, spreadsheets, graphics, images, and sound from other programs</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Document</td>
                  <td class="table"> Creation and management of databases of documents in a variety of views</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"> Search and retrieval of individual or groups of documents based on indexes or free text searches</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Customization</td>
                  <td class="table"> Direct manipulation of user interface</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Modification of default views and database templates</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Integration</td>
                  <td class="table"> Connection between various features: communication, text editing, and document management</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Replication</td>
                  <td class="table"> Periodic, scheduled duplication of designated databases across Notes servers in a network</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Support for stand-alone computers through dial-up into a Notes server</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Security</td>
                  <td class="table"> Provision of password protection and ID verification to control access to databases</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Support for data encryption at level of e-mail messages, databases, documents, and particular fields</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Application</td>
                  <td class="table"> Programming of unique database applications via Notes Application Programming Interface</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Development</td>
                  <td class="table"> Computation of totals, averages, and other statistics on any field</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> (from DeJean and</td>
                  <td class="table"> DeJean 1991)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="244" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">ELEMENTS</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="245" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">TECHNOLOGICAL PROPERTIES</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="246" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Electronic Communication</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="247" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Text Editing</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="248" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Document Management Customization</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="249" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Integration Replication</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="250" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Security</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="251" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Application Development</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="252" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Electronic messaging to geographically dispersed community via e-mail Announcements and responses on widely distributed electronic bulletin boards Importing of newsfeeds from external services Electronic mail gateways to transfer Notes e-mail messages to other systems Creation and editing of documents that include multiple field types and formats with an emphasis on free-form textual information Importing of text, tables, spreadsheets, graphics, images, and sound from other programs Creation and management of databases of documents in a variety of views Search and retrieval of individual or groups of documents based on indexes or free text searches Direct manipulation of user interface Modification of default views and database templates Connection between various features: communication, text editing, and document management Periodic, scheduled duplication of designated databases across Notes servers in a network Support for stand-alone computers through dial-up into a Notes server Provision of password protection and ID verification to control access to databases Support for data encryption at level of e-mail messages, databases, documents, and particular fields Programming of unique database applications via Notes Application Programming Interface Computation of totals, averages, and other statistics on any field</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="254" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">(from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="253" class="deo:Reference">DeJean and DeJean 1991</xref>)</region>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="256" page="12" column="1">A design debate we had a lot was: Does every copy of Notes have the ability to design applications or do we have a "developer's copy" and "user copies"? In practice, while it is a night- mare for the MIS person to have this [design] capability on every copy of Notes, it makes the product more exciting for the users because anyone can turn from a user to a developer over- night. We wanted individuals to have independence over their work.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx258">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_012.image_13.png" thmb="62lg.page_012.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="261" page="12" column="2">414</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="262" page="12" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="263" page="12" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="264" page="13" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="265" page="13" column="1">Figure 3</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="266" page="13" column="1">L</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="267" page="13" column="1">Collaboration Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Developers in Iris I Distributed Authority - - ParticipativeCulture - - -_ _- ,_ I ; NonhierarchicalStructure l ~ ~~~ I- I I I ~ ~~~~~ Collaboration Technology-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="268" page="13" column="1">!.. -. .-..- ..-.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="269" page="13" column="1">-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="270" page="13" column="1">-- ---.. - --.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="271" page="13" column="1">_.. _.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="272" page="13" column="1">Facilities, Norms, Interpretive Schemes,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="273" page="13" column="1">*</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="274" page="13" column="1">iC</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="275" page="13" column="1">e.g., e.g., e.g., * electronic mail technology is powerfultool * discussion databases tools arebestdesigned for collaboration (readandwrite) colaboraive extensivetechnical expertise * text entryandedit * by evolvingunderstanding of *database creation and suogcnrl the valueof Notes for customization collaborative design</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="276" page="13" column="1">i l: Developers use Notes extensively to collaborate on the design and development of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="280" page="13" column="1">been exposed to Notes, the CIO was persuaded that it offered the functionality not only to provide corporate- wide electronic mail support, but also to facilitate broad knowledge sharing. These properties, he believed, would address the considerable "reinvention of the wheel" which occurred when Alpha consultants in different offices worked on similar client problems without sharing ideas, approaches, or solutions, thus duplicating effort and not "leveraging the existing expertise and experience of the firm." The CIO purchased thousands of copies of Notes for Alpha' s consultants, and orderedhis technology staff to install it (and the supporting infrastructure of hardware and networks) rapidly in all offices, so as to establish a critical mass of users as quickly as possible. I studied the use of Notes by both consultants and technologists. As the latter were the first to encounter Notes within Alpha, I will begin with their experiences of using Notes. Collective Problem-Solving Technology-in-Practice. Alpha's technology group consisted of some 40 technology staff who reported to the CIO. The group was re- sponsible for setting corporate technology standards and supporting the firm's technological infrastructure.Most of the group members had technical backgrounds, having worked as programmers and computer support staff for most of their careers. While providing support to the firm's consultants, these technologists were not regarded as consultants. As a result, they were not required to bill their time to clients, and were not subject to the rigid timing and high risk associated with Alpha's hierarchical consulting career path. In addition to implementing Notes throughoutthe firm, <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> these technologists used the Notes technology extensively in their work. They used electronic mail for coordinating and scheduling their activities, and they maintained a variety of electronic discussions within Notes databases. Most of the technologists frequently accessed and con- tributed to these discussion databases, exchanging information about technical problems, solutions, and new or upgraded products. Some had also created their own database designs, using the feature within Notes that allows customization of database templates. Not subject to the competitive culture, "up-or-out" career tension, and "billable hours" pressures faced by the consultants, and supported by the cooperative norms of technical support, the technologists used many of the properties of Notes to promote their collective technical work, and to cooperate with each other. They also modified the technology over time as they added data to the databases and created or customized databases. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, technologists drew on their detailed knowledge of Notes and their technical support work practices and norms to interact with such properties of Notes as electronic mail, text entry and editing, discussion databases, and database design. This recurrentaction enacted a set of rules and resources which structuredtheir work in terms of cooperative trou- bleshooting and technical knowledge sharing, while modifying the technology itself (by adding content, creating new databases, and customizing templates). In turn, this technology-in-practice of collective problem-solving re- affirmed the value of cooperation within Alpha's technology group and reinforced their established cooperative work practices and norms, further encouraging the technologists to keep using Notes to support their work of maintaining Alpha' s technological infrastructure (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="279" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>). In contrast to this pattern of Notes use, the consultants I studied within Alpha engaged with Notes quite differently and enacted two distinct technologies-in-practice. Limited-Use Technology-in-Practice. The most common technology-in-practice I observed in the consulting group involved limited use of Notes, and was enacted by consultants at all levels of the firm. Such use of Notes was minimal, even perfunctory, and involved opening electronic mail folders a few times a week, rarely, if ever, sending a message, and only occasionally accessing a discussion database to examine activity in it. My data suggest that this technology-in-practice was enacted for at least three different reasons. First, some consultants had doubts about the value of Notes for their own and the firm's performance. Some of these consultants based their skepticism on the view that Notes primarily facilitated information transfer while</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx278">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_013.image_14.png" thmb="62lg.page_013.image_14-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="281" page="13" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="282" page="13" column="2">415</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="283" page="13" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="284" page="14" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="285" page="14" column="1">Figure 4</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="286" page="14" column="1">Ci)</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="287" page="14" column="1">Z3 I Individual and Collective Incentive Structure</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="288" page="14" column="1">Collective Problem-Solving Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Technologists in Alpha I.-------------------------- I Cooperative Culture -__ - ' J - --__ _ _ - -_ - _ - - - -_ _ - - - II '-'</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="289" page="14" column="1">Collective-Problen-Solving Technology-in-Pracflce</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="290" page="14" column="1">Facilities, Norms,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="291" page="14" column="1">Interpretive Schemes,</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="292" page="14" column="1">e.g., e.g., electronicmail * technicalproblem-solving e.g., discussiondatabases is complexand is better technologyis useful fo i (readand write) performed cooperatively problemsolving daiabase text database entryand creaon creation edit and * knowledgesharingand help-givingis technica support expectedin detailedunderstandin technicalsupportwork of the utility of Notesfor</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="293" page="14" column="1">~d i</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="294" page="14" column="1">custonmization</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="295" page="14" column="1">Technology staff use Notes frequently for technical problem solving and cooperation</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="297" page="14" column="1">their work as Alpha consultants was to manage client relationships. Other consultants were skeptical about technologies in general and applied this same skepticism to Notes. A vivid illustration of such skepticism was provided by a manager who handed me a cartoon clipped from the morning's newspaper, commenting: "You asked me what I thought of Notes. Well, here' s your an- swer" (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="296" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>). The skepticism felt by these consultants was exacer- bated by their limited knowledge of Notes' functionality. The training sessions conducted about Notes dealt with the mechanics of using the software and were technical and abstract. The collaborative aspects of Notes were not highlighted and there was little illustration of how Notes could be used in Alpha's consulting practice. Most consultants found the training condescending and unhelpful, and many had not referred to the Notes documentation which they had all been issued. These often lay, still shrink-wrapped,in the corners of offices or on the tops of bookshelves. Thus, despite training and access to Notes, consultants remained skeptical and unmotivated to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="298" page="14" column="1">Figure 5</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="299" page="14" column="1">Example of Skepticism Towards Technology</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="300" page="14" column="1">FOR~</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="301" page="14" column="1">YOU JU5T DON'T UNDERSTAND TECMNOLOGY, DO</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="302" page="14" column="1">THIS 15 MYNEW OPTLAYER D15K T PLAYER ThE COMPUTER. )i' /</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="303" page="14" column="1">NOWI CAN IN5TANTLY ACCE5S THE WORKS OF SHAKE5PEARE K OR [D OFE G5TREECE( OFGREECE! HO OFTEN DO X (. &lt;v YO( NEEDTO DOTHAT?</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="304" page="14" column="1">1rr UST A DOG.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="305" page="14" column="1">DILBERTreprinted by permission of United Feature Syndicate, Inc.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx306">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62lg.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="314" page="14" column="2">spend much time using the technology. I shadowed half a dozen managers and partners for a few days after they had received Notes training, and found that they accessed Notes for an average of two minutes a day-usually just to check if they had received any electronic mail. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, consultants drew on their firm's orientation to relationship management, their limited knowledge of Notes, their view of it as "simply a solution in search of a problem," their prior experiences with and assumptions about computers as in- appropriate or ineffective, and their perfunctory use of Notes' electronic mail and discussion databaseproperties, to enact a set of minimal rules and resources which barely influenced their existing consulting work practices and did not alter the technology. In turn, this limited-use technology-in-practice, because it provided them with little value, strengthened the consultants' assumptions and experiences of Notes as less than useful for their consulting work practices, and reinforced the firm's orientation to relationship management. The second reason why consultants enacted a limited- use technology-in-practice with Notes was rooted in their ongoing enactment of Alpha's time-based billing structure. For all consultants except partners, there was an expectation that most if not all hours should be "chargeable," that is, billed to clients and hence revenue- producing. Consultants were held accountable for any "below the line" (nonchargeable) hours they incurred and most consultants studiously avoided having any.10 One consultant noted: "Seniors and managers never have nonchargeable hours. It's just not done. It doesn't hap- pen." Because many consultants did not see using Notes as an activity that could be billed to clients, they were unwilling to spend time learning or using it, as this would have required them to incur "nonchargeable hours" or to give up some of their personal time. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, consultants drew on their knowledge of Alpha's institutional practices (in particular, the corporate norm against "nonchargeable" hours), their perception of Notes as not useful for client work, and their limited use of Notes' electronic mail and discussion database properties, to enact a set of minimal rules and resources which had little influence on their existing consulting work practices or their technology. In turn, such a limited-use technology- in-practice, because it provided minimal value to the consultants, bolstered their assumptions about Notes as not valuable in client work, and as not worth the cost of either nonchargeable hours or their own personal time. It also reinforced the legitimacy and importance of the firm's time-based billing structure. The third reason consultants enacted a limited-use <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> technology-in-practice with Notes arose from their fear that use of its collaborative properties would threaten their status within Alpha. The competitive culture at Alpha, strongly reinforced by the "up-or-out" career path, was seen by many consultants as encouraging the development of individually distinctive competence. As one manager put it:<marker type="block"/> In an environment where "knowledge is power," many consultants believed that any sharing of expertise-par- ticularly via the global and relatively anonymous network provided by Alpha's Notes infrastructure-would hurt, not help, their chances of generating some unique expertise and consequently of securing the sought-after pro- motions. Thus, use of Notes was perceived by consultants to be counterculturaland incompatible with their individual advancement and success in the firm. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, consultants drew on their understandingof Notes as a tool for broad distribution of expertise, their knowledge of Alpha's culture as competitive and individualistic, and their perfunctory use of Notes' electronic mail and discussion database properties to enact a set of minimal rules and resources which did little to alter their existing consulting work practices or their technology. In turn, such a limited-use technology-in-practice, because it offered no counterev- idence to the consultants' fears, further increased their reluctance to use Notes to share expertise, and reinforced their firm's practice of rewarding individual effort and distinctive competence rather than cooperation and knowledge sharing. While the limited-use technology-in-practice was pre- dominant among the Alpha consultants I studied (see Figure 6), another technology-in-practice emphasizing individual productivity was also evident in the practices of a different set of consultants. Individual Productivity Technology-in-Practice. Another (smaller) set of consultants in Alpha did not view Notes as either irrelevantor threatening;instead, they saw it as an opportunity to enhance their own individual effectiveness by speeding up existing ways of doing things. Thus, a few managers and senior consultants began to use Notes regularly to perform activities previously conducted on paper or with other media. For example, they began distributing memos via Notes ratherthan on paper, sending electronic rather than voice mail messages, and transferringfiles electronically to other offices ratherthan using the fax machine or express mail services. Some managers also used Notes to obtain electronic newsfeeds</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="308" page="14" column="2">416</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="309" page="14" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="310" page="14" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="311" page="15" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI. Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="313" page="15" column="1">In Alpha we have a lot of problems getting people to share expertise and information. That is not in the culture. .. People hide information because it gives them an edge.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx315">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_015.image_16.png" thmb="62lg.page_015.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="316" page="15" column="2">Figure 6 Limited-Use Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Consultants in Alpha r --- -- ----------- _ __ I Individual Incentive Structure X ?) ; Competitive Culture I -4 ; Time-based Billing Structure r Zj y? | ,I-? Relationship _ _ _ _ _ _ Management _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ L - I</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="317" page="15" column="2">Limited-Use Technology-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="318" page="15" column="2">r - - -- - ---.-..-._.._... ._._._.._...- - -- - - -- - . ... Facilities, e.g., Norms, Interpretive Schemes, (read-only) develop distinctive - poor understanding of</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="319" page="15" column="2">0 i</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="320" page="15" column="2">e.g., : eectronic mail cultivateclient relations e.g., * discussion (read-sc onl databases * your charge100 time to percentof clients skepticismtowards technologyin consulting competenceto get ahead the utility of Notesfor * knowledge is power consultingwork</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="321" page="15" column="2">Consultants use Notes minimally, sporadically, and perfunctorily</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="323" page="15" column="2">from Reuters or to access Alpha publications, previously available on paper or from a centralized computer system in Alpha's library. Applying a new technology to existing tasks is a common response to encountering unfamiliartechnologies, as Barley (1988, p. 50) notes, "[workers] often attempt to assimilate new technologies under previous patterns of practice and interpretation." Because these consultants' use of Notes automated established practices and increased efficiency, it did not violate institutional norms, and thus did not undermine their professional standing within the firm. Indeed, these consultants believed their use of Notes would give them a competitive edge in the firm by enhancing their personal productivity. In this recurrent practice of technology use, consultants drew on their knowledge of Alpha' s culture, their moderate knowledge of some of the functionality of Notes, and engaged specific properties of Notes (electronic mail, newsfeeds, databases, and file transfer) to enact a set of rules and resources which increased their work productivity and incrementally modified the technology (via customizations to the desktop and content added to databases). In turn, such a technology-in-practice of individual productivity, because it provided demonstrable improvements in efficiency, supported these consultants' view of Notes as an effective tool for personal productivity gains, while reinforcing the individualistic and efficiency orientation of the firm (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="322" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>). Members of Alpha from the consulting and technology support communities thus used the Notes technology to enact three different technologies-in-practice. Members</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="324" page="15" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="325" page="15" column="2">417</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="326" page="15" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="327" page="16" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="328" page="16" column="1">Figure 7</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="329" page="16" column="1">tsX -I-____ - --------------I</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="330" page="16" column="1">b;</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="331" page="16" column="1">Individual Productivity Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Consultants in Alpha r----------------------- Individual Incentive Structure Competitive Culture E Time-based Billing Structure Relationship Management '</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="332" page="16" column="1">s niidual-Productivity</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="333" page="16" column="1">Technology-in-Practicea</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="334" page="16" column="1">Facilities, Norms, -</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="335" page="16" column="1">Interpretive Schemes,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="336" page="16" column="1">-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="337" page="16" column="1">- -</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="338" page="16" column="1">e.g., e.g., i electronicmail develop distinctive e.g., l * discussiondatabases competenceto get ahead * technologycan speed up (readand write) knowledgeis power some existingtasks newsfeeds professionals are * specificunderstanding of efficientin theirwork the utility of Notesfor * file transfer automatingsome tasks</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="339" page="16" column="1">Consultants use Notes regularly to improve their personal efficiency</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="342" page="16" column="1">of another user community-this one within the Zeta or- ganization-used Notes in still different ways. Example of Enactment: Two Technologies-in- Practice Within Zeta Zeta (a pseudonym) is a Top 50 U.S. software company, producing and selling a range of powerful marketing analysis products. In 1994, Zeta earned $100 million in revenues and employed about 1000 employees in its Mid- west headquarters and regional sales offices around the world. My colleagues and I examined the implementation and use of Notes in Zeta's customer support department (CSD). Customer support at Zeta involved providing technical consultation via telephone to clients, client service representatives in the field, and other Zeta employees. The technical consultation provided by customer support specialists was a complex activity, typically in- volving several hours or even days of research including searches of reference material, attempts to replicate the problem, and review of program source code. The CSD employed fifty specialists, and was headed by a director and two managers. In early 1992, the CSD purchasedNotes and developed a customized application within it, the Incident Tracking Support System (ITSS), to help keep track of customer calls. The acquisition of Notes was motivated by a real- ization that the existing call tracking system was ineffi- cient and poorly used, and the anticipation of increased calls due to a growing client base and an expanding product range. Following a successful pilot in the latter half of 1992, the CSD deployed Notes and ITSS throughout <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the department.We studied the use of Notes in the CSD from 1992 to 1994 and found that over time the support specialists enacted two distinct, but complementary, technologies-in-practice with Notes. Process-Support Technology-in-Practice. Specialists' initial use of Notes enacted a technology-in-practice of process support. Such a recurrentpractice of technology use involved two primary activities: work documentation and information search. In documenting their work process, specialists used the online input and text-editing properties of Notes to enter every customer call they received as an incident in the ITSS database, to maintain a complete trace for each incident as they worked on it, and to record the final problem resolution when they closed the incident. The work documentation generated by specialists began to accumulate in the ITSS database, growing from about 4,000 entries in December 1992 to 35,000 in December 1994. This information became increasingly valuable as specialists started to search the database to try to find existing solutions for new problems. By December 1994, specialists reported being able to resolve up to 50 percent of new incidents simply by using the Notes search function to probe the ITSS database. Search- ing ITSS was seen by the specialists to be helpful not just because prior entries revealed potentially reusable problem resolutions, but also because they provided a detailed trace of the work process followed to resolve different types of incidents. The specialists' engagement with Notes for their support work utilized many of its properties-electronic text entry and editing, as well as database searching and document management. As technical support specialists, the CSD members were knowledgeable about technology in general, as well as Notes in particular.This latter knowledge was acquired through a series of official training sessions (referred to as "Notes jam sessions") which included intensive hands-on use of Notes during which specialists simulated their production work in the Notes environment, taking "fake calls" from colleagues and then documenting these in the ITSS database. Specialists' use of Notes to record and reuse problem resolution knowledge was in direct contrast to the action of many of the Alpha consultants, who had felt inhibited by their competitive culture to create and share knowledge within Notes. In comparison, Zeta specialists reported that the CSD's cooperative culture and its team orientation encouraged such behavior:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx341">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_016.image_17.png" thmb="62lg.page_016.image_17-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="343" page="16" column="2">I don't care who grabs credit for my work.. This support department does well because we're a team, not because we're all individuals.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="344" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">Specialists' ongoing enactment of a process-support</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="345" page="16" column="2">418</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="346" page="16" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 1 1, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="347" page="16" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="348" page="17" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="350" page="17" column="1">technology-in-practice was further reinforced by managerial action which redefined the evaluation criteria used to assess specialists' performance. Managers modified these criteria to include use of Notes for entry and documentation of customer calls, and rewarded specialists for creating high quality process documentation and for re- using existing solutions in the database. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, specialists drew on their knowledge of the CSD's norms of cooperation and collegiality, its team incentive structure and expectations of effective client service, their familiarity and experience with computer technology in general, their detailed technical knowledge of Notes, and used the text entry, editing, searching, and documentation properties of Notes to enact a set of rules and resources which provided electronic process supportto their technical support work. They also modified aspects of their technology through such use by generating document templates and adding content to the database. In turn, this process- support technology-in-practice, because it provided im- mediate and tangible benefits to the CSD specialists served to amplify their view that using Notes facilitated customer support work, and reinforced their cooperative and team oriented department structure (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="349" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>). Many of these support specialists also enacted another pattern of using Notes. Improvisation Technology-in-Practice. A subsequent technology-in-practice enacted by the CSD specialists involved their use of Notes to respond artfully to unanticipated problems and unexpected opportunities that arose in their work. Such improvisational action went beyond</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="351" page="17" column="1">Figure 8</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="352" page="17" column="1">Process-Support Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Support Specialists in Zeta r Learning Orientation X r?-------? , Oi) E Cooperative Culture I -I.__ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _, i I TeamIncentiveStructure r</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="353" page="17" column="1">* % Process-Support Technology-in-Practice *</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="354" page="17" column="1">r--------.-.._.._._... Facilities,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="355" page="17" column="1">...._..._....._.._.... .._.._.._.._.._.. Norms, Interpretive</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="356" page="17" column="1">*</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="357" page="17" column="1">* *</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="358" page="17" column="1">e.g., e.g., SChemes, e.g., ! i * * text databasesearching databasesearching entry and edit deliver ana and tlmely timely high service quality quaity technology quality and can speed improve of work i * electronicmail act professionally * specific understandingof * document management be a team player the utility of Notesand ITSSfor technicalsupport</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="359" page="17" column="1">Support specialists use Notes and the ITSS application routinely to deliver electronic technical support to clients</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="360" page="17" column="1">. _ . _ . _ .. .. .. . _ . _ . _ . _. _ . .. .. .. _ . _ . _ _ . _ . _ .. .. . ,.. ... _ _,. ,.,._,.,. ,, ._,. _</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx361">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_017.image_18.png" thmb="62lg.page_017.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="374" page="17" column="2">the process-support technology-in-practice, and typically generated workarounds or new processes for conducting technical support work. For example, one such process concerned the expectation, set by the CSD managers and provided for in the design of ITSS, that specialists would directly enter calls into the ITSS database as they received them, so as to produce an up-to-the-minute trace of all incoming calls. However, many specialists found the process of entering calls into ITSS while on the phone too difficult, and so they developed a workaroundby writing down call details on paper, and then entering these into the ITSS database just after the phone call finished. Specialists' rationale for this practice was grounded in their concerns about typing skills and the importance of fully understandingtheir customers' technical problems before entering them into the ITSS database. Further improvisational use of Notes arose when specialists began to use it to collaborate on incidents. Before the implementation of Notes, specialists helped each other only when asked to do so. Specialists tended to work on their own incidents in private until they felt stuck, at which point they would approach a colleague-either by phone or face-to-face-and solicit help. In this interaction with colleagues, they would also learn new skills and knowledge. As specialists used Notes for process support, they gained access to the entire ITSS database, which included all calls, past and present, worked on by members of the CSD. Specialists got into the habit of browsing through each others' calls, and using these to engage in an ad hoc learning process: <marker type="block"/> There were two consequences of such browsing. One was that specialists realized the potential for using the ITSS databaseto trainnewly-hired specialists. Thus, a few senior specialists extracted sample problems from the ITSS database and created a "training database" within Notes which new hires worked with to learn the process of problem resolution. Their interaction with this training database was then monitored by a designated mentor, and in this way new recruits received guidance and practice in the techniques of online technical support work. The second consequence of browsing the database was that specialists got to see still-open calls where they might have some expertise to help. This created an opportunity for specialists to offer each other proactive help, in contrast to the reactive mode which had operated previously. Rather than waiting to be approached to give assistance on specific incidents, specialists now took the initiative as they browsed the ITSS database to offer unsolicited<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> help on calls where they believed they had some particular knowledge:<marker type="block"/> While the enactment of the improvisation technology- in-practice was initiated by specialists, it was supported by the "learning" orientation emphasized by departmen- tal managers who actively encouraged specialists to explore alternative ways of working and offer suggestions for improving processes in the CSD. While managersrec- ommended a particularuse of ITSS, they did not rigidly enforce it, accepting workarounds and variations if these produced valued results. In this recurrentpractice of technology use, specialists drew on their knowledge of their CSD environment (in particularnorms of cooperation and expectations of learning and experimentation), their familiarity and experience with computer technology in general, and their detailed technical knowledge of Notes, to use multiple properties of Notes (text entry and editing, database browsing, electronic mail, and data analysis), and modify them (e.g., by adding content and creating a new training database). Such recurrentuse enacted a set of rules and resources which supported specialists' improvisation beyond their process-support technology-in- practice and helped them to overcome practical difficulties and to innovate additional ways of working and learning. In turn, this improvisation technology-in- practice, because it provided value to the specialists' work, affirmed their view that using Notes could enhance their work through ongoing experimentation and change, and reinforced the cooperative culture and learning-ori- ented structureof their department (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9" id="371" class="deo:Reference">Figure 9</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Taken together, these empirical illustrations show that people enact different technologies-in-practice with the same type of technology across various contexts and practices. We have seen that they do so in response to various technological visions, skills, fears, and opportunities, influenced by specific interpretationsand particular institutional contexts, and shaped by a diversity of intentions and practices to collaborate, solve problems, preserve status, improve efficiency, support work processes, learn, and improvise. These technologies-in-practice are structuresenacted through the recurrentuse of a technology. They are not embodied within the technology; rather, they emerge from the ongoing and situated interactions that users have with the technology at hand. Thus, in the case of Iris Associates we see that developers drew on their earlier experiences of different technologies, their visions about collaborative use of technology, their knowledge of software design, and their</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="363" page="17" column="2">If it is quiet I will check on my fellow colleagues to see ... what kind of calls they get, so I might learn something from them.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="365" page="17" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 1 1, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="366" page="17" column="2">419</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="367" page="17" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="368" page="18" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="370" page="18" column="1">Sometimes, if I see something that's open on somebody's calls which I've seen before, I may put a note in the incident and say "Hey, I think I've seen this before, this might be this and this."</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="373" page="18" column="1">Examples of Enactment: Summary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F9">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_018.image_19.png" thmb="62lg.page_018.image_19-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="376" page="18" column="2">Figure 9</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="377" page="18" column="2">Improvisation Technology-in-Practice Enacted by Support Specialists in Zeta r?-?---------------______ E Learning Orientation - - - - - - - - -? --? I E Cooperative Culture - ;- ~~~r- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -_____ Team Incentive Structure I _</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="378" page="18" column="2">Improvisaihon Technolo-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="379" page="18" column="2">Facilities,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="380" page="18" column="2">*</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="381" page="18" column="2">Norms,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="382" page="18" column="2">Interpretive Schemes,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="383" page="18" column="2">* *</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="384" page="18" column="2">e.g., e.g., * text entry and edit deliver high quality e.g., * databasesearching and timely service technologycan improve and browsing * act professionally ways of working * electronicmail be a team player * some understandingof * documentmanagement collaboratewith others how Notesand ITSScan * data analysis learn throughdoing improve ways of working</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="385" page="18" column="2">Support specialists use Notes and the ITSS application to experiment with new ways of working</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="441" page="18" column="2">start-up environment to recurrently enact a collaborative technology-in-practice that both created and engaged the collaborative and distributed design properties of Notes as rules and resources for their software development efforts. Technology members of Alpha, influenced by an institutional context that supported and rewarded cooperation in technical support work, recurrently enacted a technology-in-practice that engaged many of the collaborative and design properties of Notes as rules and resources for collective problem solving. Consultant members of Alpha, influenced by their firm's hierarchical career path, individual criteria for evaluation and pro- motion, time-based billing system, and their personal skepticism and apprehensions, recurrently enacted technologies-in-practice that engaged very few of the properties of Notes as rules and resources for either limited use or individual productivity gains. Finally, Zeta support specialists, influenced by a collegial environment which encouraged experimentation and learning, and motivated by a personal interest to be cooperative and deliver more effective service, recurrentlyenacted technologies- in-practice that engaged many of the collaborative and design properties of Notes as rules and resources for process support and improvisation of customer service work. These examples further illustrate how a practice lens allows us to see what, when, where, how, and why different groups enact different structures (technologies-in- practice) through their recurrentinteraction with a particular set of technological properties, in similar and different contexts, at the same time, and over time. In addition, such a practice lens allows us to examine the <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> institutional, interpretive, and technological conditions which shape the ongoing constitution of different structures, and how such constitution in turn reinforces or modifies those institutional, interpretive, and technological elements. I turn now to some of the implications of a practice lens for studying technologies in organizations.<marker type="block"/> In this paper, I have sought to augment the existing structurationalperspective on technology by proposing a view of technology structures, not as embodied in given technological artifacts, but as enacted by the recurrentsocial practices of a community of users. This view directs researchers' attention to what people do with technology in their everyday practices, and how such use is structured by the rules and resources implicated in their ongoing action. Rather than trying to understand why and how a given technology is more or less likely to be appropriated in various circumstances, a practice lens focuses on knowledgeable human action and how its recurrent engagement with a given technology constitutes and reconstitutes particular emergent structures of using the technology (technologies-in-practice). Thus, the research orientation is inverted-from a focus on given technologies, embodied structures, and their influence on use- to a focus on human agency and the enactment of emergent structuresin the recurrentuse of technologies. While a practice lens recognizes that technology use is always situated and emergent, it does not imply that such use is completely unique. On the contrary, because regular use of the same technology tends to be recurrent, people tend to enact the same or similar technologies-in- practice over time. In this way, enacted technology structures become routine, taken for granted, and even institutionalized within certain circumstances. Such stabilization for now of technologies-in-practice allows researchers to seek bounded generalizations about the types of technologies-in-practice likely to be enacted by particular types of users with specific technologies in various contexts and times. As Giddens (1984) notes, generalizations about human social conduct are of two types: those that "hold because actors themselves know them-in some guise-and apply them in the enactment of what they do" (p. xix); and those that refer to the unintended consequences of agents' patterns of action (p. 347). Both of these generalizations hold only in histori- cally and contextually-specific circumstances. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="393" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> suggests some provisional generalizations of both types based on comparisons across the conditions<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and consequences associated with the six technologies- in-practice enacted by members of Iris, Alpha, and Zeta with essentially the same technology (a customizable groupware tool, Notes installed on networked personal computers). Three kinds of conditions (acknowledged or unacknowledged) are salient here: interpretive, technological, and institutional. Interpretive conditions refer to the conventional understandings and shared meanings that members of a community construct to make sense of their world (including the technology they use). Technological conditions refer to the technological properties (both tool and data) available to the users in their work practices. Institutionalconditions refer to the social structures (normative, authoritative)that constitute part of the larger social system within which users work. Three kinds of consequences (intended or unintended) are relevant here: processual, technological, and structural.Processual consequences refer to changes (if any) in the execution and outcome of users' work practices. Technological consequences refer to changes (if any) in the technological properties available to the users. Structuralconsequences refer to changes (if any) in structures that users enact as part of the larger social system in which they are partici- pating. The comparison of the conditions and consequences associated with whether and how humans use the technology to enact different technologies-in-practice suggests that three clusters or types of enactment can be dis- cerned. These are associated with three distinct kinds of consequences: consequences that represent no evident change in process, technology, or structure;consequences that represent some change in one or more of process, technology, and structure; and consequences that represent significant change in one or more of process, technology, and structure. Whether or not the technology or the work practices are changed is often an intended outcome of people's knowledgeable actions; the structural consequences are much more likely to be unintendedcon- sequences of actions. The first type of enactment may be characterized in terms of inertia, where users choose to use technology to retain their existing way of doing things (see first row of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="396" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). It results in the reinforcement and preservation of the structuralstatus quo, with no discernable changes in work practices or the technological artifact. Inertia is represented in my data with the limited-use technology- in-practice, where users choose to use their new tool rarely and perfunctorily, and show little or no interest in integrating its use into their ongoing work practices. In the one case where this enactment was evident in my data, it was associated with interpretive conditions that included users having limited understanding and/or being<marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> skeptical of the technological properties available to them, and institutional conditions that included a rigid career hierarchy, individualistic incentives and task as- signments, and a competitive culture. Thus, as a type of enactment, inertia involves drawing on and not changing existing interpretive, technological, and institutional conditions, and, in this way, reproducing and reinforcing them over time.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The second type of enactment may be characterizedin terms of application, where people choose to use the new technology to augment or refine their existing ways of doing things (see next four rows of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="415" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). Such enactment results in the reinforcement and enhancement of the structural status quo, noticeable changes to the data and/or tool aspects of the technological artifact, as well as noticeable improvements to work processes.<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Application is represented in my data by four technolo- gies-in-practice-collaboration, individual productivity, collective problem-solving, and process-support-which were enacted in all three of the research sites I examined. Looking across the rows of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="421" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>, it is evident that this enactment occurred with users having moderate, com- petent, or extensive understanding of their technology at hand, and being either moderately or highly motivated to use it to enhance their work practices. These users worked within and drew on a range of institutional conditions (from hierarchical and competitive to collaborative and participative). While the interpretive and institutional conditions associated with these sites are diverse, com- monality lies in the users' intentions and actions. That is, all of the users in these four cases used the technology with the intention of improving or enhancing their existing work processes. Thus, as a type of enactment, application involves users drawing on existing institutional, interpretive, and technological conditions over time and reproducing them in an enhanced or improved form. For example, where the institutional conditions are hierarchical and individualistic, enactment in the form of application results in action that increases such hierarchy and individualism, as when the individual productivity technology-in-practice was used to furtherindividual ratherthan collaborative efforts within Alpha. Similarly, when the institutional conditions are nonhierarchicaland participative, as in the case of Iris, the enactment of the collaboration technology-in-practice helped to improve the shared and collaborative design efforts of the developers. The third type of enactment may be characterized in terms of change, where people choose to use the new technology to substantially alter their existing way of doing things (see last row of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="422" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). Such enactment results in transformation of the structural status quo, and significant modifications to users' work practices as well as the technological artifact. Enactment of change is represented here with the improvisation technology-in- practice, where specialists use the technology to experiment with and implement new ways of working and organizing, and to adapt/customize aspects of their tool and its data content. In the one case where this enactment was evident in my data, it was associated with interpretive conditions that included users being very knowledgeable about technology and highly motivated to use it in their work practices, and institutional conditions that included a strong team focus, a cooperative culture, and a strong commitment to ongoing learning. Thus, as a type of enactment, change involves drawing on and transforming<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> existing institutional, interpretive, and technological conditions over time, and, in this way, significantly changing the organizational status quo. Like the six technologies-in-practice, the three types of enactment characterized here are not comprehensive or exhaustive, but suggestive of the kinds of comparisons that may be made across the conditions and consequences associated with people's use of technologies. In this way, and through further research, a typology of enactment types may be identified that associates recurrent human action with clusters of technologies-in-practice enacted by using specific properties of technologies in specific interpretive and institutional contexts. The types of enactments discussed here all involved the use of the same kind of technology. Examining other kinds of technologies offering different properties to those of Notes would generate furtheropportunitiesto study how users draw on different technological conditions to enact particular types of technologies-in-practice with particular social consequences. Similarly, exploring different cultural (e.g., non-U.S.) and institutional (e.g., governmental, educational) contexts to those studied here would also expand our understandingof how users recurrentlystruc- ture their use of technologies in different circumstances. Additionally, future research could benefit from attending more carefully to the meanings and emotional attachments that users develop for the technologies they use. Beyond the skepticism displayed by some of the consultants within Alpha, my empirical data did not capture the richness of users' affective connections with technology. Understanding these attachments and meanings could offer richer explanations for the range of structural responses enacted by users as they engage with technologies in practice. Identifying types of structuresof technology use should help both researchers and practitionersbetter understand how and why people are likely to use their technologies and with what (intended and unintended) consequences in different conditions. Of course, the types identified through such research can never exhaust the technologies-in-practice which users may enact in practice. A practice lens assumes that people are purposive, knowledgeable, adaptive, and inventive agents who engage with technology in a multiplicity of ways to accomplish various and dynamic ends. When the technology does not help them achieve those ends, they abandon it, or work around it, or change it, or think about changing their ends. A practice lens thus recognizes that users may always choose to do otherwise, and any typology of enactment types and technologies-in-practice must always remain an open set, as users will continue to modify their<marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> technologies and continue to change their uses of technology over time. Recognizing that the possibility to change technology structures is inherent in every use of technology allows us to understand when, where, how, and why people choose to reinforce, ignore, enhance, undermine, change, work around, or replace their existing structuresof technology use. The focus on technologies-in-practice also allows an examination of the extent to which users realize designers' intentions for a technology. That is, it can help us identify and analyze how the technological properties designed into and available in artifacts deployed on shop floors, installed on desktops, or downloadable from Web servers, are used in situated and emergent ways by people attempting to get something done in their daily activities. It has long been recognized that technologies are often not used as designed or intended (Bijker 1995, von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="430" class="deo:Reference">Hippel 1988</xref>), but generating an adequate understandingof how, where, and why the slippage between design and use occurs in practice has been difficult. By distinguishing between technologies as artifacts and technologies-in- practice, we have a way to explore and explain this process. For example, the examination of the Notes technology and its properties, as well as its designers' intentions, provides a profile of potential use that may be com- pared to the technologies-in-practice realized in a range of recurrentpractices. It suggests, for example, that where users' social practices are compatible with designers' intentions and the properties inscribed within a technology, a technology-in-practice may be enacted that more closely realizes those designers' intentions and their technology' s properties. We saw this in the case of the Alpha technologists and Zeta specialists whose work practices of technical support and peer collaboration corresponded with the Notes designers' visions and norms of supporting collaboration through technology. Not surprisingly, the technologies-in-practice they enacted (collective problem-solving, process-support, and improvisation) were relatively compatible with the collaborative use envisioned by the Iris developers and provided for in their technology. In contrast, the work practices of the Alpha consultants (individual tasks, competition, knowledge hoarding, client-oriented time-keeping, limited technology experience) were incompatible with the Notes designers' visions of supportingcollaboration through technology. Not surprisingly, the technologies-in-practice enacted by the Alpha consultants (limited-use and individual productivity) did not come close to realizing the collaborative use envisioned by the Iris developers and provided for in their Notes technology. But even as we can explore compatibilities between users' recurrent social practices, designers' intentions,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> and technological properties, the practice lens reminds us that use of technology is always situated and emergent, and hence that users in their recurrent interaction with technologies may always choose to depart from designers' a priori intentions and the inscribed properties of the technology. Indeed, the correspondence between use and properties is expected to become, on the one hand, more loosely coupled, as newer reconfigurabletechnologies become increasingly available in organizations, and on the other hand, more integrated, as the rise of internetworking connects more and more artifacts together in new and complex configurations. With respect to the former trend, what are sometimes referred to as "radically tailorable tools" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="433" class="deo:Reference">Malone et al. 1992</xref>) tend to be less fixed-function than prior computing technologies, serving as general purpose platforms on which users may build local applications which convert the generic delivered technology into a customized and situated work tool. Sproull and Goodman (1990, p. 257) note: "[P]rogrammable technology allows for the possibility of continuous redesign." Reconfigurable technologies will provide users with the opportunity of defining a wider array of local properties with which they may be able to enact an even wider variety of technologies-in- practice. Of course, whether and how they do so depends not just on the properties of the technology, but as we saw above, on their social practices and the intentions, interpretations, and institutional contexts shaping those practices over time. Given such open-ended properties of new technologies, the ability to examine what people do with them in practice will be helped by being able to distinguish between the technological properties and the situated technologies-in-practice enacted with them. With respect to the latter integrating trend, the increased use of the Internet for conducting business requires more interconnections among more players than before (Iacono and Kling, in press). Organizations wish- ing to link to other businesses or to the Internet will need to provide standardinterfaces and consistency of performance across a range of technological platforms to ensure the interoperability of multiple artifacts. Providing for such interconnections increases interdependence and complexity, coupling the artifacts more tightly together in larger technological systems or infrastructures.Such integration is likely to reduce the degrees of freedom available to users to experiment with and modify their technological artifacts in use. As users become more de- pendent on using integrated technologies, the variety of technologies-in-practice that they will enact may decrease. Of course, whether such restriction in malleability actually occurs in any situation is an empirical question, and will depend on people's practices and how these are<marker type="page" number="23"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> affected by such influences as intentions, interpretations, and institutions. The distinction between technologies and technologies-in-practice further suggests that researchers and managers measuring technological investment or deployment to predict performance impacts may get more meaningful results if they look for returns on the use of technology ratherthan only at returns on the technology. Technology per se can't increase or decrease the productivity of workers' performance, only use of it can. This may sound like semantic hair-splitting, but how people talk has profound implications for how they think and act in the world. By emphasizing technology in their talk, people tend to emphasize the technology (not its use) in their allocation of funds, attention, and measures. Such an emphasis, as the examples within Alpha showed, typically leads to a neglect of recurrent and situated technology use (i.e., technologies-in-practice). By not examining or understandingwhat actually happens during use of technology, researchers and managers miss the crucial point, that it is whether and how people interactwith technology in their day-to-day activities-not the mere presence of the technology on the desktop or factory floor- that influences performance outcomes and consequences. Knowing what we know about the different technologies- in-practice enacted within Alpha and Zeta, there is no difficulty in understanding why these firms should have experienced significantly different outcomes from their investments in the same type of technology. The distinction between technologies and technologies-in-practice thus reminds us that measures of technology investment or deployment are not sufficient indicators of organizational change or effectiveness. Such change or effectiveness depends not on technologies alone, but on whether, how, and what technologies-in-practice are enacted with them. In this paper, I have proposed that the existing structurational perspective on technology be augmented with a practice orientation which focuses specifically on how people's recurrent interaction with technologies enacts distinctive structuresof technology use. These structures of technology use (technologies-in-practice) are not fixed or given, but constituted and reconstituted through the everyday, situated practices of particularusers using particular technologies in particular circumstances. By attending to such ongoing (re)constitution, a practice lens entails the examination of emergence, improvisation, and change over time as people reconfigure their technologies or alter their habits of use, and thereby enact different technologies-in-practice. A practice lens thus allows us to deepen the focus on human agency and recognize "the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> essentially transformational character of all human action, even in its most utterly routinized forms" (Giddens, 1984, p.117). Acknowledgments</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="387" page="18" column="2">420</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="388" page="18" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 1 1, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="389" page="18" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="390" page="19" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="392" page="19" column="1">Implications of the Practice Lens for Studying Technology</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx395">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_019.image_20.png" thmb="62lg.page_019.image_20-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="398" page="19" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VO1. 1 1, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="399" page="19" column="2">421</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="400" page="19" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="401" page="20" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="402" page="20" column="1">Table 2</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="403" page="20" column="1">Types of Enactment-Conditions, Actions, and Consequences</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx404">
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> Interestin</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="20">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Type of</td>
                  <td class="table"> using the</td>
                  <td class="table"> Interpretive</td>
                  <td class="table"> Technological</td>
                  <td class="table"> Institutional</td>
                  <td class="table"> Technology-in-</td>
                  <td class="table"> Processual</td>
                  <td class="table"> Technological</td>
                  <td class="table"> Structural</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Enactment</td>
                  <td class="table"> Technology</td>
                  <td class="table"> Conditions</td>
                  <td class="table"> Conditions</td>
                  <td class="table"> Conditions</td>
                  <td class="table"> Practice</td>
                  <td class="table"> Consequences</td>
                  <td class="table"> Consequences</td>
                  <td class="table"> Consequences</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Inertia</td>
                  <td class="table"> Low</td>
                  <td class="table"> Limited</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Hierarchical</td>
                  <td class="table"> Limited-Use</td>
                  <td class="table"> *None</td>
                  <td class="table"> *None</td>
                  <td class="table"> Reinforce and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Individualistic</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> preserve</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table"> computer *Customizable groupware tool</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Competitive</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Application</td>
                  <td class="table"> VeryHigh</td>
                  <td class="table"> Extensive</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Nonhierarchical</td>
                  <td class="table"> Collaboration</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Increased</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table"> Reinforce and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Collaborative</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> effectiveness in</td>
                  <td class="table"> the tool</td>
                  <td class="table"> enhance</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table"> computer</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Participative</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> development</td>
                  <td class="table"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Customizable</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Improved</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the data</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> groupware</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> collaboration</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Moderate</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Moderate</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Hierarchical</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Individual-</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Increased</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Reinforce and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Individualistic</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Productivity</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> efficiencyin</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the data</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> enhance</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> computer</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Competitive</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> communication</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Customizable</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> groupware</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> High</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Detailed</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Communal</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Collective-</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> -Increased</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Adaptations to</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Reinforce and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Cooperative</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Problem-</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> effectiveness in</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> enhance</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> computer</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Solving</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> problemsolving</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Customizable</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Increased</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the data</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> groupware</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> cooperation</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> VeryHigh</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Competent</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Team-focused</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Process-</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Increased</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Adjustments</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Reinforce and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Cooperative</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Support</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> effectiveness in</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> in the tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> enhance</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> computer</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Learning-oriented</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> customer</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Customizable</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> service</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the data</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> groupware</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> * Increased</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> efficiencyin</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Calltracking</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> communication</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Change</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> High</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Competent</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Networked</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Team-focused</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Improvisation</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Redefined work</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Adaptations to</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Transform</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> technical</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> personal</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Cooperative</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> distribution</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> status quo</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> knowledge</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> computer</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Learning-oriented</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Shift in type of</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Changesto</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Customizable</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> collaboration</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> the data</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> groupware</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Changein ways</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> of learning</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> *Calltracking</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> tool</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="405" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Interestin Type of using the Interpretive Technological Institutional Technology-in- Processual Technological Structural Enactment Technology Conditions Conditions Conditions Practice Consequences Consequences Consequences</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="406" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Inertia Low</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="407" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Application VeryHigh</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="408" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Moderate</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="409" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">High</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="410" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">VeryHigh</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="411" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Change High</region>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="412" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Limited *Networked *Hierarchical Limited-Use *None *None Reinforce and technical personal *Individualistic preserve knowledge computer *Competitive status quo *Customizable groupware tool Extensive *Networked *Nonhierarchical Collaboration *Increased *Changesto Reinforce and technical personal *Collaborative effectiveness in the tool enhance knowledge computer *Participative development *Changesto status quo *Customizable *Improved the data groupware collaboration tool Moderate *Networked *Hierarchical Individual- *Increased *Changesto Reinforce and technical personal *Individualistic Productivity efficiencyin the data enhance knowledge computer Competitive communication status quo *Customizable groupware tool Detailed *Networked *Communal Collective- -Increased *Adaptations to Reinforce and technical personal *Cooperative Problem- effectiveness in the tool enhance knowledge computer Solving problemsolving *Changesto status quo *Customizable *Increased the data groupware cooperation tool Competent *Networked *Team-focused Process- *Increased *Adjustments Reinforce and technical personal *Cooperative Support effectiveness in in the tool enhance knowledge computer *Learning-oriented customer *Changesto status quo *Customizable service the data groupware * Increased tool efficiencyin *Calltracking communication tool Competent *Networked *Team-focused Improvisation *Redefined work *Adaptations to Transform technical personal *Cooperative distribution the tool status quo knowledge computer *Learning-oriented *Shift in type of *Changesto *Customizable collaboration the data groupware *Changein ways tool of learning *Calltracking tool</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx414">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_020.image_21.png" thmb="62lg.page_020.image_21-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="417" page="20" column="2">422</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="418" page="20" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="419" page="20" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="420" page="21" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx424">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_021.image_22.png" thmb="62lg.page_021.image_22-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="426" page="21" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="427" page="21" column="2">423</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="428" page="21" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="429" page="22" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx432">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_022.image_23.png" thmb="62lg.page_022.image_23-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="435" page="22" column="2">424</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="436" page="22" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="437" page="22" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="438" page="23" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx440">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_023.image_24.png" thmb="62lg.page_023.image_24-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="442" page="23" column="2">8j</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="449" confidence="possible" page="23" column="2">I would like to thank the Senior Editor and three anonymous reviewers for their valuable guidance during the revision process. I am also grate- ful for the helpful comments I received on earlier versions of this manu- script from Steve Barley, Suzi Iacono, and JoAnne Yates. This work was supported by the Centers for Coordination Science and Information Systems Research at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Endnotes 'A number of extensive discussions of this technology literature are available, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="443" class="deo:Reference">Kling (1980)</xref>, Barley (1988), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="444" class="deo:Reference">Powell (1987)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="445" class="deo:Reference">Scott (1990)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="446" class="deo:Reference">Scarbrough and Corbett (1992)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="447" class="deo:Reference">Marx and Smith (1994)</xref>. 2The notion of enactment used here is related to but broader than that given currency by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77" id="448" class="deo:Reference">Weick (1979)</xref>. It is intended here in the conventional sense of "to constitute, actuate, perform" (Oxford English Dictionary) or "to represent in or translate into action" (Merriam-WebsterDictio- nary). 31 use the term artifact here in the sense of "anything made by human art and workmanship" (Oxford English Dictionary) or "a product of artificial character due usually to human agency" (Merriam-Webster Dictionary). 4As Grint and Woolgar (1995, p.289) remind us "[Technology] exists only in and through our descriptions and practices, and hence it is never available in a raw, untainted state." Thus, even the description and observation of "technologies" and their "properties," including their designation as artifacts, is a kind of use of that technology. These re- flexive complications notwithstanding, I believe that the analytic distinction between technologies as artifacts and the use of such artifacts is an especially useful one in both empirical research and everyday usage. 5In what follows, I will conform to common usage and use the term "technology" to refer to "technological artifact." 6Jt is interesting to note that what is actually enacted here as tax rules is not the tax code as legislated, but the tax code as encoded in the software, which reflects developers' understanding of the tax legislation and their ability to translate it into executable software code. 7One of the anonymous reviewers observed that a gun is a gun even if no one pulls the trigger. Yes and no. While it is the case that most of us can recognize a particularobject as a gun through its inscribed shape, physical properties, and functions, such recognition is culturally- specific. No such recognition would be forthcoming from the members of a remote tribe in the Kalahari Desert who have never encountered the object we refer to as a "gun." Furthermore,if our knowledge of a gun comes primarily from its use, then we cannot assume that a gun "is a gun" without knowing how that object is being used. While guns are designed and built for a particular purpose, and their possession has important implications for social policy, gun possession is not sufficient grounds for presuming that a gun will be used in a particular way. People can and do choose not to pull the trigger, and that makes all the difference. wish to thank one of the anonymous reviewers for highlighting the importance of emotional connections in people's use of technologies.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="450" page="23" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="451" page="23" column="2">425</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="452" page="23" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="453" page="24" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="455" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">9See Orlikowski (1993, 1996) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="454" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski and Gash (1994)</xref> for more details of the research studies which generated these examples. l?My research study had been "officially sanctioned" and participants had been told to charge the time they spent with me to a professional activities code. Yet, many confided they would "swallow the time" so as to avoid any dreaded "below the line" hours, even apparently legitimate ones.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="456" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="457" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Akrich, M. 1992. The de-scription of technical artifacts. W. E. Bijker, J. Law, eds. Shaping Technology/Building Society: Studies in So- ciotecYnical Change. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA. 205-224.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="458" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Barley, S. R. 1986. Technology as an occasion for structuring: Evi- dence from observation of CT scanners and the social order of radiology departments.Admin. Sci. Quart. 31 78-108. . 1988. Technology, power, and the social organization of work. Res. Soc. Organ. 6 33-80. . 1990. The alignment of technology and structure through roles and networks. Admin. Sci. Quart. 35 61-103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="459" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Barrett, F. J. 1998. Creativity and improvisation in jazz and organizations: Implications for organizational learning. Organ. Sci. 9(5) 605-622.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="460" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Bazerman, C. 1994. Systems of genres and the enactment of social intentions. A. Freedman, P. Medway, eds. Genre and the New Rhetoric. Taylor &amp; Francis Ltd., London, U.K. 79-101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="461" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Berners-Lee, T. 1996. Private communication (May 17).</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="462" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Bijker, W. E. 1987. The social construction of Bakelite: Toward a theory of invention. W. E. Bijker, T. P. Hughes, T. Pinch, eds. The Social Construction of Technological Systems. MIT Press, Cambridge MA. 159-187. . 1995. Of Bicycles, Bakelites, and Bulbs: Toward a Theory of Sociotechnical Change. MIT Press, Cambridge MA. , T. P. Hughes, T. Pinch, eds. 1987. The Social Construction of Technological Systems. MIT Press, Cambridge MA. , J. Law, eds. 1992. Shaping Technology/Building Society: Studies in Sociotechnical Change. MIT Press, Cambridge MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="463" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Bourdieu, P. 1977. Outline of a Theory of Practice. Cambridge University Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="464" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Braverman, H. 1974. Labor and Monopoly Capital: The Degradation of Work in the Twentieth Century, Monthly Review Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="465" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Brown, J. S., P. Duguid. 1991. Organizational learning and communities of practice: Toward a unified view of working, learning and innovation. Organ. Sci. 2 40-57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="466" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Brown, S., K. M. Eisenhardt. 1997. The art of continuous change: Link- ing complexity theory and time-paced evolution in relentlessly shifting organizations. Admin. Sci. Quart. 42 1-34.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="467" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Brynjolfsson, E. 1993. The productivity paradox of information technology: Review and assessment. Comm. ACM 36(12) 66-77.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="468" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Buchanan, D. A., D. Boddy. 1983. Organizations in the ComputerAge: Technological Imperatives and Strategic Choice. Gower, Hants, U.K.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="469" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Bullen, C. V., J. L. Bennett. 1990. Groupware in practice: An interpretation of work experience. Proceedings of the Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work ACM/SIGCHI, Los An- geles, CA, 291-302.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="470" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Burkhardt,M. E., D. J. Brass. 1990. Changing patterns or patterns of</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="472" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">change: The effects of a change in technology on social network power and structure.Admin. Sci. Quart. 35 104-127. Button, G., ed. 1993. Technology in Working Order: Studies in Work, Interaction, and Technology. Routledge, London, U.K.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="473" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Carter, N. M. 1984. Computerization as a predominate technology: Its influence on the structureof newspaper organizations. Acad. Management J. 27 247-270.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="474" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Cassell, P., ed. 1993. The Giddens Reader. Stanford University Press, Stanford, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="475" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Child, J. 1972. Organizational structure,environment and performance: The role of strategic choice. Sociology 6 1-22.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="476" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Chalstrom, B. 1993. Enterprise Computing. InfoWorld (November 1) p. 68.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="477" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Ciborra, C. U. 1993. Teams, Markets, and Systems: Business Innovation and Information Technology. Cambridge University Press, New York. . 1996. Improvisation and information technology in organizations. Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Information Systems. Cleveland, OH. 369-380. , G. F. Lanzara. 1991. Designing networks in action: Formative contexts and post-modem systems development. R. Clarke, J. Cameron, eds. Managing Information Technology's Organisa- tional Impact. Elsevier Science Publishers, Amsterdam, Holland. 265-279.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="478" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Clement, A. 1993. Looking for the designers: Transforming the 'in- visible' infrastructureof computerized office work. AI &amp; Society 7 323-344.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="479" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Cook, S. D. N., J. S. Brown. 1999. Bridging epistemologies: The gen- erative dance between organizational knowledge and organizational knowing. Organ. Sci. 10(4) 381-400.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="480" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Daft, R. L., R. H. Lengel. 1986. Organizational information require- ments, media richness and structuraldesign. Management Sci. 32 554-571.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="481" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Davis, L. E., J. C. Taylor. 1986. Technology, organization and job structure. R. Dubin, ed. Handbook of Work, Organization, and Society. Rand McNally, Chicago, IL, 379-419.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="482" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">DeJean, D., S. B. DeJean. 1991. Lotus Notes at Work. Lotus Books, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="483" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">DeSanctis, G., M. S. Poole. 1994. Capturing the complexity in ad- vanced technology use: Adaptive structurationtheory. Organ. Sci. 5(2) 121-147.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="484" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Edwards, R. 1979. Contested Terrain: The Transformation of the Workplace in the Twentieth Century. Basic Books, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="485" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Galbraith, J. R. 1977. Organization Design. Addision-Wesley, Reading, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="486" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Gasser, L. 1986. The integration of computing and routine work. ACM Trans. Office Inform. Systems. 4(3) 205-225.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="487" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Giddens, A. 1979. Central Problems in Social Theory: Action, Structure, and Contradiction in Social Analysis. University of California Press, Berkeley, CA. . 1981. Agency, institution, and time-space analysis. K. Knorr- Cetina, A. V. Cicourel, eds. Advances in Social Theory and Meth- odology. Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, Boston, MA. 161-174. . 1984. The Constitution of Society: Outline of the Theory of Structure. University of California Press, Berkeley, CA. . 1989. A reply to my critics. D. Held, J. B. Thompson, eds. Social</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="492" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Theory of Modern Societies: Anthony Giddens and his Critics. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K. 249-301. . 1991. Modernity and Self-Identity. Stanford University Press, Stanford, CA. . 1993. New Rules of Sociological Method, 2nd ed. Stanford Uni-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="493" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">versity Press, Stanford CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="494" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Greif, I., ed. 1988. Computer Supported Cooperative Work. Morgan Kaufman, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="495" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Grint, K., S. Woolgar. 1992. Computers, guns, and roses: What's social about being shot? Sci., Tech. Human Values 17(3) 366-380. . 1995. On some failures of nerve in constructivist and femi- nist analyses of technology. Sci., Tech., Human Values 20(3) 286- 310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="496" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Grudin, J. 1989. Why groupware applications fail: Problems in design and evaluation. Office: Tech. and People 4(3) 245-264.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="497" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Hatch, M. J. 1998. Jazz as a metaphor for organizing in the 21st cen- tury," Organ. Sci. 9(5) 556-568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="498" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Hedberg, B., G. Dahlgrenm, J. Hansson, N-G. Olve. 1997. Virtual Organizations and Beyond. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="499" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Hutchins, E. 1991. Organizing work by adaptation. Organ. Sci. 2(1) 14-39. . 1995. Cognition in the Wild. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="500" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Iacono, S., R. Kling. (in press) Computerization movements: The rise of the internet and distant forms of work. J. Yates, J. Van Maanen, eds. IT and Organizational Transformation: History, Rhetoric, and Practice. Sage Publications, Newbury Park, CA. Kent, T. 1993. Paralogic Rhetoric: A Theory of Communicative Interaction. Associated University Presses, Cranbury,NJ.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="501" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Kling, R. 1980. Social analyses of computing: Theoretical perspectives in recent empirical research. Computing Surveys 12(1) 61-110. . 1991. Computerization and Social Transformations. Sci., Tech. and Human Values 16 342-367. . 1992. Audiences, narratives, and human values in social studies of technology. Sci., Tech. and Human Values 17(3) 349-365.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="502" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Kraut, R., S. Koch, S. Dumais. 1988. Computerization, productivity, and quality of employment. Comm. ACM 32(2) 220-238.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="503" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Lant, T. 1999. A situated learning perspective on the emergence of knowledge and identity in cognitive communities. Advances in Management Cognition and Organizational Information Pro- cessing 6 JAI Press, Greenwich, CT, 171-194.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="504" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Latour, B. 1992. Where are the missing masses? The sociology of a few mundane artifacts. W. E. Bijker, J. Law, eds. Shaping Technology/Building Society: Studies in Sociotechnical Change. MIT Press, Cambridge MA. 225-258.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="505" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Lave, J. 1988. Cognition in Practice. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="506" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Mackay, W. E. 1988. Diversity in the use of electronic mail. ACM Trans. on Office Inform. Systems 6(4) 380-397.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="507" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">MacKenzie, D., J. Wajcman, eds. 1985. The Social Shaping of Technology. Open University Press, Milton Keynes, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="508" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Malone, T. W., K. Y. Lai, C. Fry. 1992. Experiments with OVAL: A radically tailorable tool for cooperative work. Proceedings of the Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work. ACM/ SIGCHI &amp; SIGOIS, Toronto, Canada. 289-297. , J. Yates, R. Benjamin. 1987. Electronic markets and electronic hierarchies. Comm. ACM 30 484-497.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="510" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Markus, M. L. 1994. Electronic mail as the medium of managerial choice. Organ. Sci. 5(4) 502-527.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="511" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Marx, L., M. R. Smith, eds. 1994. Does Technology Drive History? MIT Press, Cambridge, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="512" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Noble, D. 1984. Forces of Production: A Social History of Industrial Automation. Knopf, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="513" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Norman, D. A. 1993. Things that Make Us Smart: Defending Human Attributes in the Age of the Machine. Addison-Wesley Publishing, Reading, MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="514" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Orlikowski, W. J. 1992. The duality of technology: Rethinking the concept of technology in organizations. Organ. Sci. 3(3) 398-427. . 1993. Learning from NOTES: Organizational issues in groupware implementation. The Inform. Soc. J. 9 237-250. . 1996. Improvising organizational transformation over time: A situated change perspective. Inform. Systems Res. 7(1) 63-92. , D. C. Gash. 1994. Technological frames: Making sense of information technology in organizations. ACM Trans. Inform. Systems 2(2) 174-207. , D. Robey. 1991. Information technology and the structuring of organizations. Inform. Systems Res. 2(2) 143-169. , J. Yates, K. Okamura, M. Fujimoto. 1995. Shaping electronic communication: The metastructuring of technology in use. Organ. Sci. 6(4) 423-444.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="515" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Orr, J. 1996. Talking about Machines: An Ethnography of a Modern Job. Cornell University Press, Ithaca, NY.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="516" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Perrolle, J. A. 1986. Intellectual assembly lines: The rationalization of managerial, professional, and technical work. Comput. and Soc. Sci. 2 111-121.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="517" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Perrow, C. 1983. The organizational context of human factors engi- neering. Admin. Sci. Quart. 28 521-541.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="518" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Pinch, T. J., W. E. Bijker. 1984. The social construction of facts and artefacts: Or how the sociology of science and the sociology of technology might benefit each other. Soc. Stud. Sci. 14 399-441.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="519" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Poole, M. S., G. DeSanctis. 1990. Understanding the use of group decision support systems: The theory of adaptive structuration.J. Fulk, C. W. Steinfield, eds. Organizations and Communication Technology. Sage, Newbury Park, CA. 173-193. 1992. Microlevel structuration in computer-supported group decision making. Human Comm. Res. 19(1) 5-49. , M. Jackson, L. Kirsch, G. DeSanctis. 1998. Alignment of system and structure in the implementation of group decision support systems. 1998 Academy of Management Proceedings San Diego, CA. C1-C7.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="520" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Powell, W. 1987. Explaining technological change. Amer. J. Soc. 93 185-197.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="521" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Prasad, P. 1993. Symbolic processes in the implementation of technological change: A symbolic interactionist study of work computerization. Acad. of Management J. 36 1400-1429.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="522" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Rice, R. E., E. M. Rogers. 1980. Reinvention in the innovation process. Knowledge 1(4) 499-514. , C. Aydin. 1991. Attitudes toward new organizational technology: Network proximity as a mechanism for social information processing. Admin. Sci. Quart. 36 219-244.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="523" confidence="possible" page="25" column="2">Roberts, K. H., M. Grabowski. 1995. Organizations, technology, and structuring. S. R. Clegg, C. Hardy, W. R. Nord, eds. Handbook of Organization Studies. Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA. 409-423.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="528" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Saetnan, A. R. 1991. Rigid technologies and technologial flexibility: The anatomy of a failed hospital innovation. Sci., Tech., Human Values. 16(4) 419-447.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="529" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Schryer, C. F. 1993. Records as Genres. Written Comm. 10 200-234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="530" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Scarbrough, H., J. M. Corbett. 1992. Technology and Organization: Power, Meaning, and Design. Routledge, London, U.K.</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="531" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Scott, W. R. 1990. Technology and structure:An organizational level perspective. P. S. Goodman, L. S. Sproull, Associates. Technology and Organizations. Jossey-Bass, San Francisco, CA. 109- 143.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="532" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Sewell, W. H. Jr. 1992. A theory of structure: Duality, agency, and transf6rmation.Amer. J. Soc. 98(1) 1-29.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="533" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Shaiken, H. 1985. Work Transformed: Automation and Labor in the Computer Age. Holt, Rinehart and Winston, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="534" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Sproull, L. S., P. S. Goodman. 1990. Technology and organizations: Integration and opportunities. P. S. Goodman, L. S. Sproull, and Associates, eds. Technology and Organizations. Jossey-Bass, San Francisco. 254-265.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="535" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Suchman, L. A. 1987. Plans and Situated Actions: The Problem of Human Machine Communication. University of Cambridge Press, Cambridge, U.K. . 1996. Supporting articulation work. R. Kling, ed. Computerization and Controversy 2nd ed. Academic Press, San Diego, CA. 407-423.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="536" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Taylor, C. 1993. To follow a rule. . . C. Calhoun, E. LiPuma, M. Postone, eds. Bourdieu: Critical Perspectives. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, IL. 45-60.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="537" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Tenkasi, R. V., R. J. Boland. 1993. Locating meaning making in organizational learning: The narrative basis of cognition. Res. in Organ. Change and Development 7 77-103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="538" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Thomas, R. J. 1994. What Machines Can't Do: Politics and Technology in the Industrial Enterprise. University of California Press, Berkeley, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="539" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Tushman, M. L., P. C. Anderson, C. O'Reilly. 1997. Technology cy- cles, innovation streams, and ambidextrous organizations: Organizational renewal through innovation streams and strategic change. M. L. Tushman, P. C. Anderson, eds. Managing Strategic Innovation and Change. Oxford University Press, New York. 3- 23.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="540" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Accepted by M. Scott Poole; received February 8, 1999. This paper has been with the author for one revision.</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="542" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Tyre, M. J., W. J. Orlikowski. 1994. Windows of opportunity: Tem- poral patterns of technological adaptation in organizations. Organ. Sci. 5(1) 98-118.</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="543" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">von Hippel, E. 1988. The Sources of Innovation. Oxford University Press, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R76" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="544" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Walsham, G. 1993. Interpreting Information Systems in Organizations. John Wiley, New York. , C-K. Han. 1991. Structuration theory and information systems research. J. Appl. Systems Anal. 17 77-85.</ref>
          <ref rid="R77" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="545" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Weick, K. 1979. The Social Psychology of Organizing. Addison- Wesley, Reading, MA. . 1990. Technology as equivoque. P. S. Goodman, L. S. Sproull, and Associates, eds.. Technology and Organizations. Jossey- Bass, San Francisco, CA. 1-44. . 1993. Organizational redesign as improvisation. G. P. Huber, W. H. Glick, eds. Organizational Change and Redesign. Oxford University Press, New York, 346-379. . 1995. Sensemaking in Organizations. Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, CA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R78" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="546" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Whittington, Richard. 1992. Putting Giddens into action: Social systems and managerial agency. J. Management Stud. 29(6) 693- 712.</ref>
          <ref rid="R79" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="547" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Winner, L. 1986. The Whale and the Reactor: A Search for Limits in an Age of High Technology. University of Chicago Press, Chicago, IL.</ref>
          <ref rid="R80" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="548" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Woodward, J. 1965. Industrial Organization: Theory and Practice. Oxford University Press, London, U.K.</ref>
          <ref rid="R81" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="549" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Woolgar, S. 1991. The turn to technology in social studies of science. Sci., Tech., &amp; Human Values 16(1) 20-50. . 1996. Technologies as cultural artefacts. W. Dutton, ed. Information and Communication Technologies: Visions and Realities. Oxford University Press, Oxford, U.K. 87-102. , K. Grint. 1991. Computers and the transformationof social analysis. Sci., Tech., &amp; Human Values 16(3) 368-378.</ref>
          <ref rid="R82" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="550" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Yates, J., W. J. Orlikowski, K. Okamura. 1999. Explicit and implicit structuring of genres: Electronic communication in a Japanese R&amp;D organization. Organ. Sci. 10(1) 83-103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R83" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="551" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">Zuboff, S. 1988. In the Age of the Smart Machine. Basic Books, New York.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx471">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_024.image_25.png" thmb="62lg.page_024.image_25-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="488" page="24" column="2">426</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="489" page="24" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="490" page="24" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="491" page="25" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx509">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_025.image_26.png" thmb="62lg.page_025.image_26-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="524" page="25" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 11, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="525" page="25" column="2">427</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="526" page="25" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="527" page="26" column="1">ORLIKOWSKI Using Technology and Constituting Structures</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx541">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lg.page_026.image_27.png" thmb="62lg.page_026.image_27-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="552" page="26" column="2">428</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="553" page="26" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VO1. 1 1, No. 4, July-August 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="554" page="26" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Thu, 22 Aug 2013 09:59:19 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
