<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>86baef6a8ba5f623371a54527c7fa862b83ca365e3c6aafacf5c73550bc7ace5</job>
    <base_name>62bl</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1511524</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62bl.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">.</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="4">Declaration by Design: Rhetoric, Argument, and Demonstration in Design Practice Author(s): Richard Buchanan Source: Design Issues, Vol. 2, No. 1 (Spring, 1985), pp. 4-22 Published by: The MIT Press Stable URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1511524" id="3">http://www.jstor.org/stable/1511524</ext-link> Accessed: 22/01/2014 08:01</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="5">Your use of the JSTOR</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="6">at .</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="8">archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="7">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="9">upon a wide range of facilitate new forms</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="10">. JSTOR is a not-for-profit content in a trusted digital of scholarship. For more</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="12">service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="11">support@jstor.org</email>.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="13">.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="14">The MIT Press is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Design Issues.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx15">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62bl.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="16">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="18">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed</name>
          <aff id="19">148</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="20">Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="21">Conditions</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="22">Richard Buchanan</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">Declaration by Design: Rhetoric, Argument, and Demonstration in Design Practice</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="24">ambiguous</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="25">communication, grammatical</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="26">significant</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" page="2" column="1">Introduction If one ideacouldbe foundcentral in designstudies,it most likely would be communication.1 Directly or indirectly, this ideaandits relatedthemeshave animated more discussionof designtheory and practicethan any other. I refernot only to graphicdesign, wherecommunication is an obviousgoal andwherethe concepts of classical rhetoric arenow beingapplied with promising results,2 but alsoto the larger field of design,whichrangesfromindustrial and productdesign to architecture and urbanplanningand for which there is no unifyingtheory of rhetoric.Althoughnot so obviousat firstglance,the themesof communication and rhetoric in this largerfield exertstronginfluenceon our understanding of all objects made for human use. Consider, for example, the</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="28" page="2" column="1">Communica-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="29" page="2" column="1">"Visual/VerbalRhetoric,"</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="30" page="2" column="1">Krampen,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="31" page="2" column="1">subsequently</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="32" page="2" column="1">1)"Communication" is an word often used casuallyand without regard to its manyusefulandsometimes conflicting meanings. This essay,is con- cernedwith communication as rhetoric, the inventiveandpersuasive relation of speakers and audiences as they are broughttogetherin speechesor other objects of communication. This is in sharpcontrast,for example,to recent semiotic theories of which are essentially theories concerned with a systemof nat- uralor conventional signs andthemean- ingsstoredin them.It is alsoin contrast to Marxistor other dialectical theories thatregard communication as only in relationto some economicor spiritual truth. 2) Gui Bonsiepe,"Persuasive tion: Towardsa Visual Rhetoric,"in Theo Crosby, ed., Uppercase 5, (Lon- don:Whitefriars Press, Ltd., 1963).Gui Bonsiepe, Ulm 14/15/16(1965).Thesearevaluable early explorationsof the theme, but more stronglyinfluencedby semiotics thanrhetoric. See alsoMartin "Signsand Symbolsin GraphicCom- munication," Design Quarterly 62 (1968): 3-31. An entire issue of Ico- graphic,edited by Victor Margolin,is devotedto the theme"Persuasive Communication." See Icographic 11/4 (Feb- ruary1984).SeealsoHannoH. J. Ehses, "Representing Macbeth: A CaseStudy in Visual Rhetoric," Design Issues I/1 (Spring 1984): 53-63.Thisis a usefulcase studyof invention in graphic communi- cation,although it is limited to figures of speech and the grammaticalviewpoint of semiotics. 3) Jonathan M. Designer and the Public (London: Pem- bridge Press, 1983). 4) Nikolaus Pevsner, Pioneers of the Mod- em Movement, from William Morris to Walter Gropius (London: Faber and Faber,1936).See,forexample, the chap- teron "TheEngineers of theNineteenth Century." This book was published as Pioneers of Modern Design.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="2" column="1">numerous historical, sociological, esthetic, and cultural studies of design in recent decades: they are not obviously rhetorical, yet when dealing with the influence of designers and the effects of design on an audience of consumers or society at large,3 move deeply into the domain of rhetoric. Similarly, these studies also involve a significant rhetorical component when they are concerned with the process of conceiving designs; the influence of a designer's personal attitudes, values, or design philosophy;4 or the way the social world of design organization, management, and corporate policy shapes a design.5 In addition, when studies of the esthetics of design treat form not only as a quality valuable in itself, but also as a means of pleasing, instructing, and passing information,6 or, indeed, as a means of shaping the appearanceof objects for whatever intended effect,7 these studies are rhetorical also because they treat design as a mediating agency of influence between designers and their intended audience. Ironically, a unifying theory of rhetoric remains surprisingly unexplored and, at the same time, most needed in the larger field of design, where communication is at least as significant as in graphic design. It is needed, first, because of the growing importance of technology in the twentieth century and the increasing distance between technologists and designers.8 There is a general attitude that technology is only an applied science, rather than a part of design art, and this approachhas led many to abandon hope</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="34" page="2" column="1">4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx35">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62bl.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="36" page="2" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="37" page="3" column="1">5) JohnF. Pile,Design:Purpose, Form and Meaning (New York:W.W.Nortonand Company,1979).JohnHeskett,Indus- trialDesign(London: Thames andHud- son, 1980). 6) Pile,Design.Seechapter 5, "Communi- cationthrough Form." 7) DavidPye, TheNatureandAesthetics of Design (New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold,1978). Pye definesdesignas the artthat "chooses that the thingswe useshalllook astheydo..." (p. 11).This is especially interesting when seenin the contextof the long tradition of rhetoric as an artof appearances. Inevitably, Pye has committedhimselfto settingforth rhetoricalcriteriafor good or proper appearance, involving taste, style, beauty,utility,andso forth. 8) The education of designers and technologiststoday often deepensthe division. More effort is needed to develop an integratedphilosophy of designeducation suited to the complex roleof designin the modern world. See, for example,TomasMaldonado, "Design Education and SocialResponsibil- ity,"in GyorgyKepes,ed., Education of Vision (New York: George Braziller, 1965). See also Kenneth Frampton, "Apropos Ulm: Curriculum and Critical Theory,"Oppositions 3 (May1974). 9) Pile,Design,2.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="38" page="3" column="1">10) Such criticism is, of course, better developed in architecture, but too often lacking in otherareas of design practice.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="39" page="3" column="1">identification</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="40" page="3" column="1">11)Grammatical theories oftenregard communication as the transfer of a stateof mindfromthespeaker to theaudience a passingof information and emotion. However, rhetoricaltheories tend to regard communication as aninvention of arguments(logical, ethical, or emo- tional)thatinducebeliefor in an audience. The difference may seem slight, but the consequencesof each approach are significantly different.</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="41" page="3" column="1">thattechnologycanbe seriouslyinfluenced and guidedby human valuesanda discernment of beneficial ends in the humancommu- nity.A suitable theory of rhetoric in designwouldbe one in which technology is viewed fundamentally as a rhetoricalproblem, integrated withinthe perspective of a broader design art,however radical that mayseemto technologists. The theorywould suggest productive ways in whichcloserconnections betweentechnology anddesignartcouldbe established. As important as this is, however,thereis a secondreasonwhy a theoryof rhetoric in designis neededatthistime.Theclassiccon- cepts of designhavebeenabandoned recently by manydesigners in favorof unruly,antagonistic, bizarre, or ofteninexplicable con- ceptsthatchallenge and confusethe general public, as well as the field of design. Examples might include"punk" fashions,Mem- phis furniture, or the architectural designs of Arquitectonica in Miami.In almosteveryareaof design,we encounter objects that have a strangeand startlingunfamiliarity that may provoke or evenrepelus. Althoughsuchreactions may suggestthatthepublic lackscriticalawareness about the natureof design,they alsoindi- catea newweakness in designcommunication. John Pilecontends that many people will accept any product simply becauseit is offeredas the fruitof technological advance,whetheror not it is well designed.9 Nevertheless, there arealsomanywho careabout theproducts that surround them andwho arethoughtful about the influenceand the power of objectsto enrichor impoverishthe quality of their lives. For these people, the acceptedforms of designcommunication may seemto be breaking down or designers may seem to have little interestin seriouslycommunicating with the public. A suitabletheory would be one in which the puzzlingdiversityof designcommunication as we encounter it in everydayproducts is mademore intelligible,providingthe basis for betterpubliccriticism and evaluation of design.10 Theneedfor a broadtheoryof rhetoric in designwaslessurgent whentechnologyseemedto be underrational control anddesign- ers worked within a generallyacceptedview of the way design shouldfunctionin a well-ordered society. Butnow, astechnology becomesincreasingly specialized and isolated from designpractice andas designers have so manyconflicting and confusingopinions abouttheirown practice,the need has specialurgency.To bring these problemstogetherin a single, comprehensive theory is a difficultchallenge, but one thatexplains better thananyotherthe riseof designstudiesas a seriousfieldof inquiry. Design as rhetoric Communication is usuallyconsidered to be the way a speaker discovers arguments and presentsthem in suitablewords and ges- turesto persuade an audience.11 The goalis to inducein the audi- ence.somebeliefaboutthe past (as in legalrhetoric),the present (as in ceremonialrhetoric),or the future (as in deliberative or</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="42" page="3" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="43" page="3" column="1">5</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx44">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62bl.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="45" page="3" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="46" page="4" column="1">12) Rhetoric is both the practice of persuasive communication and a formalartof studyingsuch communication, often in its mostsignificant instances.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="47" page="4" column="1">Bobbs-Merrill fundamen-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="48" page="4" column="1">Architectonic</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="49" page="4" column="1">13) Of course, there have been many sociological and anthropological studies of theinfluence and effects of technology on socialorganization and culture,but none, to the author'sknowledge,has specificallytreatedthis subject as an example of persuasion. 14) Francis Bacon, TheNew Organon and RelatedWritings, ed. FultonH. Ander- son (Indianapolis: The Company,Inc., 1960).This tal work is the first to significantly use rhetoric to studythe relation of science andtechnology. The goalof his newsci- ence,Baconsays,is not simplyto under- standnature but "tocommand nature in action."The focus of the work, however,is on the discovery of principles in nature, and subsequent studies haveseen only this aspect,reducing technology to a handmaiden of science. No one has considered the implications of Bacon's workfora rhetoric of technology. However, valuable insights may be foundin Richard McKeon, "The Usesof Rhetoric in a Technological Age: Productive Arts," in LloydF. Bitzerand Edwin Black, eds., The Prospects of Rhetoric(EnglewoodCliffs, New Jer- sey: Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1971), 44-63. 15) Aristotle,The "Art" of Rhetoric, trans. byJohnHenryFreese (Cambridge: Har- vardUniversity Press, 1967),3.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="50" page="4" column="1">Calzolari,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="51" page="4" column="1">16) Victor Margolin, "Consumersand Users: Two Publics for Design," in ChristinaRitchie and Loris eds., Phoenix: New Attitudes to Design (Toronto: Phoenix, 1984), 48-55.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="4" column="1">political rhetoric). The speaker seeks to provide the audience with the reasons for adopting a new attitude or taking a new course of action. In this sense, rhetoric is an art of shaping society, changing the course of individuals and communities, and setting patterns for new action.12 However, with the rise of technology in the twentieth century, the remarkablepower of man-made objects to accomplish something very similar has been discovered. By presenting an audience of potential users with a new product whether as simple as a plow or a new form of hybrid seed corn, or as complex as an electric light bulb or a computer - designers have directly influenced the actions of individuals and communities, changed attitudes and values, and shaped society in surprisingly fundamental ways. This is an avenue of persuasion not previously recognized,13 a mode of communication that has long existed but that has never been entirely understood or treated from a perspective of human control such as rhetoric provides for communication in language.14 We all have a share in the natural impulse to make things for practical use, to make objects that will use nature to work for our purposes, but Aristotle's remarks on the rise of rhetoric as an art of persuasion have relevance to the art of design.15 He points out that all humans have a share in rhetoric because all attempt to persuade one another of various ideas and beliefs. Yet, some do this randomly and by chance, whereas others do it out of familiarity and the kind of habit that arisesfrom experience. But it is precisely because persuasion can be achieved in both ways, that it is possible to find the reasons why some efforts are successful and others are not, and, thus, the art behind successful persuasion can be discovered. A similar pattern may be suggested for design. Some have the familiarity and habit of craftspeople, specialized in working with different materialsor meeting specific needs; others have the experience of scientific understanding that has enabled them to identify opportunities for practical applications of their knowl- edge. But because both avenues of design are possible today, we have a better perspective from which to identify the elements of art common to all the variations of design practice and to recognize design as something distinct from the labor of manufacturing products, as well as from those subjects that areuseful and related, but not of the essence of, the art. The primary obstacle to such understanding is the belief that technology is essentially part of science, following all of the same necessities as nature and scientific reasoning. If this is true, technology cannot be part of design rhetoric, except as a pre- formed message to be decorated and passively transmitted. Design then becomes an esthetically interesting but minor art that is easily degraded into a marketing tool for consumer culture.16 However, if technology is in some fundamental sense concerned with the probable rather than the necessary - with the contigencies of practical use and action, rather than the certainties of scientific</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="53" page="4" column="1">6</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx54">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62bl.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="55" page="4" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="56" page="5" column="1">inter-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="57" page="5" column="1">change produced...."</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="58" page="5" column="1">227-238.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="59" page="5" column="1">17)GeorgeBugliarello and DeanB. Doner, eds., The History and Philosophyof Technology (Urbana andChicago: University of Illinois Press, 1979). This excellentbook is the resultof an national symposium held in Chicagoin 1973. To quote from the Editors'Pre- face, 'Engineering schools continueto traingeneration after generation of pos- siblythemostpowerful agents of that our planethas ever (p. vii). 18)Peter Caws, "Praxisand Techne,"' in Bugliarello and Doner, TheHistory and Philosophy of Technology, "Technology, after all, is not merelythe theoryof thepractical arts; it is tical arts themselves,regardedas an activityof reason- the logos in the techne, rather than the logos of the techne." (p. 227).</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="60" page="5" column="1">19)Aristotle, Rhetoric, 19.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="61" page="5" column="1">20) DavidDickson,ThePolitics of Alterna- tive Technology (New York: Universe Books, 1974).Thisis published in Great Britainas AlternativeTechnology and thePolitics of Technological Change. See, forexample, chapter 2, "TheIdeology of Industrialization. "</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="5" column="1">principle- then it becomesrhetorical in a startling fashion.7 It becomesanartof deliberation about the issuesof practical action, andits scientificaspectis, in a sense, only incidental, except as it formspartof an argument in favorof one or another solutionto a specificpractical problem.18 Technologistsdiscoverways to commandnaturein order to solve such problemsand then attemptto persuadeothers that these solutions are likely to be expedientand lead to beneficial results.Theirpersuasion comes througharguments presentedin thingsrather than words;they presentideasin a manipulation of the materials and processesof nature,not language.In addition, becausethereis seldoma singlesolutionto a problemin human affairsdictatedby the laws of nature,they do not provideneces- sary solutions. Solutionsare only probableand can always be changed or set in oppositionto others.In thissense,technologyis partof the broader art of design,an artof thoughtandcommuni- cationthatcaninducein othersa wide rangeof beliefsaboutprac- ticallife for the individual and for groups. This idea may be hardto accept, especiallyfor technologists who see their primaryaffiliation,perhapspartlyfor reasonsof social status, as science. But the bridgeof exchangethat exists betweenscienceand technologyis not much differentfrom the bridgethathasexistedbetweentraditional rhetoric andthe fieldof ethics and politics.19 Rhetoricians are expertin persuasion,not ethicalor politicalphilosophy,even thougheffectivepersuasion may drawheavilyfrom knowledgeof such subjects.Suchis the case for technologists.They are expertin a form of persuasive communication, not the natural sciences,despitethattheirman- ipulation of naturalmaterialsand processesmay draw heavily fromknowledgeof suchsubjects. Incidentally, technologistsmay also be scientists.The point, however,is not simply that technologyis distinctfrom science. Moreimportant, it is thattechnologyis fundamentally concerned with a formof persuasion and, aswith traditional rhetoric,speaks from no specialauthorityabout the good life. It providesonly resourcesthat are used to supporta varietyof arguments about practical living, reflecting different ideas andviewpointson social life. Technologists themselveshold such ideas and have pressed themon the humancommunity in manyways.20 Until theirwork is recognized as persuasive and partof thepractice of design,their ideaswill remainimplicitor naivelyunexamined. This aspectof the significance of design, being acknowledged only slowly, has directconsequences for the understanding of the environment of postmoderndesign communication. Design is.an art of thought directedto practical action throughthe persuasiveness of objects and, therefore,designinvolvesthe vividexpression of competing ideasaboutsociallife. This situationis made more intelligiblewhen viewed from a rhetoricalperspective.For decades,technologistshave tried to</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="63" page="5" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="64" page="5" column="1">7</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx65">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62bl.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66" page="5" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="67" page="6" column="1">managers combined</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="68" page="6" column="1">completion,</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="69" page="6" column="1">personal</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="70" page="6" column="1">mechanics</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="71" page="6" column="1">21) The Pullman community in Chicagois one example. Designed and builtin 1893 to be a complete,harmonious environ- mentfor 14,000workersand of the Pullman Company,it the latesttechnologyand a concernfor estheticquality,attracting visitors from aroundthe world who marveled at its advanceover then contemporary planning. Within months of however,workersprotestedthe rigidi- ties and mechanical regularities that the design promotedand was attackedfor forcing his valuesandideasaboutsociallife on the residents. He couldhardlyimagine that such ideas,derivedfrom the of building railroad carriages, were ques- tionablewhen appliedto everyday life. The workers' strike of 1894, caused by a variety of factors, was one of the most bitter and violent in American labor history. See note 40. 22) The impact of various Western technolo- gies on Third World cultures provides some of the most striking illustrations of this. More important for our purposes, however, such examples give glimpses of what moments of our own culturalhistory may have been like under the influence of technological change. 23) John A. Kouwenhoven, Halfa Truth Is Better Than None: Some Unsystematic Conjectures about Art, Disorder, and American Experience (Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1982). See "Design and Chaos: The American Dis- trust of Art," 231. 24) Dieter Rams, "Omit the Unimportant," Design Issues 1/1 (Spring 1984): 24-26. This is an excellent and economical statement of one design philosophy. (Note also how the rhetoric of Rams' statement parallels the rhetoric of the productsthat he and the Braundesign group produce.)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">persuade audiences of the expediency of theirinventionsanddis- coveries,producing objects thatoften seemto meethumanneeds andpromotea better,well-ordered life. Yet,thelifetheyhavepro- moted has frequentlyprovento be harmfuland discordant with humanvalues. The concernis not with the outrightfailuresof technologicalreasoning,but with those instancesin which the resulthasbeenan inhuman mechanical order21 or evena frustrat- ing disorderand social chaos.22The concern rests with those examples where designhas servedas a tool to increase the power of politicalandsocialideologiesandhas broughtsuffering rather thanbenefit,as with the weaponsof war. This is the postmodernenvironment,a period of disillusion- mentfollowingexceptional confidence in the brightfutureprom- ised by science and technology (as well as by variouspolitical philosophiesandideologies).It is based,in part, on the recognition by manythatwe havenot gleanedfrom design(in the sense that it involvestechnology)a well-ordered life, and this percep- tion hasled to a dreadful and sometimescreative fascination with the unstablerelationship betweenorderand disorder.23 Indeed, the natureof orderin practical life is a central issue in postmodern design.In the relation of orderanddisorder, designers inventively explore new possibilitiesfor practicallife, and this relationship providesa way of distinguishing design voices in their current situation. Many continue to pursue classic ideals of orderly design, still seeking an harmoniousintegrationof design and technologyin the purposiveactivityof everyday life, evenif their designs areconsciouslyfashionedto be new expressions of older ideals.24 Other designerslook for orderin new ways, and some even deliberately overturnconventional expectations of order,as if to challenge us to rethink the meaning of orderin ourlives. In all of thesecases,however,designis a debateamongopposingviews aboutsuchmatters as technology, practical life,theplaceof emotion andexpression in the livingenvironment, and a host of othercon- cernsthatmakeupthetexture of postmodern, postindustrial living.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="73" page="6" column="1">25) Margolin, "Consumers and Users: Two Publics for Design," 49. Margolin's characterization of users, in contrast to consumers, is more like the kind of audience discussed here. The user, he says, is more likely "to define the worthwhile life in terms of the actuation of values rather than the'ownership of goods." Of course, consumers are a kind of audience, too, and many designers conceive of their audiences as groups of consumers in a narrow sense.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Elementsof designargument To examine this situation more carefully, several themesshouldbe considered: one is the ideaof the designeras a speaker who fashions a world, howeversmallor large,andinvitesothersto sharein it. Anotheris the idea of an audienceof userswho may be per- suadedto adoptnew waysandmeansto achieve objectives in their lives.25Still anotheris the idea of practical life as the subjectof design communication, howevervariedthe conceptionsof this maybe andwhethertheseconceptions are heldconsciouslyor are tacit and unexamined in the designer'smind. Most important, however,is the idea of argument, which connectsall of the elements of design and becomes an active engagementbetween designeranduser or potentialuser.This articlesuggeststhat the designer,insteadof simplymakingan objector thing, is actually</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="6" column="1">8</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx76">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62bl.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="77" page="6" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" page="7" column="1">creating a persuasive argument that comes to life whenever a user considers or uses a product as a means to some end. Three elements of a design argument are applicable here; they involve interrelated qualities of technological reasoning, character, and emotion, all of which provide the substance and form of design communication. Designers draw on all three elements to some degree in every design argument, sometimes blending them with great subtlety in a product. Nevertheless, these elements may be analytically distinguished to reveal the different resources that are availablefor persuasion. The first element, technological reasoning, is the logos of design. It provides the backbone of a design argument, much as chains of formal or informal reasoning provide the core of communication and persuasion in language. In essence, the problem of technological reasoning in design is the way the designer manip- ulates materials and processes to solve practical problems of human activity. Products are persuasive in this mode when, in addressing real needs, they meet those needs in a reasonable, expe- dient way. Technological reasoning is based, in part, on an understanding of natural and scientific principles that serve as premises for the construction of objects for use. It is also based on premises drawn from human circumstances, that is, from the attitudes and values of potential users and the physical conditions of actual use. Both kinds cf premises are evident even in the simplest objects. For example, all spoons use the same mechanical premise, employing the principle of the lever as a way to transport contents held in a small bowl (figure 1). They share several obvious human premises, which explain why they are all of a size that fits the human hand, are made of inexpensive materials, and rely on the hand for power. But they also use a variety of human premises that are not so obvious, but directly affect the specific form in which <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> the mechanical premise is presented. For example, there is a premise regarding the attitude of potential users toward tradition: two of the spoons are highly traditional and conventional within their respective Oriental and American cultural contexts, two are rather unconventional. There are similar premises regardingthe value of decoration, the eleganceor plainnessof the social occasion of eating, and perhaps even subtle moral values that are associated with these aspects and that people are hardly aware of in objects so simple. Premises drawn from human circumstances are what make technological reasoning an element of rhetorical art for communication with specific audiences rather than a deductive science concerned only with universal principles. Such premises serve to distinguish not only different audiences and the kinds of design<marker type="block"/> groups, but they also characterize different approaches taken by designers themselves in the postmodern environment. Consider, for example, the Krups coffee mill and the Memphis bookcase, Ginza, by Masanori Umeda (figures 2 and 3). Both are functional in a broad sense of the term (although the usefulness ratio of materials used to space occupied in Umeda's bookcase seems to stretch the idea of function, perhaps intentionally). Yet in each case, the specific form of technological reasoning depends entirely on different human premises, premises held by designers and assumed to be persuasive with users. Indeed, design is an art of communication on two levels: it attempts to persuade audiences not only that a given design is useful, but also that the designer's premises or attitudes and values regardingpracticallife or the proper role of technology are important, as well. The proof is a demonstration in a product. The coffee mill reflects classic design values suited to new ways of contemporary living. It is gentle and unobtrusive, subordinating the display of mechanical reasoning and other qualities to a concern for use. The object is neutral ratherthan coercive and, hence, allows users to integrate it into a variety of life-styles. It demonstrates that technology can serve without dominating, leaving users free to use the product in a variety of settings of their own choice. In contrast, the Ginza bookcase reflects values of novelty, sur- prise, and emotion. Umeda's design playfully displays mechanical reasoning and virtually talks to us, commenting on itself with irony or satire- a robot holding books created by the unmechan- ical human mind? It intensifies the environment, not to dominate users, but perhaps to offer an example of vitality and spontaneity that encourages independence and self-expression, something important for many people in the postmodern environment. It demonstrates a lively mind controlling technology, not controlled<marker type="block"/> These are two important directions in postmodern design, but they both vividly demonstrate how the designer's argument is more than technological reasoning dressed up. The argument in<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> each is only partly controlled by mechanical premises, and if the logos or reasoning of the design is reduced to mechanics alone, the designer's real argument, which is a unique synthesis of mechanical and human premises, is lost. The human premises expressed in design logos, as varied as such premises are from audience to audience and from designer to designer, are fundamental sources of persuasion in all design arguments. They give intelligibility to designs that otherwise may seem to be superfluous indulgences. It is one thing for designers to throw up their hands at the prospect of designing products for the Amish, for whom all but the most basic forms of modern technological reasoning are unpersuasive. Yet this is different only in degree from the problem faced in every other instance of technological reasoning, where beliefs and values always condition products, whether they are recognized explicitly, are implicitly assumed, or are ignored completely. Technological reasoning is persuasive in two ways, related to the two kinds of premises on which it is based. It is persuasive in process, as well as in the accomplishment of something useful. In the former, audiences are persuaded when the reasoning is clear and provides a likely solution to a problem. This involves active contemplation of a product before and during use. For a simple example, consider dividers designed to measure distances of a cer- tain scale, perhaps on a chart or map (figure 4). The technological reasoning of the large brass and iron instrument is apparent at a glance. It depends, first, on a revolute pin joint that ensures a con- tinuous relationship between two pointer arms by allowing motion with one degree of freedom. Second, there is the curved crossbar, attached rigidly to one arm by a bolt and passed through a slot in the second, maintaining stability of relation in the motion of the arms. Third, there is a spring, serving to prevent play in the crossbar due to any loosening of the bolt attachment; and, fourth, there is a wing nut that tightens on the crossbarand allows the relation between the pointer armsto be fixed at any specific distance. In contrast, the reasoning of the smaller divider is not so readily apparent. The arms seem to work on a pivot post, but the mechanism that produces tension in their relation and fixes their relation at a given point is not obvious with a casual glance, as it is shielded by a small casing. When such reasoning is concealed, it speaks intelligently only to a small technical audience, perhaps as small as the engineers of the manufacturingcompany, and reaches a broader audience only in effective use. In complex modern systems, design logos is directed to two distinctly different audiences: specialists who can actually follow and judge the reasoning as a process and general users who are concerned only with results. This is a fundamental issue in design: whether and how much to involve a general audience of users in the process of technological reasoning. There are obvious limits in the ability of audiences to follow complex trains of technological reasoning, but designers can use a<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> variety of ways to convey this reasoning suggestively rather than directly. In complex systems, the alternativemay be to suggest the logical connection of large sections, without attempting to convey the detailed reasoning of each part. This can be done through an articulation of functional components, as in the new classic design of the Braun cassette deck (figure 5).27 Similarly, designers can present the control features of a complex system so carefully and clearly that audiences grasp the technological reasoning without actually seeing its details. This is essentially a metaphoric relationship, juxtaposing control knobs, buttons, and levers as an abstract, yet visually clear, symbolization of the real processes at work in a complex machine. The new areaof product semantics is closely related to this aspect of persuasion in its attempt to engage the mind of the audience and make the workings of a product more readily accessible.28 Product semantics and similar approaches work within broader design arguments concerning the relationship between users and objects, but there are other approaches that serve quite different<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> arguments. For example, the Memphis table lamp, Ashoka, by Ettore Sottsass, not only directly displays the balance of forces used in supporting the light bulbs, a playful balance that is an important part of the design logos, but also metaphorically suggests the flow of electric current (figure 6). The ostentatious display of technological reasoning (or of pseudoreasoning, as in the case of functionless elements that are associated with machin- ery, such as basic geometric forms, pipes, struts, and so forth) is a significant feature of many postmodern products. The table lamp by Sottsass or the Bel Air armchair,by Peter Shire for Memphis, (figure 7) are examples. Such ostentation, however, is not simply a decoration; it is part of the logos. An audience is invited to consider the mechanical aspect of our world when they use such a product. In the case of the Ashoka table lamp or the Bel Air armchair,the audience is encouraged to participate actively in the argument of the design, to recognize and think about mechanical and geometric relations, rather than ignore them or take them for granted. Consider the Quisisana ceiling lamp, by Ettore Sottsass, from the Memphis collection (figure 8). It also uses metaphor to suggest the flow of electricity and makes an ostentatious display of mechanics, but it engages users in a broader argument that expands the idea of function in everyday life. Not only do products function, humans function as well. This complex design argument, while meeting narrow demands of utility, also frees us from narrow purposive activity; it encourages our more complex imag- inative processes, our emotional and intellectual functioning freed from an immediate task. It reminds us, perhaps, that imagination is the source of technological inventions and that a free play of imagination ought to be an ongoing part of daily life. All of these approaches, however, are concerned more with the appearance and accessibility of technological reasoning than its truth or validity, which, in the case of design, is a question of<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> whether a product will actually work. Audiences will tolerate a great deal of discomfort and outright suffering if only a product will do something useful. This is evident in the early history of the automobile or the rise of medical technology, when general audiences cared little for an understanding of the details of products and wanted only results. But if practicality is the truth of design reasoning, and if such reasoning is contingent on so many factors of use that there is no way of judging its effectiveness in abstrac- tion, we are reduced to estimates of probable success, the advice of experts, and a willingness to take chances. And, through all of this, there is also a continuing awareness of how often poor technological reasoning is concealed, much as a politician may cover a poverty of ideas and rational arguments with pleasant phrases and a forceful personality. This leads to consideration of the other elements of a design argument, elements that may con- ceal poor reasoning or, in fact, complement good reasoning and enhance the persuasivenessof a product and satisfaction in its use. The second element is characteror ethos. Products have character because in some way they reflect their makers, and part of the art of design is the control of such characterin order to persuade potential users that a product has credibility in their lives. In essence, the problem is the way designers choose to represent themselves in products, not as they are, but as they wish to appear. Designers fashion objects to speak in particular voices, imbuing them with personal qualities they think will give confidence to users, whether or not the technological reasoning is actually sound. This may involve something so artless and extrinsic to design as a designer label, but in its significant aspect it involves qualities of characterthat are persuasive in any example of effective communication, such as good sense, apparent virtue, and goodwill toward the audience. Character can be a subtle mode of persuasion, but it is excep- tionally important for design. Consider the different qualities of characterprojected by some of the objects already discussed. The</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="79" page="7" column="1">9</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="80" page="7" column="1">Fig. 1) Utensils differ in the quality of character that they project while shar- ing the same mechanical premise.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="81" page="7" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="82" page="7" column="1">9</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx83">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62bl.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="84" page="7" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="86" page="8" column="1">arguments that are most likely to be persuasive with different</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="87" page="8" column="1">Fig. 2) This Krups coffee mi classic design values, empho asizing illexhibits function while seeming neu itral and unobtrusive. Character an( d emotion are important but carefully subordi- nated to use.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="88" page="8" column="1">Fig. 3) This Memphis bookcase, Ginza, a robot made of wood and chrome, should be seen in color for full effect. Its emotional excitement and humor animates the environment. Design: Masanori Umeda.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="90" page="8" column="1">by it.26</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="91" page="8" column="1">26) Barbara Radice, Memphis: Research, Experiences, Results, Failures, and Suc- cesses of New Design (New York: Riz- zoli International Publications Inc., 1984). Virtually a manifesto of Memphis design philosophy, couched in a rela- tively flamboyant and whimsical style that reflects Memphis attitudes. This style of writing may be contrasted to the efficient, economical prose of Dieter Rams' statement of Braun design philosophy, with the same result as com- paring Braun and Memphis products.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="93" page="8" column="1">10</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx94">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_008.image_09.png" thmb="62bl.page_008.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="95" page="8" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="96" page="9" column="1">Fig.4) Althoughsimilarin function, thesedividers use quitedifferentper- suasivearguments.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="98" page="9" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="9" column="1">11</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx100">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_009.image_10.png" thmb="62bl.page_009.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="101" page="9" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="102" page="10" column="1">Fig. 5) This Braun cassette deck and hi-fi system masterfully displays technological reasoning in a fashion that is readily accessible to users. And it shows careful control of character and emotion. Design: Peter Hartwein.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="103" page="10" column="1">27) Rams, "Omit the Unimportant," 25. "... items should be designed in such a way that their function and attributes are directly understood.... Of course, get- ting products to 'talk' by means of design is a demanding task."</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="104" page="10" column="1">28) Klaus Krippendorff and ReinhartButter, "Product Semantics: Explaining the Symbolic Qualities of Form," Innova- tion 3/2 (Spring 1984). The entire issue is devoted to the theme "Semantics of Form."</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="106" page="10" column="1">12</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx107">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_010.image_11.png" thmb="62bl.page_010.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="108" page="10" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="109" page="11" column="1">Fig.6) Ashokatablelampby Memphis. Design:EttoreSottsass.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="110" page="11" column="1">Fig. 7) This Bel Air armchair made of wood by Memphis, is upholstered in contrasting, bright color fabrics. Design: Peter Shire. Fig. 8) Quisisana ceiling lamp by Memphis, with two light sources: a red bulb and a halogen lamp tilted toward the ceiling. Design: Ettore Sottsass.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="112" page="11" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="113" page="11" column="1">13</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx114">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_011.image_12.png" thmb="62bl.page_011.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="115" page="11" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="117" page="12" column="1">Fig. 9) Bowl and quail sugar shaker, perhaps persuasive for the intended audience.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="118" page="12" column="1">14</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx119">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_012.image_13.png" thmb="62bl.page_012.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="120" page="12" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="121" page="13" column="1">9).29</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="122" page="13" column="1">29) Gert Selle, "ThereIs No Kitsch, There Is Only Design," Design Issues 1/1 (Spring 1984).</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="123" page="13" column="1">dividers (figure 4), for example, speak in verydifferent voices. The largerinstrument, by presenting its reasoning clearly andsimply, is bothintelligent and efficient in accomplishing something useful. It speaksin a sensiblevoice anddisplaysthe virtuesof a practical, sturdy,plain character. In contrast,the character of the smaller instrumentis a little more mysteriousor remote and, perhaps, superficially more elegant.Thereis lessdirectconnection between the technological reasoning of the designargument and its ethical aspect. This instrument,too, speaks in a sensible, intelligent voice, but such a qualitycomes more fromthe objectbeingper- ceived as an instrument than from any immediatedisplayof its own sensibleworkings.Withrespectto character, it persuades by looking authoritative, and authorityis a virtueprized by many audiences over good senseor intelligence. The problemof character in productsis a fundamental issue of designin the postmodern environment and one on whichdesign- ersanddesigncriticshaveyet to focusprecisely. It is in the areaof ethosrather than technological reasoning or esthetics that someof the sharpestconflictsand differences are evident. Consider,for example,the vast range of mass-produced objects that fill our product cultureand are regarded by many as kitsch(figure Suchobjectsarepersuasive not becausethey possessbeauty,but becausethey show a concernfor beauty.They speakin familiar, believablevoices that display esthetic sensibility as a virtue, whetheror not realitymatchesappearance. Perhaps most objects of massculturearepersuasive in a similar way, not because of any specialsubstanceor even clever emotionalappeal,but because they speakin familiar voices, show concernfor commonplace virtues and,hence,seemauthoritative. Ironically,designerswho believe they are advancing cultural standardsor challengingthe imaginationin constructiveways haverelatively little authority with massaudiences. Their designs often seem hostile and intimidating or areso subtlethat they go unappreciated. This is trueof the avant-garde, whose workspre- sentan ethosof spirited,unruly,andsometimes intelligent imagi- nation but -thatlack virtue or trustworthiness as judgedby the standards of massaudiences who suspectthemselves to be thebutt of a joke. This is also trueof designers such as those at Braunand Krups,whose designsare often so modest and unobtrusive that they almost go unnoticed. These designers compensate by emphasizing user-friendly products,usinggoodwillasthepersua- sive force of theirethos; modestas the Krupscoffee mill is, it is also delightfullyeasy to use. Avant-garde designersmost often ignore the problemor counterit by goingevenfurther in cultivat- ing an eccentric ethos thatis intendedto appealto a limitedaudi- ence of supposed trend-setters.After all, the avant-garde has always been a character type, romantic,virtuous(by their own standards),and heroic in standingagainstconventionaltastes, refinedor otherwise.Yet both groupsof designerscontinueto</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="124" page="13" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="125" page="13" column="1">15</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx126">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_013.image_14.png" thmb="62bl.page_013.image_14-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="127" page="13" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="128" page="14" column="1">30) Susan Sontag, "Notes on 'Camp'," in Against Interpretation (New York: Noonday Press, 1966).</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="129" page="14" column="1">31) Dick Hebdige, Subculture: The Meaning of Style (London: Methuen and Co. Ltd., 1979).</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="130" page="14" column="1">32) John Dewey, Art As Experience (New York: Capricorn Books, 1958) 35. In this major statement of esthetic philosophy, Dewey attempts to restore continuity between artisticobjects, which have been separated from the conditions of their origin, and the esthetic qualities of everyday experience found in encounter with our environment.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="131" page="14" column="1">Fig. 10)Thecompelling curve of this wrenchconveyssubtleemotional persuasion.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" page="14" column="1">grapple with the problem of ethos and virtue, and in the broader cultural debate, they are often the less persuasive voices. Perhaps in frustration an audience otherwise sympathetic to sophisticated design ideas has come to prize the "camp. "30 For this audience, irony is the virtue that is most persuasive, and some designers now deliberately attempt to play on this by imitating objects of mass culture. However, such design argumentsare only superficially amusing; in fact, they arenascently bitter expressions about the postmodern environment. They reach honest and direct statement perhaps only in recent punk styles, whose design argument is essentially one of protest.31 The technological reasoning in punk styles is either destroyed outright or grudgingly presented, as in clothing, with rips and tears that are metaphoric expressions of what are perceived to be the moral consequences of contemporary life. The third element of a design argument, emotion or pathos, is sometimes regarded as the true province of design, giving it the status of a fine art. Certainly, some designers think of themselves as essentially fine artists, and perhaps this is why they acquiesce in the equivocal role assigned them by those art historians for whom design is only a minor art concerned with decoration. But emotion is only a bridge of exchange with esthetics and the fine arts, just as technological reasoning is the bridge with the natural and social sciences and characteris the bridge with ethics and politics. When emotion enters design, it is not an end in itself but a mode of persuasive communication that serves a broader argument. The problem for design is to put an audience of users into a frame of mind so that when they use a product they are persuaded that it is emo- tionally desirable and valuable in their lives. Design provides an organization of the way we feel in a direct encounter with our environment; it provides a clarifying and fulfilling experience that may even remind us of fine art, although the objective is practical and perhaps mundane.32 The resources for emotional persuasion are the same for all design arguments, coming from physical contact with objects or from active contemplation of objects before, during, and afteruse. Much feeling is conveyed in the experience of movement, whether in the gestures made in using an object or in the shift of visual attention across its lines, colors, and patterns. This is what makes the emotive argument of a design so powerful and persuasive: it collapses the distance between the object and the minds of the users, leading them to identify with the expressive movement and allow it to carry them where it will. What helps to distinguish different design arguments is where the movement carries us. Consider the wrench pictured here (figure 10). Whatever the technological reasoning that requires such a configuration, the simple curve is so compelling that even people who would have no occasion to use the tool may feel something of its emotional appeal. It seems to send the mind of the observer <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> back and forth in a dynamic balance that is visually satisfying and when the tool is held, physically satisfying as well. Emotion here, as in classic design, serves and enhances use, but it also defines the object as an independent, autonomous whole. The Krups coffee mill (figure 2) and the Braun cassette deck (figure 5) seem self- contained and self-sufficient. These can be contrasted with the tense quality of the Ashoka table lamp (figure 6). Although sym- metrical, it seems to radiateoutward in every direction. Similarly, Shire's Bel Air armchair(figure 7) and Sottsass's ceiling lamp (figure 8) reach beyond themselves and give overtones to the sur- roundings and perhaps to the social context in which they will be used. Emotion here intensifies the environment, perhaps capturing the social occasion of dining, even as the objects perform their simple functions. Instead of appearing self-sufficient, they seem to seek connections and relationships with other objects or people around them, because the emotional excitement is directed out- ward. Contrast both of these uses of emotion with the spirited, playful lines that are patterned on the cup (figure 11). The bound- aries of the cup itself seem gentle, but the animation of the pattern holds us with surprisingintensity; some elusive regularity or sym- metry is sensed, but users are too caught up in the vitality to worry about balance. The cup seems to reachout to us, and we aretempted to pick it up. Emotion here has neither classic calm nor outwardly expanding excitement; instead, it involves a quiet and delicate play that reaches subtly into the mind of the user and sets loose the imagination. It is surprising to realize how far we are led into figurative language to express the persuasiveness of lines. This occurrence is a sign of the strong identity achieved between observer and object in the emotional aspect of design. As the art historian Joshua Taylor remarked, "To say that a line in a painting twists and turns is, of course, a highly figurative statement. It does nothing of the sort. It is we who twist and turn looking at it. 33 How far such an identity can go in design is evident when understood that in the strength of a design argument's emotional appeal, objects for use are sometimes transformed into objects for pure contemplation, valuable in themselves ratherthan as the means to some other end. The vase and cup pictured (respectively from Japan and Morocco) and other objects previously discussed could be regardedas works of art, valued without regard to their use. And this is true for the handcrafted mask (figure 12), as well. Designed for practical use, with obvious control of the elements of technological reasoning and ethos that make it suitable to be worn in rituals and festivals important in the everyday life of the people of a so-called primitive culture, it makes use of an emotive argument that reaches deep into human nature and across cultural barriers; it compels us to quite a different kind of contemplation - if not of the beautiful, then of the grotesque and terrifying. The emotional appeal of products ranges from the trivial to the<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> profound, and in the postmodern environment the full range is encountered. Some designers use emotion in a superficial and coercive way. They try to excite the passions of potential customers with trivial gimmicks that have little connection with technological reasoning or character. The arguments of such designers are hardly arguments at all, but only attempts to impose unexamined attitudes and marketing messages on passive and captive audiences, without concern for whether the product actually accomplishes the purpose for which it was intended. Other designers, who make many of the objects of our product culture, rely on weak and often sentimental emotions that are adapted to the existing tastes of audiences and to popular beliefs about what is artful or beautiful (compare such objects in figure 9 with the unconventional Memphis porcelain table service by Matteo Thun in figure 13).<marker type="block"/> The strongest designers, those who are most articulate if not always most persuasive, are concerned with discovering new aspects of the utility of emotional expression in practicallife. Their products attractand hold audiences in surprisingly different ways, and in this lies the importance of emotion as a mode of persuasion. It offers no conclusive proof of a designer's ideas about technology or social life, yet it helps an audience to entertain new possibilities for practicalliving and to remain open to the technological reasoning and characterof a product.<marker type="block"/> Purpose of design arguments Having identified the elements of a design argument and shown how they are interrelated in a variety of products, the next question is, what do such argumentsaccomplish? Do design arguments accomplish the same things as rhetorical arguments in words? To answer these questions, I want to return for a moment to the earlier discussion of the relationship between rhetoric and design. I suggested that our understanding of rhetoric has been limited to the rhetoric of words, but that the vast output of man-made objects in the present represents another, unrecognized mode of communication, a rhetoric of things. There seems to be little question that some kind of communication exists in designed objects. This is evident not only in the influence of rhetorical themes in shaping methodologies in the history, theory, and criticism of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="133" page="14" column="1">16</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx134">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62bl.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="135" page="14" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="136" page="15" column="1">Fig. 11) Handmade Moroccan cup and mass-produced Japanese vase give different qualities of space and motion.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="137" page="15" column="1">33) Joshua C. Taylor, To See Is To Think: Looking At American Art (Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution Press, 1975), 85. This is from an essay called "Persuasion." See also the essay "The Pure and the Impure" for esthetic theories that have interesting relevanceto design.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="138" page="15" column="1">Fig. 12)Thishandcrafted mask from Balidisplays a persuasive emotional argumentthat transcends the rhetori- calpurpose for whichit wasdesigned. It becomes sculptural art andspeaksto a universal audience.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="140" page="15" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="141" page="15" column="1">17</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx142">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_015.image_16.png" thmb="62bl.page_015.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="143" page="15" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="145" page="16" column="1">Fig. 13)Compare this Memphis porce- laintableservicewith the bowland sugar shaker in figure 9. The objects are, from left to right, a pepper shaker, Ontario;a toothpickholder,Erie;an appetizer holder, Superior; and a salt shaker, Michigan. Design: Matteo Thun.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="148" page="16" column="1">18</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx149">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_016.image_17.png" thmb="62bl.page_016.image_17-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="150" page="16" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="151" page="17" column="1">design,but alsoin the growingbody of specificinformation about how rhetorical considerations actually guidethepractice of design. The significant question,however,is what the natureof such communication is. Does a designed object communicate simply in the sense that it is a sign (or set of signs)of the conditionsof its production,much as smoke is a sign of fire? Is an objectcom- municative to the extentof its styling,whichis expressive of emotion and estheticqualities? Or, is therebound up in the idea of design a kind of communication that involvesall aspectsof the making of objectsfor use, so thatdesignitself, whatever the type of objectproduced,is not anartof adornment, but a rhetorical art thatcreates objects persuasive in everyaspect? Theprimary obstacle to thelatterviewliesin ourunderstanding of the nature of technology. If technology or technological reasoning is regarded merely asa deduction from scientific principles, thereis no significant sense in whichit canbe seenaspersua- sive. Technological development would be regarded as aninevita- ble process growingout of scientificadvance,and questionsof value and social consequence would be regarded as irrelevant to the essenceof design, more properlyleft to politiciansand the publicthanincluded as a consideration for designers. However,as important as science is in the developmentof technology, the activity of technologicalreasoninginherentlyinvolves human valuesselectedknowinglyor unknowingly as important premises thatdirectlyaffectthe essential characteristics of objects,not just theirsuperficial appearance. If thispremise is correct,a rhetoric of design becomesa distinctpossibility,evenif its precisenature and qualities yet remain to be discovered. It is possible because technological reasoning, the coreaspectof designthatmayappear objective andremotefromhumanvaluesandopinions,is, in fact, developed in terms of an audience. Its success is not judged theoretically by appealing to the knowledgeof a smallgroupof experts, but practically by appealingto the interests,attitudes, opinions,andvaluesof users. Basedon this, the feasibilityof a rhetorical study of designed objectshas been shown in this articleby applyingthe themesof rhetoricthat are traditionally used in the study of verbalcom- munication. The resultis a concreteillustration of ways in which objectscan be persuasive and designerscan deliberately control the threeelementsof argument to shapeobjectsandachievesome kind of persuasion.But what kind of persuasion is it? Surelyit would be fatuousto suggestthat we interactwith objectsin the sameways thatwe interact with words.If we did, whatdistinctive valuewouldtherebe in wordsandwhy wouldhumanbeingshave</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" page="17" column="1">instinctively or knowingly, and over such a long period of time, designed the language system as it is? Persuasion in language can be oriented in any of three directions. It can be oriented to the past, as in a law court, where we are persuaded to make necessary judgments of fact. Also, it can be</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="153" page="17" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="154" page="17" column="1">19</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx155">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_017.image_18.png" thmb="62bl.page_017.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="156" page="17" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="157" page="18" column="1">Olbrechts-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="158" page="18" column="1">increases hence,strength- speaker around</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="159" page="18" column="1">34) Chaim Perelmanand L. Tyteca,TheNew Rhetoric: A Treatise on Argument (Notre Dame:Universityof Notre DamePress,1969),47-51. Perel- man arguesthat epideictic is centralto the artof persuasion because it adherence to values and, ensthedisposition to action. The establishes a senseof communion values recognized by theaudience.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="160" page="18" column="1">Object:</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="161" page="18" column="1">other</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="162" page="18" column="1">35)HaroldRosenberg, The Anxious Art Today and ItsAudience (New York: The New American Library,1964),20. Thisimportant study of thefineartsfalls well withinthe rhetorical tradition that regards painting, poetry, and modesof fineartasepideictic rhetoric.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="163" page="18" column="1">36)Rosenberg, The Anxious Object, 21.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="164" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">both cases.36</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="165" page="18" column="1">orientedto the future, as in politicaldebate,wherewe are per- suadedto make judgmentsabout contingentcoursesof action. And, finally,it can be orientedto the present,as in a varietyof socialceremonies, where we arepersuaded to considersomething as valuable or worthlessand, hence,to praiseor blamethe matter offered for consideration.The latter is known as epideicticor demonstrative rhetoricand is perhapsthe most puzzling of all rhetorical forms becauseit grows out of materials from the past andhintsatpossibilities for the future,yet is mostconcerned with attitudes in the present.34 Of thesethreeorientations, design arguments and the rhetoric of thingsaremost like demonstrative rhetoric.They aredemon- strationsor exhibitions,growingout of the past (asin traditional shapesand forms or in alreadyknown scientificprinciplesthat providethepremises for construction) and suggesting possibilities for the future(asin futureactivities that a givenobjectmaymake possible), yet existingprimarilyin the presentas declarations. Productsareimportant to us in use and, hence,they existsignifi- cantly in a kind of omni-present. Unlike words, which can per- suadepeople to specificjudgmentsabout the past or futureand assertattitudes,ideas, andvaluesthatarerecognized in the present, designedobjects primarilyasserttheir own existenceand, throughthatexistence,the attitudes that areanintegral part of an object'spresentbeing. In this respect,the productsof designsharea rhetorical status similar to worksof fineart.As criticHaroldRosenberg said of the artobject, "Itsnatureis contingentupon recognition by the current communionof the knowing. Art does not exist. It declares itself."35 What he meansis that the existenceof a work and its statusas fine artis not somethingthatcanbe takenfor granted; a work in the presentculturemustdeclare itself to be a work of fine artandpersuade an audience to recognizeits statusassuch,other- wise therecanbe no way of distinguishing fine artfromanyother type of man-madeobject. As Rosenberg seems to suggest, designedobjectsdeclare a statusotherthanfineart- the attitudes andvaluesasserted are different,for the designedobjectdeclares thatit is fit for use, whereasthe work of fine artasserts a freedom from specialized utility - yet the rhetorical form is the samein If productsaffectandshapeattitudes,they do so only through persuasive assertion,which may be recognizedor not. Beyond this, users must then carry out their own deliberationabout whetheror how to use productsin the future.For example,the Krupscoffeemill (figure2) is a gentleassertion or demonstration of an effectiveway to grind coffee. It is quite persuasive as an object, andthe sourcesof thatpersuasion come fromthe character and emotion of the argument,as well as from its technological reasoning.Yet it is only an assertion; users may then begintheir own deliberations about whetherto buy it and how to use it in</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="166" page="18" column="1">20</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx167">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_018.image_19.png" thmb="62bl.page_018.image_19-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="168" page="18" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="169" page="19" column="1">example, Michaels,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="170" page="19" column="1">37)Consider, for example, the roleof public policy formation, a classicsituation for verbal rhetoric, with regard to the development and implementation of technological systems. See,for RobertF. Baker,Richard M. and EverettS. Preston, Public Policy Development: Linking theTechnical and Political Processes(New York: John Wiley&amp; Sons,1975).</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="171" page="19" column="1">38) McKeon,"TheUses of Rhetoricin a Technological Age," 45.</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="172" page="19" column="1">larger</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="173" page="19" column="1">through</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="174" page="19" column="1">rhetorical</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="175" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">in urban planning.39</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="176" page="19" column="1">39) Not accidentally, this list is to something in theMiddle Ages thatwas calledthe quadrivium, the four artsof thingsthatdealtwithsuccessively andlarger integrative problems. The dis- coveryof a modern quadrivium a rhetoricof thingsis one of the most intriguing aspects of the approach to design,suggesting again that designis a primary architectonic art in ourculture. 40) The expansion of the artof rhetoric to architectonic status in thetwentieth century follows our growingawareness of evidencefor significant rhetorical considerations in many areas previously ne- glected.We are discovering, for example, that scientific discourse involves serious rhetorical features. For one study, see Ricca Edmonson, The Rhetoric of Sociology (London: The MacMillan Press Ltd., 1984).Evidence for a rhetoricof thingsis found in the demonstrations discussed in this paper. Evidence for a rhetoric of actionis found in phenomena such as civil rights marches or otherprotestactionsthatare demonstrations of grievances or injus- tices.Fortheuseof actions to communicate protest, see, for example, Saul Alinsky,Rules for Radicals (New York: Random House, 1971).In thisrespect, it is interesting to compare the rhetoric of GeorgePullman's demonstration in the buildings of thePullman community and theworker's demonstration in theirpro- teststrike (see note21).</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="177" page="19" column="1">theirlives. In this case, the objectis so gentlein its assertion and demonstration that how to combine it with other objects in a home environment can easilybe seen. Indeed,one of its virtuesis that it combineseasily and well with many kinds and styles of objects.And the factis, peoplehavechangedtheirdailyroutines becauseof what the productassertsanddemonstrates that it can do for them. As trivialas this example may seem, the situationis little differentfor any orderof designproductor technological complexity: the assertoric rhetoric of the product quickly becomespartof the broaderverbalrhetoricused in deliberating aboutthe futureor judgingthe past.37 In effect,the productasks for recognitionthroughall of the modes of argument that have beendiscussed,but thenwe areleft, andevenrequired, to placeit in a broadersocialcontextwhereverbalrhetorichas full forcein determining the implementation of the product. Rhetoricand designas architectonicarts One importantimplicationconcernsthe natureof architectonic artsin ourculture today. Architectonic arts arethosethatorganize the effortsof other artsand crafts,givingorderand purposeto production.38For example, architecturehas long been an architectonic art with respectto the host of specialized disciplines involved in constructionbecauseit orchestrates their contribu- tions and rationalizestheir individualproducts into a single, whole product.In essence,it providesthe thoughtor ideathatis the soul of production. There aremanyindications, however, that architecture is only one form of a broaderarchitectonic art that hasemerged in the modernworld.Indeed,the termarchitecture is used in a varietyof new ways as a metaphorfor structureand organization of many things other than buildings:for example, the architecture of computersystemsor the architecture of the threevast, interconnected technological systems that distinguish our historical period, the electricpower grid, the transportation system, and the communications system. The naturalword for thisnew, modernarchitectonic art surelyis design.Designis what all formsof productionfor use havein common. It providesthe intelligence, the thoughtor idea- of course,one of the meanings of the termdesignis a thoughtor plan- thatorganizesall levels of production,whetherin graphic design, engineering and indus- trialdesign,architecture, or the largestintegrated systems found But if designis an architectonic art with respectto things, its effortsand productsare guidedin turnby anotherarchitectonic art that furtherintegrates objects into social activitiesand even guidesthe practice of designateveryturn.Thisarchitectonic art is rhetoric- not simply the old verbalrhetoricbut, rhetoricas an artof thought.Rhetoric is architectonic with respect to thoughtas it is formulated and presented for an audience, whetherin words, things, or actions.40 This articlehas alludedin passingto some</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="178" page="19" column="1">Design Issues: Vol. II, No. 1</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="179" page="19" column="1">21</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx180">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_019.image_20.png" thmb="62bl.page_019.image_20-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="181" page="19" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="182" page="20" column="1">41) Pile, Design, 6.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="183" page="20" column="1">42) Amplification is a well-known device in rhetoric, today usually meaning the expansion of a simple statement into more elaborate or complete language. However, Aristotle refers to it as a topic of invention and also as a form of argument specially suited to epideictic (demonstrative) rhetoric. Furthermore, he regards amplification not merely as a verbal device, but as a way of elaborating the qualities of a subject. See Aristotle, Rhetoric, 105, 343. As used in this paper, amplification is a way of elaborating the living environment to enhancethe quality of life.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">aspectsof the architectonic art of rhetoric as it mayunfoldin verbal rhetoric,but this conceptcanbe illustrated a litle morein the practice of design. ConsiderJohn Pile'sdefinitionof design,not as a nounbut as a verb: "Wedo not havean idealword for the processesof choiceand decision-makingthat determinehow things are to be made. Designwillhaveto serveus, althoughits manymeanings - from decorative pattern, to the selectionof sizes for plumbing pipes can be a sourceof confusion.The word is used hereto meanthe making of decisionsaboutsize, shape,arrangement, material, fab- ricationtechnique,color andfinishthatestablish how anobjectis to be made.The objectcanbe a city or town, a building,avehicle, a tool or anyotherobject,a book, anadvertisement or a stageset. Designers are people who make such decisions, althoughthey will, most often, havesome othernamedescribing their specialized concern: architect,engineer, town planneror, possibly, craftsman. "41 It canbe seenthatthesensein whichdesign,through thoughtful decision, is architectonic with respectto makingthings, but the role of rhetoric in guidingthatthoughtcanalsobe noticed.When asking for the basesof decisionin all of the areasthat Pile iden- tifies, we areat once caughtin a web of humanfactors,attitudes, andvaluesthatareof central concern to rhetoric. The skillfulprac- tice of designinvolvesa skillfulpracticeof rhetoric,not only in formulating the thoughtor planof a product,throughall of the activitiesof verbalinventionand persuasion that go on between designers,managers, and so forth, but also in persuasively pre- sentinganddeclaring that thoughtin products.Fromthe smallest, most incidental object to the largest,integrated technological system, designersare providingan amplification of ideas through man-made things.42 Hence, insteadof regarding the historyand currentpracticeof design as the inevitable result of dialectical necessitybasedon economicconditions or technological advance, we may do well to regard the apparent confusionof our product cultureas a pluralistic expression of diverseandoften conflicting ideasandturnto a closerexamination of the varietyandimplica- tions of suchideas. There is no reason to believe that the architectonicart of rhetoricis any better understoodat presentthan the similarly emerging architectonic art of design.Rhetoric is undergoing a new development in the twentiethcentury,and designersare among those who areshapingit to meet modernproblems.If designers canbenefitfromexplicittalkaboutrhetorical concerns,thosewho areinterested in rhetoric can benefitevenmorefromstudyinghow designcontinuesto influenceand shapesociety by its persuasive assertions. We areleft with aninescapable conclusionthatdesign- ers are discoveringan entirely new aspect of demonstrative rhetoric that will significantly affect ourunderstanding of rhetoric as a modernarchitectonic art.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="185" page="20" column="1">22</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx186">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62bl.page_020.image_21.png" thmb="62bl.page_020.image_21-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="187" page="20" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.139 on Wed, 22 Jan 2014 08:01:25 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
