<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>31f6b5e005fe8842875528656b5fe6f60cb7d93d747180d9bd35b82471407432</job>
    <base_name>62j8</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s0191-8869(02)00359-8">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/135467899394066</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62j8.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62j8.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">An Interdisciplinary Journal on Humans in ICT Environments</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="3">ISSN: 1795-6889</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">www.humantechnology.jyu.fi</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">Volume 5 (1), May 2009, 90–113</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="6">MENTAL MODELS, MAGICAL THINKING, AND INDIVIDUAL DIFFERENCES</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="7">Phil Turner</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="9">Emilia Sobolewska</name></contrib></contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">Centre for Interaction Design, Centre for Interaction Design, School of Computing, School of Computing, Edinburgh Napier University, Edinburgh Napier University, Edinburgh, UK Edinburgh, UK</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="11">interaction, cognitive style, mental model,</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="12">Abstract: Broadly, there are two mutually exclusive accounts of how people (non- specialist users) reason about and conceptualize interactive technology. The first is based on classical cognitive psychology and is characterized by the term mental model. The second, drawing on concepts from social cognition, observes that people often anthropomorphize technology. We argue that people are able to exhibit both of these quite different styles of cognition, which Baron-Cohen has described as systemizing and empathizing. The former is associated with the drive to analyze, explore, and construct a system, whereas the latter is the ability to spontaneously tune into another’s thoughts and feelings. The propensity to systemize might give rise to a mental model, while the empathizing tendency might tend to anthropomorphize technology. We present an empirical study that lends support for the above position. Keywords : human–computer anthropomorphization .</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" page="1" column="1">Interactive technology is one of the defining characteristics of modern society, and how we design, use, and think about it is, consequently, of considerable importance. To this end human–computer interaction (HCI) is a multidisciplinary field that has drawn on psychology, software engineering, anthropology, sociology, and philosophy. Indeed, in the preface of the first great HCI text, The Psychology of Human-Computer Interaction (Card, Moran, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Newell, 1983</xref>), we find, “The domain of concern to us, and the subject of this book, is how humans interact with computers. A scientific psychology should help us in arranging the interface so it is easy, efficient and error free” (p. vii). Recalling the early days of HCI, Carroll (2003, p. 3) observes that, “the initial vision of HCI as an applied science was to bring cognitive-science methods and theories to bear on software development.” In due course, Card and his colleagues went on to propose the model human processor (as a means of modeling</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">© 2009 Phil Turner &amp; Emilia Sobolewska , and the Agora Center, University of Jyväskylä URN: NBN:fi:jyu-20094141412</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="17" page="1" column="1">90</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18" page="2" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="2" column="1">how people reason about and use technology) and to create an essentially task-based approach to the design of the user interface. This dual use of cognition has remained with us to this day. Some 20 years later, HCI has successfully developed numerous cognitive models and psychologically plausible engineering models of human behavior ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="19" class="deo:Reference">Gardiner &amp; Christie, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Hollnagel &amp; Woods, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Payne, 1991</xref>) that, to a greater or lesser extent, have proved to be able to model aspects of the behavior of people using interactive systems and devices. Strongly predictive models, such as the keystroke-level model (Card, Moran, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Newell, 1980</xref>), have, for example, been used to predict the time to complete a task for a skilled individual, while cognitively inspired tools like GOMS (goals, operators, methods and selection) have been used in the design and evaluation of user interfaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="23" class="deo:Reference">John &amp; Kieras, 1996</xref>). This “golden age of HCI” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Carroll, 2003</xref>) has also witnessed the adoption of mental models as a means of accounting for how we learn to use and conceptualize interactive technology (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Gentner &amp; Stevens, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Norman, 1983</xref>). The term mental model first appeared in Craik’s The Nature of Explanation (1943) and then reappeared in the 1980s, as Johnson-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Laird (1983)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Gentner and Stevens (1983)</xref> independently adopted the term to describe complex cognitive representations. These models are very diverse and include systems (e.g., our knowledge of banking), devices (e.g., the operation of pocket calculators), physical forces (e.g., the nature of electricity), or a concept (e.g., the administration of justice). HCI mental models also have had the dual role of being used to reason about how to create an interactive system and as a means to represent people’s understanding of a particular interactive device or system (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Norman, 1983</xref>). While subsequent research has moved beyond this exclusively cognitive stance (discussed below), there remains the assumption that cognition (mental models in particular) still has a role in how people use interactive technology. However a recent report in New Scientist magazine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Marks, 2008</xref>) reminds us of another aspect of our cognition that manifests as a tendency to treat inanimate objects like pets or even friends. The magazine cites a report of 1 people’s interactions with Roomba, a robot vacuum cleaner. It was reported that some of the owners of this vacuum cleaner dressed it up, assigned it a gender and even gave it a name. It is suggested that this kind of behavior is commonplace. Indeed, a decade or so earlier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Reeves and Nass (1996)</xref> presented evidence that users treat computers, television, and other new media as though they were people, that is, response to or interaction with them is primarily social. We are, for example, polite (and rude) to interactive technology and these responses, they suggest, are the products of our “old brains” being misled amid the glamour of these new media. They also argue that media representations and techniques have been progressively designed over time specifically to activate these very social responses. For the purposes of this discussion, and in keeping with more recent research, we will characterize these descriptions as anthropomorphic accounts that arise from aspects of our social cognition. So it appears we are potentially faced with a dichotomy. Either people conceptualize interactive technology by way of a mental model, which is characterized as set of processes that can be modeled, or as a friend—“superstitious” in character and comprising “magical thinking”—that is, ascribing agency, feelings, and intentions to technology. However, it could be both. Our treatment of this mismatch is to recognize that these two views reflect two distinct cognitive styles that appear to correspond with the distinction Baron-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Cohen (1995, 2002, 2004)</xref> has named systemizing and empathizing cognition. Systemizing cognition is<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> associated with the drive to analyze, explore, and construct a system and, as such, is a candidate for the mechanism (or mechanisms) responsible for creating a mental model. Empathizing cognition, in contrast, is the ability to spontaneously tune into another’s thoughts and feelings. Empathizing cognition is closely related to what has been called theory of mind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Premack &amp; Woodruff, 1978</xref>) and may be the source of our tendency to treat technologies as though they have thoughts, feelings, moods, and desires of their own. Baron- Cohen also has shown that this is not an either-or situation, but rather individuals having both abilities in different proportions. This observation may allow us to account for people being able to hold both positions with respect to interactive technology.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="34" page="2" column="1">91</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="35" page="3" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="38" page="3" column="1">COGNITIVE ACCOUNTS, RATIONALISTIC APPROACHES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="3" column="1">Most of the work on mental models was conducted in the 1980s and 1990s, but began to lose favor when a raft of new concepts in human–computer interaction appeared. Cognition itself is now recognized as being situated (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Suchman, 1987</xref>), distributed (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Hutchins, 1995</xref>; Hollan, Hutchins, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Kirsh, 2000</xref>), external (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Scaife &amp; Rogers, 1996</xref>), embodied (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Clark, 1997</xref>; van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Dijk, 2009</xref>, this volume; Valera, Thompson, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Rosch 1991</xref>), and even collective (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Engeström, 1987</xref>, 1999). Although classical cognition, as typified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Fodor (1983)</xref>, no longer has as much currency as it once had, it has proven to be remarkably resilient, as the work we have just cited are extensions to cognition, not evidence of its abandonment. As for mental models themselves, Gillian Crampton Smith, the doyenne of interaction design, notes the importance of a good mental model in the design of interactive technology, in that, “we need a clear mental model of what we’re interacting with” (Crampton Smith, n.d., cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Moggridge, 2007</xref>, p. xv). As we have already noted, mental model accounts have been used both to inform design and as an explanatory medium, though this has not always been made explicit. A consequence of this, although there are other contributory factors, is that there is no agreement on the precise nature, function, or composition of mental models. Indeed Rouse and Morris (1986, p. 360) have noted, At present, this area of study is rife with terminological inconsistencies and a preponderance of conjectures rather than data. This situation arises, to a great extent, because a variety of sub-disciplines have adopted the concept of mental models, and proceeded to develop their own terminology and methodology, independent of past or current work in this area in other sub-disciplines.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Mental Models as the Basis of the Design of Interactive Technology</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" page="3" column="1">From the design perspective, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Norman (1983)</xref> introduced a number of different forms of mental model. The first is the user-constructed model of the computer system (the target system) with which he/she is interacting. The target system should be designed in such a way as to communicate its underlying conceptual model. Later he revised this account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Norman, 1986</xref>) so that the target system becomes the system image that includes the physical model of the system: input/output devices, documentation, training, error handling, and so forth. The conceptual model becomes the design model created by the designer, and the user’s model is<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> now the result of interaction with the system image. Thus, good design is embodied and determined by the quality of the mapping between the system image and the resultant user’s mental model. If the system image is not a clear reflection of the design model, then the user will end up with the wrong mental model.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="54" page="3" column="1">92</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="4" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="57" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Mental Models as the Basis of How We Reason about Interactive Technology</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="4" column="1">From the explanatory perspective, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Young (1981, 1983)</xref>, for example, explored a number of the properties of mental models through a series of empirical investigations. His studies investigated how people reasoned about the use of calculators. Of particular interest to Young were the role of analogy, the stability of mental models in long term memory, their propositional content, and the rules governing the operation (i.e., their “grammar”). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Norman (1983, 1986)</xref> also concluded that (a) mental models are incomplete and unstable, since people forget details of the system; (b) people’s abilities to “run” their models (in the sense of running an internal simulation) are severely limited and do not have firm boundaries; that is, similar devices and operations get confused with one another; (c) mental models are unscientific; and (d) mental models are parsimonious. People are willing to undertake additional physical operations to minimize mental effort; for example, people will switch off the device to reboot and start again rather than trying to recover from an error. Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Payne (1991)</xref> reported what he called a descriptive study of mental models. He recruited 16 participants who were interviewed about their beliefs and understanding of the mechanisms behind ATMs (automated cash dispensers). He was specifically interested in (and whether) people spontaneously create explanatory mental models about the ATM’s operation. Following an informal content analysis of the resulting interviews, Payne observed that “it is clear that many subjects had already constructed mental models of bank machines—they had speculated about the inner working of the system in advance of being promoted to do so by a curious psychologist” (1991, p. 18). In all, he concluded that mental models can be used to predict behavior by means of “mental simulation,” which in turn rely on analogy to function. Despite the weaknesses of the mental model accounts of how people think about the operation of interactive technology, it is worth reiterating that no other widely held explanation has yet appeared to directly replace it, except, of course, when people think of interactive technology as their friends.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="4" column="1">ANTHROPOMORPHIC ACCOUNTS</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="64" page="4" column="1">The ascription of human-like characteristics to computing technology has become integral to our design, use, training, and communications with regard to computing technology and it has been argued to be the most common metaphor used in computing discourse. (Johnson, Marakas, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Palmer, 2008</xref>, p. 169)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="4" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Reeves and Nass (1996)</xref> were among the first to recognize that the way in which we treat interactive technology, television, and other new media is essentially social. In their The Media Equation, they show in a surprisingly wide variety of ways that the apparent blurring of real and mediated life is commonplace. They present evidence that we interact with media in the same<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> way we respond to other people, using the same rules that govern face-to-face interpersonal interactions. This equation is recognized as being particularly remarkable and counterintuitive, since people know that the medium they are interacting with is not a real person. Interactive technology is, of course, distinguished from other technologies by virtue of its very interactivity, a trait it shares with humans. Computers also use language. Computers are instructed to perform by way of programming languages. HCI designers are concerned with dialogue design, that is, how the interaction between person and interactive technology is structured. Computers can produce human-sounding voices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Nass &amp; Moon, 2000</xref>; indeed it has been noted by many that the only really human character in Stanley Kubrick’s 1968 movie 2001: A Space Odyssey, was HAL, the computer). Studies of social presence have revealed that users easily and regularly ascribe human characteristics, emotion, and behavior to avatars created within collaborative virtual environments (for a review, see Biocca, Harms, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Burgoon, 2003</xref>.) Perhaps most importantly, computers now fill roles traditionally held by humans. Computing technology is ubiquitous in our society, often mediating our basic daily interactions, such as communication, banking, paying bills and taxes, and governing much of our working lives. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Winograd and Flores (1987)</xref> also have observed that computing technology has apparent autonomy, complexity of purpose, structural plasticity, and unpredictability—all of which are human-like characteristics. Nass and Moon (2000, p. 86) have examined what they describe as the fundamental truth that “the computer is not a person and does not warrant human treatment or attribution.” They point out that computers do not have faces or bodies—unlike, say, a child’s toy—are unresponsive to human affect, and never express emotion themselves. Yet for all of this, there is abundant evidence that people mindlessly apply social rules and expectations to interactive media. In a series of experiments, they further found that people tend to “overuse human social categories” (p. 82), such as gender and ethnicity, politeness and reciprocity, and behave as though computers have personality traits, such as friendliness. People also have been found to use social rules and respond to computers with different voices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Nass &amp; Steuer 1993</xref>), to feel psychologically close to or connected with a computer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Lee &amp; Nass, 2005</xref>), to respond to computer personalities in a similar manner as they respond to human personalities (e.g., Brave, Nass, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Hutchinson, 2005</xref>), and even to respond to flattery from the computer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Fogg &amp; Nass, 1997</xref>). Evidence shows that people with strong anthropomorphic beliefs are more likely to ascribe responsibility for their interactions with and outputs of a decision support system than those with weaker anthropomorphic beliefs, even though the ultimate interactions and decisions were within the control of all users (Johnson, Marakas, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Palmer, 2006</xref>). In all, there are fewer studies of this kind than the corresponding classical cognitive accounts and their findings are yet to be translated into design features. Nonetheless, their results are very robust. Next we consider these two different cognitive styles.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="67" page="4" column="1">93</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="68" page="5" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="5" column="1">DIFFERENT COGNITIVE STYLES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" page="5" column="1">Baron-Cohen’s (1995, 2002, 2004) systemizing–empathizing account of psychological sex differences is based on neurological differences in “male” and “female” brains. While Baron- Cohen emphasizes functional and structural brain difference, we, like others (e.g., Focquaert, <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> Steven, Wolford, Colden, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Gazzaniga, 2007</xref>), are more concerned with the differences in the resulting cognitive style and their consequences for how people think about interactive technology. We approach this concept with some caution since we believe that this is first time Baron-Cohen’s work has been applied to the domain of HCI. Baron-Cohen claims that the female brain has a predominant propensity for empathy while the male brain is predominantly wired for understanding and building systems. In support of this position, he introduces evidence to suggest that male and female brains develop differently from conception. The source of these differences is the presence of prenatal androgens (male sex hormones) that can permanently affect the development of the neural structure and function of the brain. However, while male brains are more commonly found in men and female brains in women, this distinction is in no sense absolute. The propensity to analyze a system in terms of the rules that govern it in order to predict its behavior and the propensity to identify and understand the mental states of the other in order to predict his/her behavior, and to respond appropriately in either case, is found in both men and women (Baron-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Cohen, 1995</xref>, 2002, 2004; Baron-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Cohen &amp; Wheelwright, 2004</xref>). Excepting a few extreme examples, no one would suggest that men are incapable of empathy, nor women incapable of understanding the workings of a system. Every individual has a propensity for each cognitive style in varying proportions. Individual systemizing and empathizing quotients can be derived means of a pair of administered questionnaires that Baron-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Cohen (2004)</xref> has developed (see Appendixes A and B). These questionnaires consist of 60 questions for either a Systemizing Quotient (SQ) or an Empathy Quotient (EQ), and are based on a Likert scale, with answers ranging from strongly agree to strongly disagree. The questions related to the SQ are of the form, “When I listen to a piece of music, I always notice the way it’s structured” and “If I were buying a car, I would want to obtain specific information about its engine capacity,” which are designed to capture a person’s tendency to systematize. By contrast, the EQ questions are of the form, “I can easily tell if someone else wants to enter a conversation” and “I find it difficult to explain to others things that I understand easily, when they don’t understand it first time” [sic]. Questions are scored 1 or 2 points on the respective scales, although there are also some null questions that afford no score. From the resultant scores, people can be categorized as high, average, or low empathizers or systemizers, remembering that the two scales are independent. These quotients can be interpreted using the guidelines, which may be found <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="5" column="1">94</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="6" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="88" page="6" column="1">HOW PEOPLE THINK ABOUT THEIR MOBILE PHONES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="6" column="1">Before describing the procedure we adopted, it is worth taking a moment to examine the methodology that inspired this work. It will be recalled (see Section 2) that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Payne (1991)</xref> conducted a series of interviews with the intention of exploring the mental models people spontaneously create to mediate their interaction with technology. In his study, he interviewed people regarding their attitudes and understanding of ATMs. The interviews were conducted in an unrestrained manner. Payne’s subsequent treatment of the data is not well documented but appears to be an informal content analysis.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91" page="6" column="1">95</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92" page="7" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="94" page="7" column="1">Table 1. Interpreting the EQ and SQ Results (after Baron-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Cohen, 2004</xref>, p. 216).</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="95" page="7" column="1">Empathizing Quotient (EQ) i.e., the ability to understand how other people feel and responding appropriately 0-32 Lower than average 33-52 Average ability 53-63 Above average 64-80 Very high ability Systemizing Quotient (SQ) i.e., the ability to analyze and explore a system 0-19 Lower than average 20-39 Average ability 40-50 Above average ability 2 Very high ability (three times as many people with Asperger syndrome score in 51-80 this range compared to typical men, and almost no women score in this range) Note: In the EQ scoring, most women score about 47 and most men score about 42, while in the SQ scoring, most women score about 24 and most men score about 30.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="96" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Research Questions</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" page="7" column="1">Modern mobile phones are no longer limited to simply making and receiving calls; they now routinely have a range of interactive functions and, as such, can be treated as interactive technology. Therefore, we propose that the SQ and EQ of the individuals in this study are indicative of their propensity to describe the operation of interactive technology (i.e., mobile phones in this instance) using language that is rich in technical, systemizing terms (for those with above average SQs), or filled with anthropocentric, empathizing terms (for those with above average EQs), or a mixture of technical and anthropocentric language (for those balanced in their SQ and EQ). Although we have not proposed formal hypotheses for this study, it is worth considering the null, or alternate, hypothesis before proceeding to a discussion of the method. We have been careful to stress that while our research questions (described above) are indicative, myriad other factors may well mask these systemizing and empathizing propensities. While a formal experimental protocol may have been able to isolate and control for these factors, our interest was in (a) reproducing Payne’s explicitly descriptive study, and (b) exploring the everyday, rather than the experimental, aspects of people using their mobile phones.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="98" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Method</h2>
          <region class="unknown" id="99" page="7" column="1">Participants</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" page="7" column="1">In all, 16 males and 7 females agreed to participate. All were non-immigrant native English speakers. They were aged between 18 and 45 years, with median age of 22 years. These <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> people had been recruited from the postgraduate research students and undergraduates from the School of Computing at the Edinburgh Napier University.<marker type="block"/> All 23 participants first completed the two questionnaires that measured their individual EQ and SQ. These were scored by the second author using the guidelines that accompany them. Of the 23 participants, 13 achieved balanced score (EQ = SQ, which we operationally define as EQ = SQ ±5), 4 achieved an above average score in empathy abilities (EQ&gt;SQ) and 6 people scored above average systemizing abilities (SQ&gt;EQ). On the basis of these results, 12 3 people (4 above average EQs, 4 above average SQs, and 4 balanced ) were randomly selected to participate in the interview portion of the study. The selected participants were individually taken aside to a quiet room to be interviewed. The participants were asked to complete a consent form and were informed that the collected data would be transcribed, analyzed, and may be submitted for publication. The participants were assured that this was not a test of their knowledge, and they were not obliged to provide the interviewer with an answer. An audio recording, using a Sony DAT recorder, was made of the interviews. The interviews themselves varied in length from around 10 to almost 40 minutes (varying with the loquaciousness of the interviewee). The interview procedure was designed to constrain the interviewee as little as possible, although some limited prompts were necessary. All were also asked to demonstrate and talk-through the typical use of their mobile phones. Participants were encouraged to discuss how they used mobile phones and the role of this technology in their lives. A full list of questions asked of every participant can be found in Appendix C. As in much qualitative research, content analysis is fundamentally interpretive, meaning is often implicit and can only be understood through deep and repeated familiarity with the entirety of each participant’s interview protocol. What follows are both illustrative and representative of the participants’ answers to two of the questions we posed. The quotations were selected by the authors to reflect the participants’ cognitive style, that is, whether they tended to systemize, empathize, or give balanced answers.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="101" page="7" column="1">96</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="102" page="8" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="104" page="8" column="1">Procedure</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="106" page="8" column="1">RESULTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="8" column="1">The question “What is inside a mobile phone?” was so phrased to more likely prompt a technical answer. We expected that those individuals with relatively high SQs would offer detailed technical answers.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Above Average SQs (40–50)</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="109" page="8" column="1">Of six participants with high SQs, all but one provided highly technical answers; the other gave answers using systematizing language, although it was considerably less technical. What’s in the telephone? Ummh--lots of transistors and chips and things, and the battery, [pause] and [pause] liquid crystal display for the screen and the speaker, and the microphone, and the camera [pause]. (Participant 1, SQ = 40)</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="110" page="8" column="1">97</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="111" page="9" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="112" page="9" column="1">Many things, circuit boards, chips, transceiver [laughs], battery [pause], a camera in some of them, a media player, buttons, lots of different things. [pause] Well there are lots and lots of different bits and pieces to the phone, there are mainly in ... Eh, like inside the chip there are lots of little transistors, which is used, they build up to lots of different types of gates and/or “x” these types of gates or electronic gates. There are resisters and diodes; [pause] there’s a fair amount of copper on, I’d imagine, on circuit boards. There are lights, some of which are light-emitting diodes; in fact they are all probably light emitting diodes. There’s a camera, as I have already said. There’s a battery, and in most modern mobile phones they use lithium polymer batteries, um... because they last longer and have greater capacity.... (Participant 4, SQ = 44) What is in the phone? Um, all kinds of circuitry and devices. I know there’s a camera in the phone, so there will be a light detector for that. And there is a wireless card, so there’s a wireless interface for that. There’s a memory slot, so there will be an interface for that. There’s a SIM card; the SIM card contains your personal information, it’s a sort of chip that contains your unique identifier for the network, so basically your phone number and such. Uh, it has onboard memory for storage; it has onboard memory, volatile memory for operating system use, umm, and it has the various hardware that drives the screen. (Participant 6, SQ = 45) In... inside the telephone? Well, I mean it’s ... eh ... you know, you're going to have a printed circuit board, known as a PCB. Ahh ... that ... that allows for communications between the different, ah ... chips on the PCB for things like voice encoding and decoding, umm... so I can hear and speak ahh ... with people. Umm ... This also allows for power to come from the battery to the different elements, umm ... and obviously to the screen as well. (Participant 7, SQ = 50)</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="113" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Average SQs (20–39)</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" page="9" column="1">Participants with average SQ scores tended to be less loquacious, saying less about what is inside their phones than those with higher scores. What's in it? It's a little computer; it's a microchip, and a screen, and shit like that. (Participant 8, SQ = 24) No. [laughs] A speaker and a microphone and a camera, if you got a camera [laughs], phone umm ... and a battery and a SIM card. That's about all I know. (Participant 10, SQ = 27) There were no participants with low SQs in the sample with whom we could compare accounts.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="115" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">How People Think Mobile Phones Work</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="122" page="9" column="1">Following Payne’s protocol, we asked, “How do you think the telephone works?” with the coda, “Pretend you are answering to the intelligent Martian who has no experience with the devices.” <marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> All participants with balanced EQ and SQ scores tended to give answers that contained strong evidence of neither systemizing nor empathizing elements. Ok [long pause] Umm... Ok... I... I... I...think like, Mmmh ... of course it's working over satellite and, mmmh ... it's provided with software for the text messages, like that I can use T9 and stuff like that. And I think it's almost just based on software and this, umm ... code is transferred over satellite. [pause] And the, the, the calling is just like with a normal phone but it's not transferred over a landline but over umm satellite, that’s... yeah. (Participant 11, SQ = 33, EQ = 38) Participant 11, unlike those scoring above average on the systemizing scale, shows little or no evidence of having a detailed mental model of the phone’s operation. Instead she describes the operation of a mobile phone coherently but in a high level, fairly general manner.<marker type="block"/> All highly empathizing participants provided similar sorts of answers to the same question that tended to highlight the surface features of their phones. It flashes the lights, screen flashes, and the buttons lights up, and it vibrates. It comes to life on the inside and it comes to life on the outside, and you talk to the one side and someone is answering on the other side [long pause]. Umm... well, all the different elements connect and work in the phone so enable you to ... make the phone call. I don't know how, but yeah ... I don't know. It’s a mystery. It’s magical [laughs]. I have no understanding of how it works. So it really is magical. (Participant 3, EQ = 55) [Interviewer] What happens if you enter your PIN code incorrectly? Three times? It locks me out. [interviewer] And what does it mean? It means I can't use it and I cry quite a lot. (Participant 8, EQ = 56) For Participant 3, who shows above average empathizing propensity, the language is quite different from that of the other extracts. This participant ascribed agency to her phone (“It comes to life”) and often referred to her phone as being magical. Space prevents a fuller account of these interviews but what is clear is that there is a relationship (but not a simple one) between the systemizing quotients and the nature of the answers people gave. People with high SQs appear to have complex, well populated mental models of their phones; people with lower SQs less so. For those with high EQs, the picture is less clear. There is some evidence of anthropomorphism, but we suspect the demand characteristics of the situation may have obscured this. The balanced individuals are best characterized as being disinterested, with no real evidence of either systemizing or empathizing propensities.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="117" page="9" column="1">98</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="118" page="10" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="119" page="10" column="1">Balanced Individuals (EQ = SQ ±5)</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="121" page="10" column="1">Above Average EQ (55–63)</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="123" page="10" column="1">DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="129" page="10" column="1">As we have seen, there is a considerable body of evidence regarding how people reason about and conceptualize everyday interactive technology. We have argued that Baron-Cohen’s <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> (1995, 2002, 2004) distinction between systemizing and empathizing cognition is used here differentially to create either mental model or anthropomorphic descriptions, as required. The data we have presented from the study of how people think about their mobile phones indicate that people who demonstrate high SQs tend to produce detailed, technical accounts of technology. This finding is consistent with the mental models hypothesis. people who demonstrate high EQs correspondingly show little technical knowledge and are given to describing the workings of technology in terms of magic and anthropocentricism. people who demonstrate a balanced EQ and SQ appear to offer explanations on how technology works that are neither overly technical nor anthropomorphic. However a powerful factor in an experimental setting such as this is the way in which we posed the questions. Cognition cannot be observed directly, but the very ways in which we study it necessarily affect the results. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Orne (1962)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Orne and Whitehouse (2000)</xref> have identified what they describe as demand characteristics that can be encountered in psychological studies. They found that people, understandably, attempt to make sense of what the experimenter is trying to achieve. So as soon as we ask questions about how people think about something, we are (a) necessarily asking biased questions, and (b) effectively prompting them to answer in a particular way. Demand characteristics, more formally, refer to the totality of cues and role expectations that are inhered within all social contexts, including a study such as this. The consequences or effect of demand characteristics in this situation will vary with the extent to which they are perceived, as well as with the motivation and ability of the person to comply. Demand characteristics are very difficult to control for and, in asking people about the operation of mobile phones, we can recognize that some questions will tend to elicit or prompt a technical answer while other questions will tend to prompt more discursive nontechnical answers. This then is consistent with Norman’s (1993) and Clancey’s (1997) observations concerning situated cognition. As Norman (1993, p. 4) observes, situated cognition places an emphasis on the structures of the world and how they constrain and guide behavior.... Human knowledge and interaction cannot be divorced from the world. To do so is to study a disembodied intelligence, one that is artificial, unreal, and uncharacteristic of actual behavior. What really matters is the situation and the parts that people play. One cannot look at just the situation, or just the environment, or just the person. To do so is to destroy the very phenomenon of interest. After all, it is the mutual accommodation of people and the environment that matters, so to focus upon only aspects in isolation is to destroy the interaction, to eliminate the role of the situation upon cognition and action. Therefore, we must be aware that all of the responses we received were, in part, a function of the demand characteristics of the study condition; in short, technical questions elicit technical replies and everyday questions elicit everyday answers. Given this, we conclude that the explanations people gave as to how technology works was a function of their ability to adopt the appropriate cognitive style and to manage the situation demanding this cognition. So how people think about interactive technology may be thought of as an interaction between their cognitive propensities and the situation in which their cognition is exercised.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="125" page="10" column="1">99</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="126" page="11" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="130" page="11" column="1">100</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="131" page="12" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="132" page="12" column="1">FURTHER WORK</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140" page="12" column="1">So what are the practical applications of these findings? While it is difficult to imagine how cognitive style might be used to guide the design of, say, custom-made interactive technology (e.g., a mobile phone for above-average empathizers, although its usefulness in marketing is quite clear), it may have consequences for the evaluation of interactive technology. Evaluation is the cornerstone of HCI; it lies at the heart of the user-centered approach to the development of interactive systems (e.g., the star lifecycle model; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Hartson &amp; Hix, 1993</xref>). It is the means by which the user experience of the system is fed back to the designer; it is the obverse of design. Many different evaluation techniques are available to the HCI practitioner, but they can be reasonably categorized into four basic themes: 1. Expert evaluation is characterized by the absence of the intended end user of the system but the presence of an expert (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Smith &amp; Mosier, 1986</xref>). The expert makes judgments about the design of the interactive technology against a set of guidelines. 2. Model-based evaluation is based on predictions about user behavior made using a psychologically plausible or ergonomic model (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Card et al., 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="136" class="deo:Reference">John &amp; Kieras, 1996</xref>). 3. Scenario-based, task-based, and cooperative forms of evaluation involve one or more representative users. A typical scenario or task is created with the users working through it, during which problems are identified (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Carey &amp; Rusli, 1995</xref>). 4. Finally, there are evaluation techniques that simulate the presence or behavior of a user, such as the cognitive walkthrough (e.g., Poulson, Bovair, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Kieras, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="139" class="deo:Reference">Spencer, 2000</xref>). It is important not to overstate any criticism of these approaches, as they have significantly contributed to the creation of very many usable systems. However all four styles of evaluation treat users like experimental subjects, just as in the classic psychological experiments that (a) sought to make statements about the general population, rather than individuals; and (b) tested hypotheses of the form, interface/artifact A is “better” than interface/artifact B. In all, there typically is no treatment of individual differences beyond a gross categorization, such as novice and expert, or frequent and infrequent users. It may be that this fairly simple systemizer–empathizer–balanced categorization may prove to be both a useful and, just as importantly, a practical means of saying something about individual differences in the experience of end users of a given interactive technology.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="141" page="12" column="1">ENDNOTES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">1. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://store.irobot.com" id="142">http://store.irobot.com</ext-link> for more information. 2. Baron-Cohen (2004, pp. 135–136) describes Asperger syndrome (AS) as a variant of autism. He writes, “A child with AS has the same difficulties in social and communication skills and has the same obsessional interests. However, such children not only have normal or high IQ (unlike those with high-functioning autism) but they also start speaking on time. 3. Balanced scores can be so at all three levels of SQ and EQ: high, medium, and low.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144" page="12" column="1">101</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="145" page="13" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="146" page="13" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="13" column="1">Baron-Cohen, S. (1995). Mindblindness: An essay on autism and theory of mind. Cambridge, MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="13" column="1">Baron-Cohen, S. (2002). The extreme male brain theory of autism. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 6, 248–254.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="13" column="1">Baron-Cohen, S. (2004). The essential difference. London: Penguin.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="13" column="1">Baron-Cohen, S., &amp; Wheelwright, S. (2004). The empathy quotient: An investigation of adults with Asperger syndrome or high functioning autism, and normal sex differences. Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, 34, 164–175.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" page="13" column="1">Biocca, F., Harms, C., &amp; Burgoon, J. K. (2003). Toward a more robust theory and measure of social presence: Review and suggested criteria. Presence: Teleoperators and Virtual Environments, 12, 456–480.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="13" column="1">Brave, S., Nass, C. I., &amp; Hutchinson, K. (2005). Computers that care: Investigating the effects of orientation of emotion exhibited by an embodied computer agent. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 62, 161–178.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="13" column="1">Card, S. K., Moran, T. P., &amp; Newell, A. (1980). The keystroke-level model of user performance time with interactive systems. Communications of the ACM, 23, 396–410.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="13" column="1">Card, S. K., Moran, T. P., &amp; Newell, A. (1983). The psychology of human-computer interaction. Hillsdale, NJ, USA: LEA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="13" column="1">Carey, T., &amp; Rusli, M. (1995). Usage representations for reuse of design insights: A case study of access to online books. In J. M. Carroll (Ed.), Scenario-based design: Envisioning work and technology in system development (pp. 165–182). New York: John Wiley and Sons.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="13" column="1">Carroll, J. M. (2003). Introduction: Towards a multidisciplinary science of human–computer interaction. In J. Carroll (Ed.), HCI models, theories and frameworks (pp. 1–9). San Francisco: Morgan Kaufmann.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="13" column="1">Clancey, W. J. (1997). Situated cognition: On human knowledge and computer representations. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Clark, A. (1997). Being there: Putting brain, body and world together again. Cambridge, MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="13" column="1">Craik, K. J. W. (1943). The nature of explanation. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="13" column="1">van Dijk, J. (2009). Cognition is not what it used to be: Reconsidering usability from an embodied embedded cognition perspective. Human Technology: An Interdisciplinary Journal on Humans in ICT Environments, 5, 29–46.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="13" column="1">Engeström, Y. (1987). Learning by expanding: An activity-theoretical approach to developmental research. Helsinki, Finland: Orienta-Konsultit.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="13" column="1">Engeström, Y. (1999). Expansive visibilization of work: An activity theoretic perspective. Journal of Computer Supported Cooperative Work, 8(1-2), 66–92.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="13" column="1">Focquaert, F., Steven M. S., Wolford, G. L, Colden, A., &amp; Gazzaniga M. S. (2007). Empathizing and systemizing cognitive traits in the sciences and humanities. Personality and Individual Differences, 43, 619–625.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="13" column="1">Fodor, J. A. (1983). The modularity of mind: An essay on faculty psychology. Cambridge, MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="13" column="1">Fogg, B. J., &amp; Nass, C. (1997). Silicon sycophants: The effects of computers that flatter. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 46, 551–561.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="13" column="1">Gardiner, M., &amp; Christie, B. (Eds.). (1987). Applying cognitive psychology to user-interface design. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="13" column="1">Gentner, D., &amp; Stevens A. (Eds.). (1983). Mental models. Hillsdale, NJ, USA: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="13" column="1">Hartson, D., &amp; Hix, H. R. (1993). Developing user interfaces. New York: John Wiley and Sons.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="13" column="1">Hollan, J., Hutchins, E., &amp; Kirsh, D. (2000) Distributed cognition: Toward a new foundation for human– computer interaction research. ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction, 7, 174 –196.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="14" column="1">Hollnagel, E., &amp; Woods, D. D. (1983). Cognitive systems engineering: New wine in new bottles. International Journal of Man-Machine Studies, 18, 583–600.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="14" column="1">Hutchins, E. (1995). Cognition in the wild. Cambridge. MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="14" column="1">John, B. E., &amp; Kieras, D. E. (1996). Using GOMS for user interface design and evaluation: Which technique? ACM Transactions on Human Computer Interaction, 3, 287–319.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="14" column="1">Johnson, J. D., Marakas, G. M., &amp; Palmer, J. W. (2006). Differential social attributions toward computing technology: An empirical examination. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 64, 446–460.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="14" column="1">Johnson, J. D., Marakas, G. M., &amp; Palmer J. W. (2008). Beliefs about the social roles and capabilities of computing technology: Development of the computing technology continuum of perspective. Behaviour &amp; Information Technology, 27, 169–181.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="14" column="1">Johnson-Laird, P. N. (1983). Mental models. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Kubrick, S. (Director &amp; Producer). (1968). 2001: A Space Odyssey [Motion Picture]. United States: MGM, Polaris, &amp; Stanley Kubrick Productions.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="14" column="1">Lee, K. M., &amp; Nass, C. (2005). Social-psychological origins of feelings of presence: Creating social presence with machine-generated voices. Media Psychology, 7, 31–45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Marks, P. (2008, April 5). The rise of the emotional robot. New Scientist [online]. Retrieved April 18, 2008, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://technology.newscientist.com/article/mg19826506.100-the-rise-of-the-emotional-robot.html" id="180">http://technology.newscientist.com/article/mg19826506.100-the-rise-of-the-emotional-robot.html</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="14" column="1">Moggridge, B. (2007). Designing interactions. Cambridge. MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="14" column="1">Nass C., &amp; Steuer J. (1993). Voices, boxes, and sources of messages: Computers and social actors. Human Communication Research, 19, 504–527.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Nass, C., &amp; Moon, Y. (2000). Machines and mindlessness: Social responses to computers. Journal of Social Issues, 56, 81–103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Norman, D. A. (1983). Some observations on mental models. In D. Gentner &amp; A. Stevens (Eds.), Mental models. Hillsdale, NJ, USA: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Norman, D. A. (1986). Cognitive engineering. In D. A. Norman &amp; S. W. Draper (Eds.), User centered system design: New perspectives in human computer interaction (pp. 31–61). Hillsdale, NJ, USA: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Norman, D. A. (1993). Cognition in the head and in the world: An introduction to the special issue on situated action. Cognitive Science, 17, 1–6.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" page="14" column="1">Orne, M. T. (1962). On the social psychology of the psychological experiment: With particular reference to demand characteristics and their implications. American Psychologist, 17, 776–783.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="14" column="1">Orne, M. T., &amp; Whitehouse, W. G. (2000). Demand characteristics. In A. E. Kazdin (Ed.), Encyclopedia of psychology (pp. 469–470). Washington, DC, USA: Oxford Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" page="14" column="1">Payne, S. J. (1991). A descriptive study of mental models. Behaviour and Information Technology, 10, 3–21.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="14" column="1">Poulson, P. G., Bovair, S., &amp; Kieras, D. (1982). Transfer between text editors. Proceedings of the 1982 Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 27–32). New York: ACM.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="14" column="1">Premack, D., &amp; Woodruff, A. J. (1978). Does the chimpanzee have a theory of mind? Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 4, 515–526.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" page="14" column="1">Reeves, B., &amp; Nass, C. (1996). The media equation: How people treat computers, television and new media like real people and places. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="14" column="1">Rouse, W. B., &amp; Morris, N. M. (1986). On looking into the black box: Prospects and limits for mental models. Psychological Bulletin, 100, 349–363.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="14" column="1">Scaife, M., &amp; Rogers, Y. (1996). External cognition: How do graphical representations work? International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 45, 185–213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="14" column="1">Smith, S. L., &amp; Mosier, J. N. (1986). Guidelines for designing user interface software (Tech Rep. NTIS No. A177 198). Hanscom Air Force Base, MA, USA: AFSC, United States Air Force. <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> Spencer, R. (2000). The streamlined cognitive walkthrough method, working around social constraints encountered in a software development company. Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 353–359). New York: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="15" column="1">Suchman, L. (1987). Plans and situated action. Cambridge, MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="15" column="1">Valera, F. J., Thompson, E., &amp; Rosch, E. (1991). The embodied mind. Cambridge, MA, USA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="15" column="1">Winograd, T., &amp; Flores, F. (1987). Understanding computers and cognition: A new foundation for design. Norwood, NJ, USA: Ablex.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Young, R. M. (1981). The machine inside the machine: Users’ models of pocket calculators. International Journal of Man-Machine Studies, 15, 51–85.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Young, R. M. (1983). Surrogates and mappings: Two kinds of conceptual models for interactive devices. In D. Gentner &amp; A. L. Stevens (Eds.), Mental models (pp. 35–52). Hillsdale, NJ, USA: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="15" column="1">Author’s Note The EQ and SQ questionnaires are reproduced with the kind permission of Professor Simon Baron-Cohen. All correspondence should be addressed to: Phil Turner School of Computing</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="15" column="1">Edinburgh Napier University Edinburgh, UK EH 10 5DT <email id="206">p.turner@napier.ac.uk</email></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="170" page="13" column="1">102</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="171" page="14" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="197" page="14" column="1">103</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="198" page="15" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="208" page="15" column="1">Human Technology: An Interdisciplinary Journal on Humans in ICT Environments ISSN 1795-6889 www.humantechnology.jyu.fi</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="209" page="15" column="1">104</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="210" page="16" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="211" page="16" column="1">APPENDIX A: THE EQ QUESTIONNAIRE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="212" page="16" column="1">The Empathy Quotient is intended to measure how easily you pick up on other people’s feelings and how strongly you are affected by other people’s feelings. Please read each of the 60 following statements very carefully and rate how strongly you agree or disagree with them by circling your answer. There are no right or wrong answers, or trick questions.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="213" page="16" column="1">1. I can easily tell if someone else wants strongly slightly slightly strongly to enter a conversation. agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 2. I prefer animals to humans. agree agree disagree disagree 3. I try to keep up with the current trends strongly slightly slightly strongly and fashions. agree agree disagree disagree 4. I find it difficult to explain to others strongly slightly slightly strongly things that I understand easily, when agree agree disagree disagree they don't understand it first time. strongly slightly slightly strongly 5. I dream most nights. agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 6. I really enjoy caring for other people. agree agree disagree disagree 7. I try to solve my own problems rather strongly slightly slightly strongly than discussing them with others. agree agree disagree disagree 8. I find it hard to know what to do in a strongly slightly slightly strongly social situation. agree agree disagree disagree 9. I am at my best first thing in the strongly slightly slightly strongly morning. agree agree disagree disagree 10. People often tell me that I went too far strongly slightly slightly strongly in driving my point home in a agree agree disagree disagree discussion. 11. It doesn't bother me too much if I am strongly slightly slightly strongly late meeting a friend. agree agree disagree disagree 12. Friendships and relationships are just strongly slightly slightly strongly too difficult, so I tend not to bother with agree agree disagree disagree them. 13. I would never break a law, no matter strongly slightly slightly strongly how minor. agree agree disagree disagree 14. I often find it difficult to judge if strongly slightly slightly strongly something is rude or polite. agree agree disagree disagree 15. In a conversation, I tend to focus on strongly slightly slightly strongly my own thoughts rather than on what agree agree disagree disagree my listener might be thinking. 16. I prefer practical jokes to verbal strongly slightly slightly strongly humour. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="214" page="16" column="1">105</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="215" page="17" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="216" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">17. I live life for today rather than the strongly slightly slightly strongly future. agree agree disagree disagree 18. When I was a child, I enjoyed cutting strongly slightly slightly strongly up worms to see what would happen. agree agree disagree disagree 19. I can pick up quickly if someone says strongly slightly slightly strongly one thing but means another. agree agree disagree disagree 20. I tend to have very strong opinions strongly slightly slightly strongly about morality. agree agree disagree disagree 21. It is hard for me to see why some strongly slightly slightly strongly things upset people so much. agree agree disagree disagree 22. I find it easy to put myself in somebody strongly slightly slightly strongly else's shoes. agree agree disagree disagree 23. I think that good manners are the most strongly slightly slightly strongly important thing a parent can teach agree agree disagree disagree their child. 24. I like to do things on the spur of the strongly slightly slightly strongly moment. agree agree disagree disagree 25. I am good at predicting how someone strongly slightly slightly strongly will feel. agree agree disagree disagree 26. I am quick to spot when someone in a strongly slightly slightly strongly group is feeling awkward or agree agree disagree disagree uncomfortable. 27. If I say something that someone else strongly slightly slightly strongly is offended by, I think that that's their agree agree disagree disagree problem, not mine. 28. If anyone asked me if I liked their strongly slightly slightly strongly haircut, I would reply truthfully, even if agree agree disagree disagree I didn't like it. 29. I can't always see why someone strongly slightly slightly strongly should have felt offended by a remark. agree agree disagree disagree 30. People often tell me that I am very strongly slightly slightly strongly unpredictable. agree agree disagree disagree 31. I enjoy being the centre of attention at strongly slightly slightly strongly any social gathering. agree agree disagree disagree 32. Seeing people cry doesn't really upset strongly slightly slightly strongly me. agree agree disagree disagree 33. I enjoy having discussions about strongly slightly slightly strongly politics. agree agree disagree disagree 34. I am very blunt, which some people strongly slightly slightly strongly take to be rudeness, even though this agree agree disagree disagree is unintentional. 35. I don’t tend to find social situations strongly slightly slightly strongly confusing. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="217" page="17" column="1">106</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="218" page="18" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="219" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">36. Other people tell me I am good at strongly slightly slightly strongly understanding how they are feeling agree agree disagree disagree and what they are thinking. 37. When I talk to people, I tend to talk strongly slightly slightly strongly about their experiences rather than my agree agree disagree disagree own. strongly slightly slightly strongly 38. It upsets me to see an animal in pain. agree agree disagree disagree 39. I am able to make decisions without strongly slightly slightly strongly being influenced by people's feelings. agree agree disagree disagree 40. I can't relax until I have done everything strongly slightly slightly strongly I had planned to do that day. agree agree disagree disagree 41. I can easily tell if someone else is strongly slightly slightly strongly interested or bored with what I am agree agree disagree disagree saying. 42. I get upset if I see people suffering on strongly slightly slightly strongly news programmes. agree agree disagree disagree 43. Friends usually talk to me about their strongly slightly slightly strongly problems as they say that I am very agree agree disagree disagree understanding. 44. I can sense if I am intruding, even if strongly slightly slightly strongly the other person doesn't tell me. agree agree disagree disagree 45. I often start new hobbies but quickly strongly slightly slightly strongly become bored with them and move on agree agree disagree disagree to something else. 46. People sometimes tell me that I have strongly slightly slightly strongly gone too far with teasing. agree agree disagree disagree 47. I would be too nervous to go on a big strongly slightly slightly strongly rollercoaster. agree agree disagree disagree 48. Other people often say that I am strongly slightly slightly strongly insensitive, though I don’t always see agree agree disagree disagree why. 49. If I see a stranger in a group, I think strongly slightly slightly strongly that it is up to them to make an effort agree agree disagree disagree to join in. 50. I usually stay emotionally detached strongly slightly slightly strongly when watching a film. agree agree disagree disagree 51. I like to be very organised in day to strongly slightly slightly strongly day life and often make lists of the agree agree disagree disagree chores I have to do. 52. I can tune into how someone else strongly slightly slightly strongly feels rapidly and intuitively. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="220" page="18" column="1">107</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="221" page="19" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="222" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">strongly slightly slightly strongly 53. I don't like to take risks. agree agree disagree disagree 54. I can easily work out what another strongly slightly slightly strongly person might want to talk about. agree agree disagree disagree 55. I can tell if someone is masking their strongly slightly slightly strongly true emotion. agree agree disagree disagree 56. Before making a decision I always strongly slightly slightly strongly weigh up the pros and cons. agree agree disagree disagree 57. I don't consciously work out the rules strongly slightly slightly strongly of social situations. agree agree disagree disagree 58. I am good at predicting what someone strongly slightly slightly strongly will do. agree agree disagree disagree 59. I tend to get emotionally involved with strongly slightly slightly strongly a friend's problems. agree agree disagree disagree 60. I can usually appreciate the other strongly slightly slightly strongly person's viewpoint, even if I don't agree agree disagree disagree agree with it.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="223" page="19" column="1">108</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="224" page="20" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="225" page="20" column="1">APPENDIX B: THE SQ QUESTIONNAIRE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="226" page="20" column="1">The Systemizing Quotient gives a score based on how interested you assess yourself to be in each of the following forms of systemizing. Systemizing is the drive to analyse and explore a system, to extract underlying rules that govern the behaviour of a system; and the drive to construct systems. Please read each of the following 60 statements very carefully and rate how strongly you agree or disagree with them by circling your answer. There are no right or wrong answers, or trick questions.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="227" page="20" column="1">1. When I listen to a piece of music, I strongly slightly slightly strongly always notice the way it's structured. agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 2. I adhere to common superstitions. agree agree disagree disagree 3. I often make resolutions, but find it hard strongly slightly slightly strongly to stick to them. agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 4. I prefer to read non-fiction than fiction. agree agree disagree disagree 5. If I were buying a car, I would want to strongly slightly slightly strongly obtain specific information about its agree agree disagree disagree engine capacity. 6. When I look at a painting, I do not strongly slightly slightly strongly usually think about the technique agree agree disagree disagree involved in making it. 7. If there was a problem with the strongly slightly slightly strongly electrical wiring in my home, I'd be able agree agree disagree disagree to fix it myself. 8. When I have a dream, I find it difficult strongly slightly slightly strongly to remember precise details about the agree agree disagree disagree dream the next day. 9. When I watch a film, I prefer to be with strongly slightly slightly strongly a group of friends, rather than alone. agree agree disagree disagree 10. I am interested in learning about strongly slightly slightly strongly different religions. agree agree disagree disagree 11. I rarely read articles or webpages strongly slightly slightly strongly about new technology. agree agree disagree disagree 12. I do not enjoy games that involve a strongly slightly slightly strongly high degree of strategy. agree agree disagree disagree 13. I am fascinated by how machines strongly slightly slightly strongly work. agree agree disagree disagree 14. I make it a point of listening to the news strongly slightly slightly strongly each morning. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="228" page="20" column="1">109</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="229" page="21" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="230" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">15. In maths, I am intrigued by the rules strongly slightly slightly strongly and patterns governing numbers. agree agree disagree disagree 16. I am bad about keeping in touch with strongly slightly slightly strongly old friends. agree agree disagree disagree 17. When I am relating a story, I often strongly slightly slightly strongly leave out details and just give the gist agree agree disagree disagree of what happened. 18. I find it difficult to understand instruction strongly slightly slightly strongly manuals for putting appliances together. agree agree disagree disagree 19. When I look at an animal, I like to know strongly slightly slightly strongly the precise species it belongs to. agree agree disagree disagree 20. If I were buying a computer, I would want to know exact details about its strongly slightly slightly strongly hard drive capacity and processor agree agree disagree disagree speed. strongly slightly slightly strongly 21. I enjoy participating in sport. agree agree disagree disagree 22. I try to avoid doing household chores if strongly slightly slightly strongly I can. agree agree disagree disagree 23. When I cook, I do not think about exactly how different methods and strongly slightly slightly strongly ingredients contribute to the final agree agree disagree disagree product. 24. I find it difficult to read and understand strongly slightly slightly strongly maps. agree agree disagree disagree 25. If I had a collection (e.g. CDs, coins, strongly slightly slightly strongly stamps), it would be highly organised. agree agree disagree disagree 26. When I look at a piece of furniture, I do strongly slightly slightly strongly not notice the details of how it was agree agree disagree disagree constructed. 27. The idea of engaging in "risk-taking" strongly slightly slightly strongly activities appeals to me. agree agree disagree disagree 28. When I learn about historical events, I strongly slightly slightly strongly do not focus on exact dates. agree agree disagree disagree 29. When I read the newspaper, I am drawn to tables of information, such as strongly slightly slightly strongly football league scores or stock market agree agree disagree disagree indices. 30. When I learn a language, I become strongly slightly slightly strongly intrigued by its grammatical rules. agree agree disagree disagree 31. I find it difficult to learn my way around strongly slightly slightly strongly a new city. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="231" page="21" column="1">110</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="232" page="22" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="233" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">32. I do not tend to watch science strongly slightly slightly strongly documentaries on television or read agree agree disagree disagree articles about science and nature. 33. If I were buying a stereo, I would want strongly slightly slightly strongly to know about its precise technical agree agree disagree disagree features. 34. I find it easy to grasp exactly how odds strongly slightly slightly strongly work in betting. agree agree disagree disagree 35. I am not very meticulous when I carry strongly slightly slightly strongly out D.I.Y. agree agree disagree disagree 36. I find it easy to carry on a conversation strongly slightly slightly strongly with someone I've just met. agree agree disagree disagree 37. When I look at a building, I am curious strongly slightly slightly strongly about the precise way it was agree agree disagree disagree constructed. 38. When an election is being held, I am strongly slightly slightly strongly not interested in the results for each agree agree disagree disagree constituency. 39. When I lend someone money, I expect strongly slightly slightly strongly them to pay me back exactly what they agree agree disagree disagree owe me. 40. I find it difficult to understand information the bank sends me on strongly slightly slightly strongly different investment and saving agree agree disagree disagree systems. 41. When travelling by train, I often wonder strongly slightly slightly strongly exactly how the rail networks are agree agree disagree disagree coordinated. 42. When I buy a new appliance, I do not strongly slightly slightly strongly read the instruction manual very agree agree disagree disagree thoroughly. 43. If I were buying a camera, I would not strongly slightly slightly strongly look carefully into the quality of the lens. agree agree disagree disagree 44. When I read something, I always notice strongly slightly slightly strongly whether it is grammatically correct. agree agree disagree disagree 45. When I hear the weather forecast, I am strongly slightly slightly strongly not very interested in the meteorological agree agree disagree disagree patterns. 46. I often wonder what it would be like to strongly slightly slightly strongly be someone else. agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 47. I find it difficult to do two things at once. agree agree disagree disagree 48. When I look at a mountain, I think strongly slightly slightly strongly about how precisely it was formed. agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="234" page="22" column="1">111</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="235" page="23" column="1">Turner &amp; Sobolewska</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">49. I can easily visualise how the strongly slightly slightly strongly motorways in my region link up. agree agree disagree disagree 50. When I'm in a restaurant, I often have strongly slightly slightly strongly a hard time deciding what to order agree agree disagree disagree 51. When I'm in a plane, I do not think strongly slightly slightly strongly about the aerodynamics agree agree disagree disagree 52. I often forget the precise details of strongly slightly slightly strongly conversations I've had agree agree disagree disagree 53. When I am walking in the country, I am strongly slightly slightly strongly curious about how the various kinds of agree agree disagree disagree trees differ 54. After meeting someone just once or strongly slightly slightly strongly twice, I find it difficult to remember agree agree disagree disagree precisely what they look like 55. I am interested in knowing the path a strongly slightly slightly strongly river takes from its source to the sea agree agree disagree disagree 56. I do not read legal documents very strongly slightly slightly strongly carefully agree agree disagree disagree 57. I am not interested in understanding strongly slightly slightly strongly how wireless communication works agree agree disagree disagree strongly slightly slightly strongly 58. I am curious about life on other planets agree agree disagree disagree 59. When I travel, I like to learn specific strongly slightly slightly strongly details about the culture of the place I agree agree disagree disagree am visiting 60. I do not care to know the names of the strongly slightly slightly strongly plants I see agree agree disagree disagree</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="237" page="23" column="1">112</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="238" page="24" column="1">Mental models and magical thinking</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="239" page="24" column="1">APPENDIX C: THE QUESTIONS ASKED OF THE PARTICIPANTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="240" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">What kind of phone do you have and how often do you use it? What do you use the phone for other than calling? What happens if you enter the wrong pin number to switch on the phone? What is in the telephone? What is in the SIM card? How is the information used? Do you know what the PIN code does? How do you think the telephone works? Is there a difference between messaging &amp; email? What happens to the ‘phone during the connection? Why does the battery go flat when you don't use the phone? What does the signal availability mean? What does it mean when the network is busy? What makes the battery life go down fastest? What do the bars on the phone mean?</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="241" page="24" column="1">113</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
