<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>0969a899fc74acdcaf02d6283dca45d7353f41a77a13fc0f819369d58fdc53d1</job>
    <base_name>62nt</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-84628-733-6_14">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0956-7143(94)90019-1</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library] On: 14 February</name>
          <aff id="2">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">At: 09:29 Publisher: Taylor</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Francis Informa Ltd Registered in England</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered office: Mortimer House</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Mortimer Street</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">London W1T 3JH</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">UK</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="9" confidence="possible">CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx10">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62nt.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62nt.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="11">Ethics,</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="13">Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20" id="12">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20</ext-link> The use of design patterns in overcoming misunderstandings in collaborative interaction design a b Klas Karlgren &amp; Robert Ramberg a Department of Learning, Informatics, Management and Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden b Department of Computer and Systems Sciences, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden Version of record first published: 01 Nov 2012.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">To cite</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="15">Journal</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="17">this article: Klas Karlgren &amp; Robert Ramberg (2012): The use of design patterns in overcoming misunderstandings in collaborative interaction design, CoDesign: International CoCreation in Design and the Arts, 8:4, 231-246 this article: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2012.734829" id="16">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2012.734829</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="18">of To link to</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19">PLEASE</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="20">SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="21">Full</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="22">This</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="24">terms and conditions of use: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-" id="23">http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-</ext-link> conditions article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial or systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, or distribution in any form to anyone is expressly forbidden.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="25">The that the</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="26">sources. demand,</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="27" confidence="possible">publisher does not give any warranty express or implied or make any representation contents will be complete or accurate or up to date. The accuracy of any instructions, formulae, and drug doses should be independently verified with primary The publisher shall not be liable for any loss, actions, claims, proceedings, or costs or damages whatsoever or howsoever caused arising directly or indirectly in connection with or arising out of the use of this material.</abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28">CoDesign Vol. 8, No. 4, December 2012, 231–246</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible">The use of design patterns in overcoming misunderstandings in collaborative interaction design Klas Karlgren a * and Robert Ramberg b a Department of Learning, Informatics, Management and Ethics, Karolinska Institutet, b Stockholm, Sweden; Department of Computer and Systems Sciences, Stockholm University, Stockholm, Sweden (Received 17 October 2011; final version received 25 September 2012) In collaborative design there is a need to create a shared understanding of design ideas and proposals. Misunderstandings and communication breakdowns often get in the way and need to be resolved. Little empirical research has addressed the use of design patterns in collaborative design work. An empirical study was carried out on students’ collaboration while working on design tasks. Data were analysed using interaction analysis focusing on how the participants resolved misunderstandings and communication breakdowns, and the role of design patterns. Particular attention was paid to gaps in the collaboration; situations where designers had difficulties understanding each other and how to continue the design work. One type of gap concerned difficulties seeing or finding solutions to problems. However, many gaps concerned how to define or frame problems underlying design proposals. The results contradict the conception that design patterns are examples serving the role of inspiration for reuse of design ideas: simply showing a pattern solution was not enough to resolve gaps. The main observations were that patterns had an important role in overcoming difficulties in discussions regarding rationales and problem framing, and explicitly referring to design patterns by their names was decisive for the patterns to become useful. Keywords: interaction design; design pattern; collaboration; misunderstanding; language use; gaps</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="2" column="1">Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="2" column="1">Designers have their own ways of thinking and communicating, as shown by recent design research ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Cross 2006</xref>). As the field of interaction design is young and a developing field it largely still lacks an established language and shared practice of judging design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Bardzell 2011</xref>), which poses a challenge for interaction designers as well as students. Interaction designers are involved in creating user interfaces but the primary object of interaction design is to design users’ interaction with a system and with others through the system. Moreover, in a broad sense, the object of design can be viewed as not only the interaction with a system but also the use of an interactive system. It is, for obvious reasons, difficult to picture, understand or foresee possible future interaction or future uses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Arvola 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Tholander et al. 2008</xref>).<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> It has been argued that for designers to develop their sense of design quality and to be able to express their ideas about design, designers need to develop a language (Lo  ̈ wgren and Stolterman 1998). Moreover, a design language forces designers to make their design ideas more precise (Lo  ̈ wgren and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Stolterman 1998</xref>). Typically, style guides, guidelines, heuristics, standards and design principles are employed to facilitate interaction design. However, they have come under criticism on several counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Mahemoff and Johnston 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Borchers 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Pemberton 2000</xref>): for their difficulty of interpretation, for being too simplistic, for the excessive effort required to find relevant sections, for requiring sophisticated interpretation, for the risks of neglecting or misinterpreting advice and guidelines, etc. Design patterns have been claimed to offer a richer resource and to add what is missing, e.g. in lists of guidelines. Patterns include the meta-information surrounding simple imperative instructions, drawing attention to the problem that the patterns solves, and conceiving of the solution to the problem as resolving conflicts in a field of interacting social and physical relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Pemberton 2000</xref>). A pattern is a three- part rule, which expresses a relation between a certain context, a problem and a solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Alexander 1979</xref>). The current interest in patterns is associated with Christopher Alexander who, in The timeless way of building and A pattern language, presented a number of archi- tectural patterns, as well as his theory of and attitude to architecture and planning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Alexander 1977</xref>, 1979). Alexander used a specific format to structure his design patterns, which were an attempt to document collective knowledge about urban design at different scales ranging from regions and cities, to buildings, rooms, and even to the detailed level of doorknobs. Other design fields such as software engineering, human–computer interaction (HCI) and interaction design have made similar efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Dearden and Finlay 2006</xref>). Within HCI and interaction design, various formats have been used to present design patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Fincher 2009</xref>). Common to the formats is that they present a problem that is related to the use of an artefact, a proven solution to the problem and a context (in terms of users, tasks, contexts of use, etc.) giving rise to the problem, as well as when the solution is considered suitable. One example is the Wizard pattern created by Martijn van Welie, intended to support users in performing complex tasks consisting of several steps which may be dependent on each other (van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Welie 2008</xref>). The pattern is presented in a highly abbreviated form below.<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> Empirical work on the use of design patterns is rather scarce. However, Griffiths and Pemberton (ndb) have described three approaches to incorporate a pattern language in interface design education, at the University of Brighton. The first is teaching about pattern languages and design, making connections to the debates on design theory in architecture and industrial design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Cross 1984</xref>). The second is teaching through a pattern language by letting students use a pattern language in practical exercises. Griffiths and Pemberton report that both the quality of discussions within design teams and the products were improved. Their third approach was encouraging students of interaction design to discover and define patterns for themselves. Identifying good patterns is difficult and the results were disappointing; suggestions stayed at the level of ungeneralised examples and lacked the abstraction necessary for pattern finding. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Chung et al. (2004)</xref> observed that patterns helped new and experienced designers unfamiliar with ubiquitous computing in generating and communicating ideas, and in avoiding design problems early in the design process. Although some research has been conducted on the use of design patterns, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Dearden and Finlay (2006)</xref> point to the importance of examining the use of patterns in carrying out design through empirical and observational studies, and demonstrating and evaluating the benefits that the use of patterns can have, in both design practice and design education. Arvola similarly argues for the need to look into the efficacy of interaction design patterns on design work in educational and other settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Arvola 2006</xref>). We wanted to understand in more detail what goes on in collaborative design discussions when using design patterns and investigate the role that patterns play in supporting design discourse and collaboration.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="37" page="2" column="1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email id="36">klas.karlgren@ki.se</email> ISSN 1571-0882 print/ISSN 1745-3755 online Ó 2012 Taylor &amp; Francis</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40" page="2" column="1"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2012.734829" id="38">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2012.734829</ext-link> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com" id="39">http://www.tandfonline.com</ext-link></outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="41" page="3" column="1">232</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="3" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="54" page="3" column="1">Wizard Problem: The user wants to achieve a single goal but several decisions need to be made before the goal can be achieved completely, which may not be known to the user. Solution: Take the user through the entire task one step at the time. Let the user step through the tasks and show which steps exist and which have been completed. Used when: A non-expert user needs to perform an infrequent complex task consisting of several subtasks where decisions need to be made in each subtask. The number of subtasks must be small, e.g. typically between about three and 10. The user wants to reach the overall goal but may not be familiar with or interested in the steps that need to be performed. The tasks can be ordered but are not always independent of each other, i.e. a certain task may need to be finished before the next task can be done. To reach the goal several steps need to be taken but the exact steps required may vary because of decisions made in previous steps.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="55" page="4" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="56" page="4" column="1">233</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="4" column="1">Analysing design discourse</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="4" column="1">Design processes can be investigated in many ways (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Cross et al. 1996</xref>). Our focus is on interactions and discourse between design students with a view to learning and developing competence emphasising the role of mastering the language use of a domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Karlgren and Ramberg 1996</xref>). Our analysis has a particular focus on the ‘gaps’ that occasionally occur in the collaborative design work; people usually interact on the assumption that certain premises are shared until they notice from utterances or other interactions that this is not the case. To bridge a gap, a current framing of the issue at hand needs to be made explicit, for instance by the use of clarifications, explanations, descriptions or justifications (Ma  ̈ kitalo et al. 2009). The framework is inspired by the work of Wickman and O  ̈ stman, who studied how university students manage gaps in the language games of science learning (Wickman and O  ̈ stman 1999, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Wickman 2004</xref>). We believe that focusing on language games and gaps is particularly suitable for analysing the domain of interaction design: the field is less established and less prescriptive than scientific disciplines and since interaction design is about creating novel artefacts, design activities are to a large extent characterised by a continuous need to negotiate, discuss and evaluate ideas and proposals where developing a language game is central and gaps are inevitably frequent. Wickman and O  ̈ stman (O  ̈ stman and Wickman 2001, Wickman and O  ̈ stman 2002) introduced four concepts inspired by Wittgenstein’s later writings about meaning-making. In a language game certain actions and language uses stand fast, which means that they are not questioned when we talk and act but are used as points of departure in encounters with the world in speech and in action–: not<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> everything can be questioned in a practice, or the practice would stop and we would no longer be able to communicate with each other. When people encounter something (utterances, artefacts, natural phenomena, etc.) during talk or action, a gap may occur. A gap thus amounts to noticing that a relation is needed for moving on. A gap can in practice be identified as a hesitation, as a question, etc. (O  ̈ stman and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Wickman 2001</xref>). By establishing relations to what stands fast, what is and what occurs in the encounter can be established and the relations may thereby fill the gap. ‘Gaps are situations where former similarities and differences will not suffice to establish meaning, that is situations where people establish or try to establish new relations to what already is standing fast’ (Wickman and O  ̈ stman 1999, p. 2).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="67" page="5" column="1">234</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="68" page="5" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="5" column="1">Method</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" page="5" column="1">A study was carried out involving four students of HCI and interaction design. The participants were in the final year of their study programmes. A number of design sessions and meetings were carefully planned: the designers worked in pairs and each pair first collaborated in creating a design proposal. These proposals were then shared with the other pair of designers, who were first given the opportunity to study the other pair’s proposals, then the two pairs collaboratively continued the development of the proposals. Each individual participant worked for 1.5 days and the entire experiment lasted for 2.5 days. The design meetings took four hours in total and were recorded on video. The participants attended a lecture on the history, theory and use of design patterns in general and in interaction design in particular. The lecture covered capturing and naming features of recurring design solutions, structuring design knowledge and creating pattern languages by relating patterns to each other. Different formats for presenting design patterns in interaction design and several concrete examples were also discussed. Eight design patterns were especially highlighted. The patterns were Swedish versions of interaction design patterns formulated by van Welie, Tidwell, Griffith and Pemberton, addressing navigation, selection, guidance/feedback and presentation, and they were based on van Welie’s format (Griffith and Pemberton nda, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Tidwell 1999</xref>, 2007, van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Welie and Trætteberg 2000</xref>, van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Welie 2008</xref>). The included patterns ranged from general patterns about how to structure entire websites to more detailed patterns. The following were included: Step-by-Step-Instructions, Navigating-between-Spaces, List Browser, Favourites, Grid Layout, Unambiguous Format (also called ‘Date Selector’), Warning and Progress indicator.<marker type="block"/> The design task The design task was to create a web-based travel ticket booking functionality for an (imaginary) company in the travel business. The assignment was fairly complex and intentionally not fully specified. The participants were allowed to work as they wished but the work was supposed to result in a digital prototype. The designers first worked in pairs and later together to come up with a design proposal and prototype.<marker type="block"/> Model for analysing the design discourse Analysing video data can make use of various analytical methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Derry et al. 2010</xref>). Our analysis draws upon ethnomethodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Garfinkel 1967</xref>) and conversation<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Sacks et al. 1974</xref>). To try to neutralise any preconceived notions of the authors, the viewing and transcribing of the video material was conducted both individually and in collaboration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Jordan and Henderson 1995</xref>). In our analysis we strove towards creating an account of how the designers collaboratively present and provide for their understanding through their talk and other actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Koschmann et al. 2007</xref>). The video data were transcribed in detail, focusing on talk, gestures, movement and positioning, as well as the development of design representations and use of artefacts. We paid particular attention to passages in the interaction and discourse where communicative breakdowns occurred; more specifically, explicit passages where explanations were asked for, with ‘what do you mean?’, or other more specific signs of misunderstandings and requests for elaborations. We also focused on less explicit signs of misunderstandings, often occurring as hesitations or other utterances calling for making things more explicit in the form of clarifications, explanations, etc. In terms of our analytical framework, we have looked for gaps in the design students’ interactions and the roles that design patterns have played in bridging these, i.e. how patterns were introduced and used as encounters or to build relations. More specifically, the video-recordings of each design meeting (each meeting lasting for roughly 65 minutes) were first analysed individually. The observations were then discussed among the authors. The gaps that were focused on were gaps that concerned design work and lingered more than just momentarily (not misunderstandings concerning other topics than design work or cases where the designers simply misheard each other), and in which design patterns were either explicitly mentioned or seemed to play a role in the design work. There are no established standards regarding how to transcribe video data, and researchers need to make pragmatic decisions about which transcription convention is best for a particular purpose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Jordan and Henderson 1995</xref>). In addition, there are several alternative modes for how to present results from ethnographic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Karlsson 2012</xref>). Decisions need to be made about how much and which kinds of data to present, which best demonstrate the points of the main observations. In this paper, the spoken language of the designers is in focus and we have therefore, for the sake of readability, not included most of the data regarding gestures (such as pointing at or looking at various parts of screens and each other), positions of participants vis-a`-vis each other and screens, distances to screens, use of artefacts, etc. In cases where such data are needed to understand the interactions of the designers, we have added information in parentheses in the excerpts.<marker type="block"/> Analysis of collaborative design work Overall, a continuous dialogue between the designers characterised the design meetings. However, in the more detailed analyses of the dialogues we observed that the designers ran into difficulties when framing design problems, finding solutions to problems, or more generally when trying to communicate ideas or understand each other. Following each author’s individual analysis, the observations were jointly discussed and any differences in interpretations were paid particular attention to until consensus was reached regarding types of gaps, their extensions over time and the roles of design patterns. Typically, these deliberations resulted in six or seven serious gaps being agreed upon for each design meeting; these gaps thus concerned design work and lingered more than just momentarily, and patterns seemed to play a<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> role in addressing these. Below, observations and the analysis of the collaboration between the designers E and F, and G and H are exemplified.<marker type="block"/> Example 1: Gaps are bridged by referring to design patterns The two designers E and F are discussing how to structure the information in the system. Ideas from design patterns appear which are discussed in the context of problems found in F’s design proposal. F describes her design proposal and explains her rationale and says that she considered tabs to structure the information on the page in line with the Navigating-between-Spaces pattern because she is concerned for the elderly, who may have difficulties reading on cluttered pages.<marker type="block"/> E wants to know how users are allowed to move around in the prototype, seeing an interaction problem if the system is realised as F suggests. A gap seems to appear here – they seem not to understand each other: E sees that there could be problems with F’s design proposal that F does not see and F does not see what E had planned. E’s analysis of the problem is based on the Step-by-Step-Instructions design pattern which describes cases when users want to reach a goal and need to proceed through several steps which are dependent on each other. E elaborates extensively and has to spend quite some time explaining the severity of the potential interaction problems in the existing design proposal before they go on to try to solve them with a new design. After a lengthy discussion, E stages an ‘encounter’ to illustrate the problems in F’s proposal (line 2, below). According to E, users should be allowed to freely go back to previous steps, but not move ahead as freely since there are dependencies between the different tabs. On line 3, F seems to follow E’s reasoning and suggests that an OK button should be included.<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> E has managed to make F become aware of the problem (i.e. a gap) that he noticed and he suggests relations to bridge that gap – on lines 12 and 14 he suggests that users should confirm by clicking an OK button. At the end, on line 17, F contributes to the design proposal by suggesting an addition of a feedback functionality described in the Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern, thereby suggesting that they have a shared understanding of what they are building and which problems they are solving. E’s explanation is indexical (‘If you’ve arrived here, then you can go here, here and here . . . ’), based on pointing at the different tabs (see line 12 and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>) without any explicit reference to the more abstract ideas in the pattern. A plausible<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> hypothesis is that if E had explicitly referred to the Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern when discussing the dependency issues then they would probably have been helped by the pattern. Now they have had to reinvent part of the pattern while working. Later, however, they do refer explicitly to the design patterns (see lines 18– 19 below).<marker type="block"/> F realises that what they have created is based on two design patterns and seems enthusiastic about this finding (line 18). They go on to refer to parts of the pattern later.<marker type="block"/> Now that both are aware of their design work relating to the patterns they seem to be able to make use of that, referring to elements (numbers of ‘steps’) in the patterns without any need to explain these to each other (lines 21–23). F also brings up the need to indicate where, on which step, users are as described in the Step-by-Step- Instructions pattern (line 23).<marker type="block"/> Example 2: Discussing rationale by referring to a design pattern Later, the design proposal of E and F is handed over to G and H. They have difficulties understanding it and the rationale behind it. But at one point H recognises that E and F have used the Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern (line 1) and mentions this to his co-designer.<marker type="block"/> The recognition of the design pattern leads to G and H also discussing dependencies between steps and structuring information. H re-creates the underlying rationale behind the design (line 2), i.e. they not only identified the pattern but also discussed why it was used.<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> As H has explicitly mentioned the Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern (on line 1), H is then able to make references to elements of it (‘steps’ on line 2). G catches on and is able to ascribe rationale to the design proposal (line 3) without having to do a bottom–up analysis of each part of the proposal. The pattern is now a common ground to relate to. H continues explicating the rationale behind the design (line 4). Even later, G is able to refer to elements of the design pattern without difficulty (‘steps’, line 5 below).<marker type="block"/> Example 3: Presenting a counter-example to illustrate a gap solved by a pattern E suggests a solution based on the Navigating-between-Spaces pattern to solve a problem concerning layout and structuring of information as there is too much information to fit on one page (the pattern suggests that information on the page is grouped into tabs). But F does not quite follow what is meant.<marker type="block"/> F appears to be unaware of the proposal being a pattern and views it solely as a discussion about which headers to use and therefore, once again, E seems to have difficulties explaining a problem to F and a gap related to problem framing appears. E suggested the Navigating-between-Spaces pattern but without discussing its rationale. F does not see why E suggests this solution and even perhaps that the proposal solves a problem. After some more discussion E notices this, and he then constructs an ‘encounter’ by describing what would happen if the pattern is not followed (line 3). This counter-example illustrates the gap and is an elaboration of the problem solved by the pattern; available display space is limited and cannot show all the needed information.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> In this way, E manages to put focus on the problem and this in turn leads to their eventually agreement on the pattern solution.<marker type="block"/> Example 4: Two parallel gaps resolved using a solution from a design pattern Here, E and F are working on a subtask concerning dates; they discuss how users who are booking trips can choose dates in the system. F points at her proposal on the screen showing drop-down menus for filling in the date of departure. She seems to see a potential interaction problem and suggests a modification: it would be better to let users fill in dates freely and not have to choose between predefined dates, which may be considered arduous. Here, a gap consists in E and F focusing on different problems underlying two design proposals. E is worried since E sees a problem in F’s new proposal of letting users write dates freely. E brings up his original solution and points at the calendar function (line 1 below) which is used for picking dates. E manages to solve the problem from his perspective. On line 2 below, F’s question shows, however, that she has not seen which problem E’s proposal solves. Being concerned with the risks associated with free text input, E therefore offers a rationale (lines 3 and 5 below) by referring to future interaction. E is basing it on the Unambiguous Format pattern, although not mentioning the pattern name explicitly (yet). According to the pattern, it can be used whenever structured data such as dates need to be entered into a system and when unexpected formats may cause mistakes or confusion.<marker type="block"/> F is not satisfied with E’s proposal since it does not solve the problem she has pointed out (Figure 2). Later, F not only proposes an alternative solution but starts explaining the design problem as she sees it (lines 6 and 8 below), and she thereby offers a relation to fill in the gap.<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> At this point, E has become aware that F is not misunderstanding his proposal but that she is worried about another problem (a broader user group, line 6 above), which forces them to find a solution which solves both problems. Now they are instead confronted by another challenge: what to do about the two conflicting goals. E has consulted the Unambiguous Format pattern and shows an example which he has found in it that he thinks has a good alternative (line 9 below) and which handles both of their problems by combining his calendar and allowing free text input.<marker type="block"/> Once again, the example illustrates the importance of explaining the problems underlying the design proposals to each other, thereby creating a common understanding allowing the two designers to move on with their design work.<marker type="block"/> Example 5: Discussion about design patterns In this example, G and H talk about design patterns. Although H has based much of his reasoning on design patterns in suggesting improvements, G does not see the point in them and does not seem to have a clear understanding of what they are. H tries to bring them up while G says she already knows the ideas ‘by heart’.<marker type="block"/> On lines 4 and 6, G appears to view design patterns as simply being ‘models’ or ‘standards’ based on what typical design solutions such as web pages look like. But viewing design patterns simply as ‘models’ or as ‘common-sense’ standards is not likely to result in making use of the full potential of the other elements such as the relations between solutions and problems in design patterns.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="80" page="6" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="81" page="6" column="1">235</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="89" page="7" column="1">236</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="90" page="7" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="93" page="7" column="1">Time 08:09 1 F: . . . or, then I was considering tabs . . . because I was already considering kind of like . . . like my dad who is elderly . . . they become . . . they can’t see anything with their small portable computers that they have . . . and then they have to have . . . they can’t see . . . (F explains that she was considering tabs)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="95" page="7" column="1">Time 10:07 2 E: *laughter* That’s right . . . here. *pause* Well . . . the problem is that if there are . . . that is . . . , if there are several that have not been filled in . . . then where are you thrown in that case? . . . Mmmm But, that is why I think that if we use . . . kind of . . . tabs . . . that . . . 3 F: Then there has to be an ‘OK’. 4 E: That is, forward is kind of like ‘tap’, ‘tap’, ‘tap’ (drawing a dashed line on the Smartboard) . . . well, you know . . . 5 F: A bit greyed? 6 E: Yeah, or dashed . . . 7 F: I think kind of more like this: you should have the opportunity to go back and modify. Now you have to go back with a button down here . . . or what? 8 E: Ahh, yeah. (E seems to realise that F has not fully followed his line of reasoning)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="96" page="8" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="97" page="8" column="1">237</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="98" page="8" column="1">9 F: That’s not what I thought . . . I thought that you should be allowed to jump there . . . 10 E: Yeah, you are allowed to jump . . . but the thing is that if you allow . . . If you allow . . . (F points at the tabs) 11 F: Or both. 12 E: If you’ve arrived here, then you can go here, here and here and jump to wherever you like. If you’ve arrived here, then you can jump to here, here, here . . . . . . back and forth . . . but you can not . . . if you have arrived here . . . you can not jump to here . . . 13 F: Yes, exactly. (F seems to accept E’s argument and confirms it) 14 E: . . . without clicking there. *laughter* 15 F: An ‘OK’ there then. (confirms E’s suggestion) 16 E: Yes, exactly. 17 F: And then one ought to have, we could have one of those that you had . . . one of those: ‘This-is-how-far-you’ve-gotten-so-far’.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62nt.page_008.image_02.png" thmb="62nt.page_008.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="102" page="8" column="1">Figure 1. Designer E points out dependency problems that may occur in the design proposal.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="103" page="9" column="1">238</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="104" page="9" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="106" page="9" column="1">Time 36:13 18 F: So how do we explain this? The tab system is the ‘over-arching’ (on the top of the screen). Look we have a damn good thing here. Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern and Navigating between Spaces system, we’re using both! 19 E: Yeah.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="108" page="9" column="1">Time 43:02 20 E: . . . this could be a good thing. 21 F: Well, the question is whether it really is step 1, since you can go back. 22 E: This is step 1, isn’t it? . . . At least the way we have designed it. 23 F: Yes, but somewhere so that one realises that . . . unless just tabs are enough I would like if it said ‘step 1 of 4’ or something like that . . . or 4 within parentheses.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="111" page="9" column="1">Time: 04:22 1 H: Well there was one, the Step-by-Step-Instructions pattern which was the more over-arching. As I understood it, steps 1–5 are somehow supposed to make it clear to the users that there are five steps.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="113" page="10" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="114" page="10" column="1">239</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="115" page="10" column="1">Time 05:08 2 H: And then this thing about navigating, the idea is surely that one is supposed to see the other steps ahead of you but you’re not supposed to be able to go to those steps until you’ve filled in everything correctly on the step that you’re on, if you know what I mean, so that you can use them to go back with in a simple way. 3 G: So that you have an idea about where you are. 4 H: Exactly, you see what you’ve done, where you are and what remains.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="117" page="10" column="1">Time 16:40 5 G: The question is whether we should do the last three steps as well?</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="119" page="10" column="1">Time 16:57 1 E: Do we want Navigating between Spaces? (E starts drawing) First ‘Temaresor’, perhaps? (the name of the imaginary company) 2 F: We are only supposed to do the booking part, right? So it should perhaps say ‘Booking’ at the top?</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="121" page="10" column="1">Time 17:48 3 E: The other alternative is to put everything on one screen. But that can be strange, arduous. 4 F: I think it can be arduous . . . Firstly, we must get it straight so that one knows where to go . . . and then I am thinking about people who can’t see so well. 5 E: OK!</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="122" page="11" column="1">240</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="123" page="11" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="126" page="11" column="1">Time 07:26 1 E: . . . I think the best would be to have something like this . . . 2 F: Because it’s easier to . . . read? 3 E: . . . because it is . . . because it can’t go wrong 4 F: . . . no (She agrees; meaning: ‘no, that’s true’) 5 E: because I can . . . if I write ‘two’ with letters then it might become . . . be interpreted in another way than if I write ‘two’ with numbers . . . that is, it becomes more programming-like *pause* But that may be an entirely different thing . . . and, then they don’t have to use them . . . that is . . . they can simply click their way on.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="128" page="11" column="1">Time 31:25 6 F: . . . I don’t think that it is so clear. . . . (laughs) . . . ’cause I’m thinking about . . . I’m thinking that everyone should be able to use it . . . users who are a bit older users won’t get that . . . They have to have one of those (points at a drop-down menu) – or – write (the date) themselves. That’s the way it is. 7 E: Wait . . . OK, I’m thinking about* 8 F: My mother would never understand. She would just go ‘Uh, what? November, December? I don’t wanna go in November!’ (the preselected value).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="129" page="12" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="130" page="12" column="1">241</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx131">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62nt.page_012.image_03.png" thmb="62nt.page_012.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="132" page="13" column="1">242</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="133" page="13" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="135" page="13" column="1">Time 32:37 9 E: this is pretty good. 10 F: . . . month, year . . . 11 E: so you can either . . . Twelve-0-four . . . (demonstrating the possibility of free text input of month (twelve) and year (04)) 12 F: so you can write there first then? 13 E: Exactly . . . and then it chooses, or it does like that . . . 14 E: they recommended that as a design pattern. . . . Or did you want to have something even more specific? 15 F: There, at least, you can write yourself. 16 E: Exactly.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="138" page="13" column="1">Time 16:01 1 H: I don’t know how much connection there is to . . . you know arguments from these principles, and these patterns? 2 G: Naw, my way of evaluating, I guess, is to pretend to be a user. 3 H: Exactly. 4 G: I didn’t look so much at the design models (sic), it feels like I already know them by heart. If you’ve seen a number of web pages. They all look alike. 5 H: . . . then you know what usually goes wrong and what annoys you. 6 G: There’s a standard, I suppose that’s what design patterns are.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="140" page="14" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="141" page="14" column="1">243</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="142" page="14" column="1">Discussion and concluding remarks</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156" page="14" column="1">Now and then, the designers ran into problems and misunderstandings. This is not surprising when two or more people are collaborating in creating a rather complex system. One type of gap concerned difficulties seeing or finding solutions to problems (‘how do we design this?’). However, the analysis showed that many of the gaps in the data were of a different kind, recurring over and over again: these gaps concerned how to define or frame problems. Such gaps involved difficulties describing and defining which problem was to be solved or avoided, or which problems were solved by a particular proposal, and were rather about building a shared understanding concerning the framing of design problems, understanding each other’s problems or seeing the problem that others were focusing on. Considerable time was spent on convincing and explaining problems, creating counter-examples to highlight problems, and so on. Regarding the role of design patterns in the collaborative design work, two main observations can be highlighted. First, and contrary to common belief, the main role of the design patterns was not simply an ‘inspirational’ role, which is a role often taken for granted (see Example 5) and emphasised in the literature (Lo  ̈ wgren 2005). As seen in Examples 1, 3 and 4, the discussions were to a large extent about the problems underlying the proposals, rather than figuring out new solutions. Rather than simply being inspirational resources for reuse of design ideas, the design patterns were used as tools or resources for framing design problems. Moreover, designers’ misunderstandings about each other’s proposals were not resolved simply by showing a pattern solution to a co-designer (see Examples 3 and 4). More decisive was that designers first agreed on which problem was to be solved; once the designers agreed on framing the problems they were able to move on to proposing designs which resolved the problems. Here, patterns can play an important role beyond the obvious one of providing inspiration and ready-made solutions, by providing a structured format of relating problems to solutions. Secondly, not until designers realised that they were talking about a solution based on a design pattern were they able to make use of the pattern in a constructive manner. Therefore, referring to the names of the patterns was crucial for the patterns to become useful resources; not until the names were used explicitly did their co- designers catch on, as in Examples 1 and 2. Again, the inspiration brought about by simply showing a design solution based on a pattern was not enough; the designers needed to understand that the solution represented a design pattern to make use of it. Again, this observation challenges the view of patterns as simply being ‘inspirational’ resources. Design is about creating things and ultimately design work must be judged in the light of what it results in, i.e. what is produced. It could be argued there is no clear mapping between the quality of design dialogues and quality of the produced artefacts. But it could be assumed that there is a general connection (design teams that constantly get stuck on misunderstandings are less likely to produce high quality artefacts). Design dialogues cannot be expected to be without any misunderstandings whatsoever, but many misunderstandings can be avoided and those that do take place can be handled in a more or less fruitful way in the sense that design work can proceed rather than getting stuck in extended explanations and argumentation owing to a lack of adequate conceptual tools. Quality in collaboration can thus be seen as a capability of a design team and its members to recognise, avoid and handle possible misunderstandings between the designers. <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> The results found here are in line with previous study by Griffiths and Pemberton (ndb), which reported that the quality of discussions was improved in exercises using Tidwell’s HCI pattern language. As in Griffiths and Pemberton’s study, the students did not analyse the problem descriptions in depth or create their own patterns. Explicit use of the design pattern terminology was often notably lacking. As seen in Example 1 (line 12), the language was from time to time instead extremely indexical, relying on pointing and gestures and incomprehensible to anyone outside the immediate context:<marker type="block"/> Nevertheless, they seem to understand each other, but not until after a long and laborious discussion with numerous misunderstandings. The positive role of vagueness and ‘sketchy talk’ has been highlighted: ambiguity may introduce room for negotiation and in conversations between architects and building users vagueness may draw clients into the designing activity itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="148" class="deo:Reference">McDonnell 2010</xref>). We acknowledge that the openness to possibilities which is inherent to sketches is important to design language as well, as it invites sketchers as well as the audiences of the sketchers to become engaged regardless of whether they are clients or co-designers, as in our case. As pointed out by Luck, while explicit design knowledge can be available through codes and guides (and patterns) it cannot be completely represented in a propositional, non-contextual form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Luck 2003</xref>). The focus of this paper has, however, rather been on designers’ difficulties in making themselves understood and avoiding or repairing misunderstandings. Here, design patterns may play an important role as they provide a structure between some of the most crucial aspects of design proposals: they make explicit the connection between a design solution and the problem solved and they can thereby be a useful tool to resolve misunderstandings regarding these links. We readily acknowledge that a risk of any terminology is that established concepts risk inhibiting creativity and fossilising design thinking. Moreover, it is certainly the case that misunderstandings can provide valuable learning opportunities involving clarifications of ideas and positions as well as opportunities to explain and try out design ideas, especially in educational settings. However, as discussed, when pattern solutions were suggested without referring to their names explicitly there was a risk of misunderstanding simply because others missed which design problems were being solved. Conversely, referring to pattern names is a way of signalling that behind a proposal lies a line of reasoning and a rationale that can be shared and debated. Hence, at least in a pedagogical context, the use of the existing design pattern vocabulary in itself is an indication of quality. The key is thus that design students familiarise themselves with the terminology, refer to it explicitly but at the same time retain a critical and independent attitude towards the ideas presented in the patterns.<marker type="block"/> Concluding remarks Constructing problem analyses is certainly hard work, demanding creative thought, and it is difficult to get students to talk about their design proposals in terms of<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> design patterns and their elements. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="154" class="deo:Reference">Alexander (1979)</xref> says: ‘many people find it hard to make their design ideas precise . . . [and] . . . are unwilling to express them with the precision needed to make them into patterns’ and it ‘is at least as hard as anything in theoretical physics’ (p. 261). We agree with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="155" class="deo:Reference">Guy (2005)</xref> that the ideas implicit in some patterns may appear folksy and ahistorical. And to us the value of design patterns does not lie in that they supposedly offer timeless solutions to interaction design problems. But using a pattern format to make explicit the problems solved by design proposals can certainly be (timelessly) useful to avoid getting stuck in recurring design discussion gaps.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144" page="15" column="1">244</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="145" page="15" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="147" page="15" column="1">E: If you’ve arrived here, then you can go here, here, and here and jump to wherever you like. If you’ve arrived here, then you can jump to here, here, here . . . . . . back and forth . . . but you can not . . . if you have arrived here . . . you can not jump to here . . . . F: Yes, exactly.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="152" page="16" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="153" page="16" column="1">245</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="157" page="16" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="158" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">We would like to thank the anonymous reviewers and the editors for constructive suggestions that have improved this article. We would also like to thank the participants of the study reported in the article. This work was funded by a grant from the Swedish Research Council, Educational Research.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="159" page="16" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="16" column="1">Alexander, C., 1977. A pattern language. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="16" column="1">Alexander, C., 1979. The timeless way of building. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="16" column="1">Arvola, M., 2005. Shades of use: the dynamics of interaction design for sociable use. PhD thesis. Linko  ̈ ping University.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="16" column="1">Arvola, M., 2006. Interaction design patterns for computers in sociable use. International Journal of Computer Applications in Technology, 25, 128–139.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="16" column="1">Bardzell, J., 2011. Interaction criticism: an introduction to the practice. Interacting with Computers, 23, 604–621.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="16" column="1">Borchers, J.O., 2000. Interaction design patterns: twelve theses. In: Position paper for the workshop pattern languages for interaction design: building momentum CHI2000, 2–3 April. The Hague, Netherlands. New York: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" page="16" column="1">Chung, E.S., et al., 2004. Development and evaluation of emerging design patterns for ubiquitous computing [electronic version]. Human–Computer Interaction Institute, Paper 70, 233–242. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://repository.cmu.edu/hcii/70." id="166">http://repository.cmu.edu/hcii/70.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="16" column="1">Cross, N., 1984. Developments in design methodology. Chichester: John Wiley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Cross, N., 2006. Forty years of design research. Design Research Quarterly, 1 (2).</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="16" column="1">Cross, N., Christiaans, H., and Dorst, K., 1996. Analysing design activity. Delft University of Technology.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="16" column="1">Dearden, A. and Finlay, J., 2006. Pattern languages in HCI: a critical review. Human– Computer Interaction, 21, 49–102.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Derry, S.J., et al., 2010. Conducting video research in the learning sciences: guidance on selection, analysis, technology, and ethics. Journal of the Learning Sciences, 19, 3–53.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="16" column="1">Fincher, S., 2009. The pattern gallery. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/" id="173">http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/people/staff/</ext-link> saf/patterns/gallery.html#D [Accessed 15 March 2012].</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="16" column="1">Garfinkel, H., 1967. Studies in ethnomethodology. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="16" column="1">Griffiths, R.N. and Pemberton, L., nd a. Don’t write guidelines write patterns! Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cmis.brighton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/guidelinesdraft.html" id="176">http://www.cmis.brighton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/guidelinesdraft.html</ext-link> [Accessed 26 January 2007].</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="16" column="1">Griffiths, R.N. and Pemberton, L., nd b. Teaching usability design through pattern language. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.it.bton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/CHIpaper.html" id="178">http://www.it.bton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/CHIpaper.html</ext-link> [Accessed 26 January 2007].</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="16" column="1">Guy, E.S. (2005). Designing activity with patterns (Part III in the Ph.D. thesis ‘‘From rollout to appropriation changing practices of development and use during a groupware project’’). University of Brighton, Brighton.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">Jordan, B. and Henderson, A., 1995. Interaction analysis: foundations and practice. Journal of the Learning Sciences, 4, 39–103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="17" column="1">Karlgren, K. and Ramberg, R., 1996. Language use and conceptual change in learning. In: European conference on artificial intelligence in education (EuroAIED), 30 September–2 October, Lisbon, Portugal. Lisbon, Portugal: Edic  ̧ o  ̃ es Colibri, 45–51.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="17" column="1">Karlsson, G., 2012. Instructional technologies in science education: students’ scientific reasoning in collaborative classroom activities. PhD, University of Gothenburg.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="17" column="1">Koschmann, T., Stahl, G., and Zemel, A., 2007. The video analyst’s manifesto (or the implications of Garfinkel’s policies for studying instructional practice in design-based research). In: R. Goldman et al., eds. Video research in the learning sciences. New York: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="188" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Lo  ̈ wgren, J., 2005. Inspirational patterns for embodied interaction. In: Nordic design research conference (Nordes), 29–31 May 2005, Copenhagen. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.nordes" id="187">http://www.nordes</ext-link>. org/old/index.html [Accessed 15 March 2012].</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="189" page="17" column="1">Lo  ̈ wgren, J. and Stolterman, E., 1998. Design av Informationsteknik: materialet utan egenskaper. Lund: Studentlitteratur. [In Swedish. English version published as Thoughtful interaction design. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.].</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Luck, R., 2003. Dialogue in participatory design. Design Studies, 24, 523–535.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="191" page="17" column="1">Mahemoff, M.J. and Johnston, L.J., 1998. Principles for a usability-oriented pattern language. In: OZCHI ‘98, 29 November–4 December, Adelaide. Los Alamitos, CA: IEEE Computer Society Press, 132–139.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="17" column="1">Ma  ̈ kitalo, A  ̊ ., Jakobsson, A., and Sa  ̈ ljo  ̈ , R., 2009. Learning to reason in the context of socioscientific problems – exploring the demands on students in ‘new’ classroom activities. In: K. Kumpulainen, C.E. Hmelo-Silver and M. Ce  ́ sar, eds. Investigating classroom interaction. Rotterdam: Sense Publishers, 7–26.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="193" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">McDonnell, J., 2010. Slow collaboration: some uses of vagueness, hesitation and delay in design collaborations. Bonn: International Institute for Socio-Informatics.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="17" column="1">O  ̈ stman, L. and Wickman, P.-O., 2001. Practical epistemology, learning and socialisation. In: 82nd Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association (AERA), Seattle.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="17" column="1">Pemberton, L., 2000. The promise of pattern languages for interaction design. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cmis.brighton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/HF2000.html" id="195">http://www.cmis.brighton.ac.uk/staff/lp22/HF2000.html</ext-link> [Accessed 26 January 2007].</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="17" column="1">Sacks, H., Schegloff, E.A., and Jefferson, G., 1974. Simplest systematics for the organization of turn-taking for conversation. Language, 50, 696–735.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="17" column="1">Tholander, J., et al., 2008. Where all the interaction is – sketching in interaction design as an embodied practice. In: Paper presented at the designing interactive systems (DIS2008)25– 27 February 2008, Cape Town, South Africa. New York, NY: ACM, 445–454.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="17" column="1">Tidwell, J., 1999. COMMON GROUND: a pattern language for human–computer interface design. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.mit.edu/*jtidwell/interaction_patterns.html" id="199">http://www.mit.edu/*jtidwell/interaction_patterns.html</ext-link> [Accessed 15 March 2012].</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="17" column="1">Tidwell, J., 2007. UI patterns and techniques. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.time-tripper.com/" id="201">http://www.time-tripper.com/</ext-link> uipatterns/Introduction [Accessed 27 January 2007].</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="17" column="1">van Welie, M., 2008. A pattern library for interaction design. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.welie" id="203">http://www.welie</ext-link>. com/ [Accessed 15 March 2012].</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="17" column="1">van Welie, M. and Trætteberg, H., 2000. Interaction patterns in user interfaces. In: 7th Pattern languages of programs conference (PLoP 2000), 13–16 August 2000, Monticello, Illinois. St. Louis, MO: Washington University.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="17" column="1">Wickman, P.-O., 2004. The practical epistemologies of the classroom: a study of laboratory work. Science Education, 88, 325–344.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="17" column="1">Wickman, P.-O. and O  ̈ stman, L., 1999. University students during practical work: can we make the learning process intelligible? In: Paper presented at the second international conference of the European Science Education Research Association (ESERA), 31 August– 4 September 1999, Kiel, Germany. Dordrecht, The Netherlands: Kluwer, 319–324.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="17" column="1">Wickman, P.-O. and O  ̈ stman, L., 2002. Learning as discourse change: a sociocultural mechanism. Science Education, 86, 601–623.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="182" page="17" column="1">246</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="183" page="17" column="1">K. Karlgren and R. Ramberg</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
