<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e780dab26ef1cf5f5b0b060de94d43e9a5b1169f08af04e21d54d713ee7f7a88</job>
    <base_name>62rc</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/0747936041423253">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/springerreference_168660</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Toward a Participatory Design Approach to Service Design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Daniela Sangiorgi</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">INDACO _ Faculty of Design Politecnico di Milano Via Durando 38/A, 20158 Milano, Italy +390223995918 <email id="3">daniela.sangiorgi@polimi.it</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">This paper introduces service design as a potential Participatory Design (PD) theme. It proposes that the success of designing good services can be increased by including the perspectives and practices of the future service participants into the design process. Through the description of an action-research project, the paper explores the potentials and limitations of using an ethnographic approach and Activity Theory to frame the service design process and interpret the complexity of services.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="6" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">Service design, service encounter, Activity Theory, ethnography</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="13">Brendon Clark</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="1" column="1">In this paper we introduce service design as a potential Participatory Design (PD) theme. We describe an action-research project initiated under the assumption that services can and should be an object of design and that service design could benefit from the incorporation of PD principles and practices. A main objective of the research project was to introduce these concepts to our industrial partners through the development and use of service design tools derived from ethnography and activity theory. Our contribution places itself within a research field that studies services starting from the interaction moments between the user and the supplier system, the so-called service encounter [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="9" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. The service encounter refers to the period of time during which a consumer directly interacts with a service [II] . One of the main characteristics of a service encounter is the active role users play during the interaction. Users are considered as service active participants as they bring their resources, competencies and capacities into the interaction. Their contributions are crucial for service success. Services are therefore co-produced by users and suppliers and should be viewed as a type of partnership. Some of the most elusive aspects of designing an intangible service that is co-produced by users and suppliers during a service encounter are to identify the object of design and finding a way to explain that to others. Services are complex social systems made up of situated activities where people behave and interact following and negotiating predefined roles and rules and using available tools and information. The design of a service refers to envisioning the service encounter and providing an interaction<marker type="block"/> In PDC-04 Proceedings of the Participatory Design Conference, Vol 2, Toronto, Canada, July 27-31, 2004, under a Creative Commons license. CPSR, P.O. Box 717, Palo Alto, CA 94302. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.cpsr.org" id="11">http://www.cpsr.org</ext-link> ISBN 0-9667818-3-X</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="1" column="2">Mads Clausen Institute University of Southern Denmark Grundvigts Aile 150, Sonderborg, Denmark +45 6550 1667 <email id="14">brendon@mci.sdu.dk</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" page="1" column="2">pla(form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="16" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>] (made up of the physical tools and signs, people's competencies and roles, the provided information and interaction rules) that frames and supports the way service participants interact. A guiding hypothesis throughout our project is that the success of designing good services can be increased by alleviating potential conflicts during the service encounter through synchronizing the perspectives, goals and existing practices and capacities of service participants. To address this, the perspectives and practices of the service participants should therefore be included in the design process. It is our contention that models and tools can help service designers understand and handle this kind of complexity, and help them facilitate the involvement of other stakeholders throughout the design process. After describing the context of our research and introducing how we included service participants in the design process, we will further discuss what we have found to be the value and challenges of using an ethnographic approach and Activity Theory to frame the design process and interpret the design object.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="18" confidence="possible" page="1" column="2">2. CONTEXT</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">3.2 Design activities</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" page="3" column="1">Toward the end of the project we held a 2-day service design workshop as the main design event during the action-research project. The workshop provided us with the opportunity to introduce contextual representations [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="46" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>] of service participants into the design activities conducted with representatives of our industrial partners to actively enVISion potential design encounters. Inspired by the "design by doing" participatory approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="47" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] we acted as the workshop facilitators proposing design materials and "hands-on experiences" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="48" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] to collaboratively design service ideas with the workshop participants.<marker type="block"/> The design activities aimed at defining what kind of services Danfoss could offer to supermarkets in order to improve the cold chain maintenance activities while incorporating service participants' needs and perspectives. We therefore faced the challenge of how to incorporate the service participants' perspectives and practices into design activities using the categories from Activity Theory and the exploratory ethnographic inquiry, the part of the workshop we will address in this paper. In line with our understanding that active workshop participation should be based on an appropriation process of the contextual data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="50" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], we held two activities as a way of facilitating the sharing and personal interpretation of the information we had collected:</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="52" page="3" column="1">Activity</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="53" page="3" column="1">portraits</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">System Map discussion. We had prepared four poster-sized maps that synthetically represented the Activity System of each of the four main organizational contexts we visited. (2 supermarkets, I technical service contractor, I education center). During this session, we briefly introduced the Activity System concept and then used the posters as mediating tools exchange information and stimulate conversation. Service Participant Appropriation. We had prepared written and short video clips for each of service participants we had interviewed. After the maps discussion, the workshop participants were each asked to read the portraits and watch the video of two people and then return to the group to report what they had discovered and discuss the various service participants.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" page="3" column="1">The context appropriation activities and tools were intended to level the workshop participants' knowledge of the cold chain system and actors before they engaged in idea generation activities. We used this background knowledge together with another tool, the issue cards, as a basis for the service idea generation activities. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The issue cards, inspired by the video card game developed by Buur and Soendegaard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="58" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>], used the Activity Theory concept of contradiction. The cards represented, through a brief text and a representative image, existing problematic situations and conflicting perspectives of the service context and participants. We used the cards as a stimulus for a brainstorming activity with the aim of identifying what kind of services could be provided to supermarkets in order to address the contradictions.<marker type="block"/> One of the main results of this collective reflection was identifying that many of the conflicts came from the opposite and co-existing demands of local versus remote control or supermarket staff empowerment versus the atomization of work. For instance, the push for local responsibility and awareness of food quality issues (by a large supermarket chain's Quality Manager and the State Agency), in contrast to an increase in delegation of remote responsibility for refrigeration system efficiency and maintenance (as favored by the supermarket managers, the supermarket chain's technical office and the external service contractors).<marker type="block"/> During the following design activities for envisioning potential service encounters, workshop participants proposed service ideas that focused on alleviating these existing conflicts of exigencies and perspectives working on the main theme of the "integration between local and remote".</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rc.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62rc.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="57" page="3" column="2">Figure 3. Activity System Map</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" page="1" column="2">The "cold chain service design project" was conducted for 7 months, from December 2002 to June 2003 , as a collaboration between the INDACO department of Politecnico di Milano, the Mads Clausen Institute at the University of Southern Denmark, and Danfoss Refrigeration and Air Conditioning. The project was initiated and developed by Daniela Sangiorgi, an industrial design PhD student from Politecnico di Milano, in collaboration with Brendon Clark, a research assistant from the Mads Clauden Institute with an MA in anthropology. The main goal of the collaboration was to explore the relevance of a service design approach for practical application in a business setting. After a pre-study in Milan, Italy, the project was conducted in Denmark based out of the Mads Clausen Institute where the User Centered Design group, led by Jacob Buur, provided support in field studies, workshop organization and facilitation, and industry contacts. For this project, the cold chain in a supermarket context includes the human and technical efforts that regulate the temperature of meat, dairy, and frozen food products from the time they enter the store until the customer leaves with the product. While Danfoss RlAC has a long tradition of supplying refrigeration components and supporting products, they are not an established service provider. The goal of this project was to introduce and test the service design approach with Danfoss RI AC and the Mads Clausen Institute's User Centered Design Group, while exploring and designing potential cold chain maintenance service ideas.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="20" page="1" column="2">148</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="21" page="2" column="1">"</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="22" page="2" column="1">Figure 1. The supermarket "Cold Chain" The cold chain service context includes: the equipment In the</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">supermarket that maintains and measures temperature (refrigerators, freezers, thermometers, remote monitoring systems and their software); the people that come in contact with the products and equipment (the employees from a variety of departments including frozen foods, deli, produce, bakery, dairy); and in-house management, technicians and external contractors (the people and policies that monitor the legal and health requirements including the people who educate and train the people in all of these positions, and the state health regulators).</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="24" page="2" column="1">3. DESIGN PROCESS</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="2" column="1">We identify four iterative cycles in our service design process. Each design cycle concluded with an event (meeting or workshop) in which we received feedback from the industrial partners and provided input for the following cycle (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="25" class="deo:Reference">figure 2</xref>).<marker type="block"/> For the purpose of this paper we can place our activities in two main areas of emphasis:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="27" page="2" column="1">MA' 2003 JUNE 2003</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="28" page="2" column="1">DfCEM8ER 2002 Italy Denmark</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="29" page="2" column="1">o</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="30" page="2" column="1">Figure 2. Design Process</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx32">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rc.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62rc.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">the service context of the cold chain where we sought to understand and represent the people that would participate in or be influenced by a potential cold chain service. the design context where we focused on creating activities that used the understanding and representations from the service context as a starting point for imagining and planning new service encounters-understanding and representing how the service context would then be different.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="34" page="2" column="2">3.1 Exploring service context</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="2" column="2">The design of effective service encounters asks for the analysis and understanding of the potential service participants' context and practices. For us this meant developing an overall idea of the "cold chain" system and developing a detailed understanding of the perspectives and practices of the participants in the system. Exploring and getting insight into the complexity of the "cold chain" proved to be a daunting task. It was ultimately shaped by time constraints, accessibility to various participants, and their willingness to participate in the project. <marker type="block"/> Ethnographic principles and techniques inspired the way we carried out the field analysis[I). We sought to interview and observe people in the context of their work activities, producing documentation for analysis and to develop representations for later use. To do this we used a combination of video and audio recordings, digital photos, and field notes. By traditional ethnographic standards, our fieldwork was brief and disconnected only providing an introduction to the various contexts. In relation to the practices of our industrial partners, our approach was broad in scope and rich in detail about previously unexplored work contexts.<marker type="block"/> Our field studies in Denmark included interviews and shadowing:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">Interviews (1 to 4 hours each) 18 people from three supermarkets (managers, department heads, staff, technician), a European supermarket corporation (sector managers), a supermarket education center (manager), and a refrigeration service contractor (manager and technician)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">Shadowing (half day each) four people from two supermarkets (Frost &amp; fruit department, deli/meat department, restaurant) and refrigeration service contractor (technician)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="2" column="2">We looked to Activity Theory as an analytical filter to interpret the collected data as it proposes a set of concepts and a basic model, the Activity System[6), for the analysis of human activity. <marker type="block"/> Ethnography and Activity Theory share two main principles in the way they approach human behavior: the holistic approach, according to which human action should be understood within the larger context in which it occurs (in this case the "cold chain" activity system), and the members point of view, that underlines the importance of gaining the perspectives and "voices" of the people studied (potential service participants).<marker type="block"/> However, ethnography and Activity Theory answered to different necessities in the design process. While we needed to explore and describe the complexity of the service context, we also sought to develop a handy model with stable categories to synthesize and<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> communicate during design activities. Consequently, as we will describe below, the richness of contextual data has been collected through ethnographically inspired approach and interpreted through the main categories of the Activity System model: subjects, arttracts (technical tools and psychological tools like knowledge and experience), roles, rules (explicit rules or implicit rules like habits) and objectives.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="43" page="2" column="2">149</outsider>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="62" page="3" column="2">4. DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" page="3" column="2">In the action-research project described here, we introduced and further developed a service design approach with industrial partners based on the assumption that the design of successful services depends upon a holistic and participatory approach. During the project, with these ideas in mind, we attempted to use and develop tools that both helped us and others appreciate the richness and complexity of a service context and to incorporate those understandings during the service design process under realistic industrial and research constraints of time and resources. While this was a project that concentrated on the idea generation phase of service design, and not the final design and implementation of services, we will discuss some of the challenges we faced during the project and some of the feedback from the project participants. We conducted two reflection <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> activities with project participants after the workshop and at the end of the final hand-off meeting at Danfoss. Through these sessions we learned that:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="64" page="3" column="2">150</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">integrating existing perspectives and practices of the potential service actors (portraits, video clips, issue cards, activity system maps) helped the workshop participants (in particular the industrial representatives) go beyond their previous stereotyped ideas of supermarket staff roles and their needs. highlighting existing conflicts, mainly through the issue cards, proved to be a stimulus for service idea generation. the holistic approach to the analysis of the "cold chain" system provoked the workshop participants to widen their perspectives from a product focus (refrigeration components) to that of services (cold chain maintenance).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="4" column="1">This last point is particularly important to us, as the workshop participants had notably experienced resistance and difficulties to think in terms of services. We initially had hoped that the introduction and application of Activity Theory model, describing and explaining the main elements that characterize a service action, would support this change. The intention to provide predefined categories to frame and support both the analysis and the design of services resulted in contradictory results for both the workshop participant and us. During the field studies it quickly became obvious that the strict application of the Activity Theory would come at the expense of a less exploratory attitude. We therefore used the Activity System model as a sort of background reference to help guide our activities. Along the same lines, for the workshop we prepared both static representations such as the Activity System maps complemented by fluid materials such as the portraits and videos. As summarized below, the feedback from the participants was encouraging:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">The balance of the different kind of tools worked well as the maps gave a good "birds-eye perspective" of the contexts while portraits and videos were useful to gain a direct understanding of service actors' roles and interests (Danfoss RefrigerationiAC European Development Manager commented that, "portrait descriptions, based on field studies, are very useful in understanding tasks, responsibilities, and priorities of all involved persons"). Additionally, while the Activity System maps were reported to be difficult to understand at first glance ("as a presentation tool"), and too complex to understand, the workshop participants reported that the maps worked well once they got used to working with them. Activity System maps proved to be a good analytical and design conceptual tool as they actually helped to frame and organize the service context information (Danfoss RefrigerationiAC Marketing manager said, "Activity System forces you to structure information and relations") and to describe the service system (a designer noted that, "the Activity System map is a good visual figure to explain a complex idea or concept")</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62rc.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62rc.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="4" column="2">The results of the action-research project offer insight into the potential value of bringing the service participants, via representations, into the design process during strategic decision and planning activities. At the same time, they also highlighted the necessity to further develop tools and methods that support the communication and design of the 'complexity' of services. While using ethnography and Activity Theory provided encouraging results, more must be done on the compromise between two opposing demands: the necessity to understand and represent the richness and complexity of a service context, while creating a design and communication language able to handle it.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="4" column="2">5. REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="72" page="4" column="2">[I] Blomberg, J., Burrell M., and Guest G. An Ethnographic Approach to Design. In Jacko, J. and Sears, A (Eds.), The Human-Computer Interaction Handbook. Fundamentals, Evolving Technologies and Emerging Applications. Lea Publishers, London, 2003, 965-984.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="73" page="4" column="2">[2] Brandt, E., Event-Driven Product Development. Ph.D. Thesis, Technical University of Denmark, Lyngby, Denmark, 200 I.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="74" page="4" column="2">[3] Buur, J. and Soendergaard A., Video Card Game: An augmented environment/or User Centred Design discussions, DARE 2000, Elsinore, Danmark, April 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="75" page="4" column="2">[4] Czepiel, J., Solomon M. and Suprenant C. (eds.), The Service Encounter. Managing Employee/Customer Interaction in Service Business, Lexington Books, Lexington (MA), 1985.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="76" page="4" column="2">[5] Ehn, P., Scandinavian Design: On Participation and Skill, in Shuler, D. and Namioka A. (Ed.), Participatory design. Principles and practices, LEA Publishers, Hillsdale, 1993.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="78" page="4" column="2">[6] Engestrom, Y., Learning by expanding: An activity- theoretical approach to developmental research, Helsinki : Orienta-Konsultit, 1987 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://lchc.ucsd.edulMCAlPaperlEngestrom" id="77">http://lchc.ucsd.edulMCAlPaperlEngestrom</ext-link>!expanding/toc.h tm).</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="4" column="2">[7] Engestrom, Y., Miettinen R., and Punamiiki R., Perspectives on activity theory, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1999.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" page="4" column="2">[8] Greenbaum, J., and Kyng, M . (Ed.), Design at work: Cooperative Design o/Computer Systems, LEA Publishers, Hillsdale, New Jersey, 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="4" column="2">[9] Morgensen, P.R. Challenging Practice: An Approach to Cooperative Analysis. Computer Science Department, Aarhus University, 1994, Wiklud, M: Usability in Practice, AP Professional, 1994.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="82" page="4" column="2">[10] Pacenti, E., II progetto dell'interazione nei servizi. Un contributo altema della progeltazione dei servizi, tesi di dottorato di ricerca in Disegno Industriale, X cicio, Aprile 1995 - Ottobre 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" page="4" column="2">[11] [Shostack, G., Planning the Service Encounter, in Czepiel, 1., Solomon M., e Suprenant C. (ed.), The Service Encounter. Managing Employee/Customer Interaction in Service Business, Lexington Books, Lexington (MA), 1985,243- 253 .</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84" page="4" column="2">151</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
