<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>376fa0bf08b3c069084bc18456efa71bcd43a689d508b5e87048054038a00447</job>
    <base_name>62p9</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2470654.2481395</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Materials, Materiality, and Media</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Verena Fuchsberger</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Martin Murer</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Manfred Tscheligi</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Christian Doppler Laboratory for “Contextual Interfaces” HCI &amp; Usability Unit, ICT&amp;S Center, University of Salzburg Salzburg, Austria { firstname.lastname } @sbg.ac.at</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8">In HCI, and especially in interaction design, the material aspect of interactions is currently emphasized. Nevertheless, it is challenging to theoretically frame the variety of digital or immaterial, and physical materials. In order to contribute to this materiality discourse, we reflect on McLuhan’s work on media analysis and on Latour’s Actor-Network Theory in this paper. Both emphasize the active role of the material – be it media or any other kind of non-human actors – in the interplay with the human. Thus, we establish junctures between their findings and materials, as used in interaction design in HCI. We discuss McLuhan’s claim to focus on new sensory effects and ways of interaction brought forth by new media. Furthermore, we illustrate how describing the connections between materials, designers, and users in terms of Latour’s Actor-Networks can be beneficial for interaction design. Finally, we discuss the respective methodology and its relation to research through design.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="9" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Author Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible">Actor-network theory; design; materiality; materials; media theory</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">ACM</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Classification Keywords</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">H.5.m. Information Interfaces and Presentation (e.g. HCI): Miscellaneous</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" page="1" column="1">INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="1" column="1">In HCI, design materials are getting more and more attention. At CHI 2012, a panel was held on “Material Interactions” – From Atoms &amp; Bits to Entangled Practices outlining different perspectives on materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="15" class="deo:Reference">51</xref>]. The panelists provided heterogeneous approaches to an understanding of materials. Hiroshi Ishii talked about his vision of tangible interfaces and respective properties of the materials. Paul Dourish referred to the complexity of the interplay between current materials and design in HCI. Anna Vallg arda outlined her understanding of computational composites as design materials. While</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. CHI 2013 , April 27–May 2, 2013, Paris, France. Copyright 2013 ACM 978-1-4503-1899-0/13/04... $ 15.00.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" page="1" column="2">Petra Sundström emphasized the crafting aspects of working with digital materials, Daniela Rosner referred to the cultural histories embedded in technology. Tobie Kerridge focused on public engagement. Finally, Mark Rolston provided an industrial point of view on creative usage of materials. The presented notions of materials were thus manifold. On one hand, the design practice with both digital and physical materials was discussed, which finally aims at providing rich user experiences. On the other hand, the theoretical point of view was emphasized. However, a lack of shared terminology and framing, which would facilitate the discussion about materials in HCI, was recognized. In order to strengthen this framing, we reflect on two theories from other disciplines, i.e., McLuhan’s media analysis and Latour’s Actor-Network Theory. Both have focused on the interplay between humans and artifacts and provided a theoretical understanding within their disciplines. The reason for reflecting on these very theories is their explicit emphasis on the active role not only of humans, but also of artifacts. This emphasis complies with the current notion in interaction design that material properties and qualities have an underes- timated influence on the design of interactive artifacts. First, we will refer to Marshall McLuhan’s theoretical work on media (e.g., [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="18" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]). McLuhan studied the relation between media, humans, and society, and focused especially on sensory effects and transitions from one medium to another. One of his arguments is that media are not only transmitting information, but are information themselves. This will be the starting point for our theoretical reflection, as materials in HCI are also considered to be more than solely “the stuff that things are made of” [19, p. 1]. Thus, we aim to find out whether McLuhan’s further inferences on media effects are also true for materials in HCI. Second, we will describe Bruno Latour’s Actor-Network Theory (ANT; e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="19" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]), a sociological theory. This theory understands human and non-human artifacts as actors that form a network. As long as an actor influences another person or artifact, the network not only exists, but also changes continuously. Considering materials as actors might help us to describe and understand their active role in the interplay with the user, as well as with the designer. Our aim is to reflect on McLuhan’s and Latour’s work in order to identify what they can contribute to strengthen the theoretical framing of materials in the HCI design realm. According<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> to Jung and Stolterman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="24" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>], design in general is the materi- alization of meanings into an artifact form. While the design process in HCI focuses on the communication with the users and their needs (i.e., a conversation based on words, actions, or objects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="25" class="deo:Reference">43</xref>]), the design process of traditional design disciplines (e.g., product or graphic design), is rather characterized by crafting particular materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="26" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>]. Fernaeus and Sundström [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="27" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>] provide several reasons why material knowledge is un- derestimated when it comes to interactive system design in HCI. For instance, there is the illusion that the digital allows building everything. Furthermore, the complexity of digital material makes it hard to show, share, and fully understand it. Fernaeus and Sundström [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="28" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>], as well as Jung and Stolterman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="29" class="deo:Reference">22</xref>], argue to nevertheless “integrate a designerly approach in an analytical HCI approach” [22, p. 403], taking the properties of the materials explicitly into account; or as Hallnäs and Redström put it: “Interaction design is product- and systems design where computational technology is a basic design ma- terial” [16, p. 24]. These notions emphasize the importance of understanding the effects of the complex digital material on designers and users. Therefore, we will reflect on McLuhan’s work on media and their sensory effects and on Latour’s ANT, which offers an instrument to describe the dynamic nature of (non-human) materials and their interplay with other (human) actors. Both McLuhan and Latour highly value the material (be it media or any other non-human artifact) and its influence. While McLuhan emphasizes the effects of media and the respective consequences for the design, Latour provides methodological possibilities to describe the complex interplay between the artifact and the human. In order to identify the potential of those two perspectives for the materiality discussion in interaction design, we will ini- tially depict definitions of materials, materiality, and media and explore their similarities and differences. A reflection on McLuhan’s and Latour’s work will follow, including some already existing connections to HCI, and parallels to the materiality discourse. Finally, we will discuss our main question, i.e., what elements McLuhan and Latour can provide for a theoretical framing of materials in interaction design.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="21" page="1" column="2">2853</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="22" page="2" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23" page="2" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="31" page="2" column="1">TOWARDS MATERIALS AND MATERIALITY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="2" column="1">Ingold [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="32" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>] defines materials for the anthropology realm: “I mean by materials the stuff that things are made of” [19, p. 1] (or according to Schön material objects “are just what they are” [42, p. 9]). However, in HCI things are not only made of materials, they might also be represented by further materials. When for example users manipulate content, they interact not directly with it, but through input and output modalities, like computer screens, keyboards or mice (i.e., materials for interacting with materials). Interaction design thus works with the content and the representation, and both content and representation can be digital (which means here virtual or immaterial material) or physical materials. These multidimensional aspects of materials become tangible in a design perspective, When designing computational things the material is some- how absent and only conceptually present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="33" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>]. Vallg arda and Redström [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="34" class="deo:Reference">48</xref>] propose to think of computational composites,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> i.e., computation needs to be combined with other materials, to become a material itself which can be used in design practice. Furthermore, computational materials are coming to be over time and in context, i.e., they cannot be reduced to the terms of being or doing, but must be understood as constantly in movement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="36" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]. Consequently, several temporal combinations of physical or digital content with physical or digital representations can be the basis for interaction design to work with. The designer is in progressive relationships with the material, i.e., in conversation, “where she is getting some response back from the medium” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="37" class="deo:Reference">43</xref>]. Herein, Schön [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="38" class="deo:Reference">43</xref>] emphasizes the designers’ reflection on action (i.e., pausing to think back over what has been done), and reflection in action (i.e., reflecting on the design without stopping). Having clarified what we understand by materials in HCI’s design, we will now proceed with the term materiality. Ingold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="39" class="deo:Reference">19</xref>] states it as: “To understand materiality, it seems, we need to get as far away from materials as possible” [19, p. 2]. Although Ingold relates this argument to anthropology, what he is referring to is similar to HCI. It is about the abstract discussion of materiality without considering the properties of the individual materials. Ingold even poses the question whether materiality was the academic perversion of materials and their properties. In our opinion it is though an abstract term, but not a purposeless one. Similar to the distinction between method and methodology, we understand materiality as the theoretical discourse about materials. This includes all illustrations and discussions of materials in HCI, like their roles in design processes, their forms, functions, ontologies, etc. Thus, under the umbrella of the materiality discourse we are talking about materials when we refer to what things are made of or represented by. On basis of this understanding of materials and materiality, we will proceed by exploring how the term media relates to materials.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="41" page="2" column="2">FROM MATERIALS TO MEDIA</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="2" column="2">The term media is used in various ways and in various disciplines. Most often, it is used as an expression for means of communication (e.g., [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="42" class="deo:Reference">34</xref>]), especially in relation to social media. The primary purpose of (social) media is to speed up and increase the likelihood of communication, facilitate coordination of actions, especially with changing interaction partners and finally to allow complex cooperation. Thus, media are more than technical instrumentalizations, as they also include natural languages or writing systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="43" class="deo:Reference">41</xref>]. However, besides the exchange of information in a dialogue, interaction with information can also be a monologue, i.e., an individual perception and reflection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="44" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>]. As information is principally dematerialized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="45" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], it needs a material to manifest in order to provide humans a way to perceive this information. The information can be regarded as the content and the manifestation, like the media, is the representation of the content. Thus, media can be any material that allows to interact with the information, and in HCI it will most often be the material interaction design works with. Although not defined explicitly, the term media has often been used in this way in HCI, e.g., by Ames and Naaman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="46" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>] or Carter and Mankoff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="47" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>].<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> As McLuhan focused on media analysis throughout his work, we will reflect on it in the following. After illustrating his connections to HCI, we will discuss his notion of media and consider relevant aspects in detail.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="49" page="2" column="2">2854</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="50" page="3" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="51" page="3" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" page="3" column="1">MARSHALL MCLUHAN’S MEDIA ANALYSIS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="3" column="1">Marshall McLuhan (1911-1980) was a Canadian English Pro- fessor, who focused on media analysis, and many of his arti- cles relate to media education [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="54" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. McLuhan has been related to HCI several times, mainly in reference to his book “Understanding Media: the extensions of man” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="55" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>]. This is not surprising, as McLuhan describes his interpretation of 26 different types of media in one chapter each. His discussions from the spoken word to photography to automation allow for immediate connections to any related subject (see as examples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="56" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="57" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="58" class="deo:Reference">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="59" class="deo:Reference">50</xref>]). In 2011, McLuhan would have had celebrated his 100th birth- day, which motivated several discussions about his work. Although considered ambivalently in academia, e.g., being a charlatan through neglecting the need for evidence (see e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="60" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] or [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="61" class="deo:Reference">36</xref>]), there were many events for resurrecting his ideas. One of those events was a conference entitled re-touching McLuhan, which dealt with McLuhan’s take on sensory effects of electronic media, and his legacy on artistic and digital cultural practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="62" class="deo:Reference">39</xref>]. It focused on questions of tactile sensing and embodiment, and aimed to link McLuhan’s work with today’s media reality. In comparison, we will reflect on McLuhan’s basic ideas in order to identify connection points to interaction materials and materiality.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="64" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Overview of McLuhan’s Work</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" page="3" column="1">One of McLuhan’s most attention-getting books (with Quentin Fiore as co-author) is about the medium being the message. Put very briefly, McLuhan’s basic idea is that the medium influences if not determines its effect on the individuals. While one could argue that he is just another technology determinist, Friesen and Hug [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="65" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] respond that, although McLuhan would see media “coming before” other considera- tions, it does not mean that media found or give rise to social, cultural and historical phenomena. However, McLuhan considers the content as having a subordinate role in messages. Instead, by stressing the importance of the media, he argues, the chance of perceiving and influencing the impact of new technologies on humans is increased, and the revolutionary environmental transformations can be extensively used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="66" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>]. Stadler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="67" class="deo:Reference">44</xref>] argues that the medium-content distinction is related to the figure-ground discussion from Gestalt psychol- ogy. It is assumed that perception is based on both the figure, on which we focus, and the ground, which appears un- structured in the background. The boundary is perceived as a shape belonging to the figure, while the ground appears to be shapeless. Nevertheless, the ground is essential for perception. According to McLuhan, the media are like the ground, they are the shapeless environment of the content, but they are pervasively influencing perception and impressions. This is also strongly related to what Fallman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="68" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>] refers to as the non-neutrality of technology, i.e., technologies not being neu- tral means for realizing human ends, as they actively shape<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the users’ experiences of the world; and they not only influence the users’ experiences, but also the designers’ ways of designing. While Fallman emphasizes that technology is actively influencing human’s experiences, McLuhan even considers media, and especially electronic technology, as extensions of the human. You’ve got to remember that my definition of media is broad; it includes any technology whatever that creates extensions of the human body and senses, from clothing to the computer. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="70" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>] Again, the medium is the message, as not the content is ex- tending the human senses, but the medium itself (e.g., the phone being an extension of the ear). Furthermore, McLuhan separates four stages of cultural history: a primitive tribal culture, an audile culture, using the oral technology of speech, the “Gutenberg Galaxy”, i.e., a visual culture, using the me- chanical technology of printing, and finally the electronic age of television and computers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="71" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. His claim is that the media, which were prominent in the different ages, did not necessar- ily address all human senses. As a consequence, the deprived senses were affected negatively, and the humans unlearned to perceive with all their senses comprehensively. For instance, the audile culture extended the auditive sense, but left behind the visual or tactile sense. But it is necessary to understand the power and thrust of technologies to isolate the senses and thus to hypnotize society. [. . . ] Every new technology thus diminishes sense interplay and consciousness, precisely in the new area of novelty where a kind of identification of viewer and object occurs. [30, p. 272] McLuhan argues that the media of the electronic age have the capability to affect and transform all human senses through activating a sensual interplay, whereas for example the manuscript culture in the Gutenberg Galaxy extended a single sense, i.e., the visual sense. Addressing solely for example the visual sense would be associated with linear con- tinuity, uniformity, abstraction, and individualization, and a culture dominated by visuality would be characterized by sep- aration, distance, alienation and the dissociation of sensibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="72" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. The argument is that media, which characterize certain societies or cultures, affect the whole human perception. As an example, McLuhan referred to the television, which at McLuhan’s times requested the viewer to actively partici- pate in filling in vague and blurry images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="73" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>]. Media, which require such a strong involvement through providing slight granularity (like the electronic age), McLuhan called “cool” media, opposed to “hot” media, which provide enough details to not require strong involvement, like the radio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="74" class="deo:Reference">32</xref>].</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="76" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">Media Analysis and Materials</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="3" column="2">McLuhan’s understanding of human involvement with media illustrates that the media, i.e., the representing material or the ground surrounding a figure, essentially impress and affect the humans. Furthermore, according to McLuhan, past media ages influence the subsequent ones. In order to discuss what this means for interaction design, we will reflect on those aspects in detail in the following. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Sensory Impressions and Effects Friesen and Hug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="81" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] emphasize McLuhan’s distinction between sensory impressions and sensory effects; while the first are what a medium can provide (e.g., releasing sound waves), the latter is the sense obtained, i.e., the sensory impact (e.g., acoustic perception). Friesen and Hug furthermore refer to Aristotle and his notion of a common sense, which combines all senses. Not the unique senses, but the movement, rest, number, and magnitude become important parts of the perception. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the distinction between sensory</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="78" page="3" column="2">2855</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="79" page="4" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="80" page="4" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="84" page="4" column="1">Figure 1.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Can you hear the bang? Multiple sensory effects through visual impression (based on [33, p. 111f]).</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="4" column="1">effects and sensory impressions. It is in the style of a page in McLuhan’s book The Medium is the Massage, showing a graph in comic style. While the sensory impression is constituted of color and contrast, the sensory effect goes beyond the physical reality. Looking at the picture might also result in hearing the bang, or even feeling it. The picture is perceived dynamically, as the reader is engaged with several senses. Also the book title expresses the distinction of impressions and effects. It was supposed to be The Medium is the Mes- sage, but due to a compositor’s error, it got The medium is the Massage. After recognizing the error, McLuhan was delighted, as it even more expressed what he wanted to say, i.e., the media affect more senses than the mode of presentation would suggest, like being a massage to the senses [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="86" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. Friesen and Hug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="87" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] emphasize that “An imbalance of the senses induced by media can deprive one of rationality or consciousness” [13, p. 91]. Similarly, Ullmer and Ishii [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="88" class="deo:Reference">47</xref>] argue that GUIs represent information in an almost entirely visual form, which would neglect the various possibilities to address human senses. Ishii [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="89" class="deo:Reference">20</xref>] expresses concerns that: Our visual and auditory sense organs are steeped in the sea of digital information, but our bodies remain impris- oned in the physical world. [20, p. XV] Also Goodman and Rosner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="90" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] recognized the importance of addressing various senses with digital tools. They inves- tigated how to combine handwork experiences, like knitting or gardening, with digital tools. They emphasized that, especially for handwork, the sensory sensitivity is crucial, be it<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> a physical or digital activity. While Ullmer and Ishii [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="92" class="deo:Reference">47</xref>] as well as Goodmann and Rosner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="93" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] implicitly assign the re- sponsibility of addressing various senses to the design of interactions, Friesen and Hug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="94" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] argue for training the senses and perception in education in order to re-establish sensual interplay and unity. Both perspectives are related to McLuhan’s concerns about people’s sensory capabilities. McLuhan assumes that in different media cultures sensory capabilities are brought forth or inhibited by the media. Furthermore, the effects of preceding cultures often continue also in the age of new media. As an example, manuscript culture (i.e., the Gutenberg Galaxy) addressed primarily the visual sense. Although the electronic age offers the possibility for various sensory experiences through multimediality, there are be- havioral or perceptual leftovers from the manuscript culture. “They [people] suspect the ear: they don’t trust it” [33, p. 117]. This means that things that are visible, and preferably constant, are more likely to be considered as real [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="95" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. McLuhan and Fiore argue that people sometimes would not understand purely verbal concepts, as seeing things would en- sure a certain feeling of safety. There would be evidences in the language, like speaking of visionaries or seers when talking about wise people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="96" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]. This leftover can also be found in Dourish’s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="97" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>] description of coding signals in interactive systems. He argues that extracting information content from a medium requires the ability to decode signals, which “[. . . ] typically arises as variety of issues around the topic of ‘vis- ibility’“ [8, p. 165]. Dourish refers to the visibility of the activities from one person to another across time and space, or the system’s response to a user’s activity. Having put the term visibility in quotation marks himself, leads us to the as- sumption that the term does not perfectly fit; although it could be a coincidence, this might still implicitly address the lack of appropriate terms for expressing the sensory effects of new media and subsequently of new materials. Thus, turning towards new materials, new media or environments not only requires explicit processes, but also new ways to express them. Through sensitively making use of new interaction possibilities, which the electronic age provides, and establish- ing new ways of experiencing the interaction, design can help overcome the sensory deprivations. This also relates to McLuhan’s claim that new mediatic environments require new ways of interaction, which will be discussed in detail in the following section.<marker type="block"/> The Old and the New According to McLuhan and Fiore [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="99" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>], new media require new ways of dealing with them, and new perspectives to understand their effects. The main obstacle to a clear understanding of the effects of the new media is our deeply embedded habit of re- garding all phenomena from a fixed point of view. [33, p. 68] They emphasize that the interplay between old and new environments would be problematic and confusing, as the new media would be forced to do the work of the old. People would rather stick to an asynchronous action-reaction mode,<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> which has different time patterns than what the electronic age would suggest; action and reaction would occur almost at the same time. Today, this is still true for e.g., some newspapers, which are provided online and issued on a daily basis, instead of being distributed continuously. However, there is a transition from the rather “static” newspaper to continuous news exchange, including the possibility for direct feedback in form of comments to the newspaper entries. This complies with McLuhan’s and Fiore’s argument that media, and especially electric technology, reshape and restructure patterns of social interdependence and every aspect of our personal life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="104" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>]. A more subtle but similar perspective is provided by Dourish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="105" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], who refers to a transformative materiality of digital networks. Digital technologies intentionally or acciden- tally shape and modify physical or social environments, like WiFi networks shaping public spaces. Following McLuhan’s claim to deal with new environments in new ways, one could ask whether the combination of the physical and the digital would be contradictory then, as the physical is what we traditionally dealt with, and the digital is the new environment’s material. However, designers’ aware- ness of the constitution of the materials and the various ways to combine and work with them, will meet McLuhan’s claim. So far, we reflected on several aspects McLuhan referred to, which we consider highly relevant in the context of materials in interaction design. According to McLuhan, media, which can be interpreted as materials representing content, are pervasively influencing human perception and impressions. However, sensory impressions are not necessar- ily equal to sensory effects. While impressions are what the medium (the material) provides, the effect is rather the sense obtained [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="106" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. Consequently, new media and materials require new ways of designing them in order to overcome perceptual leftovers from former media ages and to enable rich sensory effects. In the following we will thus focus on the effects of interactive media in detail.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="101" page="4" column="2">2856</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="102" page="5" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="5" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="5" column="1">AFFECTING ARTIFACTS: INTERACTION DESIGN</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" page="5" column="1">In order to differentiate more clearly between the effects of materials on the users and the effects on the designers, we refer to Lim et al. [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="109" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>], who distinguish between user experience, interaction gestalt, and interactive artifact. Lim et al. consider the interactive artifact to have properties, which are not equivalent to the usage qualities that the users experience. The designers’ task is thus to bridge this gap by translating interaction attributes (like movement or connectivity) to the interactive artifact properties in order to shape the interaction, i.e., the interaction gestalt. Designers anticipate how a certain gestalt will be experienced by the users. Or as Hallnäs and Redström [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="110" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>] highlight, interaction design increasingly focuses on what we do with the interactive artifact (which is in their terminology the act that defines the intended use of things and systems), rather than the things as such. According to the model, which Lim et al. propose, the designers translate and manifest attributes to the artifacts’ properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="111" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>]. Nevertheless, the artifact properties need to play an active role in this process, like Fernaeus and Sundström emphasize:<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> [. . . ] in terms of interaction design, choices made on the technical level of tools and materials are essential not only in the fine-tuning, but also for achieving the fundamental properties of the envisioned design. [12, p. 494] Thus, artifacts with their (im)material properties sensorily affect both the designers during the act of designing, and also the users while experiencing the artifact. In order to further illustrate the dependencies of materials, designers, and users, we will in the following section reflect on Bruno Latour’s Actor-Network Theory (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="113" class="deo:Reference">26</xref>]), which also stresses the active role of artifacts.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="115" page="5" column="2">BRUNO LATOUR’S ACTOR-NETWORK THEORY (ANT)</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="5" column="2">Bruno Latour, a French sociologist and anthropologist, was significantly involved in the development of the Actor- Network Theory. ANT describes the interplay between humans, and non-human actors. Non-human actors can be analogue artifacts, technology, or anything else (e.g., describing Pasteur’s agriculture discovery of a vaccine against anthrax in terms of ANT was one of Latour’s first and most prominent examples). The term activity is a central one in ANT, i.e., everyone and everything can be an actor as soon as he/she/it evokes an action of someone or something else. Thus, a network of actors emerges, “whenever action is to be redistributed” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="116" class="deo:Reference">27</xref>], be it between humans, between human and non-human actors, or solely between non-human artifacts (e.g., machine-2- machine communication). A behavior can be imposed onto humans by non-human delegates (e.g., technology), which is called prescription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="117" class="deo:Reference">25</xref>]. Actors are connected as soon as they influence each other, and this happens within a network, which they form in turn. As there are human and non-human actors, Latour calls it a hybrid network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="118" class="deo:Reference">24</xref>]. A network consists of associations, which have to be established. These associations define the relatedness of the actors within the network, and can be described with the terms collaboration, clash, addition, tension, exclusion, inclusion etc. Associa- tions are also sometimes called tinkering, emphasizing the step-by-step activities performed by the actors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="119" class="deo:Reference">35</xref>]. [. . . ] there is not a net and an actor laying down the net, but there is an actor whose definition of the world outlines, traces, delineate, limn, describe, shadow forth, inscroll, file, list, record, mark, or tag a trajectory that is called a network. [24, p. 11] Consequently, a network is not stable, but constituted by the actions of the actors involved. Besides the emphasis on activity, ANT also includes a methodological claim. Through describing all relations (actions, actors, etc.) in detail, an understanding of a phenomena is developed, theory is thus embedded and extended in empirical practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="120" class="deo:Reference">28</xref>]. The detailed description of networks is the researchers’ task, and ANT provides the respective terminology and methods. In a later section we will illustrate what this methodological claim holds for interaction design research. Prior to this, we will discuss the connection between ANT, HCI, and especially materials in interaction design.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="122" page="5" column="2">2857</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="123" page="6" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="124" page="6" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="125" page="6" column="1">ANT</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="126" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">and Materials</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" page="6" column="1">In HCI, there have been several references to ANT or Latour, e.g., [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="127" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="128" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="129" class="deo:Reference">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="130" class="deo:Reference">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="131" class="deo:Reference">45</xref>]. Suchman [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="132" class="deo:Reference">45</xref>], for example, described among others machine agency referring to ANT. Besides the description of the interplay between users with technology as such, like Suchman used ANT for, we are focusing in the following on the interplay not only between technology and users, but between materials, designers, and users.<marker type="block"/> If we consider materials and designers as influencing each other and thus forming a network, one might argue that the specific characteristic of HCI, the user perspective, needs to play a central role in this network too. In order to clarify the connections between materials, designers, and users, we again refer to Lim et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="136" class="deo:Reference">29</xref>]. Lim et al. outline that the designer anticipates how the interaction gestalt (i.e., the shape of the interaction) will be experienced by the users, and considers this in the design. This process of anticipating the users’ experiences with the artifact or the interaction gestalt is called inscription in ANT. It is the designer’s or engineer’s effort to influence the user’s interaction in a specific way; however, the inscription can succeed or fail. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> illustrates this network. It shows that the network consists of different levels, i.e., the material, the interaction gestalt, and the interactive artifact. Furthermore, the designers and the users both are active parts in this network, but they are only connected with each other in a mediated way, i.e., only indirectly and asyn- chronically. The networks are thus of a dynamic nature, they emerge in activity, and are absent in disactivity. In 2011, Latour held a keynote on network multidimension- ality in the digital age at the international seminar on network theory. He related the digital to ANT, and argued that: [. . . ] the expansion of digitality has enormously increased the material dimension of networks: the more digital, the less virtual and the more material a given activity becomes. [27, p. 8] What he refers to is the material representation of the digital (“Go tell Google engineers that their vast array of servers are<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> just virtual!” [27, p. 8]). When we focus on the network of designers and materials, this means that the dependencies of materials, their properties, and qualities are central in the respective actor-network. Viseu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="139" class="deo:Reference">49</xref>] puts it that way: [. . . ] the objects themselves have competencies which must be taken into account. These competencies give them agency. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="140" class="deo:Reference">49</xref>] The activity of objects (or materials) depends on competencies, and those competencies derive from the objects’ properties and qualities. What ANT can thus contribute to a theoretical framing of materials in interaction design is the perspective on the actors and the respective descriptions. In the following, we will bring together Latour’s and McLuhan’s con- siderations with interaction design.</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="134" page="6" column="1">Interactive Artifact IA Interaction Gestalt IG Material M . .. tou ibe s, es, ... stim ul c he s in scr orc a tes , al es , s, f , dir ters , p ain ect ob fts, sha ,c on str s , im ject s, cra es pre . .. pir sse ns s, i . .. mediated network Designer User</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="135" page="6" column="1">Figure 2. Actor-network between materials, interaction gestalt, interactive artifacts, designers, and users</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="142" page="6" column="2">INTERACTION DESIGN LINKED TO MCLUHAN &amp; LATOUR</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" page="6" column="2">Having reflected on McLuhan’s work on media and Latour’s ANT, we are now transferring these theoretical notions to interaction design in HCI by sketching the junctures between them. We explicitly emphasize that the following sections do not provide practical implications; they rather illustrate a theoretical framing of materials in interaction design.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="144" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">Rich Sensory Effects Through New Media</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="6" column="2">McLuhan complained that the printed page separated, for example, poetry and music [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="145" class="deo:Reference">30</xref>]. Following McLuhan’s argumentation, materiality needs to be a holistic paradigm of feeling and sensing the material, which allows also subtle pe- culiarities of materials to be recognized and used in design. As an example in the context of education, the importance of recognizing the “material” as a substantial element in the learning process has been discussed by Friesen and Hug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="146" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>]. Friesen and Hug criticize that media are often used for con- ventional educational purposes, like having instructional media, which take over or complement the traditional role of a teacher. They claim that Instead, media need to be seen as thoroughly interpene- trating school and classroom, and educational practices and purposes. The implication is that education taken as a whole, needs to be radically re-thought in a sustained manner, from a mediatic perspective. [13, p. 85] They emphasize the effects of media on educational outcomes by arguing that the properties and qualities of new media cannot be neglected, and suggest to take the sensory effects, as described by McLuhan, as a starting point. Rich sensations that can be achieved through the usage of specific materials and their interplay, go beyond pure physical stimuli. In an age of twitchspeed and twitter, multitasking and multimedia, such a radical exploration of alternative sensual orientations and subject constructions in education is both current and compelling. [. . . ] any purchase re- maining for thought or practice to engage media and their determinations will be of no small value. [13, p. 99] In our opinion, this is especially true for interaction design, which also requires a radical exploration of alternative sen-<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> sations, which can only start in the design by experiencing and playing with the materials. Considering the interplay of senses as a desirable state, which not only affects but also ex- tends humans, spaces evolve to facilitate and understand this interplay. Interaction design faces the difficulty of designing sensory impressions, i.e., what the material can provide, in order to allow sensory effects. With the complexity of digital and physical material, this is even more difficult, as the material itself sensorily affects the designer in various ways, or as Schön expresses it: “The designer designs not only with the mind but with the body and senses [...]” [42, p. 5]. Consequently, interaction design in HCI needs to assess the sensory effects the material has on the designer, acknowledge the qualities or properties of materials and design the sensory impressions in a way that they result in rich sensory effects for the users. Furthermore, dedicated material studies are necessary in design research to investigate the effects in different contexts, i.e., with different human and non-human actors.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="148" page="6" column="2">2858</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149" page="7" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="150" page="7" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="152" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Rich Ways of Interaction Through New Materials</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="170" page="7" column="1">McLuhan claimed to consider the historical and social context of media, but that does not mean to carry forward traditional ways of interaction. It rather means that research needs to understand why certain media or materials led to specific ways of interaction in order to consciously identify new ways, which are enabled by new materials. About electric media, McLuhan and Fiore [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="153" class="deo:Reference">33</xref>] say that they would have an active, exploratory quality, which would involve all senses – to be “with” them. For example, they argue that television de- manded different sensory responses than for example printed media. However, the age of the Gutenberg Galaxy predeter- mined the sensory interaction with the “new” medium television. The same is true for digital materials: Using them in the tradition of physical materials will withhold maxing out the possibilities it would provide due to its immediacy (e.g., direct feedback), dimensionality (e.g., hyperlink struc- tures), and especially multimediality and multimodality (e.g., addressing various senses). The intertwining of historical contexts and new ways of interaction can be illustrated on basis of Fernaeus et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="154" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>], who examined the Jacquard Loom. This loom was a system, which was used to produce patterns of fabric in the early 19th century. Fernaeus et al. discussed its qualities in terms of interaction design, like the role of physical materials for interacting with a system, or whole body interaction, which means that the loom explicitly involved the whole body when interacting with it. They assume that: Some of these [qualities] may be aspects that we value today but that were probably not considered significant at the time of its original use. [11, p. 1597] The argumentation of Fernaeus and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="155" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>] thus includes two implications. First, interaction design should focus on qualities of the material, as the qualities constrain and enable certain ways of interaction. Second, looking into the past can help us making those subtle processes visible. The perspective of Ferneaus et al. fits McLuhan’s claim to understand former ways of interaction, while concurrently recognizing the material’s potentials and constraints. Their<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> strong focus on whole body interaction might have delighted McLuhan, as the human senses are addressed in a compre- hensive way. They also argue that the Jacquard Loom was a predecessor of modern day computers, as it worked with punched cards which define the patterns of fabric. However, they were criticized by Reeves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="157" class="deo:Reference">38</xref>] for not discussing the fundamental difference between analogue and digital computing sufficiently. Combining Reeves’ with Ferneaus and colleagues’ findings would finally comply to what McLuhan considered relevant. On the one hand, understanding the ways of interaction in preceding media or technology cultures can help us to provide new ways of interaction. On the other hand, it needs to be acknowledged that the new materials need new ways of interaction, which nevertheless can integrate formerly used interaction techniques. Ishii et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="158" class="deo:Reference">21</xref>] even go one step further: they propose Perfect Red, being what they call radical atoms. Perfect Red would be a new design material, which would change dynamically and have a complex set of respon- sive behaviors. Although Perfect Red is currently only a fic- tional material, representing a possible substance, Ishii et al. explored the interactions that would be possible with this material. However, in contrast to McLuhan, they begin with the exploration of new ways of interaction even if the correspond- ing physical material itself has not been invented. Recognizing that new materials provide new ways of interaction seems to be self-evident at a first glance. However, the various perspectives on how to explore and develop the new ways of interaction as well as how to integrate former ways result in a vast complexity. McLuhan ascribes the ability for creatively managing this complexity to artists, probably due to the fact that interaction design has not been prominent at his time. He assumes that: [. . . ] inherent in the artist’s creative inspiration is the process of subliminally sniffing out environmental change. It’s always been the artist who perceives the al- terations in man caused by a new media, who recognizes that the future is the present, and uses his work to pre- pare the ground for it. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="159" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>] Consequently, the difference between an artist and a designer needs to be the level of consciousness. While the artist might succeed in his work by subliminally apprehending the environmental changes, the designer also needs to explicitly rec- ognize, explore and understand the new environment in terms of digital and physical materials. In HCI, this is formalized by Research through Design, both theoretically (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="160" class="deo:Reference">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="161" class="deo:Reference">53</xref>]), and practically (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="162" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="163" class="deo:Reference">46</xref>]). Fernaeus and Sundström [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="164" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>] indicate that: [. . . ] there is no coincidence that the more successful interaction designs are built on deep technical understandings of the specific materials worked with [. . . ]. [12, p. 488] They rescind McLuhan’s concerns that humans are only consciously aware of the environment that has preceded it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="165" class="deo:Reference">31</xref>]. One could argue that McLuhan refers to the environment, and not to the specific material, which would make the argument<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> obsolete. Nevertheless, if we consider the environment in McLuhan’s sense as the media, or the ground that surrounds the figure, it also encompasses the materials interaction design works with.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="167" page="7" column="2">2859</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="168" page="8" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="169" page="8" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="171" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">A Network of Materials, Designers, and Users</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="174" page="8" column="1">Regarding the mediating role of artifacts between humans, McLuhan argued that: Manuscript culture is conversational if only because the writer and his audience are physically related by the form of publication as performance. [30, p. 84] This relation can also be described in terms of ANT. As the writer influences the audience, also over time, they form a network. This network would in addition to the writer and the reader consist of further actors, like the text, or the paper form of the manuscript. Whenever an action is conceived as networky, it has to pay the full prize of its extension, it’s composed mainly of voids, it can be interrupted, it is fully dependent on its material conditions [. . . ]. [27, p. 8] Latour, hereby, refers to the complexity of the networks, bringing along a difficulty in describing them thoroughly. However, the benefit of identifying the network lies in the detailed description of the connection between the actors, which includes also the materials in an active role. In interaction design this means that designers are impressed by the materials in a very different way than users, as they for example are inspired and/or constrained by the potential for crafting them. The users are influenced by the materials (or interaction gestalt, or interactive artifact), which direct them to reach a goal, be it efficient performance and/or having positive user experiences. Nevertheless, the designers and users influence each other indirectly; their network is mediated. Regarding the designer’s role in anticipating or inscribing the users’ experiences into the materials or the artifact, Latour refers to blinking text cursors (e.g., in text editors): As for the computer user input, the cursor might flash forever without the user being there or knowing what to do. There might be an enormous gap between the prescribed user and the user-in-the-flesh [. . . ]. [25, p. 237] Latour hereby refers to Don Norman’s Gulf of Execution, which he considers “[. . . ] an excellent introduction to the study of the tense relations between inscribed and real users” [25, p. 257]. However, Latour expresses regrets that Nor- man only refers to dysfunctions in the interface with the final user, instead of considering the shaping of the artifact by the engineers or the designers themselves. This is exactly what we can achieve with referring to ANT as theoretical framing; it can provide an instrument for describing the dynamic networks. The material, the designer, and the user have active parts in those networks, which do not require a priori definitions of the roles in the development process of any interaction system. Although McLuhan would argue for exclusively taking the new material into account, the historical and social <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> contexts need to be described in the networks as well, as long as they affect the current design or usage. This will facilitate understanding the effects of the materials on designers and users, and contribute to consciously explore and comprehend the new environment for designing new ways of interaction. The descriptions of these networks can finally also be regarded as the methodological grounding for interaction design research. For instance, Zimmerman and Forlizzi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="173" class="deo:Reference">52</xref>] claimed for research programs, which focus on research through design, to nurture multidisciplinary and cross- disciplinary insights into design and HCI, creating a body of examples for the community to build on. In order to contribute to that claim, it seems to be promising to take the perspectives of networks in the sense of ANT.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="175" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Doing Research Through Describing Design</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="179" page="8" column="2">Both McLuhan and Latour argue for a descriptive investiga- tion of situations, networks, or interactions. While McLuhan does not follow any paradigm or theory in doing so, Latour grounds his methodological claim in ANT. Fully established descriptions are the method used in ANT, and these descriptions do not need further explanations: “If a description remains in the need of an explanation, it means that it is a bad description” [26, p. 137]. However, he also admits that: To describe, to be attentive to the concrete state of af- fairs, to find the uniquely adequate account of a given situation, I myself have always found this incredibly de- manding. [26, p. 144] According to ANT, the more details the description com- prises, the better the scientific analysis is, which is expressed similarly in research through design. Zimmerman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="176" class="deo:Reference">54</xref>] call for a proper research methodology, realized for example by rigorous documentation of progress and evolution of research through design projects. Such documentation should preferably cover the whole process from problem framing and the idealized pre- ferred state to the final outcome. [54, p. 316] Furthermore, research examples, which are describing and examining the intentional choice and use of the research through design approach as a methodology and process would be needed. However, there is still the discussion of how to for- malize research through design (e.g., standards, processes) in order not to restrict “the ability to continually and creatively challenge status quo thinking”, which characterizes design research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="177" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>]. Gaver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="178" class="deo:Reference">14</xref>] argues that convergence cannot be the basis for a theoretical foundation in design, but discur- siveness and elaboration, as well as a specific set of detailed design examples. According to Gaver, describing design examples should be the core of design research. ANT’s methodological claim thus complies with Gaver’s notions of research through design, but also with the need for rigorous documentation of progress and evolution of research through design projects. ANT would explicitly include the activity of the involved actors into the descriptions, i.e., of materials, designers and users. It would provide a common way of describing the design examples, and thus facilitate a shared understanding especially in the materiality discourse.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="180" page="8" column="2">2860</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="181" page="9" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="182" page="9" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="183" page="9" column="1">CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="186" page="9" column="1">The junctures between Latour’s and McLuhan’s work and interaction design described above have the potential to strengthen the theoretical framing of the materials in interaction design by providing a perspective on materials, which equally integrates the activity of materials, designers and users. The strong emphasis on the effects of media on both designers and users allows to explicitly focus on, and design for new ways of interaction. Describing the design process in terms of a network reveals not only the important role of the materials as actors, but also unconscious design assumptions, procedures and constraints, which were induced by former materials or interactions. Research through design already claimed descriptions of design processes as outcome of design research. However, the discussion about how this will lead to theory in interaction design has not resulted in agree- ment. If we consider descriptions in ANT’s sense being the scientific outcome, the theoretical framing might be strength- ened. We are thus convinced that both McLuhan and Latour are valuable references in the materiality discourse, foremost by avoiding a priori assumptions about the role of materials, the designer, or the user to the benefit of describing activity caused by either human or non-human actors. Within this paper, we discussed several theoretical glimpses, which we consider being a basis for further discussions, concerns, and additions. Our prospective work will, for instance, include a discussion of McLuhan’s and Latour’s work in re- spect to Hallnäs’ and Redström’s function-expression circle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="184" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>], which has several analogies to McLuhan’s media analysis and Latour’s actor-networks, as well as a reflection on the idea of becomingness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="185" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>] in terms of sensory effects and impressions. This paper aimed at identifying elements for a theoretical framing of materials in interaction design based on Latour and McLuhan in order to facilitate the materiality discourse in HCI; when opening up such a reflection, a variety of topics for discussions and links to related notions emerges, which hopefully not only encourages us to proceed, but also inspires other HCI researchers to contribute to this discourse.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="187" page="9" column="1">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="188" page="9" column="1">We would like to express our thanks to Theo Hug and Petra Sundström for their critical and supportive comments. Furthermore, the financial support by the Federal Ministry of Economy, Family and Youth, as well as the National Foun- dation for Research, Technology and Development is grate- fully acknowledged (Christian Doppler Laboratory for “Contextual Interfaces”).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="189" page="9" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="190" page="9" column="1">1. Ames, M., and Naaman, M. Why we tag: motivations for annotation in mobile and online media. In Proc. CHI 2007, ACM (2007), 971–980.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="192" page="9" column="1">2. Austen, I. Early media prophet is now getting his due. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/26/books/" id="191">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/26/books/</ext-link> marshall-mcluhan-media-theorist-is-celebrated. html , 2011.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="194" page="9" column="1">3. Bergström, J., Clark, B., Frigo, A., Mazé, R., Redström, J., and Vallg arda, A. Becoming materials: material <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> forms and forms of practice. Digital Creativity 21, 3 (2010), 155–172.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="195" page="9" column="2">4. Bhavnani, S. K., and John, B. E. From sufficient to efficient usage: an analysis of strategic knowledge. In Proc. CHI 1997, ACM (1997), 91–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="196" page="9" column="2">5. Carpenter, E., and McLuhan, M. Acoustic space. Explorations in communication (1960), 65–70.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="197" page="9" column="2">6. Carter, S., and Mankoff, J. When participants do the capturing: the role of media in diary studies. In Proc. CHI 2005, ACM (2005), 899–908.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="198" page="9" column="2">7. de Castell, S., Taylor, N., Jenson, J., and Weiler, M. Theoretical and methodological challenges (and opportunities) in virtual worlds research. In Proc. FDG 2012, ACM (2012), 134–140.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="199" page="9" column="2">8. Dourish, P. Where the action is: the foundations of embodied interaction. The MIT Press, 2004.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="9" column="2">9. Dourish, P., and Mazmanian, M. Media as material: Information representations as material foundations for organizational practice. In Proc. Int. Symp on Process Organization Studies (2011).</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="9" column="2">10. Fallman, D. The new good: exploring the potential of philosophy of technology to contribute to human-computer interaction. In Proc. CHI 2011, ACM (2011), 1051–1060.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="9" column="2">11. Fernaeus, Y., Jonsson, M., and Tholander, J. Revisiting the jacquard loom: threads of history and current patterns in hci. In Proc. CHI 2012, ACM (2012), 1593–1602.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="9" column="2">12. Fernaeus, Y., and Sundström, P. The material move how materials matter in interaction design research. In Proc. DIS 2012, ACM (2012), 486–495.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="204" page="9" column="2">13. Friesen, N., and Hug, T. After the mediatic turn: Mcluhan’s training of the senses and media pedagogy today. Medialität und Realität (2011), 83–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="205" page="9" column="2">14. Gaver, W. What should we expect from research through design? In Proc. CHI 2012, ACM (2012), 937–946.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="9" column="2">15. Goodman, E., and Rosner, D. From garments to gardens: negotiating material relationships online and’by hand’. In Proc. CHI 2011, ACM (2011), 2257–2266.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="9" column="2">16. Hallnäs, L., and Redström, J. Interaction design: foundations, experiments. Textile Research Centre, Swedish School of Textiles, Unversity College of Bor as and Interactive Institute, 2006.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" page="9" column="2">17. Hoadley, C. M., and Enyedy, N. Between information and communication: middle spaces in computer media for learning. In Proc. CSCL 1999, International Society of the Learning Sciences (1999).</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="9" column="2">18. Huyssen, A. In the shadow of mcluhan: Jean baudrillard’s theory of simulation. Assemblage, 10 (1989), 7–17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="9" column="2">19. Ingold, T. Materials against materiality. Archaeological Dialogues 14, 01 (2007), 1–16.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="10" column="1">20. Ishii, H. Tangible bits: beyond pixels. In Proc. TEI 2008, TEI ’08, ACM (New York, NY, USA, 2008), xv–xxv.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" page="10" column="1">21. Ishii, H., Lakatos, D., Bonanni, L., and Labrune, J.-B. Radical atoms: beyond tangible bits, toward transformable materials. interactions 19, 1 (2012), 38–51.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="10" column="1">22. Jung, H., and Stolterman, E. Form and materiality in interaction design: a new approach to hci. In Proc. CHI EA 2011, ACM (2011), 399–408.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" page="10" column="1">23. Klemmer, S., Hartmann, B., and Takayama, L. How bodies matter: five themes for interaction design. In Proc. DIS 2006, ACM (2006), 140–149.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" page="10" column="1">24. Latour, B. On actor-network theory. Soziale Welt 47, 4 (1996), 369–381.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="219" page="10" column="1">25. Latour, B. Where Are the Missing Masses? The Sociology of a Few Mundane Artifacts. Psychology Press, 2003.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="220" page="10" column="1">26. Latour, B. Reassembling the social. An Introduction to Actor-Network-Theory (2006).</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="221" page="10" column="1">27. Latour, B. Networks, societies, spheres: Reflections of an actor-network theorist. International Journal of Communication 5, 2011 (2011), 796–810.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="222" page="10" column="1">28. Law, J. Actor network theory and material semiotics. The new Blackwell companion to social theory (2008), 141–158.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="223" page="10" column="1">29. Lim, Y.-k., Stolterman, E., Jung, H., and Donaldson, J. Interaction gestalt and the design of aesthetic interactions. In Proc. DPPI 2007, ACM (2007), 239–254.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="224" page="10" column="1">30. McLuhan, M. The gutenberg galaxy. University of Toronto Press, 1962.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="226" page="10" column="1">31. McLuhan, M. The playboy interview. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.nextnature.net/2009/12/" id="225">http://www.nextnature.net/2009/12/</ext-link> the-playboy-interview-marshall-mcluhan/ , 1969.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="227" page="10" column="1">32. McLuhan, M. Understanding media: the extensions of man, 6th edition ed. Routledge &amp; Keagan, 1987.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="228" page="10" column="1">33. McLuhan, M., and Fiore, Q. The Medium is the Massage. Penguin Books, 1967.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="229" page="10" column="1">34. Millen, D. R., Muller, M. J., Geyer, W., Wilcox, E., and Brownholtz, B. Patterns of media use in an activity-centric collaborative environment. In Proc. CHI 2005, ACM (2005), 879–888.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="230" page="10" column="1">35. Mol, A. Actor-network theory: sensitive terms and enduring tensions. Kölner Zeitschrift für Soziologie und Sozialpsychologie. Sonderheft 50 (2010), 253–269.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="231" page="10" column="1">36. Mullen, M. Coming to terms with the future he foresaw: Marshall mcluhan’s” understanding media”, 2006.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="232" page="10" column="1">37. Pierce, J. Undesigning technology: considering the negation of design by design. In Proc. CHI 2012, ACM (2012), 957–966.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="234" page="10" column="2">38. Reeves, S. Confusing computations. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://notesonresearch.tumblr.com/post/" id="233">http://notesonresearch.tumblr.com/post/</ext-link> 26870630666/confusing-computations , July 2012.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="236" page="10" column="2">39. Re-touching mcluhan – the medium is the massage conference. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://mcluhan2011.eu/" id="235">http://mcluhan2011.eu/</ext-link> .</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="237" page="10" column="2">40. Rosner, D. The material practices of collaboration. In Proc. CSCW 2012, ACM (2012), 1155–1164.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="238" page="10" column="2">41. Rusch, G. Medienkommunikation. Innovation durch Kommunikation (2009), 75–84.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="239" page="10" column="2">42. Schön, D. Designing as reflective conversation with the materials of a design situation. Knowledge-Based Systems 5, 1 (1992), 3–14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="240" page="10" column="2">43. Schön, D., and Bennett, J. Bringing design to software. ACM, 1996, ch. Reflective conversation with materials, 171–189.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="241" page="10" column="2">44. Stadler, F. From figure / ground to actor-networks: Mcluhan and latour. http: //felix.openflows.com/html/mcluhan_latour.html , 1998.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="242" page="10" column="2">45. Suchman, L. Human/machine reconsidered. Cognitive Studies 5, 1 (1998), 5–13.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="243" page="10" column="2">46. Sundström, P., and Höök, K. Hand in hand with the material: designing for suppleness. In Proc. CHI 2010, ACM (2010), 463–472.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="244" page="10" column="2">47. Ullmer, B., and Ishii, H. Emerging frameworks for tangible user interfaces. IBM systems journal 39, 3.4 (2000), 915–931.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="245" page="10" column="2">48. Vallg arda, A., and Redström, J. Computational composites. In Proc. CHI 2007, ACM (2007), 513–522.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="247" page="10" column="2">49. Viseu, A. How social is the social? rethinking the role of artifacts in cognitive science. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.yorku.ca/" id="246">http://www.yorku.ca/</ext-link> aviseu/eng_art-cog_content.html#two , May 2000.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="248" page="10" column="2">50. Voida, A., and Mynatt, E. D. Six themes of the communicative appropriation of photographic images. In Proc. CHI 2005, ACM (2005), 171–180.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="249" page="10" column="2">51. Wiberg, M., Ishii, H., Dourish, P., Rosner, D., Vallg arda, A., Sundström, P., Kerridge, T., and Rolston, M. ”material interactions”: from atoms &amp; bits to entangled practices. In Proc. CHI EA 2012, ACM (2012), 1147–1150.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="250" page="10" column="2">52. Zimmerman, J., and Forlizzi, J. The role of design artifacts in design theory construction. Artifact 2, 1 (2008), 41–45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="251" page="10" column="2">53. Zimmerman, J., Forlizzi, J., and Evenson, S. Research through design as a method for interaction design research in hci. In Proc. CHI 2007, ACM (2007), 493–502.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="252" page="10" column="2">54. Zimmerman, J., Stolterman, E., and Forlizzi, J. An analysis and critique of research through design: towards a formalization of a research approach. In Proc. DIS 2010, ACM (2010), 310–319.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="211" page="9" column="2">2861</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="212" page="10" column="1">Session: Narrative and Materiality</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="213" page="10" column="1">CHI 2013: Changing Perspectives, Paris, France</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="253" page="10" column="2">2862</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
