<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e8c1be54bb6b987396c16676348657d18240619ff5aba1fcc7aa2e282b838508</job>
    <base_name>62fq</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/grf.0000000000000059">http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/9780470544051.ch17</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="2">CO-DESIGN AND THE USE OF STORIES TO ENABLE EMPATHY</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">Christine KINGSLEY</name>
          <aff id="4">1</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="5">1 University of Dundee</footnote>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6" confidence="possible">The altruistic concepts of social responsibility, citizenship and sustainability are set to reframe Design Education in the 21 st century from feeding consumptive markets to responding to issue driven agendas. Current thinking suggests that a way of moving towards this may be through co-creation (Sanders 2008). The new transferable skill set, seen as giving competitive edge and economic value (Design Council 2007 et all), needs to be explicitly practiced within the design curriculum. If co-creation is the new design process it requires us to change how design education communicates. If this change is effective, it could have unimaginable significance in the way our graduates approach employment and utilize their transferable skills, forming graduates for the 21 st century (QAA) that can cope with change. The following paper considers co-design from two perspectives, a research perspective and a teaching and learning perspective. The unifying thread between the two is the concern with the issue of effective change. Recommendations are made for the development of projects designed to expose communities to a new way of design thinking and action. Keywords: co-design; social responsibility; storytelling; transition; participation; reflection.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="7" page="1" column="1">1 INTRODUCTION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Co-design is a method. It is a way of progressing through a problem or design scenario and is used as a means of, for example, attending to behavioural change. Elizabeth Sanders (2008), one of the strongest advocates of co-design notes (in a paper with Pieter Jan Stappers) that it “refers to any act of collective creativity, that is shared by two or more people...co-design refers to the creativity of designers and people not trained in design working together in the design development process”.</region>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" page="1" column="1">This paper provides two examples of co-design, both have people at their heart and are real-world situations. The first case study, (a research project led by the author) entitled Dundee Expression used co-design as a means of capturing what it feels like to experience Aphasia, as first hand understanding of the condition was little understood due to problems of accessibility. The second example, Engage Lochee, used co-design as a way of teaching novice designers about the issue of social responsibility as part of the changing responsibilities of design and the effect upon the design process. The examples are used to explore and observe the act of changing designers approach to designing so that the ways of working and thinking reflect the new issue driven agenda. <marker type="block"/> Co-design was employed as a means of nurturing effective behavioural change in people and through a literature review a framework for evaluation was created with five generic themes initially identified, namely, story, empathy, transition in self, sharing and time (Frank, 1995; Goleman, 2006; Richardson, 1990; Sanders, 2006; Sanders and Stappers, 2008; Taylor, 2008). For brevity purposes an overview of the case studies are provided with emphasis given to presenting the tentative findings within each of the five themes.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">2 CASE STUDY 1: DUNDEE EXPRESSION</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="17" page="2" column="1">2.1 Findings from the Dundee Expression project</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="2" column="1">2.1.1 Story Participants took a holistic and personal view when visualising the maxim ‘making the invisible disability visible’. Some stories included the physical effects of a stroke and while this related to some participants medical histories, it was not representative of all. The subjective nature of the stories and experiences caused unrest among the participants and conflict emerged within the group about the representation of aphasia impairment. One participant claimed an image suggested lobotomy. Another participant’s representation told a metaphorical story. Another participant used figurative representation: reduced use of his left leg, arm and part of his head by compositionally cutting them out of the layout - a brutally honest account. There was not one image that defined the condition. It was the collection of stories and the collection of images together that provided a narrative that more closely reflected the reality of Aphasia for those who are affected by it, directly and indirectly</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">This narrative and the process of creating the narrative struck a cord and facilitated empathy. The participants recognized the collective need to exchange stories and move forward.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="20" page="2" column="1">2.1.2 Empathy</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">During the workshops facilitators observed increased empathy between the participants, noting a move away from the self towards external and community concerns. The pace of the workshops and the emphasis on visualising their accounts of aphasia nurtured empathy and provided participants with the time and tool to attune to one another’s experiences.</region>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" page="2" column="1">The social barriers, (for example exclusion from conversation, loosing their train of thought in mid- conversation) that impeded the ‘flow’ of telling a story became less evident as the process evolved and trust was noticeably forming as conversation duration extended and frequency increased. Increased social aptitude; less introspection and talking over one another; reflecting on the change in roles aphasia had imposed on carer’s and family demonstrated an empathetic change in the participants attitude.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" page="2" column="1">2.1.3 Transition in Self</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="2" column="1">The printmaking process adopted in the workshops enforced a sequence or process for image making that cannot be compromised. The relief printing gave participants a clear structure. This regulated routine and progression. Participants experienced immersion in their process and a state of flow (Lidwell et all, 2003). Family reported the participants having a new focus i.e. a new creative social activity, had an increase in self-esteem and confidence.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="25" page="2" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="26" page="2" column="1">256</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="27" page="3" column="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="28" page="3" column="1">2.1.4 Sharing</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">The workshop process was driven by the incentive that a public exhibition at Dundee Contemporary Art Centre would take place on completion of the work 1 . The sense of achievement seeing work in a professional environment was a factor. Family expressed pride in achievements on visiting the exhibition since acquiring aphasia participants had been a source of concern rather than celebration. General awareness of aphasia increased through coverage in the local press, attendance at conferences and dissemination in articles in multidisciplinary journals. The University and NHS primary trust stakeholders realised the significance and financed further support through the launch of a postcard pack showing selected images and method for use in rehabilitation.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="3" column="1">2.1.5 Time</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="3" column="1">Time was a key consideration in planning the discussion topics as people with aphasia are talked over, ignored or answered for. However, the time required to move around the workshop with participants who where physically impaired and the time necessary to qualify individual and group agreement after discussions was underestimated. Time for the act of co-creation is of central importance, as the process requires you to look at the intersections between the problem, methods, techniques and users. It is at these junctions where relationships and trust are built.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="1" column="1">Aphasia damages the speech and language centre of the brain and affects all modes of communication - reading, writing, listening and speaking. Aphasia is an invisible disability in that it has no physical outward signs on a person. People with aphasia suffer internal and external frustrations. Most people have little awareness of the condition and misunderstandings of behaviour can lead to people with aphasia being treated inappropriately e.g. A bus driver asks a person with aphasia to leave the bus mistaking their slurred speech and confusion over destination for drunkenness. The problem of misrepresentation</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="13" page="1" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="14" page="1" column="1">255</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="15" page="2" column="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">in health care information was identified as a problem as existing formats did not adequately capture the levels of frustration associated with Aphasia, nor did they sufficiently or appropriately attend to the lack of public knowledge. The Expression project was devised to collect first hand information about the condition from the participants themselves by running a series of five workshops to explore effective visual communication. The co-design project team consisted of two speech and language therapists; one brain injury centre artist with extensive experience of patients with aphasia; a design educator/illustrator (the author) and six participants with Aphasia. A central challenge for the team was the highly variable nature of the condition. This posed a problem both trying to ‘tell the story’ of aphasia from an end-users perspective and ‘interpreting the story’ from the carers, family and health professional’s viewpoint. A holistic approach to the inquiry was constructed to reflect the terms of disability used by the World Health Organisation: Participation, Impairment, Activity and Well-being. Participants were carefully selected on the basis that they had reached a level of understanding about their condition that they could reflect on the change to their life. In each of the five corresponding workshops participants used semi- structured discussion and visualisation techniques to communicate their levels of frustration associated with Aphasia.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="32" page="3" column="1">3 CASE STUDY 2:</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="33" page="3" column="1">ENGAGE LOCHEE</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">This second example of co-design is set within the context of teaching and learning, and is discussed from the perspective of the educator rather than student. It is explored in the context of teaching student designers about the changing social responsibilities of design to reflect the new issue driven agenda, for example issues such as sustainability and health. As Barnett (2000) notes, ‘Part of the responsibility of higher education in a supercomplex age...is that of creating a disturbance in the minds and beings of students. Both a cognitive and an experiential disturbance are called for’. Sanders &amp; Stappers (2008) support this view noting,‘[educators] will need to provide alternative learning experiences and curricula for those who are designing and building scaffolds to support the collective creativity of others’. The teaching and learning project was devised to enable a group of students to work at the intersections of product and interactive media design and to create services that helped communicate a regeneration programme to, and with, a local community. Lochee 2 , a significant area and community in Dundee, situated west of the heart of the city was chosen because (as typical of many industrialized areas in the early 20 th century) it continues to suffer economically with the demise of the British textile industry.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="3" column="1">3.1 Findings from the Engage Lochee project</h2>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="36" page="3" column="1">3.1.1 Story</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="3" column="1">As an educator, the teaching aim was to induce a cognitive and experiential disturbance and the objective was for the students to learn about social responsibility. The cognitive shift was to reflect the change in the design landscape; students were learning to understand the role of designer as facilitator, moving away from designer as product maker. The experiential shift was provided through the choice of project location and the social issues driving the design brief.</region>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">It was observed that the level of awareness by students concerning their future role and potential responsibilities as a designer as facilitator of change was heightened. The level of social complexity disarmed the students because it was too great a ‘disturbance’, it did not allow them to use their existing skills to best effect and the skills that were required were ones the students had low levels of experience in using in a design context. The theory to engage in a live co-design project within a local community context was simple; however, 1 The DCA is recognised as an international exhibition venue, showcasing emerging artists and visionary concepts. For the partici- pants to be invited to exhibit their work as expert was significant in their eyes and in others. 2 Lochee was once affectionately referred to as Tipperary due to the number of Irish immigrants who worked in the mills and gave the area identity</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="39" page="3" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="40" page="3" column="1">257</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41" page="4" column="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="4" column="1">the project practicalities revealed there was insufficient time to build trust with the community and for a transition in them-selves to occur. Some students struggled with a self-directed route and the slow process of achieving genuine communication with stakeholders. For example, one student noted that it was in the ‘giving and receiving’ of communication that his position changed with contact with an isolated group in the community and lots of reading of course material that design + people = success. It was not until listening to the community’s needs that he found his direction within the brief.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="4" column="1">3.1.2 Empathy</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">The theoretical and practical ‘disturbances’ witnessed by the author included the student’s discomfort when dealing with a problem finding situation in that they appeared to lack confidence when applying their transferable skills. In losing confidence, they demonstrated confusion as to their role and they questioned the appropriateness of the project. As a result, a number of workshops were devised with a series of instructions for the students to use as a framework for navigating the scenario. For example, a key concern was the cohorts’ lack of capacity to form and sustain connections with community groups and as such, one workshop discussion centred round this issue. In doing so, anxiety surrounding the student ability to cope with the project was reduced, knowledge of the local community was heightened and the skill of listening was highlighted.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="4" column="1">3.1.3 Transition in Self</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="4" column="1">There was a noticeable disparity in the student’s awareness of the role of the designer in the 21 st century. It is fair to say they predominantly associated design with products rather than process with an emphasis on popular or highly commercial brands. The intention of the co-design project was to instigate an understanding of the role of designer as facilitator and to increase their awareness of social responsibility. In doing so a change of perspective from which the students viewed a situation needed to occur. <marker type="block"/> This shift did not happen easily or quickly. Although observation of community discussions enabled students to connect more closely with individuals and appreciate the realities of the problems associated with community regeneration, the shift was difficult. As a result a storytelling workshop facilitated by the teaching team was organised to help deepen awareness within the students themselves. Visualising the information gathered by the students and using a ‘mapping’ method to expose the collective group knowledge of the issue of regeneration within Lochee facilitated an increase in confidence in the students. An awareness of the shift in approach to questioning meant students were able to move from ‘I’ to ‘we’ or ‘me’ to ‘you’ perspective.<marker type="block"/> The transition in understanding the new landscape of Design deepened as students continued to engage with real users and real-world situations. As student knowledge of the local community increased, so did their empathy towards the local community.<marker type="block"/> There was also a transition of self from the educator perspective, in that the manner in which the project was contextualised required refinement, a more transparent approach to communicating the problem finding nature of the project rather than problem solving. Thereby helping the co-design team navigate the situation and identify appropriate issues for resolution.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" page="4" column="1">3.1.4 Sharing</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" page="4" column="1">A key means of disseminating knowledge and information in design is via the method of exhibition because it allows a large body of visual work to be presented to a large number of people at one time and it is relatively cost effective in the educational environment. It was chosen to communicate the student project findings however, the choice of location for the exhibition proved ineffective because accessibility was insufficient to the local community which resulted in poor attendance. The method of exhibition did not connect with the user or local community and this can also be attributed to the level of engagement with the community.</region>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="52" page="4" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="53" page="4" column="1">258</outsider>
            <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54" page="5" column="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="55" page="5" column="1">3.1.5 Time</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" page="5" column="1">Considering the levels of disturbance created in the project time frame, twelve days was not sufficient to build trust between the students and the community and understanding of the problem finding brief. Trust, atonement and empathy are prerequisites for meaningful social interactions and relationships. Co-design within the undergraduate educational framework would benefit from a significant increase in the amount and intensity of time given to the teaching and learning associated with co-creation experience.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="57" page="5" column="1">4 CONCLUSIONS AND COMMON THEMES IN THE TWO CASE STUDIES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" page="5" column="1">To clarify the purpose of sharing observations of co-creation from the perspectives of a teaching and learning and a teaching and research both cases were used to demonstrate co-design with stakeholders for effective change: Dundee Expression to reduce misconceptions about aphasia by promoting awareness and in Engage Lochee enable the community to change through its citizens’ motivations and decisions. <marker type="block"/> Disturbance in mind and being can differ greatly depending on the levels of empathy attained. Transformation in stance, role, and expectations has to change in co-creation as the role of expert is reversed and rotates continually. Support for student developing flexibility and building confidence to become co-creators needs to happen through the complexities of real world co-creation experiences if a transferable skill set is to emerge. Attuning and empathizing with stakeholders is fundamental to successful co-creation. The significant stories that emerged from both case studies were that ‘Stories unite. They tell us who ‘we are’ Stories create memory and memory creates identity (Sacks, 2007). All stakeholders/participants/co-creators exposed fears and insecurities, uncomfortable realities, changes in behaviour, adaptability and transformation. Through the sharing of individual illness narratives Expression participants emerged with voices previously unheard. Their stories gave them a new identity enabled by co-design practice, which acted as advocate through visualisation and service. Story mapping enabled students to engage again with Lochee. By recall and recognition of individual and collective experiences in Lochee, themes were captured and categorised and sharing tentative interactions gave students confidence to push forward again envisioning new stories, characters and scenarios to share with the community. The stories showed change, student’s stories were honest, reflecting their self-interests and compared them to stakeholders needs. It demonstrated to the students the realities associated with end-user research. The shortage and fragmentation of time in both case studies belies most issues in the 21 st century. Subsequent projects of a similar nature will require a concerted period of time to build trust and develop relations in meaningful ways. As educators supporting students in this shift in design skills to design enablers and catalysts (Fuad-Luke, 2007) facilitators of thinking, negotiators and integrators of complexity and visualisers of intangibles (Inns, 2008), the conflict between students perceptions and expectation need to be aligned. The role of ‘being there’ is bridging this gap for students to envision skills in alternative contexts.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="60" page="5" column="1">5 RECOMMENDATIONS AND STRATEGIES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">It has been observed that stories enforce reflection (Greenhalgh, 2000) and stories enable connections to be made and synthesis to happen (Sacks, 2007). Creating stories about design practices should enable connections and synthesis between skills necessary for the 21 st century. Data suggests from both case studies that resonant images can emerge from stories, which draw people together that can otherwise find it difficult to connect. Story forming and making take time, realistic goals are necessary in co-creation processes for meaningful learning outcomes to emerge. Co-creation epitomises the real world experience in all its complexity. To press the stop button more often and allocate time to reflect on what has been achieved through sharing processes and thinking can build a valuable transferable skill set. This affordance of time will exhibit designerly ways of ‘being there’. The following tentative recommendations are presented to prepare students and educators for the 21 st century. Sharing stories communicating process, thinking and reflection of design outputs can bring universal resonance and meaning. Promotion and publicity through the use of existing and complimentary networks, forums, student-led initiatives that empower students, question their expectations while encouraging self-belief can contribute to our changing world. Real world projects are an opportunity to consider a social model</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="62" page="5" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="63" page="5" column="1">259</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="6" column="1">8 th European Academy Of Design Conference - 1 st , 2 nd &amp; 3 rd April 2009, The Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen, Scotland</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65" page="6" column="1">of design practice (Margolin, 2002), enabling plentiful disturbance in mind and being (Barnett, 2000). Introducing the social toolkit will not be the accomplishment of a degree but the foundations for a life- long acquisition of social skills in social awareness and social facility (Goleman, 2006) However further research is required with stakeholders across the contexts of academia, industry and society. How we use these stories will reveal the value of transferable skills for the 21 st century Design Graduate.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="66" page="6" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="67" page="6" column="1">BARNETT, R., 2000. Realizing the University in an age of supercomplexity. UK, Society for Research into Higher</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="68" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Education and the Open University Press. CHAPMAN, J and GANT, N. 2007. Designers, visionaries and other stories: a collection of sustainable design essays. UK. Cromwell Press. Chapter 2 Alistair Fuad-Luke. GREENHALGH, T and HURWITZ, B., 2000. Narrative Based Medicine: Dialogue and discourse in clinical practice. UK, BMJ Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="69" page="6" column="1">GOLEMAN, D.,2006. Social Intelligence. UK Arrow Books</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="70" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">INNS, T., 2008 Designing for the 21 st Century: interdisciplinary questions and insights. Aldershot. Gower Publishing LIDELL, W; HOLDEN, K and BUTLER,J 2003. Universal Principles of Design. USA. Rockport Publishing. HUGO, J.,2002. Designing Trigger pictures in context: the challenge of balance. Journal of Audiovisual Media in Medicine 25:3 pp99-105</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="71" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">SACKS,J.,2007. Now’s the time to tell a new story of Britain. The Times Mon 22 nd Oct page 55</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="73" page="6" column="1">SANDERS,E and STAPPERS, P,J.2008. Co-creation and the new landscape of design. [online] Available from http:// www.maketools.com/pdfs/CoCreation_Sanders_Stappers_08_preprint.pdf [accessed 21 st January 2009] TAYLOR, M., 2008 Behaviour Battles ETHOS issue 6 [online] available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://ethos" id="72">http://ethos</ext-link> journal.com</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="74" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">DEVAS, A., 2008. Widening Participation and the Media student Experience Art Design Media Subject Centre The Higher Education Academy Networks magazine issue 04</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="75" page="6" column="1">BROWN, B et all. 2008. Brighton 05-06-07 Design Manifesto Design Issues 1: 24 MARGOLIN, V and MARGOLIN, S 2002. A ‘Social Model’ of Design: Issues of Practice and Research. Design Issues Journal 18:4 pp24-30</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="76" page="6" column="1">VILJOEN, A and HOSKYNS, T., 2007. For Real: a review of the extent of ‘live practice’ within 3D design education in the UK and its potential contribution to curriculum development within the ADM subject Area [online] Report for</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="6" column="1">the HEA Learning and Teaching Project. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.adm.heacademy.ac.uk/library/files/adm-hea-" id="77">http://www.adm.heacademy.ac.uk/library/files/adm-hea-</ext-link> projects/viljoen-report.pdf [accessed 11th November 2008] High-level skills for higher value 2007[online] available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.ukdesignskills.com/pages/the_background." id="78">http://www.ukdesignskills.com/pages/the_background.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">html [accessed 11 th November 2008] MYERSON, J.,2007 Pressing the Button Intersections Conference Overview [online] transcript pdf and pod-cast</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="83" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/en/About-Design/Podcasts-and-Downloads/" id="81">http://www.designcouncil.org.uk/en/About-Design/Podcasts-and-Downloads/</ext-link> [accessed 11th November 2008] RSA Design Directions 2007/8 student awards: Engage! Catalysing social change through design-led social participation [online] available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.rsadesigndirections.org/briefs/RDD0708-Projects.pdf" id="82">http://www.rsadesigndirections.org/briefs/RDD0708-Projects.pdf</ext-link> pp9-11 QAA The Quality Assurance Agency for Higher Education enhancement themes, Graduate attributes for the 21 st century</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="84" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Acknowledgements The author would like to express thanks to the Design Studies staff team the students for their forbearance under uncomfortable changes; the Expression facilitation team; participants NHS Tayside and the University of Dundee who have supported the research presented in this paper; and Dr Louise Valentine.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="6" column="1">Christine, KINGSLEY University of Dundee Design Studies Department, Perth Road, Dundee <email id="85">c.m.kingsley@dundee.ac.uk</email> 01382 388287</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="87" page="6" column="1">EAD09/029</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="88" page="6" column="1">260</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
