<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>56b5114b3cb7b898b1e34fa142b25fd183925cb8f578022a106d05df24f09b71</job>
    <base_name>62ew</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00001199-199206000-00016">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10447310802583933</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Using Artifacts to Interpret and Negotiate Knowledge across Domains</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">Lawrence Erlbaum associates Inc.</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6" confidence="possible">Mahwah, New Jersey, Expected 2004</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="7">1</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="2" page="1" column="1">Paul R. Carlile School of Business Administration MIT Boston, MA</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Draft PLEASE DO NOT CITE WITHOUT PERMISSION FROM AUTHOR Submitted for Publication in:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Rafaeli, A. &amp; Pratt, M. (Eds.), Artifacts and Organizations:</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="2" column="1">Introduction Objects as Artifacts</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">The material world, in one shape or form, always mediates human activity. People</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" page="2" column="1">never act in a vacuum or some sort of hypothetical universe of doing but always with respect <marker type="block"/> to arrangements, tools and material objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Engestrom, 1990</xref>). Even an idea generates value</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">for the individual because it has material-objective force in terms of its consequences in the social world (Strauss (1993). “Object[s]” write Bowker and Star (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Bowker and Star, 1999</xref>),</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="2" column="1">“include many things—stuff and things, tools, artifacts and techniques, and ideas, stories and <marker type="block"/> memories—objects that are treated as consequential by a community members” (Clarke and<marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Fujimura, 1992</xref>). This is sometimes hard to recognize because objects indeed have the power</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="19" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">that they do because of the taken for granted state in which that exist in a given community. For example, in an academic setting such words as assistant, associate and full are objects that have tremendous force in our social interactions because that have consequences on hiring, grant writing, student mentoring and status. As we struggle to describe the importance of these words to those who have never been in an academic setting we begin to recognize that they have the force that they do because of their accepted, but taken for granted state within our own community. To understand how objects (artifacts) shape human activity in this chapter I examine</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="2" column="1">organizations that design and build products. The focus of the chapter will be on two things.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">First, how objects shape or structure the knowledge of the various functional communities that are involved in producing new products (i.e., sales/marketing, design engineering, manufacturing engineering, and production). The objects used by actors within a specialized domain differentiates their knowledge in problematic ways from others that result in</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="22" page="2" column="1">2</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="3" column="1">boundaries that make collaboration across them difficult (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2002</xref>). Second, despite this</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">fact some objects actually help actors from different specialized communities (Lave and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" page="3" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Wenger, 1991</xref>) to represent, translate and even jointly transform the knowledge being used to<marker type="block"/> define the product. These objects, what Leigh Star first described as boundary objects (Star,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">1989; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>) help create a shared context between specialized communities because they help actors share their knowledge and assess the knowledge being used in other specialized communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid, 1991</xref>). To resolve this apparent paradox, that some objects reinforce boundaries between</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" page="3" column="1">functional domains, while other objects actually help actors collaborate across the boundaries <marker type="block"/> between functional domains, I will outline the characteristics that allow a particular object to<marker type="block"/> play the role of a boundary object. With all this done I the describe what I call a “relational”<marker type="block"/> view which focuses on the relationship between the actors involved and the boundary objects</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">that they use. This relational view addresses both the capacity of the boundary objects to represent the differences and dependencies that are consequential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2003</xref>) between them, but also an actors ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Black, Carlile and Repenning, 2003</xref>) to wield those boundary objects as they seek to represent and even negotiate the knowledge being used to define the product.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="3" column="1">Material Artifacts and Organizations</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">The material world is a tangible one—a world of doing. It is a world that takes almost all of our time, but it is a world that is seldom focused on in the social sciences. It belongs to that bulky, but seldom examined category we call “taken for granted,” or abstractly covered up by such concepts as technology, task or even “the environment.” But as in most anyone’s work, and especially in the product development and manufacturing</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="41" page="3" column="1">3</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">work being discussed here (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Clark and Wheelright, 1995</xref>), the material world is not only the medium that shapes the knowledge that individuals use and value, but is also a collective outcome—that is, a social and contested process that produces a final product that can be sold to the costumer for a profit. Since the 1930’s the field of anthropology has taken seriously the study of material</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="4" column="1">artifacts in understanding human cultures ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Malinowski, 1953</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Reynolds, 1987</xref>). Besides the<marker type="block"/> observational methods that gives easy access to material artifacts, the most important reason<marker type="block"/> why such attention was paid to artifacts because they were so consequential in making sense</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">of and describing non-western cultures. In this effort a great deal of attention was paid to artifacts used in cooking, warfare, trade and rituals. But beginning in the 1970’s the new field of science and technology studies in sociology utilized a variety of historical and ethnographic methods which allowed the to explicitly focus on the material artifacts of science and invention to describe at a detailed level the historical evolution and social</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="4" column="1">shaping of science and technology ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Hughes, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Pinch and Bjiker, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Latour, 1987</xref>). In<marker type="block"/> the field of organization studies we don’t begin to see a particular focus on material artifacts</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">except indirectly by those taking a more situated view of technology starting in the 80’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Barley, 1986</xref>; Orlikowski, 1992)—not surprisingly this work was influenced by both anthropological methods and sociological studies of science and technology. For the most part those coming from a social psychological perspective in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="4" column="1">organization studies have not focused on material artifacts. However, this began to change in <marker type="block"/> the 1980’s with Ed Schein’s cultural frameworks that emphasized an examination of artifacts</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">as an initial means of understanding an organization’s culture. This was followed in the 1990’s by a series of scholars focusing on identity and some of the factors that determine</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="60" page="4" column="1">4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">belonging or not belonging to a given identity group (Hatch, 1993; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Pratt and Rafaeli, 1997</xref>;</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" page="5" column="1">others). Empirically this work focused on such tangible artifacts as dress and other symbols</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">of group identify or status. Based on my own background in anthropological methods, the work that I started in mid-90’s explicitly focused on the material objects used by actors in a given functional practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Bourdieu, 1977</xref>) to bring some clarity to how knowledge is shaped differently in organizations and the boundaries or challenges that result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 1997</xref>; 2002). In what follows I will review some of my work to outline the two fundamental questions laid out at</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="67" page="5" column="1">the beginning of this chapter: how do objects structure knowledge in communities differently</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">and how do objects facilitate collaboration across these communities.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="69" page="5" column="1">The Power of the Material World: Objects and their Ends</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Product development organizations are in the business of designing and producing material artifacts—often at high volume, low variability (high quality), and low cost; and to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="5" column="1">do this well demands the specialization of knowledge across a variety of functional domains.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">To achieve such specialization actors in each functional domain create and use different objects and work with them toward different requirements or ends. Fore example in sales, the focus is on the numbers (i.e., costing and volume numbers, specifications) and getting them “right”; in design, it is the prototype and hitting the required specification; in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="5" column="1">manufacturing, it is implementing a high-volume, high cycle-time process; and in production,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">it is getting good products delivered on time. The graphic below frames in a simple manner how the material world constrains and enables knowledge in a functional domain or practice. The three basic concepts contained in</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75" page="5" column="1">5</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" page="6" column="1">the graphic are objects/artifacts, problem-solving activities, and ends—three concepts that are</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">interdependent as actors try to accomplish their work.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5.1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="78" page="6" column="1">Figure 5.1 The Material World: Objects, Ends and Problem-Solving Activities</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Problem Artifacts/ Solving Ends Objects Activities In a product development context individuals work with numbers, blueprints, faxes,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="6" column="1">parts, tools, products and machines that individuals create to test and produce such products. <marker type="block"/> “Ends” are outcomes that demonstrate success in creating, testing and producing a product—</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">a signed sales contract, a prototype parts order, an assembly process certification, or a high quality part off the production line. The work itself is an ongoing series of problem solving activities (Hipple and Tyre, 1996)—a process of moving an object from its initial state to a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" page="6" column="1">desired end state. This problem solving process should be seen broadly, encompassing all of <marker type="block"/> the know-how, techniques, and “trial and error” that it takes to move a material object toward</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">a desired outcome. The objects and ends of a functional domain are not separate from the problem</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" page="6" column="1">solving activities that occupy them. Further, if the relations among artifacts, problem solving <marker type="block"/> activities and their ends, are dialectically constituted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Lave, 1988</xref>: 175), then it is not possible<marker type="block"/> to separate the means of problem solving from the artifacts and their ends. Take for example</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="90" page="6" column="1">6</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">how a material artifact such as a design print is used differently by actors in different functional specialties. To sales, the print represents a one-dimensional object to be used in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="92" page="7" column="1">creating business and negotiating price. For a design engineer, it represents a singular, three-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">dimensional object that expresses geometry, tolerances, and other key issues to insure functionality. To a manufacturing engineer, the print represents the challenge of creating a high-volume process—“how do I make 2,000 of these a day”—requiring attention to the orientation and number of parts, corners and material surfaces, and cycle time. To a production supervisor, it jogs memories of past bottlenecks, operator errors, and scrap</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="7" column="1">problems that could be encountered. In each case, the print maybe the same, but the problem <marker type="block"/> setting that an individual inhabits, shapes what approach they take to the artifact (i.e., design<marker type="block"/> print), what specification and numbers they look at, and what ends are they concerned about.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">In all of these cases, even though the artifact, the design print is the same, the ends and the specialized knowledge used to reach those ends are very different. Also by focusing on the material world we develop insight into the characteristics of knowledge that makes it so difficult to communicate or move across functional boundaries. So besides that tacit nature of knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Nonaka, 1994</xref>; Polyani, 1966) by focusing on the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" page="7" column="1">artifacts involved we observe that knowledge is localized around particular objects and ends, <marker type="block"/> is embedded in a particular practice and invested in a given outcome. This is why of course</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">that knowledge may be seen as “at stake” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2002</xref>) in the sense that communities are reluctant to give up what knowledge that has taken them period of time to earn. Overall, a focus on objects and their ends provides a more concrete description of the situated and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="7" column="1">invested nature of knowledge than has often proved illusive when less observational methods</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">are used.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="105" page="7" column="1">7</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="106" page="8" column="1">The Shaping of Knowledge: Focusing on Objects and their Ends</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">This section provides examples of how objects and ends structure actor’s knowledge in different ways. I will describe two functional domains: design work and manufacturing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" page="8" column="1">engineering work. This will provide a clear picture of how the material world faced by these</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="109" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">two types of actors creates tensions between their knowledge and interests and generates barriers in their efforts collaborate across functional domains. Objects and Ends: Structuring Knowledge in Design Work X.T. Products was in the business of designing and producing a variety of performance and safety values for automotive fuel systems. At X.T. design engineers are</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" page="8" column="1">handed the task of designing and building a prototype of the product that functions within the <marker type="block"/> specifications defined by the customer. Specifications include overall dimensions, shape (the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="112" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">space the product will be going into), weight, materials, and quantity. Other specifications deal more with the actual mechanical function of the production, such as how efficiently it</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" page="8" column="1">works (i.e., efficient use of energy), how effectively it does the work that it is designed to do <marker type="block"/> (how well it seals on a surface, cools a room, etc.), and how well it deals with heat, vibration</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">(noise), and overall wear and tear. Design drawings are a fundamental artifact used in the work that design engineers do. The process of converting specifications into a product starts with a process of sketching,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" page="8" column="1">layout and fine-tuning the dimensions and mechanical relationships on paper. Formal design</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">drawings have to be generated, checked by another engineer to see if all of the dimensions stack properly, and then sent back to the overseeing group of design engineers to identify 1 To see if all of the dimensions “stack up” refers adding up all of the smaller dimensions to see if they equal the larger dimensions on the outside. This is important because even if the smaller</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="118" page="8" column="1">dimensions, say .25 inches, 1.5 inches, and, .75 inches, 1.25 inches, and .50 inches, and .25 inches,</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="119" page="8" column="1">8</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="120" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">problems, and make recommendations. The goal of the design drawing is to work out all of the special and interdependent relationships so that prototype parts can be machined or ordered from suppliers as soon as possible. In the end, the success of a design engineer depends on their ability to make a physical prototype that can be tested to see if it works according to the required specification. As I was told by the head design engineer at X.T., hitting “spec” is “science in the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="124" page="9" column="1">making. It is trial and error. It is a lot of work, blood, sweat, and late nights.” The trial and <marker type="block"/> error character of design work comes into dramatic play as prototype products are assembled<marker type="block"/> for testing. For the design engineer, testing a design is an experience where three months of<marker type="block"/> work can be negated with a pressure test that lasts for less than 30 seconds (just enough time</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">to pressurize the valve) or a durability test that take several weeks to get results back. Most tests are often followed with other smaller, more specific tests to pinpoint the particular problem in order to make specific changes in an effort to fix the problem. At X.T., to fix a problem identified in a test, new sealing materials were often tried,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" page="9" column="1">larger or smaller springs were tried, different kinds of plastics were tried (plastics with more</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">buoyancy) or angles were modified. For example, the outcome of testing may alter the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="129" page="9" column="1">design of a part, add in an additional part, or increase the opening size in one chamber of the <marker type="block"/> valve. To access these changes, new drawings have to be worked up and approved, and then</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">new parts either machined or ordered from a supplier. For the design engineer, justifying changes to other engineers, and negotiating approval from supervisors and customer representatives takes a lot of energy and time. Until the new prototype parts are available, the design process slows to a crawl. do not equal the overall dimension for the part then the types of relationships (location of the center hole, depth of the inside shelf, and the . . .) could all be off, resulting in prototype parts that don’t</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="131" page="9" column="1">work, delayed testing results, and eventually a delayed design release.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="132" page="9" column="1">9</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Testing prototypes is the most concrete kind of problem-solving that design engineers do. The test results are concrete outcomes of the material world. In many ways, the data from testing the product is as tangible as the product itself, and the success of any design engineering efforts only come after the test results comes back positive. A prototype that “passes spec” is a combination of object and end that works—it is an outcome that a design engineer is going to “stand behind.” Objects and Ends: Structuring Knowledge in Manufacturing Engineering Work In manufacturing engineering, you begin to experience the shear volume of things—</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" page="10" column="1">the number of parts, the number of operations, the number of non-conformities—the number</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="135" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">of things that can go wrong. This is the world of manufacturing, where the law of large-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" page="10" column="1">numbers rule. However, the additional challenge here is that each of these numbers has to be</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="137" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">loaded, machined, sorted, assembled and tested. This is where lies the distinction of a “product” engineer and a “process” engineer. A product engineer—a design engineer— worries about the product and its functionality. A process engineer—a manufacturing engineer—worries about the product too (its pieces and functionality), but the problem that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" page="10" column="1">they have to solve is to design and build “a high-volume process” that creates and assembles</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">millions of parts in an efficient manner. When a manufacturing engineer talks about</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" page="10" column="1">“process” they are concerned about several issues: how parts will be fed into the system, how <marker type="block"/> parts will be properly oriented during an operation, the speed of each operation (cycle-time),</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">how bad parts will be detected, the wear and tear on machines, and how much the process will cost. Trying to express concerns about orientation, tight corners, sharp edges, and small parts helps get at the differences between assembly prints and design prints—the difference</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="143" page="10" column="1">10</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="144" page="11" column="1">between a manufacturing engineer and a design engineer. An assembly print provides a three</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">dimensional perspective that shows the interdependence between parts—the parts order,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" page="11" column="1">orientation, closeness to other parts, etc. In a nutshell, one of the most advanced skills in any</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">manufacturing engineer’s is to be able to look at a two-dimensional design print and put the parts together three-dimensionally in their head. Besides turning two-dimensional designs</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="148" page="11" column="1">into three-dimensional perspectives, another difference is how manufacturing engineers look</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="149" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">at a tolerance or dimension on a print (i.e., 0.8605 to 0.8606 or one ten thousandths of an inch—1/10,000). In building a high-volume process, the constant worry for a manufacturing engineer is</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" page="11" column="1">variability, but variability comes with the territory of building products in high volumes. The <marker type="block"/> more parts or operations that will occur, the more there is to go wrong. Variability comes in<marker type="block"/> many different forms: 1) environment: humidity, light, dark, dirt, oil, and water; 2) machines:<marker type="block"/> too little or too much pressure, electric fluctuations, test stand out of calibration, breakdowns</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">in the welder or lathe, holding tolerances and flatness; 3) parts: poor fit in the fixture, non- uniformity in parts, miss-orientation, sticky parts, defects, vendor or print changes on parts;</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" page="11" column="1">4) operators: you have to assume the worst, so you can’t assume you have a good operator—</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">therefore, you have to verify everything. For the design engineer, it is a number standing for a specified range—a representation. For the manufacturing engineer, the range is not just a representation, but introduces several practical problems that must be dealt with in order to hold that range at high volume or more descriptively thousands of times a day: what other tolerances will</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" page="11" column="1">impinge upon the ability to measure and hold this tolerance, how to hold the part, what kind</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="158" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">of machining fixture to use, the order of the machining sequence, what type of tools (how</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="159" page="11" column="1">11</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">course or fine the grinding wheel), and where to measure or gauge the part from (in relation to what, center hold, location holes, top of part), amongst others. Given these issues of high volume and variability, the default for any manufacturing engineer is to “keep it simple, stupid”—the fewest parts and the fewest operations. But if simplicity is not possible, then a manufacturing engineer needs to be able to spend enough money to insure that a “complex” product can be dealt with at high volume. Such was the case with a complex value such at the OVRV, simplicity was not going to be an option. It was a first time design with a very complicated functionality requirement. Mick, the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="161" page="12" column="1">manufacturing engineer, kept trying his best to make suggestions to the design team to make</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">it simpler, but that was a battle he was going to lose given the time frame and nature of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" page="12" column="1">current design. Given the number of parts, complex calibration and testing required, volumes</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="164" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">scheduled, and cycle-time, Mick had solicited three bids from well established automated assembly system producers. The bids to automate and achieve the kind of quality levels</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" page="12" column="1">required ranged from 4.25 million to 3.75 million. The cost figure that Mick had been given</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="166" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">to work with was 2.0 million. Mick’s comment to Ken and any other manager present was</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" page="12" column="1">that if it wasn’t going to be kept simple, then he was going to have to spend nearly double the <marker type="block"/> money to do it right. “Otherwise, this process will be a never-ending nightmare that we will</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">try to tame, but in the end we’ll have to live with.” Once a manufacturing process is implemented, it is both an artifact and an end. It is a tangible object in that is made up of various machines and operations, and handles various</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" page="12" column="1">kind of parts. It is an end also in that it is the ongoing means of manufacturing a product, and <marker type="block"/> so must be lived with and incrementally fined tuned as best it can. Unlike a complex product</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">that may have 40 to 60 parts a manufacturing process is an object that may have well over</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="173" page="12" column="1">12</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="174" page="13" column="1">10,000 parts. A manufacturing process is an object that is even more complex and harder to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="175" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">change once it is in production. A manufacturing engineer’s greatest fear is having to live with or having a stake in a “process” that is plagued with problems. Bill Curl, the head of manufacturing engineering at X.T. Products quickly pointed out to me how you can tell</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" page="13" column="1">which engineers have to live with a bad process, “Paul, after you have been here a while, just <marker type="block"/> listen to which manufacturing engineers are always being paged on the intercom to go up on</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="178" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">the 4th floor [where most of the production equipment is located]. That is an engineers [manufacturing] biggest nightmare.”</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="179" page="13" column="1">Recognizing and Resolving the Paradox of Objects in Product Development</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="180" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">These examples make clear how the objects and ends of one’s functional work structures knowledge differently. Further these differences create confliction between what is good for each community. Where as a design engineering needs to build a one of a kind</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="181" page="13" column="1">prototype (product) that hits “spec,” a manufacturing engineer needs to build a “process” that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="183" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">deals with all the variability of producing such a product 5,000 times a day. However, despite these obvious differences and the conflicts that surround them, I also observed that there were some objects that actors from differently communities used to jointly represent their knowledge, interpret differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="182" class="deo:Reference">Dougherty, 1992</xref>) and negotiate the trade-offs required to resolve cross-functional problems. I first noticed this in situations where</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" page="13" column="1">individuals from different functions who were sufficiently co-located could go next door and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="185" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">talk about a problem, easily bring a print or part to an ad hoc meeting or conversation, or walk up the stairs and view a machining process. In these cases conversations had a greater capacity to exchange concrete details and ideas, create shared problems and generate new</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="186" page="13" column="1">agreements and in the end solve many cross-boundary or cross-community problems. These</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="187" page="13" column="1">13</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="189" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">objects operated as a tangible infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="188" class="deo:Reference">Star and Ruhleder, 1996</xref>) that made cross- functional conversations more concrete and less abstract. They helped represent the knowledge differences and their dependencies between the actors and made the knowledge boundaries between function domains more visible and “workable.” This provide a shared practice where both parties would engage their experiences and problem solving skills to address these challenging problems that lie between communities. In Star’s (1989) study of heterogeneous problem-solving in pharmaceutical research, she observed that in spite of the tremendous differences between scientists in various disciplines, they nevertheless were often very successful in cooperating to create “good science.” Scientists were able to be successful through their use of what she called</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="195" page="14" column="1">“boundary objects.” Star defines boundary objects as “objects that are both plastic enough to <marker type="block"/> adapt to local needs and constraints of the several parties employing them, yet robust enough<marker type="block"/> to maintain a common identity across sites” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="192" class="deo:Reference">Star, 1989</xref>: 42). Star’s key observation was that<marker type="block"/> “in heterogeneous problem-solving, it is a problem not in computation, but in representation”<marker type="block"/> (42). The problem then, is not getting more information, but in how one’s knowledge or how</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="196" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">the objects and ends of one’s problem setting are represented to actor’s in other specialized domains. Star’s description of boundary objects gave me a category that began to help me</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="197" page="14" column="1">resolve the paradox that I was observing. Of course the question that remains is what are the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="198" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">characteristics that boundary objects have that objects within a community don’t have? Before I address this important question I will introduce you to the different types of boundary objects that Star identified and that I used in my own observations. Types of Boundary Objects in Product Development</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="199" page="14" column="1">14</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="200" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">To describe the variety of objects and how they were used I have adapted Star’s (1989) four categories of boundary objects (repositories, forms and labels; ideal type or platonic object, terrain with coincident boundaries) in the following ways. First, repositories</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="201" page="15" column="1">(i.e., cost databases, CAD/CAM databases, parts libraries) supply a common reference point</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="202" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">of data, measures, or labels across functions that provide shared definitions and value for solving problems. Repositories function advantageously as shared resource from which different actors can pull from when doing cross-domain work. Second, standardized form and methods provide a shared format for solving problems across different functional settings. Forms come in a mutually understood structure and language (i.e., standards for reporting findings, problem-solving procedures (8-D Forms, D- FMEA, P-FMEA), engineering change forms, etc.) that make defining and categorizing differences and potential consequence more shareable and less problematic across different setting. Third, objects or models are simple or complex representations that can be observed</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="204" page="15" column="1">and then used across different functional setting. Objects or models (i.e., sketches, assembly <marker type="block"/> drawings, parts, prototype assemblies, mock-ups, and simulations) depict or demonstrate the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="205" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">current or possible “form, fit and function” relationships that define the differences and dependencies between actors. Fourth, maps of interdependencies yield a snapshot of shared boundaries and dependencies that exist between functional settings with different objects and ends. Maps</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="206" page="15" column="1">(i.e., Gantt charts, process maps, work flow matrices, etc.) help clarify the interdependencies</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="207" page="15" column="1">15</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="208" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">between different cross-functional problem-solving efforts that share boundaries, resources, or other dependencies (i.e., test results, parts, deadlines). Even though these four categories of boundary objects are pretty straight forward, the actual role that they play in product development organizations is indeed illusive. For example a design drawing can be useful in driving collaboration between a design and a manufacturing engineer but when brought to be used with a representative from production who is unfamiliar with its use it can unintentionally be used to steam roll the production person’s point of view—resulting in poor agreements and downstream delays. What this reminds us of is that the characteristics that allow them to work effectively are essential but difficult to maintain as circumstances change. To begin the conversation about the characteristics of objects that make them boundary objects it is first important to describe a story that illustrates these characteristics. Developing an Up-to-date Assembly Drawings in the OVRV Design Review Phase This story centers around the design review phase of a complex product called the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="210" page="16" column="1">OVRV and is a classic example of the conflicts that occur between design and manufacturing <marker type="block"/> engineering. The OVRV was going to be a boon to X.T.’s future. The OVRV was a product</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="211" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">that fit the EPA requirements of having nearly zero gasoline fume leakage from the filler</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="212" page="16" column="1">neck of the gas tank (where the hose nozzle is inserted) and from the vapor recovery canister</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="213" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">as well. X.T. had been in a race with two other, larger competitors to provide the first working prototype of this “on-board vapor recovery system” for a major automotive firm (Major Automotive). X.T. had been successful in that race and had not only passed Major</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214" page="16" column="1">Automotives road tests, but had been the only company to even come close. Because of that</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="215" page="16" column="1">16</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="216" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">success, the working prototype was enjoying considerable approval and it embodied X.T.’s future success in the highly competitive automotive marketplace. As a story of boundary objects it describes the role of the CAD system as a common repository of information that helps produce a variety of drawings (in this particular case design and assemble drawings) to be used in cross-boundary settings. The critical characteristic this example illustrates is that both parties need to be able to represent their differences (preferences) and the dependencies or consequences between them in order to creates a better outcomes. In particular what we see is that when the assembly drawing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="217" page="17" column="1">doesn’t reflect the current design the manufacturing engineer lacks the ability and the power</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="218" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">to change the design according to what is important within his specialization. Mick Fry had been working on the OVRV project for about 3 months now. He had already been to three design review meetings, and was beginning to anticipate a lot of problems in trying to assemble and test a product with so many parts and critical sealing surfaces. As the soul representative from manufacturing engineering, he was beginning to get not only concerned, but frustrated with how things were going. Even if he wasn’t worrying about the specifics in the back of his mind he knew that the OVRV, with its 3,000,000-a-year volume, presented a completely different “beast” to be dealt with than</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" page="17" column="1">previous products. And he was determined not to let the situation evolve into its worst case <marker type="block"/> scenario by having the design frozen the way it was at this point. Mick had already begun to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="221" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">make his case about moving to a four subassembly design, but so far, he hadn’t gotten any significant design changes approved. At this point, Mick’s arguments only seemed to be inflaming the tempers of the other team members.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="222" page="17" column="1">17</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="223" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">The current working prototype had been developed over period of 3 years by the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="224" page="18" column="1">Advanced Development Team. They had faced a tremendous challenge in placing all of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="225" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">EPA’s requirements and the functional specifications of Major Automotive’s engineers in a plastic canister about the size of short quart bottle. In short, they had to put a lot of functionality (valves, sealing surfaces, springs, floats and mechanics) in a very small space.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="226" page="18" column="1">This working prototype was not only successful according to the functional requirements, but</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="227" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">also in terms of actually landing the business with Major Automotive and in placing X.T. in the driver’s seat to grab the business of another major automotive company as well. Given the difficulties of the design requirements and the success of the working prototype, the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="228" page="18" column="1">current design had set a lot of things in stone. Practically and symbolically, changing aspects</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="229" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">of the design to improve its manufacturability were going to be difficult—and besides that, Major Automotive wanted prototype parts to be delivered in less than 8 weeks. This all made for a relentless rush toward the current design. X.T. had recently invested in a new CAD system, called PRO-E and they now had the ability to not only design a product, but also do a lot of 3-D simulations and manufacturing modeling. The value of a CAD system is that it provides the possibility of a common repository of information (data points, coordinates, drawings, simulations, etc.) that can be utilized by different groups. Here, functional groups with different functional concerns can pull from a common database to make their points, build their arguments, and solve their problems. The problem was that X.T. hadn’t been using PRO-E very long, and all of the experienced CAD operators had been pulled into design engineering in order to get the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="230" page="18" column="1">design finalized so prototype parts could be ordered. In essence, all of the PRO-E operators</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="231" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">were doing drawings for design work and not for manufacturing. At the time when the</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="232" page="18" column="1">18</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="233" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">OVRV project was first given to Mick and the manufacturing engineering group, they knew</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="234" page="19" column="1">they needed the PRO-E tool to be up and running, especially on this product that contained a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="235" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">lot of new manufacturing challenges to deal with (very high volume, large number of parts, multiple functions to test and verify). At Mick’s and other departmental member’s suggestion, the head of manufacturing engineering hired a PRO-E draftsmen so they could</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" page="19" column="1">utilize the collected data on the PRO-E system in a way that would demonstrate to the design</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="237" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">team Mick’s concerns. One of the challenges that Mick had at previous meetings was that the assembly</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="238" page="19" column="1">drawings that he would bring were essentially considered inaccurate since they were not up-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="239" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">to-date with the current refinements to the design. Because of this the designers had a hard</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="241" page="19" column="1">time finding the assembly drawings useful. By the time the new PRO-E draftsman got up to <marker type="block"/> speed and had begun to produce assembly drawings and 3-D manufacturing simulations that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="242" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">were easily updatable from on-going design changes made by the design team, there was only 6 weeks left before Major Automotive’s prototype parts deadline. In the next OVRV design and review meeting, Mick made the same points, he had made before, but now with an up-to-date assembly drawing that reflected the current design. Even though Mick’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="243" page="19" column="1">arguments were no different from the ones he had made before (i.e., difficulties in assembly</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="244" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">and testing that would occur), they had a very different impact now that the assembly</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="245" page="19" column="1">drawing reflected the specs, tolerances, and locations of critical sealing surfaces that were “at</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="246" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">stake” the design engineers. This allowed Mick to describe in detail the assembly process that would be required to produce the current design and the high scrap rates the would result. On another copy of the assembly drawing Mick roughed in the the groups of parts that would allow for easily testable subassemblies, where they would be attached, and the</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="247" page="19" column="1">19</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="248" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">approximate areas were design changes would be required to connect four “large” subassemblies. After this example was penciled in on the assembly drawing, vigorous discussion began about the benefits and drawback of changing the design. One of the drawbacks uncovered was the current way of attaching parts (a high velocity spin weld that melts plastic surfaces together) had always resulted in warping parts the size of these subassemblies. Vaughn was now open to using subassemblies—but an alternative way of attaching them had to be found quickly. Two days later at the next meeting a “snap-fit” design had was proposed as a solution. A snap fit approach had two advantages over the spin weld. First, the snap fit did not</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="249" page="20" column="1">involved either a rapid spin weld of plastic parts or the warping and alignment problems that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="250" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">where common in large parts. Second, most of the snap-fit holes and their clips could be placed on the outside of the pump and should not degrade the current functionality of the value in a significant way. Over the following week, two meetings, and several informal conversations around the CAD system, the OVRV was redesigned with four independently testable sub assemblies with “snap-fit” holes and clips providing the connection. Analyzing the Story Mick had proposed going to sub-assemblies in meetings before, what was different this time? In this case, the objects, or more specifically the assembly drawings used by the group in the design and review meeting were different. The assembly drawing that was not current did allow Mick to represent his concerns about assembly and testing in a way that was valid to the design engineers since it did not reflect the current design and concerns of the design engineer. It failed to be a useful tool in representing the differences and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="251" page="20" column="1">dependencies between them. With the up-to-date assembly drawing however, both Mick and</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="252" page="20" column="1">20</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">the design engineers were able to represent what was “at stake” for each of them. The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="254" page="21" column="1">assembly drawing also represented their dependencies and their consequences (e.g., how the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="255" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">current design makes “scrap rates” high for Mick or how going to subassemblies might undermine the OVRV’s current functional capability). This allowed them to create a joint problem solving space to develop trade-offs and eventually transform the design to accommodate a new approach (4 sub assemblies with snap-fit holes and clips). By forcing explicitness about the specific details of assembling and testing the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="256" page="21" column="1">OVRV, Mick’s up-to-date assembly drawing put his “assembly troubles” within the practical</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="257" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">grasp of the design engineers. As a boundary object, the assembly drawing provided the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="258" page="21" column="1">practical infrastructure for cross-functional problem solving that led to concrete negotiations</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="259" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">and ultimately changes in the design that accommodated 4 subassemblies. When we</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="260" page="21" column="1">examine actors working across boundaries in product development, we see it more clearly as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="261" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">a process wherein each actor can competently represent their knowledge and participate in transforming—redefining and renegotiating the knowledge used to define the design of the OVRV.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="262" page="21" column="1">The Characteristics that Make Objects, Boundary Objects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="263" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">What this example of the up-to-date assembly drawing illustrates is that not every object works as a boundary object. In a collection of over 65 observations of the use of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="265" page="21" column="1">different boundary objects (i.e., drawings, prototypes, D-FMEA, process maps, etc.) in cross- <marker type="block"/> functional settings, I identified three characteristics of an object that allows it to operate as a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="266" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">boundary object. First, a boundary object establishes a shared language for individuals to represent their knowledge. In the case of Mick and Vaughn, the shareable quality of the assembly</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="267" page="21" column="1">21</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="268" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">drawing as a representation is enhanced because both parties are familiar with it. For Vaughn, the assembly drawing represented critical tolerances and functional specifications. For Mick, the assembly drawing provided a three-dimensional representation of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="269" page="22" column="1">orientation of parts and critical issues for assembly and testing. The design drawing was not</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="270" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">effective boundary object because what is “at stake” for both the design and manufacturing engineer could not be represented on it. Second, an effective boundary object provides a concrete means for individuals to specify and learn about their differences and dependencies—what is new— across a given boundary. This allows individuals to specify what they know—what they worry about—as concretely as possible to the problem at hand. In the case of Vaughn, the up-to-date assembly drawing allowed him to specify his concerns about important specs and critical sealing surfaces. For Mick, it allowed him to specify the challenges of assembling and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="271" page="22" column="1">testing a complex product at high volume. To deal with a complex knowledge boundary the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="272" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">differences and dependencies between functions or groups must be specified and the up-to- date assembly drawing identified the critical dependencies between the “functional spec” approach of the design engineers and Mick’s concerns about assembly and testing. Third an effective boundary object facilitates a process where individuals can transform the knowledge being used. If there are negative consequences identified between actors then something must change; and so the actors involved must be able to alter,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="274" page="22" column="1">negotiate or change the object or representation used (i.e., Mick’s knowledge about assembly <marker type="block"/> and testing problems before the updated assembly drawing). If an actor cannot transform the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="275" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">object being used, their knowledge will likely have limited impact on the problem at hand. In the case of Mick and Vaughn, dealing with the consequences identified required them to</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="276" page="22" column="1">22</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="277" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">propose alternatives (i.e., subassemblies) and then alter the knowledge used to define the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="280" page="23" column="1">design (i.e., location of 4 subassemblies) and the particular manufacturing process developed <marker type="block"/> (i.e., snap fit holes). Individuals must be able to draw on, alter or manipulate the content of a<marker type="block"/> boundary object to apply what they know and transform the current knowledge being used to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="281" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">define the problem. What should now be clear is that the content of a boundary object is no “magic bullet,” rather it is the process that it supports as actors use it to collaborate across boundaries. For example, an assembly drawing can be a boundary object with one set of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="282" page="23" column="1">actors, but can falter when another actor becomes involved who cannot use it to represent the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="283" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">knowledge that is important to them. By understanding the characteristics of boundary objects we recognize the relational properties that allow an object to operate as a boundary object. These relational properties are defined by the capacity of the boundary object to represent the knowledge of consequences and the ability of the actors involved to use that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="284" page="23" column="1">object. This relation between boundary objects and actors is another reminder that power has</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="285" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">a strong practical impact in working across boundary and collaborating. When successful outcomes are desired, the capacity of the object to represent the differences and dependencies among actors and the relative ability among the actors to use that capacity has to be addressed. The reason why a boundary object ceases to be one when taken to another setting is that the boundary object can no longer represent what is now of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="286" page="23" column="1">consequence and/or the actors now involved can’t adequately use or manipulate the boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="287" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">object. So whether the objects are prototypes or clothing or even more abstract cultural artifacts—if one actor has more ability to use or invoke those objects then they will have more power than the other actors involved. As we saw with Mick before the up-to-date</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="288" page="23" column="1">23</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="289" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">assembly drawing the opposite is also true because at a very practical level he did not have enough power to effectively collaborate with Vaughn to improve the design of the product.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="290" page="24" column="1">Implications: Boundary Objects and Change (or a lack of it) in Organizations</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="291" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Although this discussion about boundary objects has focused on their use at a very practical level the insights developed about their characteristics also apply to the more</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="292" page="24" column="1">symbolic artifacts identified by many of the other authors in this book. We see in the case of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="293" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Shultz, Hatch and Cicolla’s description of corporate branding how artifacts play a role in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="294" page="24" column="1">shaping and transforming the image of a company over time. Harquail’s focus on employees</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="295" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">as branding artifacts raises interesting questions about individuals as boundary objects and how they are used by both the company and customers for each of their respective interests.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="298" page="24" column="1">This indeed raises troubling questions about the power or lack of power that a given actor has <marker type="block"/> as they participate at boundary with actors who have different interests. Further, Shotter and<marker type="block"/> Cunliffe’s work describes the importance of relationally-responsive knowing for actors to be</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="299" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">successful in linguistic interactions. This strikes at a similar cord to the importance of considering the relational properties of boundary objects (both capacity and ability) to fully understand how actors successfully use an object as a boundary object. Indeed this is a reminder that artifacts not only have power to shape our lives in organizations, but also that some actors in organizations often have more power in shaping outcomes than others. However, by making the role of artifacts less taken for granted and understanding the relational properties involved, all actors in organizations can potentially more directed in the power that they have, what they can do, to shape events and outcomes.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="300" page="24" column="1">24</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="301" page="25" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="302" page="25" column="1">Barley, S.R. 1986. Technology as an Occasion for Structuring: Evidence from Observations</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="303" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">of CT Scanners and the Social Order of Radiology Departments. Administrative Science Quarterly, 31, 1, 78-108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="304" page="25" column="1">Black, L., Carlile, P.R. and Repenning, N. 2003. Formalizing Theoretical Insights from</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="305" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Ethnographic Evidence: Revisiting Barley’s Study of CT-Scanning Implementations. Pending Publication.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="306" page="25" column="1">Bourdieu, P. 1977. Outline of a Theory of Practice. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="307" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Press. Bowker, G. and Star, S. 1999. Sorting Things Out: Classification and its Consequences. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="308" page="25" column="1">Brown, J. S. and Duguid, P. 1991. Organizational learning and communities-of-practice.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="309" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Organization Science, 2 (1), 40-57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="310" page="25" column="1">Carlile, P. 1997. Transforming knowledge in product development: Making knowledge manifest through boundary objects. Unpublished Dissertation. University of Michigan.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="311" page="25" column="1">Carlile, P.R. 2002. A pragmatic view of knowledge and boundaries: Boundary objects in</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="312" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">new product development. Organization Science, 13 (4), 442-455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="313" page="25" column="1">Carlile, P.R. 2003. Transfer, translation and transformation: An integrative framework for sharing and assessing knowledge across boundaries. Publication pending.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="314" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Clark K., Wheelwright, S. 1995. The Product Development Challenge: Competing Through Speed, Quality, and Creativity. Cambridge, MA: Harvard Business Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="315" page="25" column="1">Clarke, A. and Fujimura, J. 1992. Introduction. In The Right Tools for the Job: At Working</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="316" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">in Twentieth-Century Life Sciences. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="317" page="25" column="1">Dougherty, D. 1992. Interpretive barriers to successful product innovation in large firms. Organization Science, 3 (2): 179-202.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="318" page="25" column="1">Engestrom, Y. 1990. Learning, Working and Imagining. Helsinki: Orienta Konsultit Oy. Hatch, M.J. 1993. The dynamics of organization culture. Academy Management Review, 18, 657-693. Henderson, K. 1991. Flexible sketches and inflexible data-bases: Visual communication, conscription devices and boundary objects in design engineering. Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values, 16 (4), 448-473.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="320" page="26" column="1">Hughes, T. 1983. Networks of Power: Electrification in Western Society, 1880-1930.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="321" page="26" column="1">Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="322" page="26" column="1">Latour, B. 1987. Science in Action: How to Follow Scientists and Engineers through Society. Milton Keynes: Open University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="323" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Lave, J. 1988. Cognition in Practice: Mind, Mathematics, and Culture in Everyday Life. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="324" page="26" column="1">Lave, J. and Wenger, S. 1991. Situated Learning. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="325" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="326" page="26" column="1">Malinowski, B. 1953. Sex and Repression in Primitive Society, London: RKP.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="327" page="26" column="1">Nonaka, I. 1994. A dynamic theory of organizational knowledge creation. Organization</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="328" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Science, 5, 14-37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="329" page="26" column="1">Orlikowski, W.J. 1992. The duality of technology: Rethinking the concept of technology in</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="330" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">organizations. Organization Science, 3, 398-427. Pinch, T. Bjiker, W. 1984. The social construction of facts and artefacts: Or how the sociology of science and the sociology of technology might benefit each other. Social Studies of Science, 14, 399-441.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="331" page="26" column="1">Polanyi, M. 1966. The Tacit Dimension. New York: Anchor Day Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="332" page="26" column="1">Pratt, M.J. and Rafaeli, A. 1997. Vested interests: Dress as an integrating symbol. Academy</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="333" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">of Management Journal, 40, 4, 860-896.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="334" page="26" column="1">Reynolds, B. 1987. Material Anthropology: Contemporary Approaches to Material Culture. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="335" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Star, S. L. 1989. The structure of ill-structured solutions: Boundary objects and</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="336" page="26" column="1">heterogeneous distributed problem solving. In M. Huhns and L. Gasser (eds.), Readings in Distributed Artificial Intelligence. Menlo Park, CA: Morgan Kaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="337" page="26" column="1">Star, S. L. and Ruhleder, K. 1996. Steps toward an ecology of infrastructure: Design and access for large information spaces. Information Systems Research, 7, 111-134. Strauss, A. 1993. Continual Permutation of Action. New York: Aldine de Gruyter.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="338" page="26" column="1">von Hippel, E. and Tyre, M. 1996. The mechanics of learning by doing: Problem discovery</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="339" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">during process machine use. Technology and Culture, 37: 312-29.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="319" page="25" column="1">25</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="340" page="26" column="1">26</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
