<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>9fdb4aee650ee0402d4c35e811e623a67ee1f75a005b34f7041fc8beb054183e</job>
    <base_name>62r8</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1533/9781845690816">http://dx.doi.org/10.1533/9781845696559</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">CAN POLICY BE PARTICIPATORY? – THE APPLICATION OF DESIGN PRACTICE TO POLICY DEVELOPMENT</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="2">JOHN CHISHOLM LANCASTER UNIVERSITY J.CHISHOLM@LANCASTER.AC.UK</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="4">DR. LEON CRUICKSHANK LANCASTER UNIVERSITY L.CRUICKSHANK@LANCASTER.AC.UK</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="6">DR. MARTYN EVANS LANCASTER UNIVERSITY M.EVANS@LANCASTER.AC.UK</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="8">PROF. RACHEL COOPER LANCASTER UNIVERSITY R.COOPER@LANCASTER.AC.UK</name></contrib></contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" page="1" column="2">Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="10" page="1" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="11" page="1" column="2">1</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" page="2" column="1">ABSTRACT</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">This paper considers whether participatory design practices can improve the development of policy at national, regional and local levels. The insights offered contribute another dimension to the field of participatory innovation by asserting that more effective, inclusive policy making at all levels of government can be achieved through the adoption of participatory design practice methodologies. This paper discusses how policy-makers might draw upon participatory design practice to design, implement and evaluate innovation policy. A case study of participatory and ‘co-design’ methodologies applied to developing local policy show how such methods can not only result in meaningful project outcomes, but also how local government policy makers put aside existing process and adopted unfamiliar approaches. A discussion of key challenges concludes by identifying those characteristics which demonstrate how community participation can be a credible alternative to traditional policy making. INTRODUCTION</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" page="2" column="1">Co-design is a specific design methodology within the discipline of participatory design, a discipline which prioritises users from the outset and incorporates user needs into the full product development cycle. The co- design process blurs the role between user and designer, encouraging users to develop their own solutions under the aegis of professional designers. The authors discuss what is meant by ‘participatory’ in the context of national, regional and local innovation policy and how creative techniques contribute towards non-traditional innovation, for example, by using co- design techniques to extend engagement to all participants. This paper presents alternative approaches to policy development through the application of participatory design methodologies and demonstrates through a specific case study how local participation can positively assist policy development. It is anticipated <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> that our research will be of interest to scholars both within and beyond the design and innovation field. Specifically this paper: i) discusses how policy-makers might draw upon participatory design practice to design, develop and implement innovation policy, ii) presents a case study of participatory and co- design methodologies applied to developing policy at local level, and iii) identifies the challenges inherent in participatory policy development.<marker type="block"/> The paper concludes with a discussion of the key challenges faced in participatory policy development and the opportunities offered by design to address these challenges – e.g. use of participatory design methodologies to evaluate design innovation policies.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="17" page="2" column="2">RESEARCH CONTEXT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="2" column="2">This section: i) provides a brief overview of policy and its design, implementation and evaluation in the context of participatory design innovation and ii) outlines the key characteristics of participatory design. <marker type="block"/> POLICY DEVELOPMENT Policy development traditionally takes the form of top- down objective-setting guided by perceived rationales based on available evidence, influenced to a lessor or greater extent by political and external pressures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="19" class="deo:Reference">HM Treasury, 2011</xref>). However such an approach does not necessarily reflect changes within society brought about by ‘enabling’ technologies at the individual/local level and the increasing relevance of social innovation in response to heightened expectations for inclusivity and local empowerment. In practice, however, policy decisions tend to be reactive and based on more immediate and pragmatic priorities e.g. crisis avoidance, damage-limitation and presentational issues (Parsons, 2005) – with “many of the real policy decisions ... being made well beyond the confines of Whitehall and Westminster” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Hallsworth, 2011</xref>). Participatory policy-making involving representatives of civil society, termed ‘civil society organisations’ (CSO) and the private sector has become more prominent since the 1990s – and were initially associated with developmental or environmental agendas, CSOs bringing “expertise, commitment and grassroots perceptions to the policy-making process” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="21" class="deo:Reference">IISD, 1998</xref>). True participatory governance requires politicians and public officials to share some of their power over the policy process. In particular, it requires them to share information with citizens and to learn how to communicate with so-called ordinary citizens about complex questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Stewart, 2007</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Policy networks – a conceptual reference to the interdependent relationships between actors involved in policy-making regarding a policy problem where the traditional role of government is changed into the role of broker or facilitator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Guerts &amp; Joldersma 2001</xref>). However such networks have been described as only open to stimuli from the outside whereas their reaction to such stimuli depends completely on their internal mechanisms. This self-governing characteristic requires government to ‘govern’ these networks by participatory methods e.g. by interweaving the goals of different actors by means of new fora of debate and discussion – the focus shifting from the single policy-making actor, the government, to the policy-making network as a whole. At the local level, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Michels &amp; Graaf (2010)</xref> provide some insights into the relation between the citizen and government, challenging the theoretical claim that “citizen participation in policy-making has positive effects on democracy”. From empirical case studies, they find that the role of citizens is limited to providing information, on the basis of which the government makes decisions – however, positive effects on democracy are discerned through increased public engagement; imbuing an increased sense of responsibility for public matters; exposure to a diversity of opinions; and by ascribing a higher degree of legitimacy to decision-making.<marker type="block"/> POLICY IMPLEMENTATION As early as 2002, deLeon &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="30" class="deo:Reference">deLeon &amp; deLeon (2002)</xref> have argued that a more democratic approach to policy implementation would be aligned with a broader trend in the policy sciences towards a greater emphasis on the democratic ethos and citizen participation. Crucially, a democratic approach to policy implementation would include reaching back in the policy process framework to include the policy formulation deliberations as a means to help define policy goals by talking with the affected parties well before the policy is adopted by the authorized policymaker. Also in social capital terms strengthens the link between the governing and the governed.<marker type="block"/> POLICY EVALUATION Policy evaluation needs to be a key aspect of policy development. A key finding of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Hallsworth (2011)</xref> is that the frequently cited policy cycle (Figure.1) is widely dismissed amongst policy-makers as unrealistic, a view agreed with by many academics. Four main reasons are given: 1. Policy making does not take place in distinct stages 2. Policies need to be designed not just conceived 3. Policymaking is often determined by events 4. The effects of policy are often diffuse and take time to appear.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Evaluation, review and learning in particular are characteristics that have been identified as being particularly weak. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Thissen &amp; Warren (2013)</xref> acknowledges a variety of policy analysis approaches and actors: • Traditional – focussing on modelling the system or choosing policy alternatives; • New approaches – argumentative and participative; • Procedural – focussing on the policymaking process and the roles of actors involved. As early as 2000, developments in policy analysis shifted from a “uni-central, analytic, scientific approach to a more multi-central, interactive, stakeholders approach” (Geurts &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Joldersma, 2001</xref>) where the application of a participatory approach to analysis generally involves a methodology that has to satisfy analytic criteria as well as process criteria.<marker type="block"/> In terms of participatory policy, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Michels &amp; Graaf (2010)</xref> identifies three functions fulfilled by citizen participation or ‘participative democracy’: • Educative – increasing civic skills and competency through participation through public decision- making. • Integrative – increasing citizens’ feeling of being part of their local community, also a feeling of personal responsibility for decisions made. • Legitimacy – decisions made are lent legitimacy; rules produced are acceptable to all.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="24" page="2" column="2">2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="26" page="2" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx37">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62r8.page_003.image_01.png" thmb="62r8.page_003.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="39" page="3" column="2">Figure.1: Policy Cycle - UK Green Book (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="38" class="deo:Reference">HM Treasury, 2011</xref>)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">PARTICIPATORY DESIGN Participatory design is concerned with collaboration between designers and non-designers importantly recognising the contribution of users as partners within design activities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Brandt (2006)</xref> defines participatory design as ‘the direct involvement of people in the shaping of future artefacts’ involving ‘the staging of a design process involving participation of people’. In</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" page="3" column="2">Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> recent times the terms co-creation and co-design have become synonymous with participatory design with these terms increasingly being used interchangability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Sanders &amp; Stappers, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Sanders and Stappers (2008)</xref> consider co-creation ‘to refer to any act of collective creativity, i.e. creativity that is shared by two or more people’ and refer to co-design as ‘the creativity of designers and people not trained in design working together in the design development process’. The authors do not intend to provide a comprehensive critique of participatory design as it is beyond the scope of this paper, rather they outline its key approaches in relation to the focus of this paper. For a detailed overview of participatory design see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Sanders and Stappers (2008)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Kensing and Blomberg (1998)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Brandt (2006)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Ehn (2008)</xref>, and van Ebel et al. (2011). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Clement &amp; van den Besselaar (1993)</xref> identified seven characteristics of participatory design: • access to relevant information • independent voice in decision-making • user-controlled development resources • appropriate development methods • organisational/technical flexibility • active involvement of users • increased learning and communications Participatory design can be further characterised by: • A change in the relationships between designer, client &amp; user brought on, in part, by the use of the principles and practices of design being used to address increasingly complex problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Stappers et al, in van Abel et al, 2011</xref>) with the role of designer becoming more varied: part creator, part researcher, part facilitator, part process manager. • An approach which tries to meet the challenge of “anticipating, or at least envisioning, and designing for use before it has actually taken place – design for use before use” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Ehn, 2008</xref>). • A focus on the development of specific tools and techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Kensing &amp; Blomberg, 1998</xref>) including “ethnography-inspired fieldwork techniques” for data-gathering and analysis, and scenario- generation, future workshops, design games, case- and cooperative-prototyping, to name a few. As we can see from the characteristics of participatory design, the role of the user – sometimes termed citizen in participatory design – is valued not only as end users of the designed output or artefact rather as contributors in the design and development process. Such approaches democratise decision making within the design process often resulting in designers acting as facilitators rather than decision makers. The end result can be decisions being made collectively and collaboratively by the many rather than centrally and dictatorially by the few. The authors assert that this key</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="45" page="3" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="46" page="3" column="2">3</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">feature of participatory design – collective decision making – is potentially valuable to policy making. Indeed participatory policy making has parallels with participatory design.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="4" column="2">RESEARCH METHODS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="4" column="2">The methodology for the primary research is best described as case study research (Yin, 2008; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Stake, 1995</xref>). Case studies investigate a contemporary phenomenon within its real-life context; when boundaries between phenomenon and context are often fuzzy; multiple sources of evidence are used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Yin, 2009</xref>). There can be single case studies to elaborate on a phenomenon and multiple case studies that lend themselves to comparison. This research methodology was consciously chosen because it provides opportunity to gain in-depth insights into complex and evolving issues which, in this ever-changing state of participatory innovation policy though design are not effectively communicated in the academic literature to date. Within this paper we have utilised a single case study as the vehicle for the research as this provides a meaningful opportunity to highlight key research issues while not distracting from the focus of the paper. Opportunities for exploration of additional cases are relevant and the authors would extend this research through the development of multiple cases and thus support cross case comparison. The research for Beyond the Castle was developed through a series of interactive and iterative activities. These included initial workshops with local government, visioning workshops, agenda setting events, and a series of public events held on the site and in Lancaster city centre including a curated public exhibition. All of these activities exemplify the co- design process in which participants contributed to the design and development of ideas. This approach was employed to enable a broad set of responses from citizens of Lancaster that drew upon the expertise of design as the facilitator rather than arbiter of ideas. For example, the visioning workshop held at Lancaster University involving the most active and enthusiastic public participants including professional designers, schoolchildren, residents, archaeologists and musicians. By bringing together such a diverse set of participants the opportunity for new and novel ideas to emerge is enhanced. The involvement of designers was such that they created structures that could be populated by a broad range of participants and importantly not as the expert.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="63" page="4" column="2">CASE STUDY – BEYOND THE CASTLE</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" confidence="possible" page="4" column="2">This case study describes how a recent urban regeneration project ‘Beyond the Castle’ (BTC) employed novel design-based methodologies involving local government, local communities and other stakeholders to revitalise a hitherto neglected park land</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="65" page="4" column="2">4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="4" column="2">Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> in Lancaster, UK. Lancaster is a city in the north west of England and is dominated by a hill surmounted by a castle and priory – one side of the castle is five minutes’ walk from the central shopping area of the city. The other side is an undeveloped, overgrown area of around 50 hectares (500m 2 ) and was the site of a Roman bathhouse and the remains of four Roman forts. This gives the site national archaeological significance and is strictly protected from any building works over much of the site. BTC is a collaborative project involving Lancaster University, Lancaster City Council and Lancaster County Council and which is part of a larger project ‘PROUD’ and funded through INTERREG IV. PROUD (People Researchers Organisations Using co-Design) brings designers from 7 EU member states together with public bodies, businesses and user communities to work on innovative solutions to real-world problems through the development of transnational methods for co- designing services, products and processes that address unmet needs. BTC involved participants in the development of a range of ideas regarding the potential future of the area surrounding the castle. Ideas generated included: • Music venue/campsite • A centre for historical events (re-enactments) • Sculpture park • Outdoor theatre (amphitheatre) • Treetop walks • Cycle ways and nature walks • Natural play areas • Workshops for low-impact artisan businesses • Orienteering - work-out areas Policy makers within the City Council were aware that their normal models of working with local communities, often top-down in nature, were ineffective and did not provide meaningful consultation with the local community. BTC aimed to develop a range of participatory design activities that enabled people with a very broad range of experience and expertise to have a creative (not just informational) input into the process. BTC was structured around the design of seven events ranging from the training of volunteers, to strategic sessions with decision makers to open events in the market square on the busiest shopping day. This culminated in an ‘interactive co-design exhibition’ that combined the ideas from previous events with new creative co-design solutions developed as part of the exhibition (Fig.2). In total 2300 people were involved in the project with 700 having an active creative contribution.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The application of participatory design approaches applied in BTC were critical in the success of the project. For example the visualisation and design of events and their communication throughout the project was a key component in policy-setting debates going on within the council at the time of the project. This new participatory approach contrasts with the previous methods that tended to consist of saying ‘this is what we have decided, what do you think?’ or ‘consulting at’ people. The openness of the project and the emergent, citizen- led element was initially problematic for the council officers. However, the positive outcomes from the project have no only brought about changes in the processes of co-design and consultation in the City and County Councils, but have also had an effect on the policy. The BTC project report is being used as the briefing document that planners and landscape architects will respond to when they are applying to undertake the master planning and development of the area around the castle. In this way the detailed co-design proposals documented in the report are helping to shape the policy for development in that space for the next 15 years. A key success of BTC was the recognition by local and regional policy makers that such a collaborative approach – enabled by participatory design - has the potential to enhance how they will undertake projects of this nature in the future.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="67" page="4" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62r8.page_005.image_02.png" thmb="62r8.page_005.image_02-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="70" page="5" column="2">Figure.2: Beyond the Castle – Interactive Co-Design Exhibition.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="72" page="5" column="2">DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" page="5" column="2">Participatory policy development approaches present challenges to policy makers. Traditional top-down policy making has for many years often consulted with citizens in a cursory manner, essentially playing lip- service to their views. As there has been a societal shift towards closer engagement with citizens in policy development, the challenges of a devolved and democratised decision making process have resulted in tensions that traditional policy approaches have been unable to address. <marker type="block"/> Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> By their very nature participatory policy development approaches requires the relinquishing of (some) power to citizens. In doing so policy makers need to accept that the decision and resultant policy may not be the same as they would ideally imagine. This gap between the ideal policy from a policy makers’ perspective, and the preferred policy from a citizens’ perspective, can be the deal breaker in terms of embracing participatory policy making. Engagement of citizens in policy making does not happen without investment in relationship building. In some instances there is often a reticence towards policy making (and policy makers). Barriers to the development of meaningful and mutually beneficial relationship can be resource and time intensive and a long term perspective may be needed to build confidence between the various stakeholder groups. In such instances there is a need to understand the nature of co-created policy will be manifest. We must remember that citizens are not experiences in policy development and as such are not able to imagine how a policy will be developed and implemented. To address the above challenges novel approaches are required if effective participatory policy making and engagement is to be fostered. By its very nature participatory design approaches value the contribution of the user – or citizen – in the development process. By placing the citizen in a position of relative importance, such approaches can empower the masses by recognise their contribution is not only valued but will inform the resultant policy development. Design provides a mechanism for the creative contribution of individuals by scaffolding their input. By facilitating the dialogue between policy makers and citizens, participatory design approaches has the ability to reduce the ‘them and us’ mindset often present in consultative policy development. The use of visual creative communication techniques, as exemplified within BTC, brings down barriers between the ‘expert and user’ extremes and supports iterative and open discussion. A key potential contribution of participatory design to policy making is in the form of physical prototypes which are able to consolidate an idea in a communicable form. The manifestation of an idea for a given policy situation in a physical form provides a ‘discussion point’ and takes talk into the arena of an actionable policy idea. The co-design practices employed within the development of the BTC exhibition are an effective example of how designerly creativity can draw out valuable ideal from a multitude of citizens. The essential aspect of this approach is removing barriers between the designer and citizen with this having distinct parallels through the removal of barriers between the policy maker and citizen. Application of creative techniques is central to design supporting participatory policy development. Without<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> such approaches – that are core to participatory design – the contribution of design would be minimal and perhaps reduced to the creation of nicely designed posters for consultation meetings. The key thrust of participatory design, and its contribution to policy development, is the ability of designers to develop citizen-engaging, idea generating, and mutually rewarding contexts that citizens and policy makers can conduct inhabit resulting in truly participatory policy development. Through such application, policy development, implementation and evaluation can be addressed through the contribution of a multitude of perspectives in a democratised manner.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="75" page="5" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="76" page="5" column="2">5</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="79" page="6" column="2">CONCLUSIONS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" page="6" column="2">The case study indicates a change in the attitude of the Council in respect of engagement with local citizens and the community. The participatory design (co-design) process breaks into the ‘usual’ implementation of the policy cycle, introducing a “leap of faith [which] doesn't sit very well within the Council, because we're used to having set outcomes and controlling it”. A key finding from case study was the perceived long- term value of the project (impacts) as a means of enhancing the policy-making process at the local level. This was distinct from its immediate effects (outcomes) of imbuing a community sense of engagement and the generation of ideas of a particular quality and depth. However given that the BTC project report is now a briefing document which planners and landscape architects ‘will have to respond to’ when applying to undertake the subsequent planning and development of the area around the castle is a significant step in ensuring project value – value expected to be maintained for the next 15 years. The output of a participatory design project is now being employed as a policy briefing document that has the potential to influence on-going policy development and as such acts as a legacy that can inform participatory policy development at a local and regional level for the foreseeable future. In summary, the authors assert that participatory design has direct value in informing the development of participatory policy, particularly in respect of: • access to relevant information • independent voice in decision-making • active involvement of users • increased learning and communications • address increasingly complex problems • anticipating design ‘before use’ The above participatory design characteristics are evident in the case study and demonstrate how active community participation in the design process promotes and informs policy development, as a credible <marker type="block"/> Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="81" page="6" column="2">6</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="83" page="6" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">alternative to the traditional policy making process at the local level.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="85" page="7" column="1">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="7" column="1">Brandt, E. 2006. Designing exploratory design games: a framework for participation in Participatory Design. Gianni Jacucci, Finn Kensing (ed.): Proceedings of the Ninth Conference on Participatory Design: Expanding boundaries in design, PDC 2006, Trento, Italy, August 1-5, 2006. 57-66.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="7" column="1">Clement, A. &amp; van den Besselaar, P. 1993. A retrospective look at PD projects. Communications of the ACM, 36(4), 29-37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">deLeon, P and deLeon, L. 2002. What Ever Happened</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="89" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">to Policy Implementation? An Alternative Approach. Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory. 12(4): 467-492. Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" page="7" column="1">Ehn, P. 2008. Participation in Design Things. Proceedings of the Tenth Anniversary Conference on</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="91" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Participatory Design, Bloomington, USA, 30th September – 4th October, pp.92-101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="92" page="7" column="1">Guerts, J. &amp; Joldersma, C. 2001. Methodology for participatory policy analysis. European Journal of Operational Research. 128:300-310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="7" column="1">Hallsworth, M. 2011. Policy Making in the Real World: Evidence and Analysis. Institute for Government. London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">HM Treasury. 2011. The Green Book - Appraisal and Evaluation in Central Government. The Stationery Office, London.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">IISD. 1998. Participatory Policy-Making. Developing Ideas Digest. International Institute for Sustainable Development. www.iisd.org/didigest/jan98/3jan98.html.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Accessed 02 March 2013.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="98" page="7" column="2">Imagination Lancaster. 2013. Beyond The Castle – Final Report. Available from &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://imagination.lancaster.ac.uk/activities/Beyond_C" id="97">http://imagination.lancaster.ac.uk/activities/Beyond_C</ext-link> astle&gt;, accessed: 07 March 2013</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="99" page="7" column="2">Kensing, F. &amp; Blomberg, J. 1998. Participatory Design: Issues and Concerns. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 7:167–185, 1998. Kluwer Academic Publishers.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="100" page="7" column="2">Michels, A. &amp; Graaf, L. 2010. Examining Citizen Participation: Local Participatory Policy Making and Democracy. Local Government Studies, 36:4, 477-491.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="101" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Parsons, W. 1995. Public Policy: An Introduction to the Theory and Practice of Policy Analysis. Edward Elgar Publishing, Cheltenham, UK.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="102" page="7" column="2">Sanders, E. &amp; Stappers, P. 2008. Co-creation and the new landscapes of design. CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts, 4, 1, pp5-18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="103" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Stake, R. 1995. The art of case study research. Sage Publications Inc. Los Angeles.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="104" page="7" column="2">Stappers, P., Visser, F. &amp; Kistemaker, S.in van Abel et al (ed.) (2011) Open Design Now: Why design cannot remain exclusive. BIS Publishers, Amsterdam.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="106" page="7" column="2">Stewart, J. 2007. Creating participatory governance. Chapter 3. Available from: &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://epress.anu.edu.au/anzsog/dilemmas/mobile_devi" id="105">http://epress.anu.edu.au/anzsog/dilemmas/mobile_devi</ext-link> ces/ch03s05.html&gt; Accessed 04 March 2013.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="107" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Thissen, W. and Warren, W. (ed.) (2013) Public Policy Analysis: New Developments. International Series in Operations Research and Management Science. Springer. New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="108" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Yin, R. (2009) Case Study Research: Design and</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="109" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">Methods. 4 th ed. Sage Publications Inc. Los Angeles.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" page="7" column="2">Participatory Innovation Conference 2013, Lahti, Finland</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111" page="7" column="2">www.pin-c2013.org/</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112" page="7" column="2">7</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
