<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>4c4ec8a175ef3c2a09d2019a8a175517b543fd709fd270a54b68673e4e025cce</job>
    <base_name>62d5</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/la901720a">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4471-0779-8_9</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">If Users Could Speak, Would We Understand Them? Design Games &amp; Genuine User Participation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="2">Jonas Moll</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="4">Dave Müller</name></contrib></contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Institute of Communication, Business Institute of Communication, Business and Information Technologies and Information Technologies Roskilde University Roskilde University DK-4000 Roskilde, Denmark DK-4000 Roskilde, Denmark +45 2990 1181 +45 2888 4542 <email id="5">jonas@jermiin.dk</email> <email id="6">dave@transmission.nu</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="8">Genuine involvement of users and stakeholders in design processes is essential to the success and innovative potential of the result, but making it work in a real setting is not straightforward. By examining the use of design games as a Participatory Design tool we try to bring new perspectives on the involvement and engagement of users. We use the Wittgensteinian term of language-games to understand and describe the meeting of practices that is the essence of any Participatory Design project.</abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">H.1.2 [User/Machine</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible">Human Factors.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="11" confidence="possible">Design, Experimentation, Human Factors.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="12" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Categories and Subject Descriptors Systems]: General Terms Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="17">Martin Baeré Pedersen</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">Participatory design, design games, collaborative design, genuine user participation, language-games, Wittgenstein.</region>
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="14" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" page="1" column="1">In recent years user involvement has become common practice within design of information technology, but there is still room for improvement. The immediate advantages and easily achieved results of user participation have made designers somewhat satisfied with involvement going no further than the role of informants. We suggest that there are valuable insights to be gained from a deeper form of engagement - a more genuine kind of user participation, where users are empowered to contend with the role of the designers. It is in this kind of participation that a mutual learning process can emerge.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="16" page="1" column="1">Permission to make digital or hard copies of all or part of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, or republish, to post on servers or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIDeR’07, March 8–9, 2007, Ronneby, Sweden.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="19" page="1" column="2">Institute of Communication, Business and Information Technologies Roskilde University DK-4000 Roskilde, Denmark +45 2986 8046 <email id="18">martin.baere@gmail.com</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="20" page="1" column="2">In this short paper we discuss the use of design games as a way to facilitate genuine user participation. We do this by discussing issues and concerns with the way user involvement is practiced today. We then introduce design games as an approach to involve users and stakeholders in a design process. With the use of the Wittgensteinian concept of language-games we offer an understanding of the different ways in which users and designers can learn from each other. Finally we conclude by discussing ways in which skillful use of design games can contribute to the achievement of genuine user participation.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="21" page="1" column="2">2. ISSUES WITH USER PARTICIPATION</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="26" page="2" column="1">2.1 Creativity and innovation</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" page="2" column="1">One issue we have experienced in our short life as designers of information technology is the assumption that users, by nature, are not creative, and that it takes special skill and education to be so. Therefore users aren’t very often invited to join the phases of the design project, where the design and shaping actually takes place. Users and stakeholders are only brought into the process to validate or test a prototype of a forthcoming technology. After the session the designers revise the prototype, and the cycle is repeated until a satisfying result is reached – or rather, until the powers that be decides so. From our own studies 1 of design games and design processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="27" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], we believe that this approach has many built-in complications, and we also disagree with the understanding of users not being creative (as also backed by others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="28" class="deo:Reference">10</xref>]). Under the right circumstances valuable creativity can flourish and innovative solutions will be the product of users and designers challenging the ideas of each other.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="30" page="2" column="1">2.2 Design as mutual learning</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="2" column="1">Another issue with only involving users and stakeholders as informants are the lack of true engagement. By only involving users and stakeholders occasionally – when it seems necessary, or when input is needed – the participants are not introduced to the core premise or the main challenges of the design project. Thereby the involved users can only function as informants in the process, and only comment vaguely on presented design ideas or prototypes. Furthermore the lack of involvement means that they are unlikely to feel engaged in the project, and therefore won’t react authentically to oppose design decisions that go against their original visions. Additionally the users will not be able to challenge the more deeply rooted problems of a design proposal, because they simply don’t have enough inside knowledge to spot problems that lies beyond the façade.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="32" page="2" column="1">2.2.1 Learning through participation</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" page="2" column="1">By making the participation genuine it is possible for both designers and users to incrementally build a relationship to each other, and thereby increase knowledge about each others work domains and practices. Furthermore it is argued that it is crucial to the process that “[...] design professionals need knowledge of the actual use context and workers need knowledge of possible technological options.” and “that these types of knowledge are developed most effectively through active cooperation between workers (and increasingly other organizational members) and designers within specific design projects.” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="33" class="deo:Reference">7</xref>] Therefore it is essential to genuinely involve users and stakeholders in the design process – which, we argue, at least means to involve them in decision making processes, as well as letting them participate in the conceptual shaping and development of future artifacts or processes.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" page="1" column="2">As mentioned it is commonly agreed that the engagement of users in the design and shaping of artifacts or processes is a highly valuable - and many times necessary - step towards developing sustainable and innovative information technology (e.g. as argued in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="22" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]). As a result user involvement and final user testing has become an almost mandatory part of any design process. And is by many – we believe - considered a fairly simple and straightforward task to accomplish - but at the same time very informative. But the success of this paradigm seems to have resulted in an understanding that even the slightest user involvement is sufficient. Even though this may be true for small scale projects, additional engagement is needed to attain a deeper understanding. To design participation and truly engage users in the decision making phases of a design process is not at all a trivial task. In the following we will give examples of issues that are crucial to making the participatory approach succeed, but which we think are often not considered, or left out entirely. Especially if the participation of users and stakeholders is not respected as a complex and time consuming process, and therefore not acknowledged as requiring a great deal of attention and preparation. The view that genuine user participation can be accomplished as a quick-and-dirty method, often leads to the participants being used merely as informants. Thereby the potential for innovation and creativity of the users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="23" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>], and their potential to challenge the assumptions and design ideas, stays untapped.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="25" page="1" column="2">Copyright 2007 ACM 1-58113-000-0/00/0004...$5.00.</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="2" column="1">3. DESIGN GAMES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="2" column="1">Design games are game-like design activities, where participants are invited into the design process by the use of activities based on <marker type="block"/> 1 Based on a literature study, several interviews with practitioners and two field studies involving design games in use – all part of the empirical work for our masters thesis.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> various game metaphors. The game-like situations are often defined by their use of props and materials, such as game boards, playing cards and concepts like turn-taking and role-playing. The rules of play bind these concepts together, and as the participants take turns the materials are put into play (see e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="38" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="39" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="40" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="41" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>] for further details).</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="2" column="2">3.1 Games for designing</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="46" page="2" column="2">Various games have been used in many diverse contexts, but in this paper we focus on games inspired by the design games pioneered by Ehn &amp; Sjögren [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="44" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>]. These games are concerned with the involvement of users and other stakeholders in the design process with the aim of improving the final result, by actively using the expertise of the participants in the final design. As an example Brandt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="45" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>] describes a sequence of games that, based on ethnographic field studies, explore the users, their context and their future use of technology. In one of the games the participants build stories of the users by arranging a sequence of cards, derived from the field study, and thereby construct a shared understanding of the users practice.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="47" page="2" column="2">3.2 Game qualities</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="2" column="2">Some of the immediate advantages of design games are their potential to be used as probes to explore whether the assumptions made by the design team are sound, or their use in terms of giving participants a chance to explore their assumptions and wants for the design. Design games are also well suited for supporting idea generation by opening up the design process as the game structure facilitates negotiation. Often a game is a dynamic process between users, stakeholders and designers in exploring issues of design and together building ideas for change. If used skillfully design games can downplay power relations, and support a more uninhibited design process, thereby allowing everybody to have their say [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="48" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>]. Beyond these immediate qualities, we believe the real advantage is the ability to genuinely engage users in the design process, as opposed to simply acting as informants or sources of validation.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" page="2" column="2">3.3 Using design games</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="2" column="2">In this section we present an example of using design games from our own empirical studies [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="51" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], which we will use to illustrate how design games can be used as a design tool.<marker type="block"/> In the design session we used different design games to facilitate an editorial team of an online music magazine in creating visions<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> for change. Inspired by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="56" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="57" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>] we designed a sequence of three games, with each game focusing on a separate issue, but with a clear progression from game to game. The first game focused on identifying qualities of online magazines in general, based on material from a prior competitor study, the second game was designed to facilitate the participants in discussing what core competencies the team possessed, and finally the third game was designed to generate ideas for the future by making the participants combine findings from the first two games with randomly chosen cards picturing technologies or certain physical places, e.g. a mobile device and a music festival.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62d5.page_002.image_01.png" thmb="62d5.page_002.image_01-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="54" page="2" column="2">Figure 1: A scene from the design session.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="3" column="1">4. LANGUAGE-GAMES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="3" column="1">As you may have guessed the title of this paper is a paraphrase of Wittgenstein’s famous quote “If a lion could talk we would not understand him” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="60" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>], meant to illustrate the problem of understanding someone who belongs to a different form of life. According to Wittgenstein the use of language constitutes a practice, and understanding the meaning of a word is only possible from the perspective of a particular language-game. Language-games are Wittgenstein’s notion of practice, or rather practices. As a central point is the multiplicity of practices which co-exist and overlap in society. Wittgenstein used the metaphor of the game to explain the way language constitutes a practice and used rules of a game to illustrate how we, in practice, follow and break rules. Even if the lion could speak it would make no sense to us because the social backdrop of the lion’s existence would be too different from ours. The application of Wittgenstein’s concept of language-games to design stems from Ehn’s book “Work Oriented Design of Computer Artifacts” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="61" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>] in which he develops a philosophy of design. According to Ehn any participatory design process involves a meeting of language-games. On one hand we have the language-game of the designers, involving concepts from the field of design. On the other hand we have the language-game of the users and stakeholders which is grounded in their work-practice and involving concepts from their work domain. The question of communication between these two distinct practices is not a trivial one. Therefore organizing a way for designers and users to develop a common language becomes paramount for a successful design process.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="63" page="3" column="1">4.1 Family Resemblance</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="3" column="1">A common understanding between different language-games can be reached through what Wittgenstein calls family resemblances. Think of the way in which we intuitively know something is a game even if we do not know the particular game. This is because it bears a resemblance to other games we know. One of the potential powers of design games arises from the ability to involve users in the language-game of design through a game-like activity, which bears a family resemblance to games and other situations that they know and thereby empowering users to make design moves.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="65" page="3" column="1">5. DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="3" column="1">Other authors have examined the potential of design games according to Wittgensteins language-games [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="66" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>], but we believe that the real power of these activities are generally overlooked or not emphasized properly in newer accounts of their usage (such as [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="67" class="deo:Reference">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="68" class="deo:Reference">2</xref>].<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Work within the field of Participatory Design has been very successful in organizing ways in which designers can learn about the work practice of users, e.g. through ethnographic field work. What is lacking is ways in which users can learn from the designers or rather how the two parties can approach each other by developing a common language within the design project. In Wittgensteinian terms this means providing ways in which they can understand each others language-game without actually becoming each other.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="3" column="2">5.1 Designing design games</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" page="3" column="2">Skillful use of design games involves an approach where every design situation is considered unique to the extent that the use of design games has to be carefully considered and designed for the context at hand. Like user participation in general, this is not easy. The use of design games demands a lot of preparation, and is not to be underestimated in time consummation; a badly designed game will end up being more inhibiting for the process than helpful [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="72" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>]. Therefore it is important to attend to how these games are designed by making the tacit knowledge in the process explicit, as addressed by Friis when discussing design processes in general: “If the knowledge of processes is mostly intuitive, it is difficult to create new knowledge and it is impossible to include others in the process. Our knowledge must be visible and firm.” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="73" class="deo:Reference">6</xref>] Through our studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="74" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] we have come to believe that especially two aspects - which are constraints and open-endedness - are important to keep in mind when designing design games.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="76" page="3" column="2">5.1.1 Constraints</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="3" column="2">In order to establish a foundation where participants can engage productively in the process, the design game has to stage a frame with appropriate constraints built into the rules or materials. Constraints that set a starting point, from where an exploratory dialog can emerge, while the frame helps in keeping the discussion on track. As an example the game pieces used in our third game discussed above sets the frame for which the discussion begins. By selecting the pieces to be part of the material that the participants pick randomly, we as designers construct the frame within which the game unfolds. By considering design games a design material, which can be shaped and negotiated, we as designers can make an opening design move and explore it with the participants. However it is important that these constraints are open for negotiation during and after the game.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="3" column="2">5.1.2 Open-endedness</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" page="3" column="2">As opposed to the above mentioned need for constraints the games also need to be open-ended, i.e. a balance between these two polarities has to be achieved. This can be accomplished by making certain that the materials and props provided are open for interpretation by the participants. This interpretive flexibility in turn opens for the potential of the users to challenge the assumptions of the designers. In our example game we used the random element to achieve this open-endedness, in that the participants elaborate on often surprising combinations as determined by the cards. Furthermore this also revealed a creative potential in the participants, in creating viable ideas from the sometimes absurd card combinations, even though the qualifications of the participants might have suggested otherwise.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="80" page="4" column="1">6. CONCLUSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" page="4" column="1">Within the field of Participatory Design there has been a great amount of work done on how to learn about the users work practices and ethnographic methods have contributed a great deal to this end. However users are still not actively engaged as co- designers in the design process. Staying within the Wittgensteinian language philosophy there are two obvious ways in which this can be remedied: either by teaching the users the language-game of design or by using Family Resemblances to move the design process closer to the language-game of the users, i.e. developing a common language, and thereby allowing them to participate actively. We believe design games can contribute to the latter option. Thus design games become a way for users to express themselves in a language of design - and we believe they have something valuable to tell us.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="82" page="4" column="1">7. ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="4" column="1">Results presented in this paper are part of our Master thesis which will be handed in on the 1st of May 2007. Empirical studies for our thesis consist of qualitative interviews and testing of design games in realistic settings. We would like to thank Thomas Binder (Center for Design Research, Copenhagen, DK), Jill Lawrence (Pitney-Bowes, USA), Hillary Steckbauer (Yahoo!, USA), Gitte Jonsdatter (IDEO, USA), Judith Gregory (Institute of Design, Chicago, USA), Bettina Törpel (Technical University of Denmark, DK), Eva Brandt (Danish School of Design, DK) and Keld Bødker (Roskilde University, DK) for participating in the interviews. Thanks also to our supervisors Jesper Simonsen and Robin Cheesman (Roskilde University, DK).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="84" page="4" column="1">8. REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="85" page="4" column="1">[1] Brandt, E., Designing Exploratory Design Games - can they be the guiding framework for the designer? in Ninth biennial Participatory Design Conference 2006: Expanding Boundaries in Design, (Trento, Italy, 2006), ACM Press, 57-66.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="86" page="4" column="2">[2] Brandt, E. and Messeter, J., Facilitating collaboration through design games. in Proceedings of the eighth conference on Participatory design: Artful integration: interweaving media, materials and practices - Volume 1, (Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 2004), ACM Press, 121- 131.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="87" page="4" column="2">[3] Bødker, K., Kensing, F. and Simonsen, J. Participatory IT Design - Designing for Business and Workplace Realities. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2004.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="88" page="4" column="2">[4] Ehn, P. Work-Oriented Design of Computer Artifacts. Arbetslivscentrum, Stockholm, 1988.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="89" page="4" column="2">[5] Ehn, P. and Sjøgren, D. From system descriptions to scripts for action. in Greenbaum, J. and Kyng, M. eds. Design at work: cooperative design of computer systems, Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Inc., 1992, 241-268.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="90" page="4" column="2">[6] Friis, S.K. Show It &amp; Tell It Learning Lab Denmark Quarterly, 2005, 6-7.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="91" page="4" column="2">[7] Kensing, F. and Blomberg, J. Participatory Design: Issues and Concerns. Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), 7 (3). 167-185.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="92" page="4" column="2">[8] Merit, S. and Nielsen, T. Vinderkoncepter - Brugerdrevet inovation og forretningsudvikling. Børsens Forlag, Copenhagen, 2006.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="93" page="4" column="2">[9] Moll, J., Müller, D. and Pedersen, M.B. Tradition og transcendens - Evaluering af design games som Participatory Design-metode i organisatorisk kontekst (Master thesis) Department of Communication, Business and Information Technologies, Roskilde University, Roskilde, Denmark, 2007 (Forthcoming).</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="94" page="4" column="2">[10] Robinson, K. Out of Our Minds: Learning to be Creative. Capstone, Oxford, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="95" page="4" column="2">[11] Søndergaard, A. and Buur, J., Video Card Game: An augumented environment for User Centered Design discussions. in Designing Augmented Reality Environments, (Helsingør, Denmark, 2000).</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="96" page="4" column="2">[12] Wittgenstein, L. Philosophical Investigations. Blackwell Publishing, 1953/2001.</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
