<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>c1bc653f1fd3c556fa2771ad3068f51731327e2bd2cada387209749002dc6b34</job>
    <base_name>62fp</base_name>
    <doi>10.1080/15710880701875613</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library] On: 31 October 2014, At: 05:06 Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Informa Ltd Registered in England and Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered Mortimer House, 37-41 Mortimer Street, London W1T 3JH, UK</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="3">office:</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20" id="4">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ncdn20</ext-link></region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="6">Design participation tactics: the challenges and new roles for designers in the co-design process</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx7">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62fp.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Yanki Lee a a Royal College of Art</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">Helen Hamlyn Centre</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="10">London</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="11">UK Published online: 24 Jun 2008.</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="13" confidence="possible">To cite this article: Yanki Lee (2008) Design participation tactics: the challenges and new roles for designers in the co-design process, CoDesign: International Journal of CoCreation in Design and the Arts, 4:1, 31-50, DOI: 10.1080/15710880701875613 to this article: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710880701875613" id="12">http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15710880701875613</ext-link></abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">To link</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible">PLEASE SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="16">Taylor</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="17">to</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="18">our agents, the accuracy, and views and are should of information.</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="19">or arising</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="20">out of This</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="21">&amp;</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="23">&amp; Francis makes every effort to ensure the accuracy of all the information (the “Content”) contained in the publications on our platform. However, Taylor &amp; Francis, and our licensors make no representations or warranties whatsoever as completeness, or suitability for any purpose of the Content. Any opinions expressed in this publication are the opinions and views of the authors, not the views of or endorsed by Taylor &amp; Francis. The accuracy of the Content not be relied upon and should be independently verified with primary sources Taylor and Francis shall not be liable for any losses, actions, claims, proceedings, demands, costs, expenses, damages, and other liabilities whatsoever howsoever caused arising directly or indirectly in connection with, in relation to or the use of the Content. article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial or systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, or distribution in any form to anyone is expressly forbidden. Terms Conditions of access and use can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-" id="22">http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-</ext-link> and-conditions</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24">CoDesign Vol. 4, No. 1, March 2008, 31–50</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible">Design participation tactics: the challenges and new roles for designers in the co-design process Yanki Lee* Royal College of Art, Helen Hamlyn Centre, London, UK (Received 22 August 2007; final version received 12 December 2007) This paper seeks to redefine ‘user participation in design’ and to articulate new roles for designers in order to transform design processes. The term ‘Design Participation’ was introduced in the 1971 Design Research Society conference. The main focus of this paper is to suggest ways to tackle three areas that have been neglected over 30 years of Design Participation development, namely: the aesthetic quality of design practice, the collaborative relationship of design research and participatory design thinking. The paper is a reflection by a professional designer developed through the experience of working with different groups in action research projects and these concrete case studies are used to illustrate the developing theory. Three areas of challenges were identified and the overall aim was to facilitate innovative collaboration and create platforms for social inclusion in design practice. Addressing these challenges, it is essential to reconsider the roles of designers (design developer, facilitator and generator) in order to achieve user participation in design. However, in order to avoid tokenism, the most important thing is to practice these roles as tactics of Design Participation. Keywords: design; design participation; co-design; emancipation; tactics</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="26" page="2" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" page="2" column="1">The first attempt by the design community to address user participation in the design process was an international conference entitled ‘Design Participation’ in 1971, which was sponsored and organised by the Design Research Society (DRS), the multi-disciplinary learned society for the worldwide design research community. This conference was the first to define ‘Design Participation’ as a specific field and bring ‘everyman’ into that field ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Banham 1972</xref>). Its aim was to discuss the importance of user participation in different forms of design practice and establish a community in the design field concerned with such issues. After more than 30 years, the practice of design is changing: going beyond the creation of things and expanding to design experience, services and processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Suri 1990</xref>). Additionally, involving end users in design has become an essential part in design research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Sanders 2006</xref>). In this case, this paper argues that the current focus of the Design Participation development should place more emphasis on the issues of ‘how’ or the actual design practice in order to avoid tokenism rather than just still only looking at the issues of ‘why’ or even ‘should people participate’. The best example of tokenism can be reflected by the current role of participation in housing development in the UK. Starting from the<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 1970s, participation was seen as an economic necessity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Turner 1972</xref>), an element of government policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Ward 1985</xref>) and a political initiative targeted at neighbourhood renewal, regeneration, employment, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Broome 2005</xref>). As a result, the practice of ‘participation’ by architects and other professions involved in housing development has been criticised by self-help sector practitioners as a form of tokenistic community involvement. Therefore, this paper focuses on the practical and pragmatic issues of Participation and Design and identifies three challenges for the Design Participation practice and suggests new roles for professional designers in order to tackle the issues that have arisen. The first challenge of Design Participation practice is how to recapture the aesthetic processing of design through Design Participation in order to produce better designs ‘to pass on to future generations a stock of capital assets that will allow the quality of life to be maintained’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Broome 2005</xref>) or simply for ‘sustainable development’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Brundtland 1987</xref>). As Scrivener (2007) commented, ‘design’ is separating with traditional art and design domains, and moving into the areas of engineering- and service-oriented design, which is process- and function-oriented. However, the aesthetic element of design, which is shared with art and craft, is still the core knowledge of the design professions, but is not being further developed and involved in the discourse of Design Participation. Second, more design research, especially that which regards participation in design, is being conducted by other experts such as psychologists, sociologists and anthropologists, who are more concerned with the effects and influence of designing than its forms. Very few design practitioners who are working in the high stress design field will have the time, the training or the inclination to pursue the findings from design research done by the ‘outsiders’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Mitchell 1993</xref>). This means that there are gaps between scientific design research by ‘outsiders’ and creative design practice by ‘insiders’ because of a lack of collaboration between the two groups in design. This challenge indicates that user research could become more creative for all stakeholders including users if there is more professional designer involvement. Finally, user participation in design might require design paralogy rather than innovation. As Jean-Francois Lyotard (1984: 61) explained,<marker type="block"/> Therefore, some design ideologies are referred to by different names by practitioners and academics; for example, at the Royal College of Art, Product Design is called Design Products and Interaction Design is termed Design Interactions. This is similar to the case of Inclusive Design, which was introduced as design for social inclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Coleman 1994</xref>) with the focus on older and disabled populations, but has since expanded its definition to include other marginalised groups. In this case, the best way to describe the discourse of user participation in design is like the 1971 DRS conference, to use the title, Design Participation (DP) not Participatory Design (PD). In other words, PD is one of the rules to control the design game and DP is a new attitude towards playing the game that will try to change the nature of the game. Understanding the field of DP and collecting similar ways of designing with people together can help designers and other people interested in this area to apply collaborative design thinking in different everyday situations.<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> The methodology of this research is through a self-reflection of a designer/design researcher and aims to demonstrate alternative practices of participation in design through different design projects. Throughout the research process, a series of action research projects were set up to work among different modes of participation. All the projects were spatial design related and the aims were to adapt participatory approaches into ordinary design situations: from simple private client commissions to civic education programme of environmental issues and intensive community involvement of architectural development. All these projects share the same research question of how to transform design processes through participation and explore new roles for designers.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="32" page="2" column="1">*Email: <email id="31">yan-ki.lee@rca.ac.uk</email> ISSN 1571-0882 print/ISSN 1745-3755 online Ó 2008 Taylor &amp; Francis</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="34" page="2" column="1">DOI: 10.1080/15710880701875613 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.informaworld.com" id="33">http://www.informaworld.com</ext-link></outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="35" page="3" column="1">32</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="36" page="3" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="44" page="3" column="1">Paralogy must be distinguished from innovation: the latter is under the command of the system, or at least used by it to improve its efficiency; the former is a move (the importance of which is not recognized until later) played in the pragmatics of knowledge ... The stronger the ‘move’, the more likely it is to be denied the minimum consensus, precisely because it changes the rules of the game upon which the consensus has been based.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47" page="4" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="48" page="4" column="1">33</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" page="4" column="1">2. Modes of participation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" page="4" column="1">Before discussing new roles of designers to carry out Design Participation, it is necessary to define the conceptual framework that has been used to explain the development of these new roles. This analytical framework is based on Henri Lefebvre’s (1972) social/spatial concept that the world is divided into two worlds of practice: abstract space for experts and concrete space for people. Dating from the era of modernism these two worlds were separated, with professionalism being held to be a world apart and above, while people were treated as the subjects for reactive information. When the two worlds rejoin, a new form of in-between space is created called the ‘realm of collaboration’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Lee 2007</xref>). While more and more designers are designing for users, there are many diverse definitions of the term ‘user’. ‘Design for users’ has become one of the design trends. Are users just a subject for analysis or can they be active participants in the design decision- making process? A new analytic tool is introduced to explore different perspectives on design and participation practice in general. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> is the diagram of interaction of abstract space (the realm where designers and experts work) and concrete space (the realm where people live) which provides a new dialectic way to understand Design Participation,<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> whose roots can be traced back to the widespread growth of community action and social movements fighting for social democracy in the 1960s and early 1970s. Since then, there have been a number of attempts, e.g. Arnstein’s ladder of participation (1969) and Christina Lindsay’s pyramid of user-led design (2003), made to delineate classification systems for the participation-phenomenon crossing different disciplines which intend to create hierarchies of participation rather than encourage collaboration and interactions. Applying this framework to understand Participation practice, ‘working with designers’ and ‘working with people’ are opposite poles of an axis that can be mapped parallel to this diagram of the new relationship within the three spaces. Three modes of participation are identified, including Public Participation (PP) in abstract space, Community Participation (CP) in concrete space and Design Participation (DP) across the overlap space of the realm of collaboration. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> intends to distinguish between different ways in which people practice participation and articulate its characteristics. For the design community, Community Participation projects become part of Design Participation when there are many design inputs in the processes or when designers take the initiative. When Public Participation projects involve design, especially involving the public realm, they will start to merge with the domain of Design Participation. A more specific analysis is from the domain of Design Participation, which is the focus of this paper. The main research question is ‘How can the ideology and practice of participation improve design practices?’ Answering this question, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Lee (2007)</xref> developed a new classification of Design Participation to provoke a rethinking process for those involved in Design Participation practice. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> indicates where the Design Participation practices operates, the purpose (also suggested their names), the designer/user relationship and finally the roles of designers and users. Although there is no hierarchical intention as in other classification systems, there is a difference between the use of names to ‘classify’ different practices in the field. In Lyotard’s (1975) terms, Design Participation for ‘innovation’ and ‘collaboration’ practitioners are working on the system of performativity, i.e. they are mission-oriented. For them, knowledge is reduced to its instrumental value. They are conducting Design Participation activities with designers only for people while the ‘emancipation’ practitioners are designing with people. Actually, these three types of Design Participations with designers’ involvement cover the ideology of ‘Co-Design’, which is based on the idea that all people have different opinions and should collaborate in any design process – be it architecture, information systems or business (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Co-Design)." id="61">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Co-Design).</ext-link> However, with the help of technology, the world of design is undergoing a massive change: design is becoming an everyday activity rather than a professional study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Lee 2007</xref>). In other words, it is about how the people-centred era is finally replacing the market-driven era and the bigger phenomenon is that people without design education are designing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Sanders 2006</xref>). The Design Participation for Motivation becomes more important and moves towards the co-design domain even though they are initiated by people and invite designers to work for them. This type of Design Participation seems unrelated because of no involvement of designers. It is more about design processes that are motivated by people, but this type can become the ideal situation for comparison with the other three types of Design Participation with their own style of different designer/user relationships. Within the Design Participation of motivation, the users have autonomy to steer the design process. In order to make the designer–user game more efficient, it is better to have no fixed rules. This is called ‘The Alternative Culture’ for Design Participation by Banham (1972: 17), who concluded that the only real Design Participation is ‘do-it-yourself’, where participants invent their own rules.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> Based on this design and participation discourse, this paper introduces three new roles for designers to make design a more holistic and tactical practice or research form, or even thinking that encourages mutual understanding for more collaboration between designers, researchers and users/people between different modes of participation.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_004.image_02.png" thmb="62fp.page_004.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="55" page="4" column="1">Figure 1. Three modes of participation.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="56" page="5" column="1">34</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="57" page="5" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="6" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="66" page="6" column="1">35</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="67" page="7" column="1">36</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="68" page="7" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="69" page="7" column="1">Table 2. Design participation typology.</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="7">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> The relationship between the designers’</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> What’s Design</td>
                  <td class="table"> space and</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Space of</td>
                  <td class="table"> Participation</td>
                  <td class="table"> the users’</td>
                  <td class="table"> The role of</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> operation</td>
                  <td class="table"> for?</td>
                  <td class="table"> space</td>
                  <td class="table"> ‘designers’</td>
                  <td class="table"> The role of ‘users’</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Designers’</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1. Innovation</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Masters/</td>
                  <td class="table"> Imagined user/</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> space</td>
                  <td class="table"> (designer</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> authorities</td>
                  <td class="table"> representatives</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> only)</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="70" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">The relationship between the designers’ What’s Design space and Space of Participation the users’ The role of operation for? space ‘designers’ The role of ‘users’ Designers’ 1. Innovation Masters/ Imagined user/ space (designer authorities representatives only)</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx71">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_007.image_03.png" thmb="62fp.page_007.image_03-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="72" page="7" column="1">Co-designers/ Co-workers/ facilitators partners</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="73" page="7" column="1">Realm of 2. Collaboration collaboration (designer- (between driven) designers and people)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="74" page="7" column="1">Stimulators</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="75" page="7" column="1">3. Emancipation (user-driven)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="76" page="7" column="1">Creative people/ advisers Active clients</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="77" page="7" column="1">Users/people 4. Motivation space (user only)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="78" page="7" column="1">Craftsmen/ builders</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx79">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_007.image_04.png" thmb="62fp.page_007.image_04-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="81" page="7" column="1">3. ‘Design Your Own Spaces’ pack</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" page="7" column="1">In order to encourage participation in design practice, an internal transformation of thinking in the design community is an essential part for this change. Aiming to define the new roles of designers as design developers, a series of small-scaled design projects were conducted at the beginning of this design research. All started following ordinary commercial design practice, i.e. clients employing architectural designers to design and supervise their projects. However, in these projects, the clients were invited to experience an unconventional way of designing, in which designers did not design the projects for them but with them, at the same time enabling them to control the process. Designers become the developers of participatory design processes, which aimed to achieve aesthetic quality. Starting from co-designing a clinic with a psychologist to guide a young couple to <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> design their future home, a holistic process was developed to engage clients. The idea was to insert three new steps, 3P process, into conventional environmental design projects:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83" page="8" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="84" page="8" column="1">37</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">(1) Preference stage (P1) – participants are invited to express their preference through specially designed tools. (2) Planning stage (P2) – collective brief and self study exercise to help the participant to define their design brief. (3) Processing stage (P3) – transfer abstract design tools to people-engaged games to let participants experience hands-on design.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="87" page="8" column="1">3.1. (3P) procedure</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="8" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> shows that instead of designers designing in their expert world after receiving the design brief from their clients (Step 0), the designers’ first new role is to bring clients into the Design Participation domain by reinterpreting the design process and embedding design knowledge in three new steps in order to encourage clients’ to be creatively involved in design. The first step, Preference (P1), when after a few discussions with the clients, visual images reflecting the clients’ preferred style were collected, organised and presented to them to construct a visual reference of what they wanted. This new step was added in order to find out more about what the clients wanted and also guide them to understand their needs and develop the exact brief with the designers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>). Clients were also asked about the existing usage of spaces. Then their</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_008.image_05.png" thmb="62fp.page_008.image_05-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="92" page="8" column="1">Figure 2.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">‘Design Your Space’ pack project Flow Map. 0, Existing design practice between designers and users (clients). New steps across Design Participation domain: P1, preference study; P2, Planning Design; P3, process involvement and comments on modification.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="94" page="9" column="1">38</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="95" page="9" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_009.image_06.png" thmb="62fp.page_009.image_06-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="97" page="9" column="1">Figure 3. Preference (P1) tools: participants are given some design references and a graphic questionnaire to express their expectation of their future spaces.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_009.image_07.png" thmb="62fp.page_009.image_07-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="99" page="9" column="1">Figure 4. Planning (P2) tools and result: planning game pack with spatial functions icons and game instruction (left) and client’s designed game board.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_009.image_08.png" thmb="62fp.page_009.image_08-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="101" page="9" column="1">Figure 5.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Process (P3) result: ‘quick and dirty’ model making led by designers with clients.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="10" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="104" page="10" column="1">39</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="10" column="1">answers on the functions of these spaces were developed into icons for clients to ‘design’ their own spaces by locating the icons onto a specially designed and scaled floor plan of their spaces. This second step, Planning (P2), is aimed to invite clients to take part in the planning design stage as a design partner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>). This design partnership continues from the two-dimensional design planning stage into the three- dimensional model design, which is called the Process (P3). This intends to let clients experience a simplified construction process through model-building (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>). The results showed that clients were emancipated and transformed their usage knowledge into designs that fitted their needs through the new Design Participation tools in the three-step process. Through this 3P process, design knowledge is transferred into design tools that allow for a better articulation and resolution of the clients’ real needs in the design process.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="10" column="1">4. Creating a common language</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" page="10" column="1">After discussing the internal transformation of the design process and pulling the process into the Design Participation domain, this section deals with the second area, where designers are encouraged to shift their work mode from abstract space to concrete space, where they can use their knowledge to emancipate people and help them to understand design. Defining who will be the users of the design is always a difficult task for designers, especially in public projects. An even more difficult task is to empathise with the users/ people. This requires transferring design knowledge to help people to understand new design ideas and comment on them. A real-life test of the feasibility of this redefined role of designers as design facilitators was created in the realm of environmental design in the concrete space. A long and intensive exploration with a local resident community regarding public housing in Hong Kong was initiated, based on preliminary questions which tackled issues in the three spaces from the position of design community: What is the social role of designers with other participatory practice? What is the relationship between designers and people? How can communication be improved between the two groups? The author of this paper worked intensively as an advocate designer/researcher for eighteen months with social workers and representatives from local residents’ groups in a social housing estate called the Lower Ngau Tau Kok (LNTK) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Lee et al. 2004</xref>) in Hong Kong. Its main aim was to establish a relationship between design professionals and social service providers and to investigate what designers can bring to this social action/process. The involvement of the advocate designer/design researcher was started after the first phase of the social action characterised by many protests. The result was that all the residents, as a whole community, would move together into a new-build housing estate in the area chosen by the residents. The second phase was about the design of their future estate; it was hard for the residents to imagine how their lives would be changed in the new housing estate. Over the past 40 years, these residents have adapted their lives within a fixed physical housing environment, i.e. built to the Hong Kong 1960s public housing standard: a single room with no partition, 14–27 m 2 as the average unit floor area for families with 4–8 persons, single slab blocks with central corridor access and 32–58 units at each level in 8–15 storey buildings. With improved space standards and quality of design, their future estate would have various standard units to suit the different sizes of households, from 17–52 m 2 , ranging from one-person units to three-bedroom units (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Figure 6</xref>). The typical housing</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112" page="11" column="1">40</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="113" page="11" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_011.image_09.png" thmb="62fp.page_011.image_09-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="115" page="11" column="1">Figure 6.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">A comparison of Hong Kong public housing layout design – 1960s typical 4-person studio flat and 2000s one-bedroom flat.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" page="11" column="1">estate has also developed from pure residential usage with simple shops at the ground floor level to mixed use of commercial blocks and recreational areas around the high-rise housing blocks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Figure 7</xref>). Therefore, the main purpose of the second phase was to help the residents to understand the architects’ representations in order to participate in a discussion of their future home design, since the main questions from the active residents are ‘What will our reception estate look like?’ and ‘What is its design?’</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="119" page="11" column="1">4.1. Empowerment games for community workshop</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="121" page="11" column="1">Three design workshops were created for residents with social workers to understand the complicated architectural design process in association with their everyday life experience. The aim of these workshops was to help the resident group members understand the design process and language of design. These three workshops are called awareness workshops and were developed using the 3P process described in the previous section with three ‘Empowerment games’, i.e. a series of game-like tools for community workshops, which are designed as interfaces to inspire the participants to raise their awareness of their living environment. Different scales of urban living problems are addressed through different games and inviting players to make associations is the main gaming mechanism. Through these new experiences, knowledge of design is transferred from design researcher to resident group members and then to other residents. Game 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Figure 8</xref>) aimed at enabling participants to anticipate problems and opportunities in their future home by associating their perception of positive and negative environmental factors in several newly built housing estates in Hong Kong with issues that may possibly play a role in the design of their own future homes. The aim of this first simple awareness workshop was to provoke participants’ interest in the workshops. The result was that participants were actively involved in the process and many useful dialogues about environmental issues were developed. For example, the discussion about the design of the rubbish collection system was an interesting dialogue. Participants thought that this is a good design but needed to be improved. One of the suggestions was to change the opening mechanism from a hand-operated one to a step-operated one, solving the problem of the dirty handle which had discouraged use of the system.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="122" page="12" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="123" page="12" column="1">41</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F7">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_012.image_10.png" thmb="62fp.page_012.image_10-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="125" page="12" column="1">Figure 7.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">A comparison of Hong Kong public housing layout design: the LNTK estate designed in 1967 (above) and the new LNTK estate designed in 2004 (below).</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" page="12" column="1">In the Planning Workshop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Figure 9</xref>), participants arranged icons representing the furniture and items of their day-to-day life within plans of their future flat. These individual flats were then placed within the context of the overall layout of the building block. This game (game 2) allowed participants to gain an understanding of the relationship of their private space to the communal space and overall building ensemble.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="129" page="13" column="1">42</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="130" page="13" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F8">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_013.image_11.png" thmb="62fp.page_013.image_11-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="132" page="13" column="1">Figure 8.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Game 1 for Preference Workshop – photos were taken by residents during new housing estates visits. The photos were organised and planned according to different visits. Participants were instructed to use green dots to call attention to things they see as positive and orange arrows to indicate problems.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F9">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_013.image_12.png" thmb="62fp.page_013.image_12-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="135" page="13" column="1">Figure 9.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Game 2 for Planning Workshop – different sized flats were introduced to participants. They chose the floor plan of the flat that they are going to move into in their future estate. Then they needed to arrange given furniture, wall and door icons on the chosen floor plan to show their future layout. During the process, there were a lot of associations between their existing usage patterns and the future ones. The results were unexpected and different to the architects’ designs. After understanding their own flats, participants were instructed to place their ‘designed’ floor plan into the whole building floor plan and discuss the relationship between flats and the building settings.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" page="13" column="1">It also encouraged projection of the patterns of their daily existence into the space of their future flats, leading to insights about spatial division and organisation. At the beginning, participants were confused about the concept of a two-dimensional floor plan and they did not have a concept of the relation of plan scale to actual scale. Then they started to associate the cartooned icons with their mental maps of their existing home. After many collective conversations, all participants overcame those problems and made the game into a useful tool for them to design their future home. Many creative spatial use scenarios developed. The Process Workshop ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Figure 10</xref>) tackled the most complicated and abstract issue of the project – the overall design of the estate. It is very difficult for end users to associate the<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> tremendous scale of a whole estate with their daily experience on the basis of plans alone. Therefore, game 3 was designed based on a conceptualised construction process, intended to give the participants an understanding of the constructive logic of their future estate. The other issue is to create a chance for participants to experience the transformation from a two-dimensional architectural blueprint to a three-dimensional conceptual model. This collective learning experience encouraged more conversations about the overall planning.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="139" page="14" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="140" page="14" column="1">43</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F10">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_014.image_13.png" thmb="62fp.page_014.image_13-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="142" page="14" column="1">Figure 10. Game 3 for Process Workshop – participants were instructed to organise the ‘puzzles’ collectively. Each puzzle piece represents one floor of each block. Then, participants stacked all the related puzzle pieces together and constructed the representations of all the blocks of their future estates. Finally, they needed to locate the ‘built’ blocks onto the prepared landscaped model.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="144" page="14" column="1">4.2. Design challenges for community participation</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" page="14" column="1">Through such experience, knowledge of design is transferred from designer to residents. However, three main areas of issues were raised. The first area is regarding the actual participatory process. This LNTK project showed that there is only linear movement which is target-oriented: from Community Participation to Public Participation and then to Design Participation and back into Public Participation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Figure 11</xref>). There seems to be a lack of mutual development between spaces. For example, throughout the LNTK process there were a few design academics who tried to join the team, but their interaction was limited to the social workers only or to communication with residents in a top-down attitude. To avoid this situation, the author spent time engaging with residents without any agenda but just observing the residents’ needs. After attending many residents’ meetings preceded by estate visits with different groups, an in-depth understanding of the issues was developed and a bespoke process was developed and delivered. Being design facilitators, it is also important to respect user creativity and this is the second area revealed in the LNTK project experience. Through defining the problems together, a mutual trust relationship was developed between the collaborators – social workers, resident group members – and the author of this paper, as the design researcher. Everyone in the process provided his or her expert knowledge. As stated before, this project was initiated by the social workers and the author of this paper joined in at the second stage. During the process, the author was impressed by the passion of the residents and their efforts to respect and protect their homes. Among all the residents, there were two outstanding characters: Mr. Plumbing and Mr. Balcony. Mr. Plumbing is in his seventies and was very concerned about the waste plumbing and piping system since the SARS outbreak in Hong Kong just two months before the visits, i.e. June 2003. He went straight to the toilets on every visit, making a detailed investigation of the plumbing systems and taking photos of the components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Figure 12</xref>). Every time he invited other</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="148" page="15" column="1">44</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149" page="15" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F11">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_015.image_14.png" thmb="62fp.page_015.image_14-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="151" page="15" column="1">Figure 11.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">The LNTK project flow diagram. 1, Protests for better relocation arrangement. 2, Meetings with Housing Authority. 3, Visiting new housing estates. 4, Awareness workshop 1. 5, Awareness workshop 2. 6, Awareness workshop 3. 7, Induction sessions for all residents organised by resident groups. 8, Presentation at the Hong Kong International Housing Conference.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F12">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62fp.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="154" page="15" column="1">Figure 12.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">New estate visit photo, (left) plumbing system, (right) hanging cloth. Photos by members of LNTK resident group.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" page="15" column="1">members to discuss his findings. Similarly, Mr. Balcony was obsessed about the balcony issue in the design of public housing. He is a middle-aged member who raised the question of ‘where to hang clothing if there is no balcony in the new public housing design?’ In Hong Kong housing design, a balcony has become a symbol of luxury in middle-class, high-rise housing. He insists that the function of a balcony is more than just for drying clothes. Therefore, his photo collection is full of explorations of users’ ways of hanging clothing without balconies ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12" id="156" class="deo:Reference">Figure 12</xref>). The creativity of residents inspired the rethinking of the roles of users from those being researched to co-researchers or co-designers of the processes. In this case, the design researcher offered a knowledge of design and customised specific design methods for the group, other experts invited by the social workers also<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> helped the groups to solve specific questions, such as elderly rights issues and public housing policies, etc. and resident group members shared their ways of living to give comments for the framework of future housing design. What they are asking for is the simple desire of residents that is impossible to fulfil with the present design and construction system of Hong Kong public housing. Therefore, design professionals should use their creativity to encourage mutual activities. It is more important to develop creative design interfaces to break the boundaries between the operating spaces and co-creating design processes to reduce conflicts. Organising the three awareness workshops, i.e. Preference, Process and Planning, residents’ awareness of the relationship of the daily issues and design are raised. However, this participatory design process only tackled the needs of residents without transforming design experts’ practices, i.e. there is no direct involvement of the designers who would eventually design their future home and the result is only a design awareness exercise and no design implication. In order to facilitate participatory design processes, the final and most fundamental and important element should be a change of practice by design professionals. However, for design community members who work across the spaces and in the mode of Design Participation, the main conflict in participatory processes is the issue of authorship. In this case, the author of this paper worked as a designer/design researcher and became involved in the project without a well-defined role definition during the process and as a result, a confusion of authorship happened. Many ideas were shared between the author and the social workers and co-generated the proposal of the next stage. Without any pre-agreement of authorship, there was no proper acknowledgement when the social workers submitted the proposal to the appropriate government department. The social workers also complained that the author was crossing the boundary and challenging the existing Community Participation practice. The result was that the developing trust relationship over the eighteen-month period was forced to an end and the project turned back into a working relationship between the Community and the Public Participation only, which is the usual practice in community development projects for social justice. This lesson showed that there needs to be a balance between design facilitation and intellectual property, where designers/design researchers are not trusted only as consultants on technological issues but can work with people in a partnership relationship.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="158" page="16" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="159" page="16" column="1">45</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="161" page="16" column="1">5. Campaign as community building</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="166" page="16" column="1">The final but most long-term development is about generating collaborations with other professionals through participation. Professionalism is one of the reasons for the separation of abstract and concrete operating spaces. Working with the participation of other professions, designers need to illustrate concretely the participatory design processes and make them understandable to other professions. Most Public Participation projects are research-oriented and people’s opinions are collected for the development of policy or strategies. Compared to the projects in the Design and Community participation domains, these projects are shorter and quicker or even ad hoc and the role of the designer/design researcher is more like that of a service provider. By working as design generators, designers are working in the realm of collaboration to facilitate the mixing of ‘abstract’ experts and ‘concrete’ people. On another level, designers also can help to transform the way professionals work by inserting more creative design thinking. Both these two new tactical roles for designers can be demonstrated through the Clean LNTK project which was a by-product of the original LNTK project (the previous case) responding with creative design outputs to local campaigns and also <marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> providing a different approach to the on-going bottom-up participatory project at an old social housing estate in Hong Kong. The project started after the SARS outbreak, when many people in Hong Kong tried to ‘cheer up’ the depressed city and people. Campaigns such as ‘Hong Kong Unmasked’ or Fearbuster (www.fearbuster.org.hk) were introduced in order to try and bring life in Hong Kong back to ‘normal’. The project was carried out from the abstract space: a large-scale survey and interviews were conducted with the help of experts when residents from the LNTK project were changed from specific problem- and process-owners to research analysis subjects as in many civic education projects. Throughout the project, many experts from different backgrounds in the professional network joined the project to offer ‘advice’ on public and personal hygiene and it was concluded in a civic educational event (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Figure 13</xref>) and published pamphlet.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="163" page="17" column="1">46</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="164" page="17" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx167">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_017.image_16.png" thmb="62fp.page_017.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1"> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Figure 13</xref>. Community event of the ‘Clean LNTK’ project (opening 4 exercise demonstration 4 discussion session) and Civic Exchange’s ‘Clean LNTK summer project’ distributed pamphlet designed by Yanki Lee.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="170" page="18" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="171" page="18" column="1">47</outsider>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="172" page="18" column="1">5.1. Lessons for Public Participation projects</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="175" page="18" column="1">The clean LNTK team (author and researchers from a public policy think tank) acted as a bridge between the world of experts and that of people. The first finding from this collaboration with other professions is that designers should work as design generators in order to create non-hierarchical situations. Compared to the other two projects described in this paper, this project achieved the best level of communication and highest respect from co-workers because this project was a collaboration between equals within the experts’ world (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14" id="173" class="deo:Reference">Figure 14</xref>): Public Participation experts (researchers from the Civic Exchange, a public policy think tank, and the author as an emerging expert in the field of Design Participation). This suggests that social hierarchy is relevant in all design research projects and one of designers’ tactical roles is to balance this social relationship within projects and generate participatory professionalism. This new role of design generator is also related to how design elements could make a Public Participation project more inclusive. Since the Clean LNTK project is a Public Participation project working in the Design Participation domain through the author’s instigation as a Design Participation researcher, new ways of communication design styles for the public (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15" id="174" class="deo:Reference">Figure 15</xref>) were explored to reflect the complex combination between different spaces, setting and the influences. The project was set up to find solutions and raise public awareness of public hygiene to prevent the spread of SARS and other diseases in urban situations. It was used as a demonstration to other professionals of how to create creative participation processes through collaboration between experts. It is also common</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F14">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_018.image_17.png" thmb="62fp.page_018.image_17-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="177" page="18" column="1">Figure 14.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="178" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Clean LNTK Project Flow Map. 0, Clean LNTK Project. 1, Survey of cleaning behaviour with public estate residents. 2, Publish reports and pamphlets to promote proper cleaning habits. 3, Cleaning seminar. 4, Design suggestions for future development.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="179" page="19" column="1">48</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="19" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F15">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_019.image_18.png" thmb="62fp.page_019.image_18-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="182" page="19" column="1">Figure 15.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="183" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Elderly resident reading the special design pamphlet (left). A resident expressing comments at the Civic Exchange civic education event/Exhibition (right). Photo by Yanki Lee.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" page="19" column="1">that the aims of Public Participation projects are related to civic education and awareness- building exercises and the results are usually intangible, possibly where the experience of some social concerns is enhanced, so that exemplar projects need to be generated to inspire more professionals to understand the practice of different participation projects, and design thinking can be introduced into general/public participation projects.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="185" page="19" column="1">6. Discussions and conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="186" page="19" column="1">New ways to look at how to achieve Design Participation are suggested in this paper. From defining three neglected areas, three different new roles are mapped:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="187" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">(1) Design Developers working with design community to transform design processes for participation. (2) Design Facilitators designing with people to transfer design knowledge to emancipate people to improve their lives. (3) Design Generators collaborating with professionals to explore design thinking to different implications.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="190" page="19" column="1">As the term ‘tactics’ suggests in the title of this paper, all these new roles are introduced only to provide a framework for the design community and their collaborators to develop their own ways of designing with people. These new roles for designers are embedded with different Design Participation Tactics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="188" class="deo:Reference">Lee 2007</xref>). They are ‘tactics’ but not ‘strategies’ because according to de Certeau (1984: 37–38), ‘strategy’ is based on place while ‘tactics’ are based on time and opportunities. Therefore, strategy indicates an overall game plan while tactics can be temporary or spontaneous and not necessarily linked to a planned overall approach. ‘Tactics’ represent a kind of reflective action. In contrast to ‘strategies’, ‘tactics’ depend more on hands-on experience for Design Participation by putting designers within people’s field of everyday life. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16" id="189" class="deo:Reference">Figure 16</xref> concludes with the action plan of how to apply Design Participation Tactics, i.e. designers should work as design agents to adapt different roles (design developers,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="191" page="20" column="1">CoDesign</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="192" page="20" column="1">49</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F16">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62fp.page_020.image_19.png" thmb="62fp.page_020.image_19-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="194" page="20" column="1">Figure 16.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="195" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Action plan of design participation tactics – more collaborations between those from different operating spaces.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="196" page="20" column="1">facilitators or generators) and work with different stakeholders in different situations. The aim is to bring experts and people/users into the Design Participation domain and experience new interaction with designers. With these tactical and pragmatic ways of designing, the goal is to make design a living knowledge that can emancipate people to enjoy designs and designing.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="197" page="20" column="1">Acknowledgements</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="198" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">First, I would like to thank all the ‘users’ in my research, especially the grass-roots resident group’s members (The Lower Ngau Tau Kok (II) Estate Redevelopment Concern Group and the Elderly Flats Concern Group) for their valuable time and trust in me by sharing their experience. Perhaps I should call them my ‘illegal supervisors’, echoing Hill’s (2003) ‘illegal architect’, because of their valuable insights for my design development. I hope they will not be treated merely as ‘users’ anymore. I would like to thank my respected supervisor-in-chief, Mr Timothy Jachna, and my co- supervisor, Professor John Frazer, from School of Design, the Hong Kong Polytechnic University. It was my great honour to work with Professor Roger Coleman and Professor Jeremy Myerson, Directors of the Helen Hamlyn Centre at the Royal College of Art, London, who are experts in inclusive design and innovation. This research would not have been possible without the support of the research studentship-funding scheme and help from staff members of the School of Design of the Hong Kong Polytechnic University. Finally, many thanks are given to the editors of this issue, especially Dr Thomas Binder and Dr Eva Brandt, for their valuable comments and patient tracing, and Julia Cassim for her final editing of the paper in its current form.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="199" page="20" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="200" page="20" column="1">Arnstein, S., 1969. A ladder of citizen participation. Journal of the American institute of planners, in The City Reader, 199, 244–255.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="201" page="20" column="1">Banham, R., 1972. Alternative networks for the alternative culture? In: Design participation: Proceedings of the design research society’s conference. UK: The Design Research Society, 15–19.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="202" page="20" column="1">Broome, J., 2005. Mass housing cannot be sustained. In: P.B. Jones, D. Petrescu, and J. Till, eds. Architecture &amp; participation. Oxford: Spon Press, 65–75.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="203" page="20" column="1">Brundtland, G.H., 1987. Our common future, world commission on environment and development. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="206" page="21" column="1">Coleman, R., 1994. The case for inclusive design—an overview. In: Proceedings of the 12th triennial congress. International Ergonomics Association and the Human Factors Association, Canada.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="207" page="21" column="1">de Certeau, M., 1984. The practice of everyday life. London: University of California Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="208" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Hill, J., 2003. Actions of architecture: architects and creative users. London: Routledge, 10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="209" page="21" column="1">Lee, Y., Design participation tactics: involving people in the design of their built environment. Doctoral thesis, Hong Kong Polytechnic University, 2007.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="210" page="21" column="1">Lee, Y.K. and Jachna, T., 2004. Empowerment games: empathic design probes for user participation in community housing. In: Proceedings of the participatory design conference (PDC 2004). Toronto, Canada, 27–31 July.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="211" page="21" column="1">Lefebvre, H., 1972, 2003. The urban revolution. USA: The University of Minnesota Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="212" page="21" column="1">Lindsay, C., 2003. Involving people as co-creators. In: The new everyday: Views on ambient intelligence. Rotterdam: The 010 Publishers, 38–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="213" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Lyotard, J-F., 1979, 1984. The postmodern condition—A report on knowledge. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="214" page="21" column="1">Mitchell, C.T., 1993. Redefining designing: From form to experience. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="215" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Sanders, E.B.-N., 2006. Design research in 2006. Design research quarterly, 1 (1). Scrivener, S.A.R., 2007. Editorial. CoDesign, 3 (2), 95–96.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="216" page="21" column="1">Suri, F.J., 1990. IDEO: The experience evolution: developments in design practice. In: The design journal, 6 (2), 39–48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="217" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Turner, J.F.C., 1972. Housing by people: Towards autonomy in building environments. New York: Marion Boyars.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="218" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Ward, M., 1985. Purchasing power parities and real expenditures in the OECD. Paris: OECD.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="204" page="21" column="1">50</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="205" page="21" column="1">Y. Lee</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
