<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>46620fe9c5ae350b6f3d7074714edf96c5ee91dd3054306fbea4487b752a853c</job>
    <base_name>62pt</base_name>
    <doi>10.1080/09544820802698550</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Journal of Engineering Design Vol. 20, No. 5, October 2009, 467–476</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx2">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62pt.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Emotional bonding with personalised products</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Ruth Mugge a</name>
          <aff id="5">*</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Jan P.L. Schoormans a</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Hendrik N.J. Schifferstein b</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="17" page="1" column="1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email id="16">r.mugge@tudelft.nl</email></footnote>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" confidence="possible">a Department of Product Innovation and Management, Delft University of Technology, Landbergstraat 15, Delft 2628 CE, The Netherlands; b Department of Industrial Design, Delft University of Technology, Landbergstraat 15, Delft 2628 CE, The Netherlands (Received 22 April 2008; final version received 4 August 2008 )</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="9" confidence="possible">This study investigates the effect of personalising a product’s appearance on the emotional bond with a product. We present a conceptual model for the relationships between the effort invested during the process of product personalisation, the degree of self-expression, and the degree of emotional bonding. Data from a questionnaire study in which respondents (n = 149) filled out questions concerning their (non-) personalised bicycle support our expectations. By personalising the product’s appearance, a person invests effort in the product. Our findings show that the amount of effort invested has a direct effect (as a result of the extended period of time spent with the product) and an indirect effect (via the personalised product’s self-expressive value) on the strength of the emotional bond with the product. The paper concludes by discussing the implications of these findings for product designers. Keywords: customer integration; design strategy; user evaluation; emotional bonding; personalisation</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" page="1" column="1">In today’s markets, many consumer durables are comparable with respect to their features, quality, and user friendliness. This forces designers to find new ways to differentiate their products from competitors. Consequently, designers are increasingly focusing on the ‘emotional responses and experiences’ that products can bring about rather than on their functional benefits. Emotions enrich a person’s life and can increase one’s general experience of well-being ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="10" class="deo:Reference">Diener and Lucas 2000</xref>). Accordingly, emotional responses to products can be a decisive factor in purchase decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="11" class="deo:Reference">Jordan 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Desmet 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Norman 2004</xref>). In addition, products can elicit emotional responses during ownership (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Hirschman and Holbrook 1982</xref>). In this respect, Desmet (2002, p. 187) argued that studying emotional responses for a purchase situation may not be sufficient: ’In the long run, it may be more fruitful to establish a long-term emotional relationship with the consumer’. Then, the product continues to elicit emotional responses over an extended period of time. This research investigates the experience of an emotional bond with a product, which implies that a strong relationship or tie exists between an individual and an object. Experiencing an emotional bond with products is a matter of degree. People may feel deeply attached to their most favourite possessions, whereas other possessions are less significant to them. When a person develops an emotional bond with a product, this product has acquired meaning beyond the functional. In other<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> words, the product ceases to be an ordinary object and becomes extraordinary. In general, people experience more positive emotions (e.g., happiness, love, warmth, and pride) towards products with which they feel emotionally bonded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Schultz et al. 1989</xref>). Experiencing an emotional bond with a product can also result in specific protective behaviours, because people cherish their relationship with the product and want to preserve it. Accordingly, people are more likely to handle the product with care, to repair it when it breaks down, and to postpone its replacement. Emotional bonding may thus increase a product’s lifetime. In this article, we focus on the integration of consumers in the design process of their product through product personalisation as a means for designers to strengthen this emotional bonding.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="19" page="1" column="1">ISSN 0954-4828 print/ISSN 1466-1837 online © 2009 Taylor &amp; Francis DOI: 10.1080/09544820802698550 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.informaworld.com" id="18">http://www.informaworld.com</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="20" page="2" column="1">468</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="21" page="2" column="1">R. Mugge et al.</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="24" page="2" column="1">1. Product personalisation</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="2" column="1">Based on the definition of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Blom (2000)</xref>, product personalisation is defined as a process that defines or changes the appearance or functionality of a product to increase its personal relevance to an individual.Although personalising products has recently received a lot of interest at companies, the concept is not new. Before the Industrial Revolution, all products were hand-made. Consequently, every product was unique and could be easily personalised to fit individual needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Heskett 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Weightman and McDonagh 2003</xref>). When companies started to mass produce products, products became standardised and identical for large groups of people. As a result, mass-produced products lack a personal touch. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Jencks and Silver (1972)</xref> had already argued that manufacturers standardise and limit people’s choices. They concluded that products should be designed more ad hoc, resulting in unique products for different individuals. In 1980, Toffler also discussed the changing roles of consumers. He suggested that consumers will be replaced by ‘prosumers’: individuals who are both the producer and the consumer of a product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Toffler 1980</xref>). Today, companies are still searching for ways to restore individualisation in products by integrating the consumer in the design process through product personalisation. Product personalisation can be implemented in many ways. For example, Adidas offers a mass customisation service (MiAdidas; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.miadidas.com" id="30">http://www.miadidas.com</ext-link>), which enables consumers to operate as co-designers and design their own pair of personalised shoes by allowing consumers to specify the colours for the various shoe parts. Furthermore, the shoes are specially built to match the shape of one’s feet. The result is a unique pair of Adidas shoes that matches one’s personal preferences with respect to fit and taste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Piller 2003</xref>). Changing the cover and ring tone of a mobile phone or redecorating one’s cupboard are examples of product personalisation as well. Past research has revealed several reasons for consumers to personalise their products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Blom and Monk 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Piller 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Weightman and McDonagh 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Schreier 2006</xref>). First of all, personalising a product will increase the fit to individual preferences (both functional and aes- thetic), as is evident from the MiAdidas example. Personalisation can enhance the product’s ease of use. For example, mobile phones can be programmed to play different ring tones for particular phone numbers, which enables the owner to identify the caller. Consumers may also personalise a product to reflect their personal or group identity. An example is the ownership of a modified car in the USA, which represents one’s belonging to the street racing subculture. Personalising is also a way to communicate ownership of the product. For instance, by placing one’s books in the bookcase and sticking up posters, an office room feels more personal. Furthermore, product personalisation helps consumers to recognise a product as one’s own. For example, choosing a conspicuous phone cover helps to distinguish your phone from those of your friends. In this respect, a personalised product that stands out may also reduce the risk of theft. An additional reason for consumers to personalise a product is that the personalisation process itself may be fun to do. By personalising a product, a consumer directs time, energy, and attention to the product. In other words, consumers invest effort in a product. While personalising the product, the<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> person needs to make (creative) choices (e.g., choosing the design and colours of the product’s appearance), which requires mental effort. In addition, product personalisation can demand physical effort, when people alter the product themselves (e.g., when painting or assembling a product). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Cardozo (1965)</xref> already concluded that the effort (mental, physical, and financial) consumers expend to obtain a product can contribute to the evaluation of the product: Consumers who had invested a great deal of effort in the shopping experience evaluated the product as more favourable and important. Moreover, several scholars argued that the experience of a strong emotional bond with a product is positively related to the degree of ‘psychic energy’, that is the person’s mental effort invested in a product (Csikszentmihalyi and Rochberg-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Halton 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Belk 1988</xref>). Based on these arguments, we hypothesise that if the personalisation process requires the investment of a great deal of effort, the person is occupied with the product for an extended period of time, which may positively influence the strength of the emotional bond with the product. We believe that this effect of the effort invested during the personalisation process on the emotional bond with the product can be partly explained by the fact that personalised products are more self-expressive of a person’s unique identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Blom 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Blom and Monk 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Kiesler and Kiesler 2005</xref>). The outcome of investing effort in a product during the personalisation process is a product with a personal touch. Past research on product personalisation concluded that consumers personalise products in such a way that they can distinguish themselves from others and can communicate a personal identity. Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Dahl and Moreau (2007)</xref> argued that undertaking a creative task may reinforce a person’s sense of identity. Depending on the extent to which the personalisation process was performed successfully, the personalised product may represent a personal accomplishment to the owner, because consumers created it themselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Bendapudi and Leone 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Piller 2004</xref>). In summary, a personalised product may gain the special meaning of self-expression to the owner over and above the functional meaning. Past research concluded that people become emotionally bonded with products that define and maintain a person’s self (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Wallendorf and Arnould 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Schultz et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Ball and Tasaki 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Kleine et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Mugge et al. 2006</xref>). Moreover, self-expression is distinguished as a reason for people to regard a possession as treasured or special (Csikszentmihalyi and Rochberg-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Halton 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Dittmar 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Richins 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Kamptner 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Dyl and Wapner 1996</xref>). Accordingly, we hypothesise that the effort invested during the personalisation process has a direct effect (as a result of the extended period of time spent with the product) and an indirect effect (via the product’s self-expressive value) on the strength of the emotional bond with a product (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>). Hence, self-expression is a pathway through which effort invested influences emotional bonding. These hypotheses are summarised in a conceptual model (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="37" page="3" column="1">Journal of Engineering Design</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="38" page="3" column="1">469</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_003.image_02.png" thmb="62pt.page_003.image_02-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="40" page="3" column="1">Figure 1. Conceptual model.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="63" page="3" column="1">2. Method</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="64" page="3" column="1">2.1.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="65" page="3" column="1">2.1. Respondents</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="3" column="1">A convenience sample of 149 Dutch students at the Delft University of Technology (58% male and 42% female; mean age = 21) was used for this study. The respondents studied at different <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> programmes (i.e., aerospace engineering, applied mathematics, architecture, civil engineering, computer science, electrical engineering, industrial design engineering, marine technology, mechanical engineering, systems engineering, policy analysis, and management). These students were approached at the university and all owned a bicycle.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="67" page="4" column="1">470</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="68" page="4" column="1">R. Mugge et al.</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="70" page="4" column="1">2.2.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="4" column="1">2.2. Product</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" page="4" column="1">In general, Dutch students own a bicycle, which they use on a daily basis to travel from their home to university. When these students start university, they are likely to buy a second-hand bicycle or to use an old one, because these are less expensive and because bicycles are often stolen. Bicycles were chosen as the product category under study, because these students frequently personalise the bicycles’ appearances by painting them in several (conspicuous) colours to make them more personal. This results in a bicycle that is more distinctive and attracts attention, due to which it is easier to locate in bicycle stands with large numbers of bicycles. Finally, painting a bicycle reduces the risk of theft. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>, an example of a painted bicycle is shown. The students who personalised their bicycle differ in the amount of time they spent on painting their bicycle. As a result, investigating this particular product provided us with variation in the effort invested during the personalisation process.</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="74" page="4" column="1">2.3.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" page="4" column="1">2.3. Questionnaire</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" page="4" column="1">Respondents indicated their age and gender, and responded to questions concerning their bicycle regarding the manner of acquisition, the period of time the bicycle had been in possession, whether they had personally altered the bicycle’s appearance, and the degree of usage of their bicycle. Based on their response to the question whether they had altered their bicycle’s appearance, two groups of respondents were distinguished: one in which the appearance of the bicycle was personalised by the owner (n = 58) and one in which it was not personalised (n = 91). The multi-item scales to measure the variables emotional bonding (four items: α = 0.79) and self-expression (five items: α = 0.86) were taken from past research ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Mugge et al. 2006</xref>). Effort invested was measured using four items (α = 0.86) on a seven-point Likert scale (1 = ‘strongly disagree’, 7 = ‘strongly agree’). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> displays the items for these variables. We also included an eight-item scale to measure individual differences in the desire for unique consumer products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Lynn and Harris 1997</xref>). During<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> the analysis of our data, we deleted one item (‘I rarely pass up the opportunity to order custom features on the products I buy’), to enhance the internal validity of this scale. For the remaining seven items, Cronbach’s α was 0.83. Respondents filled out the questionnaire for a bicycle they already owned.As a result, the respondents who did and those who did not personalise their bicycle differed in number and possibly they differed on other variables as well. To control for other possible effects, data were collected on a number of control variables related to the person–product relationship. These variables were chosen based on prior research on treasured and special possessions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Wallendorf and Arnould 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Schultz et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Dittmar 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Richins 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="90" class="deo:Reference">Kamptner 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Schifferstein et al. 2004</xref>, Schifferstein and Zwartkruis-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Pelgrim 2008</xref>). Specifically, we assessed memories elicited by the bicycle concerning a person (three items: α = 0.87), memories elicited by the bicycle concerning an event (three items: α = 0.85), product utility (four items: α = 0.78), product appearance (four items: α = 0.84), satisfaction with the bicycle (four items: α = 0.86), and financial value (three items: α = 0.85). Most of the items employed to measure the control variables were obtained from past research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Mugge et al. 2006</xref>, 2008a). 1 The items were presented in random order.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_004.image_03.png" thmb="62pt.page_004.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="81" page="4" column="1">Figure 2. A personalised bicycle.</caption>
          </region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="82" page="5" column="1">Journal of Engineering Design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="83" page="5" column="1">471</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="84" page="5" column="1">Table 1. Measures for the variables effort invested, self-expression, and emotional bonding.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="unknown" id="85" page="5" column="1">Variables Items Effort invested (α = 0.90) The appearance of my bicycle took me a lot of trouble I have devoted much time to altering the appearance of my bicycle The appearance of my bicycle did not cost me any effort a I have spent a lot of energy on changing the appearance of my bicycle Self-expression (α = 0.86) My bicycle reflects who I am Other people can tell by my bicycle what kind of person I am My bicycle fits my identity My bicycle suits me My bicycle says nothing about me as an individual a Emotional bonding (α = 0.79) I have a bond with my bicycle My bicycle has no special meaning to me a My bicycle is very dear to me I am very attached to my bicycle a Indicates a reversed item.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="95" page="5" column="1">3. Results</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="5" column="1">To determine whether the process of product personalisation stimulates the formation of an emotional bond with a product, we compared the respondents who did personalise their bicycle with those who did not. The variables concerning the demographic variables (i.e., age and gender) and the ownership of the bicycle (i.e., how and when the bicycle was acquired) showed no significant differences between these groups (p &gt; 0.05). Furthermore, no significant differences were found for the control variables (p &gt; 0.05; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). Based on these results, we can conclude that no other important differences existed between the two groups of respondents other than the personalisation of the product’s appearance. The two groups did differ on the variable desire for unique consumer products (t (144) = 2.98, p &lt; 0.01). Respondents who had personalised their bicycle felt a stronger desire for unique consumer products (M pers = 4.58 vs. M no person = 4.02) than respondents who had not personalised it. These findings confirmed our belief that the respondents changed their bicycle’s appearance to make it distinctive from other bicycles, which enabled them to express their identity. As expected, significant differences were also found for the variables effort invested (t (145) = 10.88, p &lt; 0.001), self-expression (t (144) = 5.01, p &lt; 0.001), and emotional bonding (t (145) = 2.36, p &lt; 0.05). Respondents who had personalised their<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> bicycle indicated to have invested more effort in their product (M person = 3.70 vs. M no person = 1.60), considered the product more self-expressive (M person = 3.52 vs. M no person = 2.43), and experienced a stronger emotional bond with the product (M person = 4.13 vs. M no person = 3.53) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>). To test our hypotheses, we performed three regression analyses on the group of respondents who had personalised their bicycle (n = 58). In the first regression analysis, product attachment was used as a dependent variable and effort invested as the independent variable (F (1, 56) = 14.06, p &lt; 0.001, R 2 = 0.20). As expected, effort invested had a positive effect on product attachment (b = 0.49, p &lt; 0.001). In the second regression analysis, self- expression was used as a dependent variable and effort invested as the independent variable (F (1, 55) = 13.49, p &lt; 0.01, R 2 = 0.20). In accordance with our expectations, effort invested had a positive effect on self-expression (b = 0.45, p &lt; 0.01). Next, a third regression analysis was performed with emotional bonding as the dependent variable and both effort invested and self- expression as the independent variables (F (1, 55) = 15.52, p &lt; 0.001, R 2 = 0.37). This analysis showed that emotional bonding was positively affected by self-expression (b = 0.47, p &lt; 0.001) as well as by the effort invested in the product (b = 0.27, p &lt; 0.05). These findings support our hypotheses and conceptual model.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="98" page="6" column="1">472</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="99" page="6" column="1">R. Mugge et al.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="100" page="6" column="1">Table 2. Overall means of variables compared between the groups.</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="6">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"></th>
                  <th class="table"> Personalisation</th>
                  <th class="table"> No personalisation</th>
                  <th class="table"> df</th>
                  <th class="table"> t</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Effort invested</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.70 (1.36)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.60 (0.98)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 145</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10.88 ∗∗ ∗∗</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Self-expression</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.52 (1.41)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.43 (1.20)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 144</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.01</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Emotional bonding</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4.13 (1.49)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.53 (1.53)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 145</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.36 ∗</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Control variables</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Satisfaction</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.35 (1.16)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.31 (1.32)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 143</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Memories concerning a person</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.11 (1.40)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.04 (1.50)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 144</td>
                  <td class="table"> 0.27</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Memories concerning an event</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.64 (1.52)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.14 (1.48)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 144</td>
                  <td class="table"> −0.70 1.96</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Product utility</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.85 (1.15)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5.98 (1.02)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 145</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Product appearance</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.94 (1.52)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3.49 (1.58)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 144</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1.70</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Financial value</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.57 (1.34)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2.74 (1.59)</td>
                  <td class="table"> 145</td>
                  <td class="table"> −0.69</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Note: ∗ Standard deviations are in</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> parentheses.</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> ∗∗ p &lt; 0.05.</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> p &lt; 0.001.</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="101" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Personalisation No personalisation df t Effort invested 3.70 (1.36) 1.60 (0.98) 145 10.88 ∗∗ Self-expression 3.52 (1.41) 2.43 (1.20) 144 5.01 ∗∗ Emotional bonding 4.13 (1.49) 3.53 (1.53) 145 2.36 ∗ Control variables Satisfaction 5.35 (1.16) 5.31 (1.32) 143 0.20 Memories concerning a person 2.11 (1.40) 2.04 (1.50) 144 0.27 Memories concerning an event 2.64 (1.52) 2.14 (1.48) 144 1.96 Product utility 5.85 (1.15) 5.98 (1.02) 145 −0.70 Product appearance 3.94 (1.52) 3.49 (1.58) 144 1.70 Financial value 2.57 (1.34) 2.74 (1.59) 145 −0.69 Note: Standard deviations are in parentheses. ∗ p &lt; 0.05. ∗∗ p &lt; 0.001.</region>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="6" column="1">4. Discussion and implications</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127" page="6" column="1">This research showed that product personalisation can serve as a potential design strategy to stimulate emotional bonding with products. By personalising a product, a person invests effort in the product. Because people evaluate a product as more favourable when they have spent an extended period of time with it, effort invested directly affects the strength of the emotional bond with the product. Furthermore, our findings show that the effect of effort on emotional bonding can be partly explained by the product’s self-expressive value as follows: The more effort a person invests in a product during the personalisation process, the more self-expressive value this product obtains, and the stronger the emotional bond with this product becomes. This research focused on personalising products’ appearances. We argue that personalising a product’s appearance is especially valuable for increasing its self-expressive value. People derive their identity to a great extent from social interaction with others ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Kleine et al. 1993</xref>). As the personalisation of a product’s appearance is more visible to others than the personalisation of a product’s functionality, it will also be more beneficial in supporting a person’s identity and, therefore, in strengthening the emotional bond with this product.<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> We investigated product personalisation by the particular case of painting a bicycle’s appearance. Nevertheless, our research shows that it is the effort invested during the personalisation process that strengthens the person–product relationship. This suggests that many other personalisation options may be valuable as well. In order to stimulate emotional bonding with products, designers should assess the totality of mental and physical effort that is required in specific personalisation options. The more by consumers can act as co-designers of their product, the more effort they will invest in the product, and the stronger the emotional bond is likely to become. We believe that the investment of a person’s mental effort will often bring about stronger emotional bonds than the investment of physical effort, because being creatively involved in the personalisation process results in a unique product with a personal touch and self-expressive value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Fox 2001</xref>). In contrast, products that demand only physical effort, such as IKEA products, may result in products that lack a personal touch. Consequently, the emotional bonds experienced with these products will generally be weaker. A popular way for manufacturers to personalise durables is by offering mass customisation services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Pine 1993</xref>). A mass customisation service allows people to create a personalised product by selecting components, accessories, and colours from a predefined set of options. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Norman (2004)</xref> argued that these mass-customised products are better in satisfying consumers’ needs, but they do not directly guarantee emotional bonding. Based on our findings, we can provide arguments why product personalisation through mass customisation is less likely to result in strong emotional bonds. We believe that the degree of effort invested in most mass customisation services is relatively low. Mass-customised products require no physical effort to be invested. In addition, the degree of mental effort is relatively low, because people are generally only allowed to make choices among predetermined alternatives. For the formation of a strong emotional bond with a product, the consumer should personalise the object through an effortful process. An example of the latter is the NOKIA 3220 mobile phone (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>) that allows people to personally design their cut-out cover using their own creativity. Although more effortful product personalisation can result in stronger emotional bonds, this might have a downside as well. As the effort invested increases, so will the perceived complexity of the task and, consequently, the possibility that people become confused (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Huffman and Kahn 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Dellaert and Stremersch 2005</xref>). People may feel that they lack the know-how, experience, and practical skills to personalise a product in the way they want to. Furthermore, people may spoil the product, because they are not sufficiently skilled to design their own products. It is<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> the designer’s task to create a context in which a balance is found between creating design opportunities and guaranteeing adequate product quality. Product personalisation may only be a worthwhile strategy if designers are able to design the personalisation process in such a manner that people can handle the consequences. Accordingly, designers could create toolkits to support people in their choice, while they may still take credit for the ultimate product design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Crabbe 2001</xref>, von <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Hippel 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Schreier 2002</xref>). An example of a company that offers a toolkit with a satisfactory balance between the product’s self-expressive value and the complexity of the personalisation process is Freitag (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.freitag.ch" id="125">http://www.freitag.ch</ext-link>). Freitag sells bags made out of recycled truck tarpaulins. Consumers can create a bag by positioning stencils on the tarpaulins that are available at that moment (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>). During the ‘design process’, the person can see which pieces of the tarpaulins are still available and which are already used for other bags. Because each part of each tarpaulin can only be used for one bag, every bag is unique.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="7" column="1">Journal of Engineering Design</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="7" column="1">473</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_007.image_04.png" thmb="62pt.page_007.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="117" page="7" column="1">Figure 3. Nokia 3220 website.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="118" page="8" column="1">474</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="119" page="8" column="1">R. Mugge et al.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_008.image_05.png" thmb="62pt.page_008.image_05-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="121" page="8" column="1">Figure 4. Freitag website.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="128" page="8" column="1">4.1.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="129" page="8" column="1">4.1. Limitations and future research</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" page="8" column="1">People develop emotional bonds with products over a period of time. A limitation of our cross- sectional research is that it was not possible to test the causal order of the relationship between the effort invested during the personalisation process and the development of an emotional bond with the product. To establish the direction of causality in our conceptual framework ( <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>), we would need to perform a longitudinal study. Another limitation of our study is the self-selection of respondents to one of the two conditions. This self-selection is a direct consequence of our research approach to study the actual practice of product personalisation. Fortunately, the literature supports the hypothesised relationships between the concepts. Furthermore, none of the control variables differed significantly between the respondents who did and those who did not personalise their bicycle, suggesting that solely the personalisation process can explain the differences in the strength of the emotional bond. Nevertheless, we acknowledge that in some cases experiencing an emotional bond with a product may also positively affect the effort invested, because people may try to repair these products. However, because our research measured only the effort invested in changing the product’s appearance, this alternative explanation cannot explain our findings. Another possible limitation is that our sample was limited to Dutch students at a university of technology. Consequently, some respondents studied a more creative program (i.e., architecture and industrial design engineering) and may have been more likely to personalise products. Indeed, we found that students from creative programs had personalised their bicycle more often (χ 2 (1) = 13.62, p &lt; 0.001) than students from the other programmes. Nevertheless, when testing our<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> conceptual model, the pattern of results is the same for both groups, suggesting that the effect of product personalisation on emotional bonding is independent from the person’s creative skills. The use of personalised bicycles limited our research to a single product category. Nevertheless, product personalisation can be applied in many other contexts, as is evident from the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Blom and Monk 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Franke and Piller 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="136" class="deo:Reference">Weightman and McDonagh 2003</xref>) and practice. Nowadays it is, for example, possible to purchase personalised credit cards, bags, mouse pads, shoes, cars, and even personalised stair lifts. This suggests that product personalisation is valuable for diverse product categories and groups of consumers. However, the reasons to personalise a bicycle seem to correspond to the reasons distinguished in the literature, suggesting that the personalisation of bicycles is similar to other examples of product personalisation. Accordingly, we believe that our findings are generalisable to other contexts. Nevertheless, future research is necessary to empirically test this supposition. Future research could investigate how product personalisation could be implemented in products in order to obtain a satisfactory balance between the effort invested and the complexity of the personalisation process. It is likely that consumers’ skills, capabilities, and personality char- acteristics affect this balance, suggesting that these moderating conditions should be taken into consideration as well. It is also interesting to study the potential negative consequences of product personalisation. For example, what are the consequences of a product that is spoiled during the personalisation process for the consumer, the company, and the brand the product belongs to? Finally, we believe that more research is needed on the emotional bonding with products. The current research presents product personalisation as a potential design strategy to strengthen the emotional bond with a product, but many other opportunities may exist as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Mugge et al. 2008b</xref>). Future research could explore other design strategies and test their effects on the experience of an emotional bond with a product. In addition, it is valuable to clarify how these emotional bonds develop over the course of time. Only through a thorough understanding of these emotional relationships designers can create products that bring about favourable emotional responses during ownership.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="132" page="9" column="1">Journal of Engineering Design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="133" page="9" column="1">475</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="139" page="9" column="1">Note</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="140" page="9" column="1">1. The measures for the control variables can be requested from the first author.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="141" page="9" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" page="9" column="1">Ball, A.D. and Tasaki, L.H., 1992. The role and measurement of attachment in consumer behavior. Journal of Consumer Psychology, 1 (2), 155–172.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="9" column="1">Belk, R.W., 1988. Possessions and the extended self. Journal of Consumer Research, 15 (2), 139–168.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Bendapudi, N. and Leone, R.P., 2003. Psychological implications of customer participation in co-production. Journal of Marketing, 67 (1), 14–28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="9" column="1">Blom, J.O., 2000. Personalization – a taxonomy. In: Extended abstracts of the CHI 2000 conference on human factors in computing systems, 1–6 April, The Hague, The Netherlands. New York: ACM, 313–314.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="9" column="1">Blom, J.O. and Monk, A.F., 2003. Theory of personalization of appearance: why users personalize their PCs and mobile phones. Human–Computer Interaction, 18 (3), 193–228.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="9" column="1">Cardozo, R.N., 1965. An experimental study of customer effort, expectation, and satisfaction. Journal of Marketing Research, 2 (3), 244–249.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="9" column="1">Crabbe, A., 2001. Expert systems and the emergence of teledesign. Design Studies, 22 (6), 543–555.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="9" column="1">Csikszentmihalyi, M. and Rochberg-Halton, E., 1981. The meaning of things: domestic symbols and the self. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="9" column="1">Dahl, D.W. and Moreau, C.P., 2007. Thinking inside the box: why consumers enjoy constrained creative experiences. Journal of Marketing Research, 44 (3), 357–369.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" page="9" column="1">Dellaert, B.G.C. and Stremersch, S., 2005. Marketing mass-customized products: striking balance between utility and complexity. Journal of Marketing Research, 42 (2), 219–227.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="9" column="1">Desmet, P.M.A., 2002. Designing emotions. Delft, The Netherlands: Delft University of Technology.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="10" column="1">Diener, E. and Lucas, R.E., 2000. Subjective emotional well-being. In: M. Lewis and J.M. Haviland-Jones, eds. Handbook of emotions. 2nd ed. New York: The Guilford Press, 325–337.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="10" column="1">Dittmar, H., 1991. Meanings of material possessions as reflections of identity: gender and social-material position in society. Journal of Social Behavior and Personality, 6 (6), 165–186.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="10" column="1">Dyl, J. and Wapner, S., 1996. Age and gender differences in the nature, meaning, and function of cherished possessions for children and adolescents. Journal of Experimental Child Psychology, 62 (3), 340–377.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Fox, S., 2001. Managing product personalisation. Engineering Management Journal, 11 (4), 174–180.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="10" column="1">Franke, N. and Piller, F.T., 2003. Key research issues in user interaction with user toolkits in a mass customisation system. International Journal of Technology Management, 26 (5/6), 578–599.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="10" column="1">Franke, N. and Piller, F.T., 2004. Value creation by toolkits for user innovation and design: The case of the watch market. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 21 (6), 401–415.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="10" column="1">Franke, N. and Schreier, M., 2002. Entrepreneurial opportunities with toolkits for user innovation and design. The International Journal on Media Management, 4 (4), 225–234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="162" page="10" column="1">Heskett, J., 1980. Industrial design. London: Thames and Hudson.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="163" page="10" column="1">Hirschman, E.C. and Holbrook, M.B., 1982. Hedonic consumption: emerging concepts, methods and propositions. Journal of Marketing, 46 (3), 92–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="10" column="1">Huffman, C. and Kahn, B.E., 1998. Variety for sale: mass customization or mass confusion. Journal of Retailing, 74 (4), 491–513.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="165" page="10" column="1">Jencks, C. and Silver, N., 1972. Adhocism: the case for improvisation. London: Secker &amp; Warburg.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Jordan, P.W., 2000. Designing pleasurable products: an introduction to the new human factors. London: Taylor &amp; Francis.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Kamptner, N.L., 1995. Treasured possessions and their meanings in adolescent males and females. Adolescence, 30 (118), 301–318.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" page="10" column="1">Kiesler, T. and Kiesler, S., 2005. My pet rock and me: an experimental exploration of the self extension concept. In: G. Menon and A. Rao, eds. Advances in consumer research. Vol. 32. Provo, UT: Association for Consumer Research, 365–370.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="10" column="1">Kleine, R.E., Kleine, S.S., and Kernan, J.B., 1993. Mundane consumption and the self: a social-identity perspective. Journal of Consumer Psychology, 2 (3), 209–235.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="10" column="1">Kleine, S.S., Kleine, R.E., and Allen, C.T., 1995. How is a possession “me” or “not me”? Characterizing types and an antecedent of material possession attachment. Journal of Consumer Research, 22 (3), 327–343.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="10" column="1">Lynn, M. and Harris, J., 1997. The desire for unique consumer products: a new individual differences scale. Psychology &amp; Marketing, 14 (6), 601–616.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="10" column="1">Mugge, R., Schifferstein, H.N.J., and Schoormans, J.P.L., 2006. A longitudinal study on product attachment and its determinants. In: K.M. Ekström and H. Brembeck, eds. European Advances in Consumer Research. Vol. 7. Duluth, MN: Association for Consumer Research, 641–647.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="10" column="1">Mugge, R., Schifferstein, H.N.J., and Schoormans, J.P.L., 2008a. Product attachment and satisfaction: the effects of pleasure and memories. In: S. Borghini, M. McGrath, and C. Otnes, eds. European advances in consumer research. Vol. 8. Duluth, MN: Association for Consumer Research, 325–331.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="10" column="1">Mugge, R., Schoormans, J.P.L., and Schifferstein, H.N.J., 2008b. Product attachment: design strategies to stimulate the emotional bonding to products. In: P. Hekkert and H.N.J. Schifferstein, eds. Product experience. Amsterdam: Elsevier, 425–440.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Norman, D.A., 2004. Emotional design: why we love (or hate) everyday things. New York: Basic Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Pine, B.J., 1993. Mass customization: The new frontier of business competition. Boston, MA: Harvard Business School Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="10" column="1">Richins, M.L., 1994. Valuing things: the public and private meanings of possessions. Journal of Consumer Research, 21 (3), 504–521.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="10" column="1">Schifferstein, H.N.J. and Zwartkruis-Pelgrim, E.P.H., 2008. Consumer-product attachment: measurement and design implications. International Journal of Design, 2 (3), 1–14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="10" column="1">Schifferstein, H.N.J., Mugge, R., and Hekkert, P., 2004. Designing consumer–product attachment. In: D. McDonagh, P. Hekkert, J. Van Erp, and D. Gyi, eds. Design and emotion: the experience of everyday things. London: Taylor &amp; Francis, 327–331.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="10" column="1">Schreier, M., 2006. The value increment of mass-customized products: an empirical assessment and conceptual analysis of its explanation. Journal of Consumer Behaviour, 5 (4), 317–327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="10" column="1">Schultz, S.E., Kleine, R.E., and Kernan, J.B., 1989. ‘These are a few of my favorite things’. Toward an explication of attachment as a consumer behavior construct. In: T. Scrull, ed. Advances in consumer research. Vol. 16. Provo, UT: Association for Consumer Research, 359–366.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="10" column="1">Toffler, A., 1980. The third wave. New York: Bantam Books.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="10" column="1">von Hippel, E., 2001. Perspective: user toolkits for innovation. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 18 (4), 247–257.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="10" column="1">Wallendorf, M. and Arnould, E.J., 1988. “My favorite things”: a cross-cultural inquiry into object attachment, possessiveness, and social linkage. Journal of Consumer Research, 14 (4), 531–547.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="10" column="1">Weightman, D. and McDonagh, D., 2003. People are doing it for themselves. In: B. Hanington and J. Forlizzi, eds. Proceedings of the international conference on designing pleasurable products and interfaces (DPPI’03), 23–26 June, Pittsburgh, PA. New York: ACM, 34–39.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="153" page="10" column="1">476</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="154" page="10" column="1">R. Mugge et al.</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx186">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pt.page_011.image_06.png" thmb="62pt.page_011.image_06-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
