<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>0d2f61aa33f406dbc8d1e7efa0dbc6301efa3bbfd18e313bd76777cef36ac9a8</job>
    <base_name>62np</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-374111-0.00012-8</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Wizard of Oz Studies with Children</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Johanna Höysniemi</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Tampere Unit for Computer-Human Interaction, Department of Computer Sciences FIN-33014 University of Tampere, Finland <email id="3">johanna@cs.uta.fi</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="5">This paper provides an overview of the literature pertaining to Wizard of Ox studies with children participants. It presents a new taxonomy for Wizard of Oz evaluations and, whilst focusing on three case studies that have been carried out by the authors, provides a presents a discussion of several ethical and organizational concerns with Wizard of Oz as a method for use with child participants. The paper concludes with some practical tips for researchers and practitioners engaged in Wizard of Oz studies with children.</abstract>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="6" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Keywords</h2>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="7" confidence="possible">Wizard of Oz, children, case studies, design, evaluation, methodology</region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="14">Janet Read</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" page="1" column="1">1. INTRODUCTION</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" page="1" column="1">The use of Wizard of Oz (WoZ) method in Human Computer Interaction has become more widespread as the user groups have diversified and as the technologies under investigation have changed. It is common, nowadays, to find multiple users of varying ages using ubiquitous and tangible technology and carrying out complex interactions. These new technologies and interactions are ideally suited to Wizard of Oz methods both for investigation and for evaluation. In a traditional Wizard of Oz experiment (shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="9" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>), there is a human wizard who manipulates the interface independently of the subject of the experiment. The method was first used by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="10" class="deo:Reference">5</xref>], although it was only named Wizard of Oz when it was described by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="11" class="deo:Reference">11</xref>]. The technique is often used in recognition systems where a wizard makes commands happen, behaving as if he was the recognition software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="12" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>]. The set up for this sort of work relies on the ability to hide the wizard, either by placing him in another location, or by making his manipulation of the interface appear invisible. There are instances where WoZ studies have been effectively carried out with children; both for design and evaluation purposes. This paper begins with an examination of how Wizard of Oz studies are designed and uses a novel taxonomy to describe some of the parameters and pitfalls. It then provides a summary of the literature in this area and examines some of the studies that have been carried out with children. Three case studies that have been carried out by the authors are then described and the paper concludes with some reflections of the efficacy of Wizard of Oz methods and contemplates some future directions for research in this area.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="16" page="1" column="2">Child Computer Interaction Group Department of Computing University of Central Lancashire, Preston, UK <email id="15">jcread@uclan.ac.uk</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62np.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62np.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="18" page="1" column="2">Figure 1. Wizard of Oz setup</caption>
      </region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="19" page="1" column="2">2. A TAXONOMY FOR WOZ STUDIES</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" page="1" column="2">In an exhaustive study of the literature on Wizard of Oz studies it became clear to the authors that there were many points of variability in Wizard of Oz set-ups. These points are summarized here; • Functionality of the technology: some studies use fully functional prototypes, others use low-tech or even non-tech prototypes. • Discretion of the Wizard: in some studies, the wizard is allowed to do whatever he pleases, in many studies the wizard is constrained to a set of options and occasionally, the wizard is in fact a pre-programmed response (termed a robot-of-oz study) • Wizard control: the wizard may be the sole provider of functionality in the system or he may be only wizarding some of the interactions with the interface providing some automatic control. Clearly, if the interface does all the controlling, this would not be a wizard of oz method. • Visibility of the wizard: The wizard may be seen or unseen’he may be seen but not known to be wizarding, or, his role may have been clearly explained to the participants. • User knowledge: related to the visibility of the wizard is the amount that the user knows about the set up. Levels of deception vary across wizard of oz experiments from the user believing that all is done by a functional interface to the user knowing that the wizard is doing all the manipulation. It is common to give the user knowledge that lies between these two extremes. • Experimental design: as with all experimental studies, wizard of oz studies vary from tightly controlled experiments to free exploration. <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> • Number of wizards: in many studies there are multiple wizards carrying out a single study, in others, wizards are exchanged during the study, causing an effect, more commonly there is one wizard carrying out all the action. • User understanding: in some studies, the user is one of the experimental team and therefore has a high level of understanding of the process, the risks, and the deception. In other studies, especially those with children, the user has little knowledge and is at more risk of harm.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="22" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">• Wizard knowledge: in a similar way, the wizard brings knowledge of the domain to the experiment. Some wizards are the system developers or designers; others are brought in for the experiment on an ad hoc method.</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="23" page="2" column="1">3. KEY STUDIES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="2" column="1">The first Wizard of Oz studies date back to 1980’ s [5][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="24" class="deo:Reference">12</xref>]. Until recently, the Wizard of Oz method has been mainly used to design and collect language corpora in speech-based systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="25" class="deo:Reference">4</xref>] and multimodal user interfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="26" class="deo:Reference">3</xref>]. During the last few years we have seen tremendous growth in using WoZ in various fields of HCI including perceptual user interfaces, ubiquitous computing, virtual reality, help systems, games, sensing technologies to name a few. In addition, advanced WoZ systems are being implemented and new user groups, especially children have taken part in WoZ experiments. Since 2000, there have been an increasing number of reported studies on using the method with children. These studies have concentrated applying the method in various contexts; in eliciting user requirements and evaluating design concepts for children’ s user interfaces [1][2][7][14][6][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="27" class="deo:Reference">17</xref>], modeling children’ s performance and behavior during system use [18][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="28" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>], collecting language and video corpora for further design and evaluation purposes [10][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="29" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>], and testing the applicability of the method in novel design contexts [16][9][<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="30" class="deo:Reference">18</xref>]. As the Wizard of Oz method is applied increasingly with children, guidelines and ethical discussion is needed to safeguard the participants from the harmful effects of the method and to design the experimental setups properly. Three case studies are described here that highlight some of the organizational and ethical issues with WoZ studies and which also show the diverse nature of WoZ studies.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="32" page="2" column="1">3.1 Collecting game player’ s physical gestures</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="2" column="1">This study, reported in [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="33" class="deo:Reference">9</xref>] describes the use of WoZ method in the design of computer vision based action games controlled with body movements. A WoZ study was carried out with 34 children of ages 7 to 9 in order to find out the most intuitive movements for game controls. Another research question was whether the WoZ method could be used to prototype perceptive action games that are based on continuous and fast-based interaction. The results showed that distinctive gesture patterns could be found by observing the children playing the games controlled by the human wizard. Further details about children’ s gestures can be found in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="34" class="deo:Reference">8</xref>]. The WoZ approach minimized the need for functional prototypes in the early stages of the design, enabled the evaluation of the game concepts with children in real-like use situation, and provided video material for both developing<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> computer vision algorithms and game character animations that try to mimic user’ s movements. The study extended the previous Wizard of Oz studies by showing that prototyping of perceptive action games was feasible with the WoZ method despite the delay caused by the wizard. In addition, as the setup was based on using two wizards, it was possible to investigate the effect of this set up. It was noticed that the wizard’ s previous gaming experience and motor abilities affected the setup. Although both wizards carried out the same practice activity, there was a significant difference between the wizards’ performance in terms of reaction times and number of errors made. In addition, the study revealed that careful attention needed to be put into selecting input devices for the wizard. In this instance, the keyboard and mouse were not the best possible choices; game pads would have provided a more natural and effective input for the wizard.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="37" page="2" column="2">3.2 Measuring Error tolerance in a pen-based writing interface</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" page="2" column="2">This study, reported in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="38" class="deo:Reference">15</xref>] used a Robot of Oz method to determine an error tolerance level for children using handwriting recognition software. The experiment was modeled on a study by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="39" class="deo:Reference">13</xref>] that had used a Wizard of Oz method to establish an error rate for adult users. The option of a human wizard was considered, but the difficulty with this was that for the experiment to work, children had to be presented with ‘ pre-set’ error rates ranging from 20% to 2%. A human wizard could not produce these to order. To overcome this difficulty, an experimental interface was built that required the children to write a piece of text using a pen and graphics tablet and when they had completed the text, it prompted them to press the recognize button whereupon a piece of pre-prepared (and unrelated) text was displayed to them with a pre-set error rate. The children then commented on whether or not this instance of work was good enough for the wall. In a follow up exercise four days later children wrote a different piece of text and were presented with a different error rate. The study showed that very few children discriminated between well-recognized and poorly recognized text, but from those that did, it was postulated than an error rate of around 9% was tolerable. The key issues in this study were in relation to the risk of discovery of deception. None of the children noticed that the errors in the presented text might have been unexpected in the text that they wrote as their knowledge of the technology was limited. The wizard (robot) had used knowledge of the domain to provide ‘ expected’errors. In other words, the success of this study relied upon the naivety of the users and the knowledge of the wizard.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="41" page="2" column="2">3.3 Investigating WoZ</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="2" column="2">Having used Wizard of Oz studies in different situations, the authors carried out an investigation to determine whether or not the wizard being hidden or seen was an issue for children. This study is reported in [ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="42" class="deo:Reference">16</xref>] and it was deliberately designed to test the Wizard of Oz method, rather than to carry out a design or investigative process. Young teenage children attended two Wizard of Oz events; one using speech recognition, and one with a navigation exercise, and each child experienced a hidden wizard and a seen wizard set up. The design was counter balanced to<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> ensure empirical validity. At the end of the two instances of use, the children were sat down with the researchers and were told about the deceptions that had taken place. At this point they were asked whether or not they had realized there was a wizard in the two instances. The majority of children were unaware of the wizard activity with the only discovery taking place in the wizard seen instance with the speech recognition. This resulted from the keyboard sounds that the children heard when they were doing the speech activity. Some children heard the typing but were unaware that it related to the speech recognition activity! At the end of this study, the children were told that, as they had been deceived, they could withdraw their consent and have their data removed. No child took this option that could indicate that deception was less important than we had thought. Form this study, it appears that in many instances, especially where there is not a great deal of keyboard input, the wizard can safely be placed in the same room as the activity without a high risk of discovery.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="3" column="1">4. WOZZING INVESTIGATED</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="46" page="3" column="1">In the three cases investigated, and in many other studies, authors have tended to conclude their papers with some comments on the operation of WoZ studies. The novel term Wozzing is introduced here by the authors to describe the process of carrying out a wizard of oz study. Wozzing is a broad term that includes the design of the experiment, the design of the interfaces, the selection and training of wizards and participants and the collection, analysis, and interpretation of the data. This section of the paper summarizes the research on Wozzing by looking at the perceived benefits and drawbacks of Wizard of Oz studies.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="47" page="3" column="1">4.1 Benefits from WoZ studies</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="3" column="1">The main benefit of using the Wizard of Oz method is the possibility to evaluate novel user interface concepts before the technology is mature enough. In addition, it has been used to study human behavior and human-computer interaction patterns in various setups even in fictional ones. The method also facilitates gathering large amount of qualitative and quantitative data on user’ s preferences and use patterns. Studies also claim that non-experts can take part in the design process more easily as the design is not solely based on technological design and implementation, and thus, enables more multi-disciplinary design teams. Depending on the WoZ setup, using the wizard provides flexibility in terms of system output, and enables creative responses that are somewhat easy to modify on the fly. Although the method has been mainly applied in academic circles, it could be applied in industry as well. Using the method during early design stages can create significant savings in terms of resources and time since iteration cycles can be shorter and alternative solutions can be tested simultaneously. The “ controlled improvisation” can also bring up design solutions and requirements that are tested with real users even before any technology is being built.</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="49" page="3" column="1">4.2</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="50" confidence="possible" page="3" column="1">Problems with the method</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="3" column="1">The problems of the method can be summarized as: (1) technology problems including creating too optimistic views on technology development, i.e. designing systems that cannot be <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> actually built using real technology, (2) method problems especially the deceptive nature of the method which in worst case may lead to unethical research where a participant might loose respect on research and never participate again in any study, and (3) wizard problems, particularly how the capability of the wizard affects the setup. These drawbacks are briefly expanded on in the next three sections.</region>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="53" page="3" column="2">4.2.1 Children as users of technology</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="3" column="2">Wizard of Oz experiments often use fragile technology and there are several pitfalls that directly result from the user of this technology being a child. These include: • Developmental stage affects, for instance an inability to read and differing ability to understand the setup or deception, role play factor • Imaginative uses of technology –the WoZ system may not have the responses ready or wizard has to improvise • Diversity in the user population - More random/erratic input: several use patters/user, children might be slower or faster than the wizard/adult</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="55" page="3" column="2">4.2.2 Ethical concerns with the method</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" page="3" column="2">Children are a vulnerable user group and need to be protected from harm during experimental work. Their ability to consent, and in particular to give informed consent, is questionable and therefore the experimenter or researcher needs to take special care to ensure that the children know what they have participated in, at least after the event has finished.</region>
          </section>
          <section class="DoCO:Section">
            <h3 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="57" page="3" column="2">4.2.3 The wizard is a human</h3>
            <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="58" page="3" column="2">Most of the practical problems and concerns of the validity of the research in WoZ setups are related to the fact that wizard is a human. The wizarding process puts the wizard under high cognitive and physical load as he has to observe user’ s input, make decisions on what response is appropriate for the given input, and deliver system output using the available user interface. In addition to coping fluently with all “ normal” user input, the wizard has to be able to manage conflicting rules, interpret boundary values, deal with state transitions, and adapt to user’ s errors and their sometimes extraordinary behavior. Using a Wizard increases latency, provide inconsistent responses, and causes errors which the wizard has to recover from. There are several factors that influence the wizard’ s reaction time and decision-making. One of the key issues is the usability and natural controls of the WoZ system. The number of input-output alternatives and their intuitive compatibility is crucial when the wizard has to act fast, especially in systems where a continuous interaction, for example in computer games, is required. The wizard’ s motor abilities including reaction time, response orientation, speed of movement, and manual dexterity all affect the performance of the setup. This is why the wizard needs to practice and master the interaction before any participant is brought in. The practicing aims at faster reaction times, correct anticipation on user’ s actions and recovering from errors without a long delay. The heavy cognitive and physical load causes stress that leads to perceptual narrowing and reduces the attention span of the wizard. This is why the test session lengths and breaks should be carefully designed into a WoZ study.</region>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="59" page="4" column="1">5. DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="4" column="1">From this review of the literature, and from our own studies, we propose the following guidelines for safe and sound Wozzing with children. • Deception should be minimized or reduced altogether users should be told afterwards what happened and their consent should then be asked for again • If possible use open setups where wizard’ s role and actions are explained to the user before testing • Where possible, record the wizard so that the wizard errors can be separated from the user’ s errors • Multiple wizards should be used to minimize individual wizard’ s effect on test data There is clearly a lot of work still to be done to determine how effective WOZ studies are with different users and different situations. Further work is expected to investigate wizard effects and to determine the effects of using open setups in different use scenarios.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="61" page="4" column="1">6. ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62" page="4" column="1">Many children have participated in these studies, their assistance, and that of their parents and teachers, is acknowledged here</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="63" page="4" column="1">7. REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="64" page="4" column="1">[1] Andersson, G., Höök, K., Mourão, D., Paiva, A., and Costa, M. (2002). Using a Wizard of Oz study to inform the design of SenToy. In Proceedings of Designing Interactive Systems, DIS’ 02, London, ACM, June 2002.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="65" page="4" column="1">[2] Buisine, S., and Martin, J.C. (2005) Children's and Adults' Multimodal Interaction with 2D Conversational Agents. In Proceedings of CHI'2005, 2-7 April 2005, Portland, USA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="66" page="4" column="1">[3] Coutaz, J., Salber, D., and Balbo, S. (1993). Towards the automatic evaluation of multimodal user interfaces. Special issue “ Intelligent User Interfaces” , Knowledge-Based Systems.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="67" page="4" column="1">[4] Dahlbäck, N., Jönsson, A., and Ahrenberg, L. (1993) Wizard of Oz Studies -- Why and How. In Proceedings of the International Workshop on Intelligent User Interfaces, Orlando, Florida, 193-200.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="68" page="4" column="1">[5] Gould, J.D., Conti, J., Hovanyecz, T. (1983). Composing Letters with a Simulated Listening Typewriter. Communications of the ACM, April 1983, 26 (4).</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="69" page="4" column="1">[6] Hammerton, L., &amp; Luckin, R. (2001) How to help? Investigating children's opinions on help: To inform the design of Metacognitive Software Scaffolding. In R. Luckin (Ed.), AIED2001 Workshop Proceedings: Help provision and help seeking in Interactive Learning Environments. San Antonio: St Mary's University, 2001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="70" page="4" column="1">[7] Henderson, V., Lee, S., Brashear, H., Hamilton, H., Starner, T., and Hamilton, S. (2005). Development of an American Sign Language Game for Deaf Children. In Proceedings of International conference on Interaction Design and Children (IDC2004), Boulder, CO, June 2005.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="71" page="4" column="2">[8] Höysniemi, J., Hämäläinen, P., Turkki, L. &amp; Rouvi, T. (2004). Children's Intuitive Gestures in Vision Based Action Games. Communications of the ACM, January 2005, 44-50.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="72" page="4" column="2">[9] Höysniemi, J., Hämäläinen, P. &amp; Turkki, L. (2004). Wizard of Oz Prototyping of Computer Vision Based Action Games for Children. Proceedings of International conference on Interaction Design and Children (IDC2004), 1-3 July 2004, Maryland, USA, 27-34.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="73" page="4" column="2">[10] Ibrahim, Z., Dimitrova, V., and Boyle, R D. (2004). Capturing human teachers strategies for supporting schema- based cognitive tasks to inform the design of an intelligent pedagogical agent. Workshop on Modelling Human Teaching Tactics and Strategies in 7th International Conference on Intelligent Tutoring Systems ITS04, 5-14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="75" page="4" column="2">[11] Kelley, J.F., Where did the usability term Wizard of Oz come from? <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.musicman.net/oz.html." id="74">http://www.musicman.net/oz.html.</ext-link></ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="76" page="4" column="2">[12] Kelley, J.F. (1984). An iterative design methodology for user friendly natural language office information applications, ACM Transactions on Office Information Systems, 2(1), March 1984, 26-41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="77" page="4" column="2">[13] LaLomia, M.J. (1994) User acceptance of handwritten recognition accuracy: in companion proceedings of. In proceedings of CHI '94. : ACM Press, New York. P 107</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="78" page="4" column="2">[14] Montemayor, J., Druin, A., Farber, A., Sims, S., Churaman, W., and D'Amour, A. (2002). Physical programming: Designing tools for children to create physical interactive environments. In Proceedings of CHI2002, ACM Press, 299- 306.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="79" page="4" column="2">[15] Read, J.C., S.J. MacFarlane, and C. Casey. (2003) 'Good enough for what? Acceptance of Handwriting Recognition Errors by Child Users. In proceedings of IDC 2003. . Preston, UK: ACM Press, 155.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="80" page="4" column="2">[16] Read, J.C., E. Mazzone, and J. Höysniemi. (2005) Wizard of Oz Evaluations with Children - Deception and Discovery. In proceedings of IDC2005. Boulder, Colorado: ACM Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="81" page="4" column="2">[17] Robertson, J. and Wiemer-Hastings, P. (2002). Feedback on children's stories via multiple interface agents. In Proceedings of the 6th Annual Conference on Intelligent Tutoring Systems, Springer, 923– 932.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="82" page="4" column="2">[18] Robins. B., Dautenhahn. K. and Dubowski. J. (2004) Investigating Autistic Children’ s Attitudes Towards Strangers with the Theatrical Robot –A New Experimental Paradigm in Human-Robot Interaction Studies. In Proceedings of the 13th IEEE International Workshop on Robot and Human Interactive Communication, Japan.</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
