<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>7ee1f820e6c9c84f2c051a1ac7fb1875d35177b4bc2afd751cdba73f6b909803</job>
    <base_name>62gu</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.4135/9781412956246.n362">http://dx.doi.org/10.1108/09534810510607074</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">Boundary objects and organizational knowledge: A discursive perspective</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Cliff Oswick</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="4" confidence="possible">The Management Centre University of Leicester, United Kingdom <email id="3">c.oswick@le.ac.uk</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="10">It is posited that boundary objects, as inscribed artefacts, can be thought of as forms of text. In this paper a discourse-analytic framework is employed to explore the processes of sharing knowledge across boundaries. Three discursive approaches are used to re-analyze existing contributions to the boundary objects literature. First, ‘intertextual analysis’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="5" class="deo:Reference">Allen, 2000</xref>) is applied to Brown’s (2004) work on public inquiry reports. Second, ‘recontextualization’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="6" class="deo:Reference">Bernstein, 1996</xref>) is used to reconsider Sapsed and Salter’s (2004) work on project management tools. Finally, Gantt charts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="7" class="deo:Reference">Yakura, 2002</xref>) are re-examined using Iedema’s (1999) concept of ‘formalization’. The power implications of a discursively nuanced account of boundary objects are discussed and the benefits resulting for a ‘boundary objects as text’ perspective are also presented.<marker type="block"/> Keywords: boundary objects, knowledge, discourse, texts.<marker type="block"/> Suggested track: C. Knowledge sharing within and across organizations and cultures.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" page="1" column="1">Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" page="1" column="1">According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer (1989)</xref>, “boundary objects act as anchors or bridges” (p. 414). Beyond this, we might also think of them as being ‘texts’ insofar as they are inscribed artefacts that in some shape or form capture, codify and/or represent some other, often tangible, object(s) to facilitate interaction across different social worlds. For example, the classification records used in Berkeley’s Museum of Vertebrate Zoology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="13" class="deo:Reference">Star &amp; Greisemer, 1989</xref>) are boundary objects that operate as textual representations that enable objects (i.e. animals) to be categorized and consumed by diverse groups of actors. An overtly textual, document-based orientation to boundary objects is also apparent in other studies, i.e. instances where they are constituted as: medical records<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/>  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Berg &amp; Bowker, 1997</xref>), engineering drawings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Henderson, 1991</xref>), activity based costing systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="18" class="deo:Reference">Briers &amp; Chua, 2001</xref>), and Gantt charts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="19" class="deo:Reference">Yakura, 2002</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Treating boundary objects as texts promotes the consideration of context and the processes of text production and text consumption. In particular, a discursive approach of this kind encourages us to explore the way in which any given boundary object (i.e. a text) is located and implicated in a wider spatial, temporal and relational context or ‘textscape’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Keenoy &amp; Oswick, 2004</xref>).<marker type="block"/> In this paper insights derived from the field of ‘organizational discourse analysis’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Grant, et al, 2004</xref>) are used as a means of offering an alternative framing of the concept of ‘boundary objects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Star, 1989</xref>, 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Star &amp; Griesemer, 1989</xref>) and their role in knowledge formation and sharing. More specifically, this contribution seeks to locate three emerging strands of research on boundary objects within a discourse analytic framework. The three strands being: the ‘pragmatic view’ of knowledge boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2002</xref>); the notion of ‘boundary infrastructures’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Bowker &amp; Star, 1999</xref>); and, the identification of ‘temporal boundary objects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Yakura, 2002</xref>).<marker type="block"/> There are four main parts to this paper. First, drawing on the concept of ‘intertextuality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Kristeva, 1980</xref>), the connectedness of a given boundary object, as a form of text, to other previous texts is explored. Second, consideration is given to the way in which knowledge sharing across boundaries involves a discursive process of ‘recontextualization’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Bernstein, 1996</xref>). Third, the projective imperatives involved in the formation of boundary objects are examined using the notion of ‘discursive formalization’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Iedema, 1999</xref>). Finally, the paper concludes with a discussion of the wider implications of adopting a discourse-analytic approach to the study of boundary objects and their role in knowledge formation and knowledge sharing.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="15" page="1" column="1">1</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="34" page="2" column="1">Boundary Objects as Intertextual Phenomena</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="2" column="1">Intertextuality provides a way of thinking about a text as incorporating elements of previous texts and as forming part of a weave of implicated texts. Building upon Bakhtin’s work on ‘dialogism’ (1981), Julia Kristeva formulated the concept of intertextuality in the late sixties. For her, a piece of text is a permutation of texts insofar as elements of other texts are contained within it ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Kristeva, 1980</xref>). Indeed, this is consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Barthes (1977)</xref> observations on the origin of the word ‘text’ as “a woven fabric” (cited in Allen, 2000:6).<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> Although a popular means of analyzing and critiquing texts, intextuality remains a rather loosely defined phenomenon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Allen, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Worton &amp; Still, 1990</xref>). Nevertheless, as Allen points out: “Intertextuality seems such a useful term because it foregrounds notions of relationality, interconnectedness and interdependence in modern cultural life” (2000:5). Arguably, exploring the relationship between texts is equally valuable within the context of knowledge sharing. It provides a means of apprehending the embedded, interwoven and multivocal nature of boundary objects and enables us to develop more complex and context-sensitive understandings of the processes of social construction and negotiation which lead to their formation.<marker type="block"/> Viewed from an intertextual perspective, boundary objects can be considered in terms of their historicity and their interconnectedness to other boundary objects. Moreover, intertextual analysis represents a potentially valuable means of developing Bowker and Star’s (1999) work on how multiple boundary objects coalesce to form ‘boundary infrastructures’ (i.e. interwoven networks of boundary objects).<marker type="block"/> An example of how intertextual analysis can be applied to boundary objects is to be found via a re-examination of the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Brown (2004)</xref>. He presents a discursive analysis of the public inquiry report into the Piper Alpha disaster (i.e. an industrial incident that destroyed an offshore oil platform). Although Brown’s work does not explicitly treat inquiry reports as boundary objects, they can nevertheless be thought of as such insofar as they facilitate interaction across different social worlds. This facilitation is apparent in the way in which these reports link together, and are consumed by, a range of different communities of stakeholders, including politicians, members of the general public, lawyers, academics, corporations, regulatory bodies, and particular professional groups with a specific vested interest in the subject matter of a given report (e.g. social workers, scientists, police, engineers).<marker type="block"/> An intertextual reconsideration of Brown’s research reveals the interconnectedness of the report into the Piper Alpha disaster (a.k.a. The Cullen Report) and other public inquiry reports. Brown demonstrates how the Cullen Report uses “highly convention- governed sensemaking narratives that employ various forms of verisimilitude in order to bolster their authority” (2004:95). Brown, albeit in an indirect and unacknowledged way, engages with a particular variant of intertextual analysis referred to as ‘architextuality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Genette, 1997</xref>). Adopting an architextual approach facilitates an<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> analysis of how the Cullen Report reproduces and adheres to the implicit conventions, modes of enunciation and discursive genres present in previous public inquiry reports. The dominant architextual structure of these reports being that: they make provenance claims (e.g. concerning who commissioned the report, the authoritative status and qualifications of those preparing it, and so on); they make claims regarding comprehensiveness (e.g. in the case of the Cullen Report evidence was taken from 217 witnesses); and, interpretations are presented as ‘facts’ which accumulate to reveal the ‘truth’ of what actually happened.<marker type="block"/> By looking at the genesis of the Cullen Report we are able to see how it functions as a boundary object and to get a sense of how it, as an implicated part of a wider body of inquiry reports, helps to create and sustain a particular ‘boundary infrastructure’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Bowker &amp; Star, 1999</xref>). In the example of the public inquiry report, the boundary infrastructure is maintained through an interwoven network of boundary objects (e.g. public inquiries, official reports of regulative bodies and adjudication documents) that “depoliticizes disaster events, legitimates social institutions, and lessens anxieties by concocting myths that emphasize our omnipotence and capacity to control” (Brown, 2004:95).</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="38" page="2" column="1">2</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="47" page="3" column="1">3</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="51" page="4" column="1">Boundary Objects and the Recontextualization of Knowledge</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="4" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Bernstein (1990; 1996)</xref> has demonstrated how a specific discourse that circulates in one particular community is ‘recontextualized’ when translated to another. His original work focused upon the recontextualisation of practical discourses into educational settings to produce pedagogic discourses that offered leverage for educationaIists. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Thomas (2003)</xref> has looked at the way in which knowledge generated in an academic context is transferred and translated to a management practitioner context. In effect, the process of recontextualization involves a sophisticated discursive shift in which the same discourse comes to mean different things in different contexts.<marker type="block"/> Because recontextualisation is concerned with the analysis of discourse across different contexts, it has obvious resonances with the study of boundaries and the processes of exchange between different ‘communities of practice’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Lave, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Lave &amp; Wenger, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Duguid, 1991</xref>). When superimposed on boundary objects, ‘recontextualization’ helps to provide an understanding of the communicative practices that generate knowledge boundaries and the necessary translations across social worlds. Moreover, this discursive approach resonates with Carlile’s (2002) ‘pragmatic<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> view of knowledge’ and offers scope for further interrogation of the assertion that: “What we see at a pragmatic knowledge boundary is not just a matter of processing more knowledge, but processes for transforming knowledge” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2002</xref>:453). Previous work has examined the recontextualising role of discourse across professional and organizational boundaries (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Linell, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Sarangi, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Scheuer, 2001</xref>), but the implications for the study of boundary objects have been somewhat overlooked.<marker type="block"/> On the surface, Genette’s (1997) conception of ‘architextuality’ appears to be remarkably similar to Bernstein’s (1990) description of the process of ‘recontextualisation’. However, the subtle difference between these two perspectives is that Genette emphasizes how a text results from a blending of an amalgam of discursive modes, styles and genres while Bernstein concentrates on how a discourse in a particular domain, locale or genre is reconfigured, appropriated and used within a different context. In terms of boundary objects, intertextuality privileges the processes of production (e.g. how a particular boundary object comes to be formed and developed) while recontexualisation emphasises the processes of consumption (e.g. who uses the boundary object and in what ways).<marker type="block"/> Although recontextualization involves the processes of ‘transferring’ and ‘translating’ knowledge, it actually has more to with ‘transforming knowledge’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2004</xref>) insofar as the shift of context and meaning gives rise to ‘creative abrasion’ (Leonard-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Barton, 1992</xref>) and the need to ‘negotiate practice’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Brown &amp; Duguid, 2001</xref>). In short, a change of context typically stimulates a discernible change in the knowledge itself, rather than simply sharing knowledge or making it more explicit.<marker type="block"/> If we take Sapsed and Salter’s (2004) study of the problematic use of project management tools as boundary objects within a global program of a major computing corporation, it is possible, albeit tentatively, to consider how their conclusions might be alternatively framed in terms of the impact of recontextualisation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Sapsed and Salter (2004)</xref> suggest that the geographically dispersed nature of the teams involved in the program was central to the failure of the project management tools. Hence, they claim:</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="59" page="4" column="1">4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">“The paper argues that in dispersed programs where there is no opportunity for face-to-face interaction, and/or ambiguous lines of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="73" page="5" column="1">5</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">authority, project management tools will be ineffectual as boundary objects and prone to avoidance” (Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004:1515).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" page="6" column="1">While this assertion may well be true, it is perhaps only part of the explanation. Elsewhere, they mention that “the services organization was predominantly at the Colorado site, while the operations core was in California, with other peripheral sites leaning to one more than the other” (Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004:1526). Arguably, the problem is possibly as much to do with the recontextualization of a ‘services discourse’ into an ‘operations context’, and vice versa, as it is to do with geography. This inference seems to receive indirect support in Sapsed and Salter’s observation that: “For some program managers the organization interests were a more significant factor than geography” (2004:1526). The ‘recontextualization viewpoint’ is further reinforced by a specific respondent:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">“...to this point we haven’t had a lot of geocentric differences, it’s been mostly between the different organizations. The service side doesn’t care nearly so much what the supplier processes are, for example, but they should care because if you need spare parts to go and fix something the suppliers are typically the ones who are supplying the depots so you want to make sure they’ve got their processes in place so that you can get pretty quick access to your spare crews or whatever” (Program Manager, cited in Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004:1526).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="6" column="1">This extract indicates that dispersal (i.e. “geocentric differences”) is less of a problem than the problems arising between organizations. Therefore, the ‘project management’ boundary object difficulties between, for example, the ‘services organization’ in Colorado and the ‘operations core’ in California might be said to be primarily attributable to the transformation of knowledge across different communities of practice, i.e. recontextualisation, rather than the transference of knowledge between dispersed locales.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="6" column="1">Boundary Objects and Discursive Formalization</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="6" column="1">To a certain extent, the real-time use of boundary objects has a kind of spontaneity and unpredictability that transcends the predetermined positions, orientations and agendas of specific social actors and the conventions of the text itself. In this regard, the utility <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> and meaning of a particular boundary object is often captured in the moment. This involves a real-time accomplishment of collective sensemaking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="81" class="deo:Reference">Weick, 1995</xref>) and the processes of social negotiation associated with ‘dialogical scripting’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Oswick et al, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Pearce and Cronen (1979)</xref> tackle the question of real-time texts (e.g. boundary objects) in a slightly different way. For them, discursive moments are not quite as improvised as the sensemaking and scripting approaches would have us believe. They argue that there is a ‘coordinated management of meaning’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Pearce &amp; Cronen, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Pearce, 1989</xref>) in operation within discourse that is partially improvised, but it is nevertheless inextricably linked by the presence of four underlying imperatives (i.e. prefigurative forces, practical forces, contextual forces and implicative forces) that simultaneously enable and constrain the interaction.<marker type="block"/> Although Pearce and Cronen’s work primarily engages with the ‘present’, the notion of ‘implicative forces’ clearly has projective overtones insofar as it is concerned with social actors weighing up the potentially negative and positive consequences of their discursive actions for themselves and for others and acting accordingly. Looking forwards in this manner has significant implications for how actions and decisions relating to a boundary object will unfold in terms of the twists and turns in the conversation and the path, or paths, that are ultimately taken.<marker type="block"/> The concept of ‘formalisation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Iedema, 1999</xref>) also has a bearing on the future-oriented framing of boundary objects. This arises because ‘discursive formalization’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Iedema, 1999</xref>) impacts upon the creation of texts in the present by evoking the future. Iedema’s work draws attention to the importance of the modes of capturing and representing (i.e. formalizing) discourse in shaping and configuring the actual interaction and, hence, the text itself. The activity of minute-taking is used by Iedema to illustrate this process. He shows how the formalization of meetings, via minute taking, mediates the actual dialogue insofar as the anticipation of the how the minutes will represent the discussion actually influences the discussion in real time. In effect, the minutes (which will appear in the future) are shaping, albeit partially, the discursive construction of the meeting (which is occurring in the present). This formalization process is arguably mirrored in the creation of boundary objects as texts. Boundary objects are typically the outcome of a process of formalization insofar as discussions and negotiations between communities of practice over time come to be represented, recorded and solidified as inscribed artefacts (e.g. written specifications, charts, maps, diagrams, and so on).<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> Moreover, given that these artefacts have projective implications their construction in the present is mediated by the future.<marker type="block"/> For example, the construction of Gantt charts as ‘temporal boundary objects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Yakura, 2002</xref>) entails projective commitments to future outcomes. After all, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Sapsed and Salter (2004)</xref> indicate: “A Gantt chart suggests how much work will be done by which time, by whom, with implications for how resources are deployed and over what duration” (p. 1530). The real-time development of this form of boundary object in the present is very clearly mediated by concerns about future accountability. Albeit less obviously, processes of ‘formalization’ are also at work in the construction of boundary objects that do not appear to have strong temporal connotations. If, for instance, we take the case of medical records as boundary objects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Berg &amp; Bowker, 1997</xref>), it is entirely conceivable that their real-time construction and use is significantly influenced by future accountability. This ‘eye to the future’ is the manifestation of a certain apprehensiveness about who gets to see the records (e.g. patient access due to data protection and freedom of information requirements) and also the fear of legal action. The net result is the actual nature and function of the medical record, as a boundary object, is affected by the process of formalisation.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="6" column="1">6</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91" page="7" column="1">7</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="97" page="8" column="1">Discussion and Conclusions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" page="8" column="1">The advent of ‘critical discourse analysis’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Fairclough, 1992</xref>; 1995; 2003) has produced a three-part approach to discourse where a discursive event “is seen as being simultaneously a piece of text, an instance of discursive practice, and an instance of social practice” (1992:4). The deployment of this critical approach draws attention to both the centrality and pervasiveness of power in developing a discursively nuanced account of boundary objects. Arguably, there are important power dynamics associated with the ‘intertextuality’, ‘recontextualization’ and ‘formalization’ perspectives when applied to boundary objects.<marker type="block"/> The intertextual analysis of public inquiry reports demonstrates how dominant interests can become embedded within boundary objects which, when viewed collectively (i.e. as a boundary infrastructure), discursively reproduce and reinforce ‘hegemonic power relationships’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Boje, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Mumby &amp; Stohl, 1991</xref>). In the case of public inquiry reports, the privileged discourse legitimates social institutions and the omnipotence of the state, and marginalises alternative readings of events. More generally, the use of intertextual approaches enables us to consider the processes by which particular boundary objects<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> replicate, or challenge, pre-existing power relationships and how they coalesce to form, or disrupt, prevailing boundary infrastructures.<marker type="block"/> The application of recontextualisation to the study of boundary objects draws attention to the power asymmetries between communities of practice. In doing so, it reveals “how inequalities in power determine the ability to control the production, distribution and consumption of particular texts” (Oswick et al, 2000:1116).<marker type="block"/> As indicated earlier, recontextualisation is inextricably linked to the ‘transformation of knowledge’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2004</xref>) and, as a consequence, it offers considerable potential for contestation. This arises because the process of transforming knowledge across boundaries produces novelty that “generates different interests between actors that impede their ability to share and assess knowledge” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Carlile, 2004</xref>:560). Hence, as illustrated in the reframing of the Sapsed and Salter’s (2004) study of project management tools as boundary objects presented earlier, recontextualisation provides a valuable means of interrogating and understanding the discursive processes that promote and inhibit the successful transformation of knowledge between different contexts (i.e. communities of practice).<marker type="block"/> The discursive process of formalization has power implications, but these are primarily concerned with the manufacture of conditions of possibility. The future orientation of formalization means that social actors engage with boundary objects in ways which are not necessarily aligned to the mutual generation and dissemination of knowledge between different groups. More specifically, the practical, everyday use of boundary objects resulting from formalization is likely to encourage groups and individuals to indulge in strategic behaviour which seeks to maximise the projective establishment control and minimize the scope for negative outcomes, such as high risk, low status, and the subordination of personal needs to those of others. In the case of Gantt charts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Yakura, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Sapsed &amp; Salter, 2004</xref>), the strategic behaviour employed is likely to focus on establishing and maintaining control over tasks and timelines (e.g. making sure timelines are not ‘too tight’). By contrast, the primary driver of strategic behaviour in the case of medical records (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Berg &amp; Bowker, 1997</xref>) is more likely to be a concern with avoiding risk and liability.<marker type="block"/> Analysis of the discursive formalization of boundary objects offers a route into understanding the way in which the real-time accomplishment of knowledge sharing is<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> achieved. Moreover, it also helps to illuminate how knowledge generation across boundaries can become compromised, or at the very least influenced, by the projective concerns of groups of stakeholders.<marker type="block"/> In conclusion, this paper outlines the potential for applying a repertoire of text-related approached to the study of knowledge at the boundaries between communities of practice. In particular, it advocates the deployment of a discourse-analytic framework that engages with the ‘fine grain’ of the formation and use of boundary objects. It is hoped that this methodological orientation will encourage further research that explores the dynamic, embedded and political imbued nature of boundary objects.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="103" page="8" column="1">8</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="114" page="9" column="1">9</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="117" page="10" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="118" page="10" column="1">Allen, G. (2000). Intertextuality. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="119" page="10" column="1">Bakhtin, M. (1981). The Dialogic Imagination: Four Essays. C. Emerson and M. Holquist (trans.), Austin, TX: University of Texas Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="120" page="10" column="1">Barthes, R. (1977). Image – Music – Text. S. Heath (trans.), London: Fontana.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="121" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Berg, M., &amp; Bowker, G. (1997). The multiple bodies of the medical record. Sociological Quarterly, 38(3), 513-537.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="122" page="10" column="1">Bernstein, B. (1990). The Structuring of Pedagogic Discourse. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="123" page="10" column="1">Bernstein, B. (1996). Pedagogy, Symbolic Control and Identity. London: Taylor and Francis.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="124" page="10" column="1">Boje, D. M. (1995). Stories of the storytelling organization: A postmodern analysis of Disney as Tamara- Land. Academy of Management Journal, 38(4), 997-1035.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="125" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Bowker, G., &amp; Star, S. L. (1999). Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="126" page="10" column="1">Briers, M., &amp; Chua, W. F. (2001). The role of actor-networks and boundary objects in management accounting change: a field study of an implementation of activity-based costing. Accounting, Organizations and Society, 26, 237-269.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="127" page="10" column="1">Brown, A. (2004). Authoritative sensemaking in a public inquiry report. Organization Studies, 25(1), 95- 112.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="128" page="10" column="1">Brown, J. S., &amp; Duguid, P. (1991). Organization learning and communities of practice: Toward a unified view of working, learning and innovation. Organization Science, 2(1), 40-57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="129" page="10" column="1">Brown, J. S., &amp; Duguid, P. (2001). Knowledge and organization: A social-practice perspective. Organization Science, 12(2), 198-213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="130" page="10" column="1">Carlile, P. R. (2002). A pragmatic view of knowledge and boundaries: boundary objects in new product development. Organization Science, 13(4), 442-455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="131" page="10" column="1">Carlile, P. R. (2004). Transferring, translating and transforming knowledge: An integrative framwork for managing knowledge across boundaries. Organization Science, 15(5), 555-568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="132" page="10" column="1">Fairclough, N. (1992). Discourses and Social Change. Cambridge: Polity Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="133" page="10" column="1">Fairclough, N. (1995). Critical Discourse Analysis: The Critical Study of Language. London: Longman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="135" page="11" column="1">Fairclough, N. (2003). Analyzing Discourse: Textual Analysis for Social Research. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="136" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Genette, G. (1997). Palimpsests: Literature in the Second Degree. C. Newman and C. Doubinsky (trans.), Lincoln, NE: University of Nebraska Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="137" page="11" column="1">Grant, D., Hardy, C., Oswick, C., &amp; Putnam, L. [Eds] (2004). The Sage Handbook of Organizational Discourse. London: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="138" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Henderson, K. (1991). Flexible sketches and inflexible data bases: visual communication, conscription devices, and boundary objects in design engineering. Science, Technology and Human Values, 16(4), 448-473.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="139" page="11" column="1">Iedema, R. (1999). The formalisation of meaning. Discourse and Society, 10(1), 49-65.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="140" page="11" column="1">Keenoy, T., &amp; Oswick, C. (2004). Organizing textscapes. Organization Studies, 25(1), 135-142.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="141" page="11" column="1">Kristeva, J. (1980). Desire in Language: A Semiotic Approach to Literature and Art, T. Gora, A. Jardine and L. Roudiez (trans.), New York: Columbia University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="142" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Lave, J. (1991). Situated learning in communities of practice. In L. B. Resnick &amp; S. Teasley (Eds), Perspectives on Socially Shared Cognition. Washington, DC: American Psychological Association.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="143" page="11" column="1">Lave, J., &amp; Wenger, E. (1991). Situated Learning: Legitimate Peripheral Participation. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="11" column="1">Leonard-Barton, D. (1992). Core capabilities and core rigidities: A paradox in managing new product development. Strategic Management, 13, 111-126.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="11" column="1">Linell, P. (1998). Discourse across boundaries: on recontextualisation and the blending of voices in professional discourse. Text, 18(2), 143-157.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="11" column="1">Mumby, D. K., &amp; Stohl, C. (1991). Power and discourse in organizational studies: Absence and the dialectic of control. Discourse and Society, 2, 313-332.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="11" column="1">Oswick, C., Anthony, P., Keenoy, T., Mangham, I., &amp; Grant, D. (2000). A dialogic analysis of organizational learning. Journal of Management Studies, 37(6), 887-901.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="11" column="1">Oswick, C., Keenoy, T., &amp; Grant, D. (2000). Discourse, organizations and organizing: concepts, objects and subjects. Human Relations, 52(9), 1115-1124.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" page="11" column="1">Pearce, W. (1989). Communication and the Human Condition. Carbondale, IL: Southern Illinois University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="11" column="1">Pearce, W., &amp; Cronen, V. (1979). Communication, Action and Meaning: The Creation of Social Realities. New York: Praeger.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Sapsed, J., &amp; Salter, A. (20040. Postcards from the edge: Local communities, global programs and boundary objects. Organization Studies, 25(9), 1515-1534.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Sarangi, S. (1998). Rethinking recontextualization in professional discourse studies: an epilogue. Text, 18(2), 301-318.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="11" column="1">Scheuer, J. (2001). Recontextualisation and communicative styles in job interviews. Discourse Studies, 3(2), 223-248.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Star, S. L. (1989). The structure of ill-structured solutions: boundary objects and heterogeneous distributed problem solving. In M. Huhns &amp; L. Glasser (Eds.), Readings in Distributed Artificial Intelligence. Menlo Park, CA: Morgan Kaufman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Star, S. L. (1991). The sociology of the invisible. In D. R. Maines (Ed.), Social Organization and Social Process: Essays in Honor of Anselm Strauss. New York: Aldine de Gruyter.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="12" column="1">Star, S. L., &amp; Griesemer, J. R. (1989). Institutional ecology, ‘translations’ and boundary objects: amateurs and professionals in Berkeley’s Museum of Vertebrate Zoology, 1907-39. Social Studies of Science, 19, 387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" page="12" column="1">Thomas, P. (2003). The recontextualisation of management: a discourse-based approach to analysing the development of management thinking. Journal of Management Studies, 40(4), 775-801.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" page="12" column="1">Weick, K. (1995). Sensemaking in Organizations. London: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="12" column="1">Worton, M. and Still, J. [Eds] (1990). Intertextuality: Theories and Practices. Manchester: Manchester University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="12" column="1">Yakura, E. K. (2002). Charting time: timelines as temporal boundary objects. Academy of Management Journal, 45(5), 956-970.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="134" page="10" column="1">10</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="156" page="11" column="1">11</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="162" page="12" column="1">12</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
