<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>f81a725fc5b2324e67455b2f7ebf0d16f530d8fd733ecc4933ca9a635a33df77</job>
    <base_name>62pj</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/j.2162-6057.1998.tb00810.x</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">~~</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">G E R R l D F. S M I T H</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Idea-Generation Techniques: R Formulary of Rctive Ingredients</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="4">The profusion of creativity techniques that have been proposed and used is based on a m u c h smaller set of active ingredients, devices that promote idea generation. This paper reports the results of a study that identified these active ingredients through an analysis of 172 idea-generation methods. Fifty idea-generation devices of three types - strategies, tactics, and enablers - were identified a n d organized in a formulary. Research results facilitate the evaluation of idea-generation methods and the selection of methods suited to particular idea- generation tasks.</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="5">INTRODUCTION</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="1" column="1">Creativity, a notoriously elusive concept, is csncerned with the generation of ideas, alternatives, and possibilities (Mumford G Gustafson, 1988). The creative process can be viewed as encompassing front-end preparation and back-end evaluation, but idea genera!ion per se is the process's indispensable core. Among psychologists and other students of creativity (de Bono, 1992; Finke, Ward, &amp; Smith, 1992; Perkins, 1981), the most c o m m o n view is that creativity is not a unitary process. People have many ways of generating ideas. The diversity of means for generating ideas is paralleled by a diversity of idea- generation techniques. There are literally hundreds, ranging from informal pieces of advice to tightly-structured procedures. Idea-generation techniques are analogous to medications. Analgesics, a typical group of medications, are used to relieve pain. The group includes various products, prescriptive and non-prescriptive, branded and not, based on a small number o f active ingredients (e.g., ibuprofen). Thus, the surface variety of pain-relieving products overlays a more fundamental set <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> o f active ingredients. These drive decisions about which prod- u c t to use in particular circumstances. Similarly, beneath the diversity of idea-generation techniques lies a substrate of active ingredients, devices used to p r o m o t e creativity. This paper reports the results of a study o f active ingredients in idea-generation methods. T h e study identified means by which creativity techniques promote idea generation. These devices were organized into meaningful categories, comprising a formulary of active ingredients. T h e formulary offers ben- efits to creativity research. It c a n also help practitioners select appropriate methods i o r idea-generation tasks. T h e paper begins b y developing conceptual background pertaining to idea-generation techniques. It describes a n d lustrates the research m e t h o d used t o identify active ingredients in these techniques. T h e paper's largest section discusses the formulary, describing each o f fifty identified devices. In concluding, the paper considers the implications of these findings a n d suggests future lines of development.<marker type="block"/> A p p l i e d scientific research is b a s e d on t h e p r e m i s e t h a t understanding a phenomenon is a prerequisite for improving related practices. Research on creativity has been motivated by the assumption "that the creative process in h u m a n beings c a n b e concretely described and, further, that sound description should b e usable in teaching methodology t o increase the creative output of both individuals a n d groups" (Gordon, 1961). Notwithstanding the value of research on the creative process, we are far f r o m having a deep, comprehensive understanding o f creativity. The remoteness of the process - its frequent reli- ance on unconscious mental activities - a n d its heterogeneity - the variety of means b y which ideas are generated - create significant research challenges. T h e huge armamentarium o f idea-generation techniques is a useful, if underused, resource for addressing these challenges. Each technique reflects beliefs about the creative process. Such beliefs c a n b e derived f r o m personal experience, popular assumptions, or scientific research. They c a n b e valid or invalid, though the widespread use o f creativity techniques suggests that m a n y are effective, indicating that their underlying assumptions are sound. Descriptive creativity research has addressed issues spawned b y prescriptive techniques. The incubation phenomenon noted by Wallas (1926) was incorporated into several methods before becoming the object of scientific study (Smith, 1995). A n analysis o f idea-generation techniques c a n<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> reveal practice-oriented beliefs about the creative process that researchers should assess. Indeed, creativity techniques constitute a significant empirical phenomenon that merits study in its o w n right. Many books a n d articles propose techniques, extolling their virtues t o potential users. A smaller set o f papers, published in academic journals, assesses whether methods enhance idea-generation p e r f o r m a n c e . Research f i n d i n g s a r e o f t e n i n c o n c l u s i v e (Basadur, Graen, &amp; Green, 1982). Few studies include careful analyses of methods or of the tasks to which they are applied. Idea-generation techniques are a n important, b u t inadequately understood, p a r t of the creativity puzzle. A first step towards improved understanding is t o decide what is t o count as a n idea-generation m e t h o d or technique. A technique is a prescription. They range f r o m highly structured procedures to informal pieces of advice. Additional require- ments are that the prescription b e plausibly effective a n d that it reach beyond c o m m o n knowledge, what everyone already knows. A m e t h o d asking users t o “think long, hard, a n d about m a n y things” should be viewed with skepticism, unless it provides means of promoting those behaviors. Generic enablers pertaining to any mental task - use a diverse group o f well- rested people - should not be regarded as idea-generation techniques since they are n o t specifically intended for that purpose. This definition o f a technique - a plausibly effective prescription expressing m o r e than c o m m o n knowledge - implies t h a t every idea-generation m e t h o d includes o n e or m o r e active ingredients. A technique c a n include steps serving administrative purposes a n d have features that m a k e it user- friendly a n d provide market appeal. B u t to b e plausibly effective, it m u s t encompass at least o n e operation that promotes idea generation. Idea-generation techniques should b e studied via their active ingredients. These are the “operational mechanisms” (Prince, 1967) that p r o m p t idea generation. Even when occur- ring within groups, creativity is essentially a mental phenomenon. A technique m u s t p r o m p t certain cognitive activities in users. It does so through active ingredients, devices produc- ing desired mental changes. Active ingredients m a y b e instruc- tions users can mentally discharge (e.g., fantasize), stimuli they c a n respond t o (e.g., visual displays), or conditions fostering idea generation (e.g., anonymity). T h e technique-aided creative process encompasses four levels:<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> 1. Techniques, idea-generation methods that have been proposed and applied. 2. Active ingredients, prescribed operations by which techniques affect user thinking. 3. Cognitive processes, m e n t a l states a n d activities involved in creative thinking, studied by psychologists. 4. Brain processes, neurological states and activities that underly creative cognition, studied by neuroscientists. The brain process level, highly technical and poorly understood, is remote f r o m practical idea-generation concern. T h e other three levels have immediate relevance t o the enhancement of creativity. Interfaced between techniques and cognitive processes, the active ingredient level is especially significant. To understand how a technique works, its active ingredients and their connections to cognitive processes must be identified. To design a technique, active ingredients that exploit human mental capacities must be devised. In view o f the large number of idea-generation techniques, it is important to characterize and classify them. Several at- tempts to this end have been made. VanCiundy (1988) discussed 105 techniques for structured p r o b l e m solving, classifying them by stages o f the problem solving process. The 61 idea-generation methods were subdivided into group and individual techniques, a distinction, he admitted, that is not always crisp. VanGundy characterized these methods along several dimensions: whether idea generation is verbal or silent: whether ideas are produced by forced relationships or free association; and whether the technique employs'stimuli that are related or unrelated to the problem. Another classification framework was proposed by MacCrim- m o n and Wagner (1994). Viewing idea generation as a matter of making connections between ideas, these authors distin- guished internal connections involving elements of a focal prob- l e m f r o m external connections between the problem and outside factors. Further distinctions split internal connections involving problem form and function from connections involving elements of purpose. External connections can be local or distant, depending on how far a technique reaches in search of ideas. Withholding judgment on these classification schemes, it is argued that the best way of characterizing idea-generation methods i s in terms o f active ingredients. There are, presum-</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="7" page="1" column="1">107</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="8" page="1" column="1">Volume 32 Number 2 Second Quarter 1998</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx9">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62pj.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="10" page="2" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="11" page="2" column="1">il-</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="13" page="2" column="1">CONCEPTUAL</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14" page="2" column="1">D"CHG"oUND</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="15" page="2" column="1">Idea-generotion Techniques</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="17" page="2" column="1">108</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx18">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62pj.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="19" page="3" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="20" page="3" column="1">Active</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="21" page="3" column="1">Ingredients</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="23" page="3" column="1">109</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx24">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_003.image_03.png" thmb="62pj.page_003.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="25" page="4" column="1">IdeaGeneration Techniques</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="26" page="4" column="1">Clossifwng 'deo-9enerot'on Techniques</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="28" page="4" column="1">110</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx29">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_004.image_04.png" thmb="62pj.page_004.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="30" page="5" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="31" page="5" column="1">ably, a manageable number of these and t h e y are, by definition, the source of a method’s power. Indeed, research and practitioner attention should be focused on active ingredients, rather than o n methods themselves. Recalling the analogy between idea-generation techniques and medications, just a s scientists at the Food and Drug Administration ignore com- mercial products in favor o f the active ingredients they contain, so idea-generation research should attend to the underlying devices that make techniques effective. Techniques should be characterized and classified in terms of the devices they employ.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">.”</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="33" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">of</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="34" page="5" column="1">Identifying</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="35" page="5" column="1">METHOD One-hundred-and-seventy-two idea-generation methods reported in t h e creativity literature were identified during two waves of search activity. The first wave identified 130 methods through a review of the author’s personal library of books and papers, a search of all past issues of the Journal of Cr-ealioe Behauior, and examination of creativity books in a university library. The second wave uncovered an additional 4 2 techniques by searching more carefully through practitioner-ori- ented books with idea-generation content. Several books (e.g., Higgins, 1994; VanGundy, 1988) were compilations of techniques published in various literatures. All 172 methods satisfied the broad definition of “technique” - a plausibly effective prescription expressing more than common knowledge - proposed earlier. Techniques range from simple questions like the “What i f . . method (Higgins, 1994) - Ask yourself, if something happened, what would t h e con- sequences be? - to elaborate methodologies like Synectics. Several were minor variations each other, though differently named. Some were applicable to other parts of the problem solving process, but all could be used to generate ideas. Though there are more than 172 idea-generation methods, t h e techniques used for this study constitute a large and presumably representative subset of the population. Active The task of identifying active ingredients in these methods ‘nQredients is an instance o f the conceptualization task in science: How does one derive scientific concepts from empirical data? The methodology used in this study is an adaptation of that proposed by Glaser and Strauss (1967; Strauss, 1987). Active ingredients were identified through an iterative, data-driven process. Data analysis was a “boot-strapping’’effort that simulta- neously identified idea-generation devices a n d assessed whether a given technique employed them.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="36" page="5" column="1">111</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx37">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62pj.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="38" page="6" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="39" page="6" column="1">Examplc</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="40" page="6" column="1">Analvsis</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="41" page="6" column="1">(1993).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" page="6" column="1">Each technique was analyzed to determine how it actually works or is intended to work. The guiding analytical question was: By what means might this method promote idea generation? The analysis took into account rationales proposed by a method’s proponents. It considered findings from cognitive and social psychology, as well as folk psychological assumptions about human thinking and group processes. In each case, the analysis identified one or m o r e operational mechanisms deemed responsible for a method’s functioning. The researcher made three passes through the initial set of 130 idea-generation techniques. Each time, I assessed how each technique functions, identifying pertinent active ingredients. These devices were subsequently evaluated: Some were deleted, others were consolidated, and new ingredients were created by splitting devices into parts. The revised set of active ingredients was used to direct the next analysis of techniques. The set was altered again as a result of that pass. Since no revisions were prompted by a third iteration, the designated set of active ingredients was deemed adequate for these data. It was organized into a formulary consisting of categories of ingredients, reflecting distinct idea-generation strategies. This formulary was used to analyze the 42 techniques that were subsequently identified. One additional idea-generation device was discovered through this analysis. Some active ingredients are more likely to be effective than others, but each has been regarded, if only by a method’s origi- nator, as an aid to creativity. Active ingredients pursue different strategies; they also vary in scope and style. Though it was usually easy to say how a method was supposed to function, judgment calls had to be made. Some methods rely implicitly o n certain prescriptive operations. With devices that often cooccur in techniques, it was necessary to decide if there is a single complex ingredient or several simple ones. Active ingredients shade into general means for enhancing mental performance - use intelligent people - a n d into logistical mechanisms - use slips of paper to record thoughts. Judg- ment was used to make distinctions in this regard. To illustrate what was done, consider the following analysis o f a method described by Grossman and Wiseman The method has three steps: 1. Divide a sheet of paper into two columns. On the top of the left side, place or identify the object from which ideas need to be pulled. On the top of the right side, state the problem for which ideas are needed.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="43" page="6" column="1">112</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx44">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_006.image_06.png" thmb="62pj.page_006.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="45" page="7" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="46" page="7" column="1">Validation of</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="47" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Results</h2>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">2. Ignoring t h e column on t h e right, list all the characteristics of the object on the left that you can think of. Try to list characteristics that are specific to or unique about that object. 3. For each descriptive item on the left, ask participants to find at least one idea pertaining to their problem. Write these in the right-side column, opposite the generating item. Write any ideas coming to mind in this way, rather than looking for direct solution relevance. Analysis of this method reveals a number of active ingredients. The method’s first step employs remole slimuli; an object unrelated to the problem is used to generate ideas. The method also uses concrete stimuli when the stimulus object is physically present for idea generation. Decomposition is t h e key device in Step 2, t h e stimulus being analyzed into parts and attributes. Step 3 is driven by relalionship search, trying to connect left-side entries to the problem situation. It may employ a force f i t device, depending on how strictly one is required to find a problem-side counterpart for each stimulus- side entry. Association is implicitly invoked by the suggestion to accept any ideas that come to mind, regardless of their solution relevance. Thus, this technique can employ a s many a s six active ingredients for idea generation, each potentially con- tributing to the method’s effectiveness. Arguably, an effective procedure for identifying active ingredients in idea-generation techniques cannot be precisely defined. In lieu of prescribing such, the research focused on process outputs: candidate devices. To be accepted a s an active ingredient for purposes of this study, a candidate had to satisfy several conditions. First, it had to be a plausibly effective idea-generation device, such that creativity techniques could be constructed around it. Ideally, each device could be supported by psychological research. Second, a device had to be clearly evidenced in at least one idea-generation method. Finally, independent assessors had to be able to reliably record the occurrence of active ingredients in idea- generation techniques. In response to the final criterion, descriptions of the 50 idea- generation devices were incorporated in a coding manual that specified procedures for analyzing idea-generation methods. A set of 26 techniques, selected by systematic random sam- pling, was used to assess coding reliability. Two raters - the author and a research assistant used the manual to inde-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="49" page="7" column="1">-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="50" page="7" column="1">113</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx51">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_007.image_07.png" thmb="62pj.page_007.image_07-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="52" page="8" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="53" page="8" column="1">42</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="8" column="1">pendently code the techniques. Each coder identified devices, three m o r e being identified by one of the two raters. Coders agreed o n 35 of the 42 assignments, an agreement rate of 83.3%. If the extra/omitted codes.are included i n the base, the agreement rate is 77.8?0 (35/45). This level o f coding reliability seems acceptable for current purposes. Disagree- ments, m o s t resulting f r o m j u d g m e n t calls, were used to sharpen definitions of active ingredients. In order to gauge the formulary’s completeness, the 172 idea-generation techniques were reviewed to determine when each active ingredient was first observed. Thirty-two (64%) o f the 50 devices appeared in the first 30 techniques that were analyzed; only four new ingredients (8%) were discovered in the last 82 methods; a n d n o n e were found in the last 32. Though the identified set of active ingredients is certainly n o t exhaustive, there is reason to believe that it is substantially complete. <marker type="block"/> The results of this study are reported in Table which lists fifty idea-generation devices, along with a brief description of each. The active ingredients have been organized into fifteen categories, identified in the table’s left-hand column. Three types o f active ingredients were differentiated: Stralegies, the m o s t numerous a n d significant type, are active means for generating ideas. Most refer to identifiable mental activities. Tactics are the least common type, comprising a single category o f devices. They are stimulatory tools that support strategies. Enablers are passive means o f promoting idea generation. Rather than directly inspiring creative output, enablers foster conditions within which ideas are m o r e likely t o appear. In the device column, next to the device name, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> reports the frequency with which each was observed in the 172 techniques analyzed d u r i n g this study. These counts suggest the popularity o f idea-generation mechanisms with designers o f creativity methods. They d o n o t indicate the over- all importance of a device in creative thinking. Some devices, Past Experience for instance, are natural parts of our thinking a n d are often used implicitly, without being expressly invoked b y a technique. The right-hand c o l u m n of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> reports a representative technique for each device, and a source describing the technique. The remainder of this section discusses each active ingredient, grouped b y category.<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> formulary of active ingredients in idea generation techniques.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="55" page="8" column="1">RESULTS</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="56" page="8" column="1">1,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="60" page="8" column="1">114</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx61">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_008.image_08.png" thmb="62pj.page_008.image_08-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="62" page="9" column="1">TABLE I .</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="63" page="9" column="1">A</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="65" page="9" column="1">- L VI</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Device Decomposition (32)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="67" page="9" column="1">Category Analytical Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="68" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Abstraction (10)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Translation ( I )</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Association ( I I )</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="71" page="9" column="1">Search Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Past Experience (2)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Analogy (10)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Imagination-Based Fantasy (10)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="75" page="9" column="1">Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Mental Simulation (14)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Identification (2)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="78" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">ng Challenge Assumptions (3)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="79" page="9" column="1">Habit-Breaki Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Negation (6)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Change of Perspective (6)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="82" page="9" column="1">L 0 5 L 0 s Y -. c</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Change of Attitude (4)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Description Reduce wholes into parts and attributes, ends into means, etc. Conceive the problem in more general terms. Conceptually convert one kind of thing into another. Mentally follow associative links among ideas in memory. Recall past experiences relevant to the current problem. Look for things similar to parts of the problem situation. Conceive of slates in which reality constraints have been dropped. Mentally enact images or dynamic scenarios. Imaginatively become a non-human part of the problem. Question beliefs associated with the problem. Adopt counter-assumptions for problem-relevant beliefs. Think about the problem from the viewpoints of different agents. Adopt different attitudes towards the situation.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="85" page="9" column="1">Technique Morphological Analysis (Allen, 1962) Func t iona I Vi suali t at ion (Taylor, 1969) Input-Ou t pu t (Whiting, 1958) Focused-Object (Whiting, 1958) Transfer Analysis (Sands, 1979) Bionics (Souder G Ziegler, 1977) Idealization (Keller G Ho, 1988) Moment to Moment (de Bono, 1992) Personal Analogies (Higgins, 1994) Escape (de Bono, 1985) Look for Opposites (Thompson, 1992) Napoleon (Higgins, 1994) Fresh Eye (VanGundv, 1988)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx86">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_009.image_09.png" thmb="62pj.page_009.image_09-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="87" page="10" column="1">TABLE 1 .</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="88" page="10" column="1">- QI</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="89" page="10" column="1">Category</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="90" page="10" column="1">Strategies</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="91" page="10" column="1">sub-</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="92" page="10" column="1">Strategies</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="93" page="10" column="1">for</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="95" page="10" column="1">Development Strategies</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="96" page="10" column="1">quo</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="97" page="10" column="1">A formulary of active ingredients in idea generation techniques. (Conlinued) Device Description Relationship-Seeking Relationship Search (21) Look for relationships between two or more things. Structure (7) Organize information to reveal relationships. Task-Focused. Goal iocus (3) Decompose problem goals into goals, seeking options for each. Boundary Stretching (3) Explore extreme values of variables in the situation. Synonyms ( 1 ) Generate and explore synonyms words in the problem statement. Combination (16) Combine elements, attributes, and other aspects the problem. Rearrangement ( 1 Change the structure of a situation by rearranging its parts. Context Inclusion Think about the environment within which the problem exists. Enhancement (8) Modify ideas to make them more feasible and effective. Compare and Contrast (3) Compare ideas with the status to find points of advantage. Integration (7) Combine alternatives into problem solutions. Bootstrapping (10) Analyze alternatives to generate new families o f possibilities. Circumstances (2) Think of circumstances in which an idea miqht be effective.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="98" page="10" column="1">Technique Stimulus Analysis (VanGundy, 1988) Affinity Diagrams (Brassard, 1989) Value-Focused Thinking (Keeney, 1994) Exaggeration (de Bono, 1992) Two-Words Technique (VanGundy, 1987) Circumrelation (Laverty, 1974) Relational Algorithms (Crovitz, 1970) Listing (Whiting, 1958) Method 6-3-5 (Warfield et al, 1975) Camelot (Higgins, 1994) SIL Method (Warfield et al, 1975) Idea Transformations (MacCrimmon &amp; Wagner, 1994) Under What Circumstances (de Bono, 1992)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx99">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_010.image_10.png" thmb="62pj.page_010.image_10-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="100" page="11" column="1">A</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" page="11" column="1">formulary of active ingredients in idea generation techniques. (Conlinued)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="103" page="11" column="1">- <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="102" class="deo:Reference">TABLE 1</xref> . 4</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Device Group Interaction (28)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="105" page="11" column="1">Category Interpersonal Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Nominal Group ( 11)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Dialectic ( 1 )</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Resource Checklists (19)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="109" page="11" column="1">Special Strategies</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Outside Sources (6)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Personal Experience (2)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="112" page="11" column="1">Stimulation Tactics</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Elaboration (1)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Changing Environment (5)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Display ( 11 )</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Concrete Stimuli (13)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="117" page="11" column="1">L 5 L</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Related Stimuli (8)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Remote Stimuli (23)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="120" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Description Verbalize thoughts in a group so one person’s ideas prompt others. Generate and share ideas silently within a group. Conduct a debate between opposina sides on an issue. Use an established set of ideation prompts to generate alternatives. Solicit ideas from outsiders and established idea sources. Involve the problem solver experientially in the situation. Enrich the problem situation to provide idea generation material. Mentally or physically leave one’s normal thinking environment. Make ideas visible in a graphic array. Use physical things or pictures in idea generation sessions. Provide stimuli that are connected to the problem solving task. Provide stimuli that are unrelated to the problem solving task.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="121" page="11" column="1">Technique Brainstor ming (Osborn, 1963) Brainwriting Pool (Warfield et at, 1975) Li-on’s.D.en (Higgins, 1994) Manipulative Verbs (Koberg &amp; Bagnall, 1974) Tell Me Stranger (Koberg G Bagnall, 1974) Experience Kit (Higgins, 1994) Storywriting (VanGundy, 1988) Get Out of Town (Koberg &amp; Bagnall, 1974) Mindmapping (Buzan, 1983) Idea Triggers (Higgins, 1994) Semantic Intuition (VanGundy, 1988) Nonlogical Stimuli (Rickards, 1974)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx122">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_011.image_11.png" thmb="62pj.page_011.image_11-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="123" page="12" column="1">TABLE 1.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="124" page="12" column="1">A</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="125" page="12" column="1">formulary of active ingredients in idea generation techniques. (Conlinucd)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="126" page="12" column="1">- + Q,</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="127" page="12" column="1">Readiness</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="128" page="12" column="1">Device Provocation (2)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="129" page="12" column="1">Category Mental Enablers</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="130" page="12" column="1">Block Removal (5)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="131" page="12" column="1">i an 2. C VI</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="132" page="12" column="1">Goal Setting (3)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="133" page="12" column="1">Mot iva t iona I Enablers</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="134" page="12" column="1">Competition (3)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="135" page="12" column="1">Persona I lnvo I vem en t</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="136" page="12" column="1">Mass Production ( I )</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="137" page="12" column="1">Description Draw attention to the problem or task. Remove mental barriers that inhibit idea generation. Set quotas for ideas or establish time deadlines. Arrange idea generation contests between groups or individuals. Foster personal feelings of affiliation with the organization. Try to generate lots ideas.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="139" page="12" column="1">Extra Effort Enablers</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="140" page="12" column="1">Force Fit (8)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="141" page="12" column="1">Incubation (4)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">for</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="143" page="12" column="1">Anti-Rutting Enablers</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="144" page="12" column="1">Non-Disclosure (2)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="145" page="12" column="1">Force unrelated ideas together to achieve breakthroughs. Set the problem aside awhile to escape mental ruts. Do not state the problem at the outset of sessions. Keep obvious ideas out of mind.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="146" page="12" column="1">Suppressed Alternatives ( I ) Deferred Evaluation (9)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="147" page="12" column="1">Anti-Inhibition Enablers</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="148" page="12" column="1">Anonymity (3)</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="149" page="12" column="1">Withhold evaluation of ideas so as not to inhibit generation. Insure that ideas can't be traced to their originators.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="150" page="12" column="1">Technique Provocation (de Bono, 1992) Creative Whack Pack (von Oech, 1992) Lotus Blossom (Tatsuno, 1990) Force-Fit Game (Warfield et al, 1975) Systematized Direct Induction (Bosticco, 1971) Crawford Slip Method (Clark, 1978) Catalog (Taylor, I96 I ) Idea Tracking (Arrnstrong, 1960) Gordon-Little (Taylor, 1961) Synectics (Prince, 1967) Trigger Method (VanGundy, 1988) Collective Notebook (Haefele, 1962)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx151">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_012.image_12.png" thmb="62pj.page_012.image_12-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="152" page="13" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="153" page="13" column="1">RnolWcol</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="154" page="13" column="1">Search</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">on</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="156" page="13" column="1">Strotegles More than any other category, analytical strategies demon- strate t h e value o f convergent thinking for idea generation. These strategies provide a more fine-grained or fundamental appreciation of t h e problem, generating mental material that can be exploited by other devices. Analysis, thinking carefully about the problem, was viewed a s an idea-generation strategy by Gestalt psychologists (Duncker, 1945; Wertheimer, 1982). More recently, Getzels and Csikszentmihalyi (1976) found that artists who did more critical analysis before and during their work were more successful in their careers. Finke's (1995) notion of "creative realism" suggests that established ideas can be analyzed a s a way of transforming them into new possibilities. The most frequently used of all strategies, at least in this study's sample of techniques, is Decomposition. Decomposi- tional methods are reductive; they convert an undifferentiated stimulus into one rich in detail, offering cues for idea generation. Decompositions c a n be from wholes into parts and attributes, and from ends into means, among others. Morphological Analysis decomposes a problem into parameters and components, searching for combinations that have promising solution implications. Abstracfion is an analytical device that asks one to think about the problem in more general terms. Situation-specific details are sloughed off to focus on underlying principles, hoping to connect t h e mind to other situations and solutions of relevance. Van Gundy (1988) cited a case in which group members were asked to think of ways to stack things, their ideas being considered a s ways of parking cars. Functional Visualization, a design method, asks one to think about the functions of an artifact and how they might, in principle, be fulfiiled. Less widely employed, Translation concep- tually converts one class of things into another. Many design methods translate functions into structures and forms. The Input-Output technique was used to devise a fire alarm: Start- ing with a fire a s input, the method identified a chain of resultant factors leading to an output alarm (Whiting, 1958). Strategies All idea-generation methods rely on retrieval of information from memory. Search strategies are especially dependent this process, calling for directed retrieval efforts. Differen- tiations within this category reflect differences in how information is stored in memory. Associalion is a search strategy following associative links a m o n g items in a network- structured memory. The strategy a s s u m e s that links can reflectsolution-relevant relationships. Studies have found mod- erate positive correlations between measures of associational</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="157" page="13" column="1">119</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx158">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_013.image_13.png" thmb="62pj.page_013.image_13-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159" page="14" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="160" page="14" column="1">G</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="161" page="14" column="1">Imaqinotion-Based</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" page="14" column="1">abilities and indices of creative achievement (Mumford Gustafson, 1988). The Focused-Object method uses stimuli that are related to and remote from the problem as starting points for free association. Past Experience is, arguably, the most widely-used idea- generation strategy: Faced with a problem, we generate solutions by recalling relevant past experiences. But experience has both positive and negative effects on idea generation, the latter when inadequate prior solutions prevent new ideas from being conceived (Stein, 1989). Owing perhaps to its everyday familiarity, this device is not used k m a n y techniques. New products have been developed through Transfer Analysis, a method that derives ideas from a n inventory of successful innovations. Techniques using Analogy rely o n similarity-based searches of memory. Bionics asks users to think about how the problem is solved in nature. Analogy plays a n important role in creative thought (Holyoak &amp; Thagard, 1995), although Perkins ( 1983), citing experimental and archival data, argued that remote analogies rarely drive creative discoveries. Imagination, our ability to conceive of possibilities, is virtu- ally synonymous with creativity. The strategies in this category require significant acts of imagination: One must imagine unrealistic states, conceive detailed mental images, or run extended scenarios. People’s abilities to do so have been demonstrated b y psychological research, which has also demonstrated the creative value of these activities (Finke, Ward, &amp; Smith, 1992). Using the Fantasy strategy, a person conceives of states in which reality constraints have been dropped. Doing so promotes the restructuring o f mental representations (Dominowski, 1995). Idealization, a version of this strategy, asks one t o d r o p all constraints a n d envision a perfect solution. The Menlal Sirnulalion strategy uses imagination to enact dynamic scenarios. Compared to Fantasy, it is less focused on constraints and more concerned with predicting how alternatives would work if implemented. With the Moment to Moment technique, one visualizes, in detail, what would hap- pen if a n idea was put into action. The most radical imagina- tion-based strategy, l d e n l i f i c a l i o n requires p e o p l e t o imaginatively become a non-human part of the problem. This device, first employed in Synectics, relies on empathy to generate insights. By imagining that they were human hairs, people at Gillette were aided in the development of a new shampoo (Higgins, 1994). <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> These strategies are based on the premise that the mind must break out of normal response patterns to think creatively. Past experience and the current problem solving context en- gender a mental set or fixedness. Researchers have found that context-induced set must be overcome for creative insights to occur (Schooler G Melcher, 1995). Habit-breaking strategies prod us out of mental ruts. Challenge Assumptions questions beliefs associated with a task. The strategy can be difficult to operationalize, since implicit assumptions rarely leap into consciousness when called. With the Escape method, one iden- tifies, and consciously tries to escape from, the main track of thought. A more radical strategy, Negation adopts counter- assumptions: Assume the opposite of what you currently believe. Negation provides more direction for idea generation and can result in dramatic breakthroughs if a counter-assumption has useful implications. A relative of the Identification strategy discussed earlier, Change off'erspectiue asks one to think about the problem from the viewpoints of different agents who may or may not be part of the situation. Empathic identification helps one recognize interests of other stakeholders, promoting idea generation. Or, as with the Napoleon technique, adopting a viewpoint associated with a famous person or different voca- tion can help one escape habitual modes of thought. Change of Al l i tu d c assumes that feelings influence thought, a view having some empirical support (e.g., lsen &amp; Nowicki, 1980). People are instructed to adopt different attitudes towards the situation. The Fresh Eye method asks one to think of something positive about the problem, and to develop solution possibilities from this. Studies have shown that when individuals combine two or more concepts, new properties can emerge (Hampton, 1997). These findings support theories of creativity (e.g., Findlay &amp; Lumsden, 1988; Koestler, 1964) that focus on mental events in which things, normally not associated with each other, are related or combined. The findings also sustain several idea- generation strategies, Relationship Seeking being the most typical. One consciously looks for relationships between two or more things, one of which is part of the problem. The Stimulus Analysis technique has people generate a list of concrete terms, unrelated to the problem; select a term, decomposing it into characteristics; and relate each characteristic to the problem in hopes of finding solution ideas. Relationship-seeking strategies could be constructed around particular types of</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="163" page="14" column="1">120</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx164">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_014.image_14.png" thmb="62pj.page_014.image_14-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="165" page="15" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="166" page="15" column="1">Hoblt-ereahlnQ Strategies</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="167" page="15" column="1">Relotionship- StrateQies</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="169" page="15" column="1">121</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx170">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_015.image_15.png" thmb="62pj.page_015.image_15-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="171" page="16" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="172" page="16" column="1">Tosk-Focused Strategies</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">relationships. For instance, Analogy can be thought of a s search driven by t h e relationship of similarity. Structure, t h e other strategy in this category, employs a special mechanism for finding relationships. Information is organized to reveal connections between elements of t h e problem. Affinity Diagrams promote idea generation by grouping ideas and information on t h e basis of “affinity” or relatedness. Similar to analytical strategies in their focus o n the problem, these devices deal with parts of the situation, generating alternatives by thinking about those aspects. They are supported by studies which indicate, for instance, that more decision options are generated w h e n people consider problem attributes one-at-a-time (Keller &amp; Ho, 1988). Goal Focus is a typical strategy. It decomposes problem goals into subgoals, generating alternatives that respond to each. Value-Focused Thinking applies this approach within a decision making fra mework. With Boundary Slrctching, one explores extreme vdlues of variables in t h e situation. Volkema (1983) found that sub- jects generated more solution alternatives when a problem’s scope was increased via a “Problem-Purpose Expansion” heu- ristic. Designers consider extreme values of properties of existing artifacts w h e n developing new design concepts. The Exaggeration method implements this strategy in a straight- forward way. The Synonyms device. observed only in t h e Two- Words Technique, is distinctive: Generate synonyms for words used in the problem definition, exploring t h e implications of these. The strategy responds to a concern expressed by Koestler ( 1964):Words overly crystallize and constrain thought. Exploring synonyms can surface conceptual distinctions with idea-generation potential. A popular strategy, Combination asks one to combine elements and attributes o f t h e problem, usually by pairs, in search of ideas. It is exemplified by Circumrelation, which uses con- centric disks to generate over 1500 combinations of factors for consideration. A less systematic variation of Combination, Rearrangemen! alters t h e structure of a situation by rearranging its parts. This strategy is often implemented with lists of relationships, a s in Relational Algorithms, a technique using words like “across.” “between” and “ w h e n ” to suggest restructurings of a problematic system. De Bono (1970) described how a motorist couldn’t get past a flock of sheep traveling down a country lane bounded by high banks. The shepherd refused to move t h e sheep to t h e side, fearing that some would be struck</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="174" page="16" column="1">122</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx175">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_016.image_16.png" thmb="62pj.page_016.image_16-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="176" page="17" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="177" page="17" column="1">Con-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="178" page="17" column="1">prod-</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="179" page="17" column="1">Development Strotegles</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="180" page="17" column="1">Interpersonal Strate91es</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="188" page="17" column="1">as the car drove through. A rearrangement of fixed a n d mov- ing elements solved the problem: The motorist stopped the car while the shepherd drove the sheep back around it. A final target of attention is the problem's context. The text inclusion strategy asks one to think about the environment within which a problem exists. Doing so fosters awareness o f unnoticed constraints a n d potential side-effects of solutions. The Listing technique can implement this strategy for new uct development: Think of products, objects, or activities found in the target product's context, and consider how a new product might accomodate these. T h e dangers of mental set notwithstanding, existing solutions often contain the seeds of their successors. Finke (1995) expressed this with the t e r m "structural connectedness." Development strategies use the status q u o and ideas generated previously. These ideas are analyzed and manipulated to create better alternatives. The simplest of these devices is Enhancement, modifying a n idea to make it more effective. With Method 6-3-5, each member of a six-person group writes down three ideas that are passed around, every member spending five minutes improving on ideas proposed by others. Compare and Contrast, a more focused strategy, compares ideas with the status quo, disclosing points of advantage to incorporate in a solution. In Camelot, the status q u o is com- pared with a n ideal solution, indicating differences solutions should try to capture. A Compare and Contrast analysis might feed into Integration, a strategy of combining alternatives into solutions encompassing the virtues of many. The challenge is to devise coherent combinations. With the SIL Method, each member o f a group successively proposes a n idea that the group tries to integrate into its emerging solution. The more radical Bootstrapping device uses existing ideas as stimuli for generating new ones. Alternatives are analyzed and characterized in order to extend them and to discover unrecognized families of possibilities. T h e Idea Transformation technique uses a list of transformation terms to generate new ideas f r o m old. More radical still is the Circumstances device. Rather than altering a n idea to fit current circumstances, it looks for circumstances that fit the idea. Post-itT" notes originated with a 3M scientist trying to think of circumstances requiring a semi- sticky adhesive. The dominant active ingredient in m o s t group methods, these devices rely o n interpersonal interaction. People stimu- late each other, one person's ideas a n d criticisms spurring <marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> others to come up with better ideas. Group Inler-action is the core strategy in this family: Group members verbalize thoughts so one person’s ideas can spawn ideas in others. Brainstorming is the strategy’s classic embodiment. It is the most widely studied idea-generation technique, though findings as to its effectiveness are not conclusive (VanGundy, 1988). Nominal Group captures synergies of interpersonal interaction, while avoiding dysfunctional side-effects. Group members share ideas non-verbally to reduce distractions and inhibitions. Members of a Brainwriting Pool write down ideas, sharing them anonymously. Studies have shown that members of nominal groups produce more, though not always better, ideas than members of interacting groups (Stein, 1975). Dialectic, the third interpersonal strategy, uses conflict to generate ideas. A debate between opposing sides is conducted; this intellectual combat stimulates idea generation and criticism. The Lion’s Den has one group propose solutions and another group criticize them. Mason (1969) presented the rationale for such an approach, and supportive evidence from a field study involving corporate planning. Both strategies in this category use a specialized outside resource, enabling idea generation to reach beyond a person’s normal mental repertoire. With Checklists, the resource is an established set of ideation prompts - words or other stimuli. These can be tailored to idea-generation tasks, like new product development; or they can be general, applicable to many problems. The Manipulative Verbs technique uses words like “multiply,” “eliminate” a n d “squeeze” to suggest ways of transforming problem elements. ideas can be gotten from Outside Sources, including individuals or publications that are acknowledged resources in a field. Alternatively, outsiders may have n o special task expertise, as in Tell Me Stranger, which asks ordinary people for ideas concerning a problem. The presumption is that a man-in-the-street perspective can offer insights long since forgotten by experts. Tactics work within a strategy, rather than being stand-alone idea-generation mechanisms. They serve a support function, providing mental stimulation that strategies direct to creative purposes. Seven Stimulation Tactics were identified. Personal Experience involves the problem solver experientially in the problem s o he/she will have a richer understanding of it. Its use is suggested by theories of “situated cognition,” which stress the influence of experiential context o n thinking activities (Suchman, 1987). A n Experience Kit immersed</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="182" page="17" column="1">I23</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx183">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_017.image_17.png" thmb="62pj.page_017.image_17-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="184" page="18" column="1">Idea.Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="185" page="18" column="1">Speciol</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="186" page="18" column="1">Resource Str0te9’es</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="187" page="18" column="1">Stlmulotlon Toctlcs</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="189" page="18" column="1">124</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx190">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_018.image_18.png" thmb="62pj.page_018.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="191" page="19" column="1">J o u r n a l of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="192" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="193" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Ross,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="194" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">of</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="195" page="19" column="1">detergent brand managers in t h e realities of home laundry operations (Higgins. 1994). The Elaboration tactic employs a similar rationale, t h e problem solver being prompted to mentally enrich t h e problem situation to provide idea-generation material. Users of t h e Storywriting technique are asked to write a story about t h e problem, and then to analyze it for possible so1utions:With t h e Changing Environment tactic, people leave their normal thinking environments, physically and/or mentally, to be exposed i to different stimuli. The tactic derives support from arguments advanced on behalf of Habit-Breaking Strategies, discussed earlier. The Get Out Town technique prompts one to mentally take t h e problem to another place, exploring it for new ideas. It is probably more effective to “get o u t of town” physically a s well. Other tactics exploit t h e attention-grabbing power of concrete and vivid information (Nisbett &amp; 1980). Methods implementing theDisplay tactic make ideas visible in a graphic array. Presumably, when visually depicted, ideas are more able to inspire new ones. Mindmapping was among the first methods to construct informal diagrams representing one’s ideas on a topic. The perceptual capacities exploited by Display favor use of Concrete Slimuli. With this tactic, physical things or pictures are employed in idea-generation sessions. The Idea Trigger: technique provides group members with tangible probes, related to t h e problem, that t h e y work with during idea generation. This technique also suggests t h e Related Stimuli tactic, providing stimuli that are connected to t h e t a s k . Related stimuli are more likely to prompt generation o f task-relevant ideas, which are more likely to solve the problem. Semantic Intuition uses brainstorming to generate words related to t h e problem. These are combined in hopes discovering interesting ideas. The opposite argument is made on behalf of Remote Stimuli: Use prompts unrelated to t h e problem to remove the mind from pormal patterns so innovative ideas are generated. The tactic’s proponents - VanGundy (1988),for instance - contend that stimuli unrelated to the problem are best able to inspire rare insights that are truly creative. Though this rationale is consistent with some theories of creativity (e.g., Koestler, 1964), it has not been tested empirically. The Nonlogical Stimuli technique asks users to expose themselves to experiences unrelated to the problem and to examine these for solutions.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="196" page="19" column="1">125</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx197">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_019.image_19.png" thmb="62pj.page_019.image_19-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="198" page="20" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="199" page="20" column="1">Mental R ~ ~ ~ l</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="200" page="20" column="1">n e 5 Enoblers</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="201" page="20" column="1">Motivational Enob’ers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="202" page="20" column="1">5 Enablers are devices that facilitate, but do not directly pro- voke, idea generation. Unlike tactics, they are stand-alone devices that don’t necessarily support particular strategies. This category of enablers promotes a state of mental readiness, as might one’s morning c u p of coffee. They are not specific to particular thinking tasks. Research on attention suggests that such stimuli can improve performance by increasing one’s general level of arousal (Kahneman. 1973). Prouocalion is a n alerting or attention-grabbing device, exemplified by de Bono’s (1992) use of the word “PO.” A provocation draws attention to a problem and may call for idiosyncratic thoughts on the issue. Block Removal is a broad enabler that includes situation- specific components. Typified by the work of Adams (1979), it tries to remove mental barriers that inhibit idea generation. Block Removal can be viewed as a less aggressive version of Habit-Breaking Strategies. As such, it is supported by research o n set-breaking (Schooler G Melcher, 1995). The Creative Whack Pack, developed by von Oech, is a set of cards offering admonitions like “Get out of the dogma house.” Methods as- sume that awareness of a block is tantamount to removing it. This assumption may n o t be valid. Motivational enablers operate o n the assumption that individuals or groups may not be adequately motivated t o solve problems. Research on the relationship between creativity and motivation supports this assumption. However, Amabile ( 1996) has argued that intrinsic motivation - pursuing a task for its own sake - is the key, whereas extrinsic motivators - those sought for external reasons - can actually degrade idea-generation performance. Unfortunately, intrinsic motivation is difficult to manipulate through a technique. Since the devices in this family of enablers tend to rely o n extrinsic motivators, it is not clear how effective they are likely to be. The Goal Setting strategy uses output goals as motivators. Techniques set quotas for the number of ideas to be generated or establish time deadlines for task completion. The Lotus Blossom technique implements this strategy in a n interesting way. It uses a diagram with eight circles around a central problem or issue. A n idea must be entered in each circle, which becomes a starting point for new iterations. Thus, the d i a g r a m i m p l i c i t l y sets a q u o t a for idea generation. Competition is another motivator; people exert themselves to win games. The Force-Fit Game involves two teams who take turns suggesting remote ideas o r developing practical solutions f r o m ideas p r o p o s e d by opponents. A referee</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="203" page="20" column="1">126</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx204">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_020.image_20.png" thmb="62pj.page_020.image_20-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="205" page="21" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="206" page="21" column="1">Extro</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="207" page="21" column="1">Effort</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="208" page="21" column="1">Rntl.Ruttlng Enoblers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="209" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">awards points for successful ideas; t h e team accumulating the most points wins t h e contest. Personal Involvement is t h e weakest but most widely used of these enablers, at least infor- mally. It motivates idea generation by fostering feelings of be- longing between individuals and an organization having a problem. Systematized Direct Induction is a large group method using this enabler. Similar to Motivational Enablers, these devices are distinctive in that they don’t inspire creative effort, they demand it. Mass Producfion is based on t h e assumption that quality follows quantity. To generate good ideas, generate lots of ideas. Empirical studies have supported this “extended effort” or “quantity” principle (Basadur &amp; Thompson, 1986; Nezu &amp; D’Zurilla, 1981 ). Related techniques require people to spend more time on idea-generation tasks, or to come up with ideas beyond what they’ve already produced. Using many people the Crawford Slip Method can be implemented with 5000 participants - is another way o f implementing the device. The other extra effort enabler has a different rationale: Rather than valuing t h e quantity of ideas, force f i t prizes the remoteness of idea-generation stimuli. Forcing together unrelated ideas, it is argued, helps achieve creative breakthroughs. Hard- to-discover relationships may have fruitful solution implications: such relationships can be discovered through sustained effort. Though this rationale is suspect, t h e device is employed in many techniques, usually in conjunction with t h e Remote Stimuli tactic. Catalog asks one to randomly select two words from a dictionary or other printed material and “force” them together to produce a problem-relevant idea. This category consists of passive habit-breaking devices. It is underwritten by a strong psychological rationale: Thinking is susceptible to an anchoring effect in which initial ideas on a topic remain mentally present despite efforts to set them aside so other ideas can be explored (Smith, 1995). Ideas create patterns of neural activation that aren’t erased simply because an idea has been rejected. So we fall into mental ruts. The most useful device in this family is Incubalion, setting t h e problem aside until ruts have been smoothed over. In addition to its deanchoring aspect, Incubation has been proposed a s a means of putting unconscious mental processes to work. This is a less persuasive rationale that is inherently hard to validate (Perkins. 1981). Idea Tracking is one of several methods employing the device. With this technique, idea generation tran- spires over a period of days, during which one is encouraged</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="210" page="21" column="1">127</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx211">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_021.image_21.png" thmb="62pj.page_021.image_21-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="212" page="22" column="1">Idea4eneration Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="213" page="22" column="1">fintl-lnhlb~tlon Enablers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="215" page="22" column="1">to set the problem aside at times, to clear the mind and to allow unconscious processes to operate. A n appealing, though less widely-used, anti-rutting device is Non-Disclosure. It assumes that the problem itself can in- duce rutted thinking. A group leader withholds stating the problem at the outset of idea-generation sessions; people are asked to think about related or more general topics. The Gordon/ Little method implements this device effectively, gradually drawing idea generation closer to the true problem, which is eventually revealed. Suppressed Alternaliues is equally well grounded psychologically, though it can be difficult to implement. The device argues that standard solutions that immedi- ately surface during idea generation have anchoring effects. To overcome this, the device keeps obvious ideas from being generated or sweeps them away once they appear. Synectics includes a “purge” stage during which standard solutions are surfaced, criticized, and dismissed so attention can move on to other possibilities. The final category o f active ingredients only applies to group idea-generation sessions. As noted earlier, group interaction is a powerful creative force. Unfortunately, group processes often include inhibiting dynamics that negate that force. Devices in this family try to keep members from experiencing social inhibitions during group creativity sessions. Deferred Evaluation is the practice o f withholding criticism of ideas so as not to inhibit their generation. People shrink from exposing themselves, through their ideas, to negative assessments by others. The device is based on evidence that inter-member criticism in groups retards the flow of ideas (Stein, 1975). However, recent research suggests that the effects of evaluation o n creativity are more complex (Amabile, 1996). Brainstorming was the first technique to employ this device. It is also used in the Trigger Method: Members generate, share, and discuss ideas, n o evaluation being allowed until later in the session. Anonymily makes it so ideas can’t be traced to their originators. The Collective Notebook technique achieves anonymity by having a coordinator serve as a collection-anddispersion point for member-generated ideas. The use of group decision support systems that allow member contributions to appear, unattributed, o n central displays i s a means of securing anonymity with methods like the Nominal Group Technique. Idea-generation methods may use active ingredients beyond those identified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="214" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> and discussed in this section. How-</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="216" page="22" column="1">128</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx217">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_022.image_22.png" thmb="62pj.page_022.image_22-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="218" page="23" column="1">Journal o f Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="219" page="23" column="1">ever, this set of of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">fifty constitutes an impressive arsenal idea- generation devices.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="221" page="23" column="1">IMPLICATIONS</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="222" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">The formulary of active ingredients has important implications for idea-generation research and practice. Three lines of development will be discussed: Promoting the prescriptive side of creativity research; facilitating the evaluation of idea-generation methods; and enabling the selection of techniques suited to particular idea-generation tasks. Creativity has been the subject of much thinking and research, especially during the past several decades. The topic’s practical importance implies that creativity research should aim at improving things, not just understanding them. Though it could be argued that all creativity research pursues a practical goal, a strong case can be made that the great majority o f past research has had little impact on idea-generation practice. As in most scientific fields, prescriptive ends have been pursued by descriptive means: If we understand creativity, we can improve it. Admitting t h e past achievements and potential value of descriptive research on creativity, it is argued that a more direct prescriptive strategy should also be pursued. This strategy focuses on methods, heuristics, and other artifacts used to improve idea-generation performance. It asserts that these must also be a primary research target. The present paper promotes this prescriptive strategy through the formulary, a systematic account of the underlying mechanisms by which people have tried to aid idea generation. One stream of creativity research that has had a prescrip. tive orientation is work evaluating the effectiveness of techniques (Maier, 1970; Stein, 1974, 1975). However, of the hundreds o f existing methods, only brainstorming has been subjected to a substantial battery of performance tests. More- over, these assessments have generally been inconclusive in their results. By identifying t h e active ingredients on which techniques are based, t h e present paper promotes more pro- ductive studies of their effectiveness. By focusing on active ingredients, rather than methods, researchers can conduct efficient empirical tests of what works and what doesn’t. Arguably. a major cause of inconsistent findings by researchers evaluating creativity methods is inadequate attention to idea-generation tasks. A technique might work well in some tasks and poorly in others. It is obvious that a checklist devised for developing new product ideas won’t help a person think of novel ideas for a birthday present. It is less apparent,</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="223" page="23" column="1">129</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx224">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_023.image_23.png" thmb="62pj.page_023.image_23-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="225" page="24" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="226" page="24" column="1">b u t perhaps no less true, that a technique based o n decompo- sition won't b e effective with tasks that don't involve decom- posable core objects; that methods using mental simulation are m o s t helpful when the problem has a strong experiential component; a n d that a m e t h o d like Bionics is best suited for problems involving functions with natural analogues. The formulary of active ingredients provides a basis for pro- posing a n d testing hypothesized task-device interactions. If interactions are discovered, the formulary offers a framework for selecting task-appropriate idea-generation methods. It suggests the value of "packaged" interventions encompassing various devices, along with guidelines indicating when each is t o b e employed. Arguably, there is no one best creativity device o r technique, b u t rather a set of devices likely t o b e effective in certain idea-generation tasks. Interventions consisting of a well-designed repertoire o f devices c a n provide users with the required range of idea-generation support.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="227" page="24" column="1">REFEAENCES</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="228" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">sfep.</h2>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="229" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">ADAMS. J. L. (1979). Coriceplual bloclibusling: A g u i d e lo bcfler idea5 (2nd ed.). New York: Norton. ALLEN, M. S. ( 1962). Morphological c r c a t i i ' i i y . Englewood Cliffs. NJ: Prentice-Hall. AMABILE. T. M. (1996). Crealirily in conlc.u(. Boulder, CO: Westview. ARMSTRONG. F. A. (1960). ldcd [ r a c k i n g . New 'fork: Criterion. BASADUR. M., GRAEN. G. B.. &amp; GREEN. S. G. (1982). Training in creative problem solving: Effects on ideation and problem finding and solving in an industrial research organization. O r g d n iz alionc il Behacior arid Human Perlorniancc, 30. 41-70. BASADUR. M.. &amp; THOMPSON, R. ( 1986). Usefulness of the ideation principle of extended effort in real world professional and managerial creative problem solving. J o u r n a l o/ Crealii'c BchaL*ior. 20, 23-34. BOSTICCO. M. ( 1971). CrcaliL'e lechniyues lor ni'iriagernen(. London: Basic Books. BRASSARD, M. (1989). Thc rncniory j o g g c r plus+. Methuen. MA: GOAL/ QPC. BUZAN. T. (1983). Usc bofh sides olyotir brdiri. New York: Dutton. CLARK. C. H. (1978). T h e CIJUi/OfdS/ip LLviting riiclliod. Kent. OH: Charles H. Clark. CROVITZ. H. F. (1970). Gallon's calk. New York: Harper &amp; Row. DE BONO. E. (1970). Laleral l h i n k i n g : CreaLii'i(y slc,p by New 'fork: Harper &amp; Row. D E BONO. E. (1985). Dc BOnO'S ( / l i n k i n g course. New York: Facts on File. D E BONO, E. (1992). Serious crealiL-ity. New York: HarperCollins. DOMINOWSKI. R. L. (1995). Productive problem solving. In S. M. Smith, T. B. Ward. &amp; R. A. Finke (eds.). Thc crealiiie cogni(ion i i p p r o ~ ~ c - (pp. h 73-95). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="230" page="24" column="1">130</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx231">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_024.image_24.png" thmb="62pj.page_024.image_24-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="232" page="25" column="1">Journal of Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="233" page="25" column="1">hlonographs.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="234" page="25" column="1">J</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="235" page="25" column="1">~</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">DUNCKER. K. ( 1945). On problem-solving. Psychological 58 (Whole No. 270). FINDLAY. C. S.. &amp; LUMSDEN. C. J. (1988). The creative mind: Toward an evolutionary theory of discovery and innovation.Jourrial O ~ S O C a n ~ d Biological Slructures. 11. 3-55. FINKE. R. A. (1995). Creative realism. In S. M. Smith, T. B. Ward, &amp; R. A. Finke (eds.). The cr-ealrc’e c o g n i l i o n a p p r o a c h ( p p . 303-326). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. FINKE. R. A,. WARD. T. 8.. &amp; SMITH. S. M. (1992). Creative cognition: Theory. rcscarcti. arid applic‘itions. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. GETZELS. J.. &amp; CSIKSZENTMIHALYI. M. (1976). The crealice uision: A longitudinal study o/p r o b / c n i f i n d i n g i n arl. New York: John Wiley. GLASER. B. G., &amp; STRAUSS. A. L. (1967). The discovery o l grounded 1tieory.Chicago: Aldine. GROSSMAN. S. R.. &amp; WISEMAN, E. E. (1993). Seven operating principles for enhanced creative problem solving training. J O L i m d / of Crealire B ~ t i d ~ ~ 21, io / I-I./. . HAEFELE. J. W. (1962). Creatii*ily a n d inrcoL’alion. New York: Reinhold. HAMPTON. J. A. (1997). Emergent attributes in combined concepts. In T. B. Ward. S . M. Smith. &amp; J. Vaid (eds.). C r e a l i r e t t i o u g h l : A n inrestigalion o/ coiiccpl~ia/ s l r u c t u r c s a n d processes (pp. 83-110). Wa shin g t o n , DC : A m e r ic a n Psycho I og i ca I A ssoc ia ti o n . HIGGINS. J. M. ( 1994). 101 crcaliLie problem solc~irig (ect!niqucs. Winter Park, FL: New Management Publishing Company. HOLYOAK. K. J.. &amp; THAGARD. P . ( 1995). Flerilal l e a p : Analogy tn C / C J ( ~ L T thought. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. ISEN. ,A. M.. &amp; NOWICKI. G. (1980). P o s i t i ~ ~ allccl c a n d creative problem s o l ~ ~ i r i Paper g. presented at the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society. Berkeley, CA. KAHNEMAN, D. (1973).Aflenliori a n d dlor I. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice- Hall. KEENEY. R. L. ( 1992). Value-focused thinking: A path to crea1ii.e decision rnakirig. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. KELLER. L. R.. &amp; HO. J. L. ( 1988). Decision problem structuring: Generating options. IEEE Transactions on Systems. Man, a n d Cybernetics. 18. 7 15-728. KOBERG. D.. &amp; BAGNALL. J. (1974). The unii‘ersal lrai’clcr. Los Altos. CA:William Kaufman. Inc. KOESTLER. A. (1964). The X I olcrealion. New York: Dell. LAVERTY. F. ( 1974). Creative ideas through circumrelation. J o ~ r n a ol l Ctealit’e BChaLlioI. 8. 40-46. MACCRIMMON, K. R.. &amp; WAGNER, C. (1994). Stimulating ideas through creativity software. hlandgernent Science. 40. 1514-1532. MAIER. N. R. F. (1970). Problem solcing and creatiisity in iridiL*icfuals a n d g i o u p s . Belmont. CA: Brooks/Cole. MASON, R . 0. (1969). A dialectical approach to strategic planning. Nariagcrncnt Science, 15, 8403-8414. MUMFORD. M. D.. &amp; GUSTAFSON. S. 6. (1988). Creativity syndrome: Integration, application, and innovation. Psychological Bulletin, 103, 27-43.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="237" page="25" column="1">131</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx238">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_025.image_25.png" thmb="62pj.page_025.image_25-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="239" page="26" column="1">Idea-Generation Techniques</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="240" page="26" column="1">T.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="241" page="26" column="1">of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="242" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">NEZU. A,, &amp; D'ZURILLA. J. (1981). Effects of problem definition and formulation on the generation of alternatives in the social problem- solving process. Cognifiue Therapy and Resedrch. 5 , 265-271. NISBETT. R.. C ROSS, L. (1980). Human inlererlce: Strategies and shortcomings olsocialjudgmenf. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall. OSBORN, A. F. (1963).Applied imaginafion (3rd ed.). New York: Scribner. PERKINS. D. N. (1981). The mind's besf work. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. PERKINS. 0 . N. (1983). Novel remote analogies seldom contribute to discovery. Journal of Crtalivc Behavior. 17. 223-239. PRINCE, G. M. (1967). The operational mechanism of synectics.Journa1 Creative Behauior. 2. 1-13. RICKARDS. T. (1974). Problem-soluing through creatiue analysis. Essex. UK: Gower Press. SANDS, S. (1979). Techniques for creating new product ideas: Which to choose? Managernenf Decision. 17. 202-213. SCHOOLER. J. W.. &amp; MELCHER. J. (1995). The ineffability of insight. In S. M. Smith, T. 8. Ward, &amp; R. A. Finke (eds.), The creaLiile cognition approach (pp. 97-133). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. SMITH, S. M. (1995). Fixation, incubation, and insight in memory and creative thinking. In S. M. Smith. T. B. Ward, &amp; R. A. Finke (Eds.). The creaticv cognifion approach (pp. 135.156). Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. SOUDER, W. E., &amp; ZIEGLER, R. W. ( 1977). A review of creativity and problem solving techniques. Research Management, 20. 34-42. STEIN, M. I. (1974). Slimulating creatiuify: Volume 1. IndiLvidrial procedures. New York: Academic Press. STEIN, M. I. ( 1975). Stimulating crealiuity: Volume 2, Group procedurcs. New York: Academic Press. STEIN, M. 1. (1989). Memory and creativity. In J. A. Glover, R. 8. Ronning. E C. R. Reynolds (eds.). Handbook ofcreafiLiity (pp. 163-176). New York: Plenum Press. STRAUSS, A. L. (1987). Qualitafiue analysis for social scientists. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press. SCICHMAN, L. A. (1987). Plans and situated acfions: The problem of h urnan?rnachine cornrn u n ication. C a m bridge, CIK: C a m bridge Universiiy Press. TATSUNO, S. M. (1990). Creafed in Japan: From imitators to world-class innoualors. New York: Harper &amp; Row. TAYLOR. D. ( 1969). Creative design through functional visualization.Journal of Creafive Behauior. 3. 122-127. TAYLOR, J . W. (1961 ).How to create ideas. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice- Hall. THOMPSON, C. (1992). W haf a great idea! New York: Harper. VANGUNDY. A. B. (1987). Creative problem soluing. New York: Quorum Books. VANGUNDY. A. B. ( 1988). Techniques of sf rucf urcd problem soloing (2nd ed.). New York: Van Nostrant Reinhold. VOLKEMA. R. J. (1983). Problem formulation in planning and design. Management Science. 29,639-651.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="243" page="26" column="1">132</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx244">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_026.image_26.png" thmb="62pj.page_026.image_26-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="245" page="27" column="1">Journal o f Creative Behavior</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="246" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">VON OECH. R. (1992). Cre, tiue wh ck pack. Stamford, C T U.S. Games Systems. WALLAS, G. (1926). The a r l of thoughf. New York: Harcourt. WARFIELD, J: N.. GESCHKA, H.. G HAMILTON, R. (1975). Methods olidea m a n a g e m e n l . Columbus, OH: The Academy for Contemporary Problems. WERTHEIMER. M. (1982). Producliue thinking (enl. ed.). Chicago: University of Chicago Press. WHITING, C. S. (1958). Creafiue lhinking. New York: Reinhold.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="247" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Gerald F. Smith, Department of Management. College of Business Administration, University of Northern Iowa. Cedar Falls, IA 50614-0125</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="248" page="27" column="1">133</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx249">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62pj.page_027.image_27.png" thmb="62pj.page_027.image_27-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
