<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>00bdaff722b66fddee50260ebdb0e7bbd2a397d43cc7d20f71683aae1a6b399b</job>
    <base_name>62lx</base_name>
    <doi>10.1080/014492996120049</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">This article was downloaded by: [Lancaster University Library]</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">On: 16 January 2014, At: 07:20 Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis Informa Ltd Registered in England and Wales Registered Number: 1072954 Registered office: Mortimer House, 37-41 Mortimer Street, London W1T 3JH, UK</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology Publication details, including instructions for authors and subscription information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/tbit20" id="3">http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/tbit20</ext-link></region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx5">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62lx.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62lx.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="6">User involvement in the systems design process-a practical guide for users</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors"><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="7">Leela Damodaran Published online: 08 Nov 2010.</name><aff id="8">:</aff><aff id="9">08</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="16">Leela Damodaran (1996) User involvement in the systems design process-a practical guide for users</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="17">Behaviour &amp; Information Technology</name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name id="18">DOI: 10.1080/014492996120049 http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/</name><aff id="19">10</aff></contrib></contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">To cite this article:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="20">To link to this article:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="21" confidence="possible">PLEASE SCROLL DOWN FOR ARTICLE</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="23" confidence="possible">Taylor &amp; Francis makes every effort to ensure the accuracy of all the information (the “Content”) contained in the publications on our platform. However, Taylor &amp; Francis, our agents, and our licensors make no representations or warranties whatsoever as to the accuracy, completeness, or suitability for any purpose of the Content. Any opinions and views expressed in this publication are the opinions and views of the authors, and are not the views of or endorsed by Taylor &amp; Francis. The accuracy of the Content should not be relied upon and should be independently verified with primary sources of information. Taylor and Francis shall not be liable for any losses, actions, claims, proceedings, demands, costs, expenses, damages, and other liabilities whatsoever or howsoever caused arising directly or indirectly in connection with, in relation to or arising out of the use of the Content. This article may be used for research, teaching, and private study purposes. Any substantial or systematic reproduction, redistribution, reselling, loan, sub-licensing, systematic supply, or distribution in any form to anyone is expressly forbidden. Terms &amp; Conditions of access and use can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-conditions" id="22">http://www.tandfonline.com/page/terms-and-conditions</ext-link></abstract>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="24">BEHAVIOUR &amp; INFORMAT ION TECHNO LOGY , 1996, VOL . 15, NO . 6, 363 ±377</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" confidence="possible">User involvement in the systems design process ±a practical guide for users LEELA DAMODARAN HUSA T Research Institute, Loughborough University, Leicestershire LE11 1RG, UK; e-mail:1.damodaran@ lboro.ac.uk</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" confidence="possible">Abstract. Increasingly users ® nd themselves `involved’ in IT design projects. This occurs because the organizational culture of the parent organization purports to promote participation, or because structured design methods are being used which require users to play a part. In either case users who ® nd themselves required to participate in IT projects are frequently unclear about what this requires. In most organizations surprisingly little brie® ng on the users’ role in design projects is provided. Users are therefore confused about their brief and concerned about their lack of expertise in computing. Although research reports on participatory design (PD) projects abound, little coherent guidance for the key stakeholders representing users’ interests is available. The contents of this paper go some way towards ® lling the gap. Clear differentiation is made in the paper between the roles of the different players involved. Detailed guidance is provided for meeting the varied requirements of the different roles. For example, the roles of `top’ m anagement and `middle’ management in supporting user involvem ent are explored, their special responsibilities speci® ed and required actions listed. The need for an infrastructure to support user involvement and how to create one is discussed. Guidance is provided on, for example, the representation process and the factors to consider in selecting user representatives. The role of user representatives is particularly problematical and therefore receives particularly close attention. Finally guidance is given regarding the common pitfalls in Quality Assurance procedures and especially how to avoid the procedures becoming a meaningless `rubber-stamping’ exercise. The guidance presented is grounded in the extensive experience of the author in participative design processes in a wide variety of contexts including the footwear industry, a major UK government department and a telecommunications and broadcasting company.</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" page="2" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" page="2" column="1">The ® eld of participatory design (PD) is represented by a vast literature which now spans several decades, a number of different academic disciplines and traditions and which has an increasingly multi-national  ̄ avour. The concept of PD is im bued with com mitment to the ideal of dem ocracy in work organizations and to the notion that the workforce should be active participants in all <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> decisions which affect their daily working lives. The term `user involvem ent’ is sometimes used as a synonym for participatory design in a technological context. Som e practitioners however, suggest it represents a lesser goal. For exam ple, Muller and Kuhn (1993) write `Much of the Scandinavian work retains an explicit comm itment to workplace democracy in the context of technological growth and business developm ent Ð that is, direct and effective worker participation (not mere `involvement’ ) in design activities and decisions, within a trade union context’ . In similar vein Clem ent and Van Den Besselaar (1993) com m ent that `It (user participation) cannot be restricted simply to the design of information systems but inevitably brings in wider elements of working life’ . The author of this paper takes the view that effective user involvement in system design does indeed `inevitably bring in wider elements of working life’ . This phenomenon occurs because m any decisions, apparently focused upon purely technical issues are in fact socio-technical in nature. Thus, for exam ple, decisions about dialogue design m ay be concerned with specifying the sequences for data entry. The outcom e of such a decision has profound implications for job design, the nature of which will depend upon the degree of discretion left to the user in perform ing the data entry tasks. The informed user involved in such a decision is thus in a position to in ̄ uence highly signi® cant aspects of working life. For user in ̄ uence to be a reality with any real power however, requires a great many preconditions and requirements to be met. In other words, empowering the user is very demanding and complex and can only be achieved by carefully structuring the organizational context. The author’ s experience of PD and user-centred design in contexts as diverse as, for example, a footwear manu- facturing company (Dam odaran 1977a and Dam odaran et al. 1977b) a major government department (Damodaran 1991, Harker 1993) and a `high-tech’ telecommunications and<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> broadcasting company (Damodaran 1994) suggests that a highly integrated strategic approach is essential to the success of the participative process. Further there is ample evidence (Damodaran 1992) to suggest that users need to be well- informed and to have real understanding of the principles underlying the processes in which their active involvement is sought. Mechanistic following of prescribed procedures without an understanding of the intended goals of the whole process is likely to prove futile at best and probably expensive and wasteful as well. Thus the strategy for PD must include the infrastructure (resources and capability) to promote learning and understanding by all of the participants. The strategy must also include the clear allocation of responsibilities to key stakeholders and clarity regarding the respective roles of the different players. The need for appropriate formal bureaucracy is supported by other investigators. Clement and Van Den Besselaar (1993) note `W hile the relationships within the group may be relatively inform al and  ̄ exible, protecting it from the outside may require formal contracts and bureaucratic structures, such as steering com m ittees and advisory panels. Re sources such as tim e, space, relief workers, and access to technology will need to be negotiated, with some control over these residing within the project group itself ’ . Given the plethora of reports on PD projects it may be thought that any further guidance on how to conduct the PD process would be super ̄ uous. An exam ination of recent literature reveals that this is not the case. There are frequent references to the signi® cance of the organizational context in PD , but rather less consideration is given to address the question of how to tailor the context to support user-centred processes. Ad hoc advice is not in short supply. Clement and Van Den Besselaa r (1993) draw from their study of PD projects a number of lessons for future projects. They report that, since PD is a com plex process which is highly dependent on speci® c organization contexts, there can be no `programm atic solutions’ . They proceed to comm ent that `Considerable improvization informed by a holistic understanding of local conditions will always be necessary. Initiators should expect the process to involve juggling m any items and balancing com peting dem ands’ . The initiator is then advised to establish an animator or group of animators; to achieve greater bureaucracy; and to seek the support and involvement of middle and top managers. The speci® c observations and general guidance offered are undoubtedly valid and are congruent with the author’ s experience. However they only address the initiator of a PD process Ð just one of many stakeholders in the process. Similarly Bjerknes (1993) offers advice, again sound, which assum es only two categories of participants; users and system experts. These examples of fragm ented advice appear to typify the published literature. Apart from well- established and valuable techniques incorporated in the ETH ICS approach (M umford 1983) there is a dearth of<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> guidance to support the multiplicity of user roles which feature in participative processes. This paper makes a contribution towards ® lling the gap. The guidance presented here was form ulated in response to the need to support users in large IT projects in UK government departm ents (where often there are structured design methods which require users to play a part). The contents were however inform ed by the author’ s experience of user-centred design in the widely differing contexts referred to earlier. As simply involving users does not guarantee their in ̄ uence in the IT development process, the practical steps required to achieve user in ̄ uence in IT design, development and implementation are described in detail in sections 3 and 4.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="30" page="2" column="2">0144-929X/96 $12.00 1996 Taylor &amp; Francis Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="31" page="3" column="1">364</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="32" page="3" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="35" page="3" column="2">2. Basic issues of user involvem ent</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="36" page="3" column="2">2.1. Context of user involveme nt</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">2.1.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" page="3" column="2">For nearly two decades m any information technology (IT) system s have failed to deliver the bene® ts expected by the users. Inadequate involvement of users in the design process is cited as a m ajor factor contributing to this shortfall between expectation and reality. All approaches to system design involve users in the design process. The difference between the various approaches lies in the degree to which users are able to in ̄ uence the system design (e.g., with SSA DM, Learmouth and Burchett, Structured Data Analysis, etc, users are involved as providers of information to the project team). In these m ethodologies users make a substantia l contribution to the project but often do not in ̄ uence key decisions. The danger remains, therefore, that the eventual IT developm ent will fail to re ̄ ect adequately real hum an and organizational needs. Disenchantm ent and two decades of experience of IT failing to deliver the expected rewards have led to increasing attempts to involve users in a m ore in ̄ uential role. Form s of involvement can be broadly characterize d as falling som ewhere on the continuum represented in ® gure 1.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="39" page="3" column="2">2.2. Bene® ts of user involvement</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">2.2.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" page="3" column="2">Findings from a variety of studies (e.g. Robey and Farrow 1982) show that effective involvement in system design yields the following bene® ts: 1. Improved quality of the system arising from more accurate user requirements. 2. Avoiding costly system features that the user did not want or cannot use. 3. Improved levels of acceptance of the system. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> 4. Greater understanding of the system by the user resulting in more effective use. 5. Increased participation in decision-m aking in the organization. Much of the emphasis on user involvement stems from a concern to avoid ill-effects on users during implementation and subsequently in the norm al operation. The major premise of m ost, if not all, of the social design approaches (e.g., Checkland’ s `soft system methodology’ , `human activity method’ , ETHICS, `Sociotechnical design’ and `quality of working life’ approaches) is that without effective user involvem ent in all stages of planning and design the organization is simply storing up problems for the future. When the problems emerge post-implementation they are likely to be serious and m ore intractable because system changes becom e more expensive as the design progresses and `hardens’ . Thus there is ample cost justi® cation for addressing hum an and organizational issues earlier rather than later in any form of planned change.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="42" page="4" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="43" page="4" column="1">365</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="44" page="4" column="1">Figure 1. Forms of user involvement.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="46" page="4" column="1">2.3. Some of the pitfalls of user involvement</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">2.3.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="4" column="1">The evidence for the effectiveness of user involvem ent is both equivocal and contradictory (Hirschheim 1983). It is not suf® cient just to have participation, what is needed is effective participation. The users should be able to in ̄ uence design, not merely `rubber stamp’ it. It would appear both from the literature and from the author’ s experience that to participate in organizational decision making is insuf® cient by itself to achieve successful IT systems. The quality and experience of the participation are crucial determinants of the eventual perform ance of IT. Hirschheim (1983) observed in his study that the term participation had a variety of meanings across the organizations sam pled. He found that the term was used to describe everything from m erely inform ing the workforce about a proposed IT project to genuine user-led design. A similar ® nding was made by Levie and Moore (1984) in an international study of workers and new technology, where despite legislation (e.g. in Scandinavia) the practice of involvement was far from the ideal that one would like to see in effective participation. For user involvement to be successful from the users’ perspective requires the users to be identi® ed closely with both the process and the outcomes. There should be explicit <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> opportunity to in ̄ uence the design process, and this should be observed in the resulting design decisions for the system. Bjorn-Andersen and Hedberg (1977 : 734 ±735) succinctly describe the process as follows: `One frequent-heard argument for users’ participation in designing is that involvem ent enables people to develop realistic expectations, and that it reduces resistance to change. This argument has often a manipulative  ̄ avour and appears to pay m ore attention to users’ feelings of in ̄ uence than to their actual ability to in ̄ uence. The effects of such insincere pretences of dem ocracy are questionable and m ay well counteract their purposes of facilitating change.’ If users are to exert effective in ̄ uence on the system design process then they m ust participate in the developm ent of the mechanisms which de® ne the design decision process (Hedberg 1975). At present users who are involved in the system design process m ay ® nd themselves in one of two equally invidious positions: that of a `hostage’ , or that of `propagandist’ .<marker type="block"/> 2.3.1. The `ho stage’ role: This role was identi® ed by Hedberg (1975) and is readily observed in m any user representatives participating in the design process. Here user involvement is effectively blocked by the professional design team. Instead the potential users operate in a way that promotes `social com fort’ and mutual esteem but limits real com munication. No effective com m unication or problem- solving takes place partly because no-one wishes to disturb the peace and partly because users feel too ill-inform ed to contribute to IT decisions. Inadequate and inappropriate training may promote the hostage phenom enon since it can leave the user representatives feeling confused and inadequate as mem bers of an IT project. In these circum stances they are likely to take away the notion that there is som ething mysterious about computers and this belief may reinforce their feeling of being in a process they do not understand and cannot control, which in turn encourages them to adopt the hostage role. The hostage role is particularly damaging because it fails to deliver any of the bene® ts of user involvement while sustaining the delusion that users are represented in the design team.<marker type="block"/> 2.3.2. The `propagan dist’ role: Hedberg (1975) labels this as the `indoctrination alternative’ . In this role any potential disruption to design from user involvem ent, as perceived by the designers, is handled by exposing the user representativ es to training in systems design m ethods. On emerging from such training, the representatives often no longer represent their original group’ s perspective, but begin to adopt the designers’ view of the design process. This change in perspective can lead the<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> indoctrinated `user representative’ to com municate more with system analysis and less with other users. Over time there appears to be a tendency for such indoctrinated `representatives’ to perceive user problems and issues from an IT perspective. This is reinforced by the observation that many such representatives subsequently pursue careers as system designers. In such a role user `representatives’ fail to safeguard the needs of the constituency they were intended to represent.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="52" page="5" column="1">366</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="53" page="5" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="55" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">2.4.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="5" column="1">2.4. Need for a `us er involvement infrastructure ’ 3.1. M aking user representation work</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" page="5" column="1">Since administrative or clerical procedures have always been subject to change it is important to appreciate the reasons why the experience of change involving IT is different in its nature from previous change processes. Conventionally most clerical system s, for example, were changed in increments by those involved in the worksÐ albeit with guidance or direction from Organization and Methods (O &amp; M) experts or other specialists. W ith IT system s the responsibility for developing the new system is in the hands of a group of IT specialists. This specialization has arisen because of the com plexity and sophistication of the technology and not because it is an ef® cient, effective or desirable way to bring about change. W hilst specializ ed IT staff possess the necessary skills to construct the system architecture and develop the software they do not usually possess the knowledge and experience of the current and future users. IT staff attempt to acquire some of the required knowledge through analysing the current system and interviewing users. This is often only partially successful because users are generally placed in a purely reactive, information-providing role with the disadvantages outlined above. For users to apply their knowledge and expertise to IT development requires considerable resources to be invested in organizing and supporting a network of users with assigned roles and responsibilities, consultative procedures and user education. This paper describes and provides guidance on how to set up such a `user involvem ent infrastructure’ , which is essen- tially a structure of communications mechanisms and services necessary to support the user involvement process.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="58" page="5" column="1">3. Elements of the infrastructure</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="60" page="5" column="1">There are m any different mechanisms for involving users in the decision-making process. Some of the most common include: · Mem bership of steering/advisory com m ittees. · Mem bership of design teams. · Mem bership of problem-solving groups. · Consultation with individuals or groups. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> · Prototypes/simulations. · Quality assurance procedures. Som e project control methods such as `PRO M PT ’ or `PRINCE’ (which are used widely in the British Government Civil Service and elsew here) suggest speci® c mechanisms to ensure users are represented in IT development projects. Since with large IT developments, it will be neither appropriate nor practicable to involve all users in all decisions relating to the IT development typically some form of representation process is set in place.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="61" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">3.1.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70" page="5" column="2">Som e of the most serious limitations with user involvement arise from shortcomings of the representative structures put in place. Critical areas include: · Selection of representatives. · Support from other users (at all levels in the organization). · Training all users. <marker type="block"/> 3.1.1. Selection of represent atives: The issue of who should represent the user population on com mittees, project teams, during consultation, in system trials, etc., is a crucial one. The aim should be to ensure that those appointed are genuinely representative of the user population and possess the necessary personal attributes. Relevant factors to consider are listed in ® gure 2 but should not be regarded as exhaustive. To ensure appropriate selection of representatives it is important to appreciate why the various types of future user need to be represented. For example, `® rst level’ users or `end users’ , who will interact directly with computer terminals to help them to perform their work, will have different interests from those users who will only utilise printed output or manage the primary users. Each type of user should in ̄ uence decisions concerning design of the facilities they will use in the future. High levels of user competence and experience need to be brought to bear in the decision-making process. Often the m ost suitably skilled and experienced people cannot be spared from day-to-day operations to become representatives. W here this applies their experience must at least be available to user representatives as a necessary part of the consultative process. The dem ands of the user representative’ s role are explored further in section 3 while section 4 examines the speci® c responsibilities of the user representative.<marker type="block"/> 3.1.2. Support from other users: Even with the required attributes, the user representative can only succeed with the support of all users throughout the organizational hierarchy.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Too often the user representative is expected to shoulder the responsibilities of representing the user population without the bene® t of an appropriate infrastructure and resourcesÐ particularly tim e and relevant skills. In addition the user representative often has to operate without the clear declaration from senior managem ent that the representative is charged with doing this important job and that all other m embers of the user population are charged to assist him/her. A multiplicity of user roles exists in the user organization and these must be integrated into a user infrastructure which supports the user representative. Characteristics of the varied roles are exam ined in section 4.<marker type="block"/> 3.1.3. Training all users: For reasons already discussed it is essential to involve users in a variety of decisions associated with the IT developm ent. To enable users to be effective in a decision-making role requires that they be given relevant learning opportunities before being faced with decisions. Demonstrations of similar systems, visits to sites using a similar system, and discussion sessions provide some examples of useful learning opportunities which need to be provided. Users also need to learn about the varied issues which will be under consideration at different stages of the development process. Strategic issues for example require senior management to be aware of human and organizational aspects of proposals, as well as the economic and `business’ aspects. Job design is particularly important to consider early in the design process. At a later stage detailed dialogue design requires knowledge of basic principles in human factors such as the preference of occasional users for a menu-driven system with many prompts, while frequent users may well prefer a fast command-driven system. End-user decisions concerned with<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> siting of VDUs, training schedules or the design of user manuals require yet different expertise. W here project management and formal design methodologies (e.g. PROM PT and SSA DM) are to be applied, users need training in the relevant techniques in order to utilise available procedures to maximum advantage. Thus it is evident that users with different roles will have different learning needs. Training will need to be tailored accordingly and this is discussed again at appropriate points in the paper.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="65" page="6" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="66" page="6" column="1">367</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="67" page="6" column="1">Figure 2. Attributes desirable for user representatives.</caption>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="71" page="6" column="2">4. User roles</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="72" page="6" column="2">4.1. Users as `owne rs’ of IT</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="73" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">4.1.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="74" page="6" column="2">Users are the future owners of IT developments. It is the users and not the system providers who will be committed to using the system, managing it, paying the operating costs, maintaining it and living with the impact on job design and work organization. Users therefore have good reason to ensure that the outcomes of IT developments are acceptable and desirable. To achieve positive outcomes requires the users to exert considerable control and in ̄ uence throughout the development process. This section addresses the varied user roles required in that process.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="75" page="6" column="2">4.2. Diversity of user rules</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">4.2.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="6" column="2">Every prospective user of a planned IT developm ent has a role to play in the developm ent process. This section indicates the variety of roles to be ful® lled by users at different grades in the user organization. Users in management grades will need to be involved in creating, maintaining and setting conditions in which user representatives and end-users can ful® l their responsibilities in the IT development process. Some users will be formally appointed as user representatives to represent the users’ interests on project steering committees, and in project teams. End-users will be involved intermittently in a variety of ways to provide information, assess proposals, evaluate products of the project team, etc. The speci® c responsibilities associated with these varied roles are exam ined in section 5.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="6" column="2">4.3. Resourc e pool of user expertise</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="79" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">4.3.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="6" column="2">The all-pervasive nature of IT m eans that widespread effects are felt even with m odest IT systems. Expertise in any organizational function is likely to be relevant at some stage of the planned developm ent. Every future user therefore needs to be regarded as a potential source of relevant expertise to the developm ent process. To re ̄ ect <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> this reality it is useful to develop the concept of a resource pool which com prises the varied skills and knowledge of all the job holders in the user organization. The notion of a resource pool fosters recognition of the differentiated areas of user knowledge which exists. Such recognition will encourage application of appropriate skills to the IT developm ent process and m itigate against assigning people on the purely pragmatic basis of availability. Recognition of the existence of such a resource pool establishes all users as being m em bers of a network of differentiated user roles. If this network is to achieve the goal of user in ̄ uence in the IT developm ent process, then it has to have a formalized infrastructure and essential resources. To appoint user representatives without establishing an infrastructure to support them is to pay lip-service to the notion of user in ̄ uence and to m iss the opportunity for effective in ̄ uence. Each grade in the organization has a role to ful® l and the rest of this section addresses these varied roles.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="81" page="7" column="1">368</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="82" page="7" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="84" page="7" column="1">4.4. `Top management’ role</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">4.4.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" page="7" column="1">4.4.1. Promoting positive attitudes to IT: As in all areas of organizational life the attitude of top m anagem ent to IT will permeate the whole organization. It is crucial for effective user involvem ent in IT that a positive and proactive view of the user role is re ̄ ected throughout the organization. This dem ands energy and resources to be devoted to IT-related activities on a continuous basis. The ® rst step in fostering a positive approach to IT requires top m anagem ent itself to develop a clear vision of what is required of it and how it should proceed. To achieve this requires an exploration of the human and organizational implications of IT and especially an awareness of the pitfalls. Sem inar and workshop sessions offer appropriate m edia for learning about the need for user involvement, the penalties of neglecting it and the available experience in how to achieve it. The expertise to present these sessions may be available in-house or may require consultant support. Gaining clarity of purpose and de® nition of its own role in the IT developm ent should be the objective of these explorations by top m anagement. It is only with a whole- hearted, keen and informed interest in the IT developm ent that users can ensure desirable and effective outcom es are achieved. It is for top management to make this clear by exam ple. Too often the only m aterial step taken by top m anagem ent in the early stages of an IT developm ent is to appoint user representatives and to regard this as the sole and suf® cient action required of them. This tempting abdication of responsibility has to be strenuously resisted. Re presentatives can only succeed to the extent that the users’ role, responsibilities and authority are appropriately constituted, supported and guided through all the stages of developm ent and implementation. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Equipped with a vision of where top management is going and what needs to be done to get there makes it possible to proceed to formulate goals, establish policy, write terms of reference for the role and mobilize the rest of the user population in a coherent and effective user involvement programme.<marker type="block"/> 4.4.2. Starting the user involvement process: An early ® rst step will need to be the selection of a number of key individuals at different levels in the hierarchy to agree collaboratively an infrastructure and a division of labour which will permit all parties to pursue the shared objective of effective user involvem ent. Again a seminar or workshop forum which provides relevant knowledge and an environm ent in which to explore the implications of user involvement is appropriate. A series of seminars/w orkshops is likely to be needed unless the IT developm ent is sm all-scale. Important objectives of these events will be to achieve a sense of m ission, to de® ne terms of reference for key users throughout the hierarchy and to formulate an agreed modus operandi. It will also be im portant to ensure that the terms of reference for the system providers oblige them to heed user concerns, and to ensure evaluation criteria are established to provide a yardstick by which to assess accepta bility of the products delivered. Early attention should be given to selecting and training user representatives. The need to provide them with the necessary resources to conduct careful investigations of the existing system and establish criteria for assessing products also merits attention at an early stage.<marker type="block"/> 4.4.3. Empowering the users: Using IT effectively requires users to understand what it can offer and to recognize its limitations. It can be very dif® cult to predict the im pact of IT from exam ining design proposals,  ̄ ow charts or data  ̄ ow diagrams. More dynamic ways of experiencing and exploring some of the technical possibilities are offered by pilots, simulations and prototyping. All these tools offer a vehicle for users to identify and then to specify their requirements to system providers. Use of such techniques should be demanded by top management as a vehicle for user involvement in the development process. The application of such techniques allows users to see the implications of different IT options and to m ake informal judgem ents on the suitability of speci® c system proposals. These techniques help to em power all levels of users to play a part in in ̄ uencing the IT development.<marker type="block"/> 4.4.4. Summary of top management role: What is required? For users to in ̄ uence IT developm ents effectively top<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> m anagem ent needs to do the following: · Create a user infrastructure which delineates clearly the roles of all users (from end-users to top management users), the communication mechanisms and the services required to support the user involvem ent process. · Formulate terms of reference for key users throughout the organizational hierarchy. · Ensure that the terms of reference for system providers place due em phasis on investigating user issues in the early stages of the development life-cycle and on the user role in the Quality Assurance process. · Select appropriate user representatives at different levels throughout the user organization to ful® l a variety of functions. · Ensure user representatives gain familiarity with PRO MPT and SS ADM where these methodologies are in use. · Ensure that the user requirement is based upon a thorough analysis of the existing system and an extrapolation of future needs. · Formulate user acceptability criteria from the data collected in investigations of the current system . · Ensure there is informed use of pilot trials, simulation exercises or prototyping techniques to promote user understanding of technical options and their relative merits. How to provide it? Top managem ent levels in the user organization m ust recognize that they have a crucial and on-going role in IT developm ents. In particular, their role requires them to take the following actions: · Explore and develop understanding of the strategic signi® cance of user in ̄ uence in IT developm ents, through the m edia of sem inars and workshops aimed at formulating the role of top m anagement , the terms of reference and the responsibilities associated with IT developm ents. · Provide a workshop forum for representativ es throughout the hierarchy to develop collaboratively an infrastructure and a division of labour, which will permit all parties to pursue the shared objective of effective user involvement. · Create an infrastructure which enables various user representatives to identify and to ful® l their responsibilities by providing opportunities for training, communications, consultation and exploration of IT options. · Ensure visibility of top managem ent com mitment to user involvem ent by allocating adequate resources (staff, ® nance and time) to the user involvem ent process.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="91" page="8" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="92" page="8" column="1">369</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="94" page="8" column="2">4.5. `M id dle managem ent’ role</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">4.5.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="101" page="8" column="2">Managers in the intermediate (middle management) grades (grades 6 and 7 in the UK civil service for example) are uniquely placed to create awareness and interest in the opportunities and pitfalls of using IT. They are also well placed to support the day-to-day functioning of user representatives. In particular they need to motivate all end-users to appreciate the responsibilities they have to ensure positive outcomes from IT developm ents. To achieve this m iddle management must provide, on a continuing basis, IT related information and tim e to discuss and digest it. <marker type="block"/> 4.5.1. Promoting consultation: Promoting consultation is a key part of the role of middle m anagem ent. The user representative will need access to a wide array of expertise to ful® l his responsibilities and cannot possibly possess all the relevant skills himself. He/she therefore needs to be encouraged to consult widely. Virtually every form of expertise in the user organization is likely to be relevant at some stage in the IT development cycle. Recognition that the organization comprises a considerable pool of resources is an important concept for middle management to promote. Any notion that for the user representative to seek assistance is to adm it inadequacy or failure should be strongly rejected. Effective consultation is the key to effective user in ̄ uence over the impact of IT. M iddle m anagem ent needs to create the conditions i.e., ensure that the relevant individuals schedule the tim e and promote the motivation and the understanding to permit such consultation to occur. The managerial role of these middle grades of managers requires them to create the environment within which organizational goals can be pursued. In the IT context the requirement is to provide the conditions in which user representatives and end-users can work together effectively in order to achieve the successful developm ent of IT. This entails application of management skills relating to planning, allocating work, m otivating people, training and com munication. These traditional management skills will be evident in the user’ s organization and are especially pertinent to the m anagem ent of technological change. The IT specialists are concerned primarily with the developm ent and delivery of the IT system and are unlikely to be able to match the user’ s com mand of traditional managem ent skills and knowledge of the user’ s organization. It is therefore im portant that m iddle managem ent apply their skills in the IT context and resist the temptation to `leave it to the experts’ .<marker type="block"/> 4.5.2. User analysis: An especially important function to be ful® lled at this level is to ensure that adequate investigation of the current form al and informal system occurs. Such an investigation involves a systematic user analysis. This<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> analysis provides the basis for formulating the criteria on which to assess acceptability of the system for its users. The analysis involves collecting and analysing information about users and about the tasks they perform. Products of the analysis inform the IT design process in technical as well as human and organizational areas. W ithout effective user analysis, mem bers of the design team would have to make assumptions about the characteristics of users and their work. Usually such characteristics are suf® ciently complex that even `inform ed’ assumptions are likely to be inaccurate and they put the basic IT developm ent at risk. It is for m iddle m anagem ent to ensure that a suf® ciently thorough user analysis has been conducted to provide valid answers to the following kinds of question:</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="9" column="1">370</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100" page="9" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Ð W ho will be affected? (this will include people who do not use the system directly). Ð Is it possible to identify just two or three m ain user categories? (based on facts such as grades of staff, possible use of system etc.). Ð W hat are the characteristics of people in each user category? (e.g. age range, com puting experience). Ð W hat are the characteristics of the task performed by each user category? (e.g. degree of guidance, am ount of hum an contact, sources of error). Ð W hat do different users like and dislike about their jobs? Ð How are the different users likely to react to the system? (which aspects will be seen as `costs’ and which as `bene® ts’ to the users?)</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" page="9" column="1">Collecting data in the user analysis process involves interviews with the users to provide factual inform ation and opinions, system atically observing work situations, and collecting relevant documentation. (The skills required for these form s of data collection, analysis and synthesis will need speci® c training if the ® ndings are to be worthwhile.) The products of a thorough user analysis provide a rich database for interrogation throughout the IT development. It provides the raw material to help formulate the following key products: · User requirements speci® cation. · Speci® cation of accepta bility criteria. · Design speci® cations for the system , jobs, organization and training. · Appropriate policies (e.g., for implementation and user involvem ent). As each of these areas is tackled it may become apparent, for exam ple, that more inform ation is needed about the users in a particular sphere of activity. User analysis can therefore be seen as a recurrent task required to meet the needs of the different stages of the system design process. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The products of user analysis are valuable in helping m iddle managers to control the developm ent process. For example, user acceptability criteria constitutes the yardstick for assessing the IT product from the users’ perspective, whether these products are proposals, sample screen formats or the eventual system. It is important to distinguish between user acceptability criteria and user acceptance criteria. User accepta nce criteria relate to the physical system (including hardware, software and docum entation). Users however m ight well ® nd an IT product unacceptable for reasons such as de-skilling effects on their jobs, reduced opportunities for com munication or decrease d job satisfaction. Such concerns associa ted with job design fall outside conventional acceptance test criteria but are crucial criteria of acceptability to the user. Thus to ensure IT systems are acceptable to users it is essential to identify from the user analysis process accepta bility criteria in order to provide guidance to the designers and to evaluate products.<marker type="block"/> 4.5.3. Summary of middle managem ent role: W hat is required? · Provide the environm ent in which user representatives and end-users can contribute to the successful development of IT. · Recognize that management skills, relating to planning, allocating work, motivating people, training, communication, etc., are essential to the effective developm ent and m anagem ent of IT in the user organization. · Resist the temptation to `leave it to the experts’ . IT experts are unlikely to have the management skills or knowledge of the users’ organization outlined above which are crucial to successful implementation of IT. · Ensure that adequate investigation of the current system occurs, covering both system analysis and user analysis. · Formulate accepta bility criteria for the planned IT development. Ensure these are included alongside the Acceptance Test Criteria. · Give special attention to job design issues and ensure that relevant specialist knowledge is obtained.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">How to provide it? · Provide an appropriate level of education, learning opportunities and training for user representatives and all users who will be involved. · Set up a consultative network throughout the user organization and in the project. · Allocate time for discussion groups/problem-solving sessions related to IT user issues during normal working hours. · Ensure that traditional management skills are applied to the IT developm ent.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="10" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="10" column="1">371</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="109" page="10" column="1">4.6. Role of user represent ative(s)</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">4.6.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113" page="10" column="1">4.6.1. User representat ives: have a m ost challenging and dem anding role in most IT developm ents. To date very little guidance or training exists to guide and support their activities. Typically they inhabit a kind of `no-man’ s land’ between the users they represent and the system provided. User representatives need a high level of interpersonal skills, the ability to persevere in dif® cult circum stances, a strong sense of mission, and a basic understanding of the technical skills involved. In order to be successful with the m ission of ensuring that users’ interests are adequately taken into account, a support infrastructure must be provided for the user representative as described in the earlier section. The other roles described in this section provide the key elements in this infrastructure. The essential requirement is to avoid isolating the user representative in his role and to ensure that other users fully support, enhance and promote his/her functioning. To characterize clearly this crucial role some of the positive and negative features usually associated with it are highlighted in ® gure 3. The guidance presented in this paper is intended to be used to enhance the positive aspects of this critical role and to minimize the negative ones by indicating the appropriate steps required to support the user representative effectively. <marker type="block"/> 4.6.2. Summary of role of user representat ive(s): W hat is required? · Understanding of the signi® cance of the role for the entire user organization. · Ability to operate independently even in a som etimes hostile environment. · Awareness of the need to consult widely. · W illingness to call on expertise of others as required. · Awareness of the need to seek support and authorisation when necessary.<marker type="block"/> Understanding of the specialized techniques and processes of IT development.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">How to provide it? · Seek training and expertise Ð espec ially in hum an and organizational aspects of IT (in the absence of off-the- shelf training modules it will usually be necessary to have customized training tailored to the needs of the individual). · Perform the bridging function between the IT experts and the `end-user’ (next section). · Ensure that clear terms of reference are agreed for the role.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="115" page="10" column="2">Figure 3. Role of the user representative.</caption>
          </region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="116" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">· Ensure that resources of time and opportunity to consult with others is provided. · Seek authority to use a wide range of resources± especially the expertise of others (both internal to the user organization and external) as the need arises. · Join or establish a support group of other user representatives to share problems and learning.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="117" page="10" column="2">4.7. Role of end-users</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">4.7.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="123" page="10" column="2">4.7.1. Every individual: who will be affected by the IT developm ent should be involved in the planning of that developm ent. This is particularly true of those who will eventually be using the planned system : the `end-users’ . To ful® l the role of end-users entails recognition that the IT system being developed will be their system . It is essential for them to be aware that their knowledge and energy are required to shape the development in accordance with their needs. Their knowledge and experience are required at different stages and for different purposes throughout the development process. The role of end-user carries the onus of responsibility for providing detailed knowledge of the user and his tasks in the user analysis <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> process and subsequently. It is im portant for end-users to appreciate that if they have knowledge and experience in a post then they are the experts on their work, whatever grade they occupy. End-users m ust be able to differentiate between the formal description, constraints, etc., of their work and the informal practices and attitudes, and be able to convey these to the user representative and others. It is also im portant for end-users to realise that however good or knowledgeable the user representative might be he/she cannot possibly know every relevant detail of all their jobs. The end-users must therefore provide such detailed information to inform the developm ent. Conveying relevant inform ation successfully requires practice to form ulate facts and ideas clearly. Discussions with colleagues can provide such practice. End-users need to appreciate that a considered and informed view is likely to be given attention by the project team whereas confused, vague or over-emotional comm ents are likely to be disregarded or dismissed as `resistance to change’ . Lack of experience and training in com munication can result in important points being excluded from the decision-making process. Training in communication skills and opportunity for practice are therefore important. In addition to providing detailed knowledge in the user analysis process, end-users may be asked to participate in Quality Assurance activities, to comm ent on proposals or m ock-up screen formats, dem onstrations, etc. W hen this occurs it is im portant for end-users to understand that the opinions they give will provide the basis for decisions which are likely to have long-lasting effects on jobs. It is therefore very important that due tim e and attention are devoted to considering issues on which views are sought.<marker type="block"/> 4.7.2. Summary of end-user role: W hat is required? · Recognition by end-users that the IT system will be theirs. · Recognition that they have an opportunity and a responsibility to ensure that the IT system m eets their needs. · Recognition that they, uniquely, possess knowledge and expertise in their area of work. · Awareness that the user representative requires support and help if he/she is to represent end-users successfully. · Awareness that the user representativ e has a com plex, demanding role with many con ̄ icts to reconcile. · W illingness to put effect into providing inform ation, making informed com ment on proposals, evaluating products, etc. · W illingness and enthusiasm to keep abreast of progress and events related to the IT developm ent. · Ability to convey clearly factual information, ideas and opinions related to the IT developm ent.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="120" page="11" column="1">372</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="121" page="11" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="124" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">How to achieve it? · Gain knowledge and understanding of the user role in the IT developm ent process. · Gain some understanding of the IT possibilities by visits to other sites, demonstrations, etc. · Ensure time is available to contribute to user analysis, product evaluation, the QA process, job design, etc. · Train in data discovery techniques.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="125" page="11" column="2">5. Responsibilities of user representatives</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" page="11" column="2">It has already been emphasized that responsibility for ensuring user in ̄ uence is exercised fully is vested in users at all levels in the user organization. Key areas of responsibility are listed below and then dealt with in more detail in subsequent sections: · Provision of detailed knowledge. · Highlighting strategic issues. · M anaging the user role. · Participating in Quality Assurance.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="127" page="11" column="2">5.1. Provision of detailed knowledge</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="128" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">5.1.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="132" page="11" column="2">Detailed knowledge is required initially in the early developm ent phases where exploration and speci® cation of the user needs is the ® rst essential step towards the design and implementation of an appropriate IT system. The quality of data collection and decision-m aking in the early stages in a project’ s life cycle (initiation, speci® cation and logical design stages in SS ADM) is re ̄ ected in a key documentÐ usually entitled the User Requirement. Responsi- bility for production of this docum ent lies with the user, or, m ore usually, with his/her representative. The quality of an IT system is in large measure determined by the quality of the User Requirem ent. The signi® cance of the User Requirem ent as a contractual document between system user and system provider cannot be overemphasized. To achieve in ̄ uence over IT development thus necessitates production of a powerful User Requirement which adequately re ̄ ects the true complexity of the users’ needs. Prototypes, simulations and pilot studies are valuable tools for assisting the users in formulation of the User Requirement. These processes provide means of communication between users and designers. They are valuable communication media because they offer users a realistic and direct experience of proposed IT designs. Users can therefore understand proposed systems features and make meaningful interpretations of the proposals instead of facing the dif® culties posed by abstract terms and representatives of data  ̄ ows etc. <marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Production of an appropriately constituted User Requirem ent requires the user population to m obilize considerable resources in collecting, analysing and presenting the necessary detailed know ledge. The user analysis process outlined above in section 3 is a key part of this important stage. (Once it has been produced relevant users m ust police the application of the User Requirement to ensure that design proceeds in accordance with the stated needs. The Quality Assurance process provides the mechanism for this policing function and is discusse d further towards the end of this paper.) The need for detailed knowledge of the users’ tasks is also required when reviewing products at the various milestones in the developm ent process. These products will vary according to the stage in the project life-cycle. In the early stages they will include proposals,  ̄ ow-charts or other representatives of the movement of data through the user organization (`data  ̄ ow diagrams’ , `entity life histories’ , for exam ple, in SS ADM terminology). At later stages the products may relate to the design of dialogues, screen formats or the design of jobs and forms of work organizations. At every stage and with every product, decisions are required which will have an im pact on the user and the user organization at a later date. Especially crucial decisions are made throughout the early stages in a project’ s life-cycle. For example, deciding which functions should be performed by the IT system and which by people is profoundly important for the quality of jobs which will result. The use of specializ ed Hum an Factors techniques such as Task Allocation procedures is required here. The user representative will need to ensure relevant specialist skills are available to support this activity. In som e areas the availability of specialist advice will not be suf® cient to inform the design decisions. It is in these areas where it will be necessary to use trials, pilots, simulations or prototypes to provide the necessary data. Expert guidance on how to plan and conduct such exercises will be essential to ensure validity of the ® ndings and to interpret the results. In other areas essential data m ay simply not have been collected and it may be necessary to initiate a data discovery process (e.g., interviewing local of® ce staff on the nature and function of checking procedures carried out as part of norm al working). In yet other instances it m ay be necessary to set up a sm all problem-solving group to identify the possible solutions to a problem and to test these options in order to determine the most desirable approach.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="130" page="12" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="131" page="12" column="1">373</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Provision of detailed knowledge: action points. W hat? · To provide detailed knowledge of their work situation to the developm ent process. · To recognize the limitations of personal knowledge and therefore undertake to consult appropriately.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">· To ensure that user input is properly representative. · To initiate a research activity where future impact is unclear (e.g. to establish a problem-solving group or work party). How? · Select relevant users (by user type, skills, functions, etc.). · Provide skilled interviewers to carry out the careful system atic data collection required to ensure that thorough analysis of the current system occurs. · Provide training in user role and in basic IT appreciation. · Participate in appropriate activities as speci® ed by the m ethodology. · Establish continuous liaison with users not assigned to project teamsÐ i.e. a bigger consultative network. · Inform/educate the whole user organization in relation to planned IT developm ents.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="135" page="12" column="2">5.2. Highlighting strategic issues</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="136" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">5.2.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="137" page="12" column="2">In m ost IT developm ents m ost users are inevitably somew hat remote from the day-to-day decision-making required in the analysis and design process. As a consequenc e many of the real im plications of design decisions m ay not com e to their notice until far too late to be averted. One of the most intellectually dem anding responsibilities of the user representatives is to be scanning the developm ent process constantly for rami® cations of potential signi® cance for the user population. W hen cause for concern is identi® ed the user representative needs to be assured of the following:</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">1. The availability of a senior user, perhaps at short notice. 2. An informed and sym pathetic hearing. 3. A willingness to use resources to check out the validity of the stated concern and to identify remedial action where appropriate.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" page="12" column="2">Where controversial or problematical issues arise which m ay require com promise on the part of the designers, the senior users are likely to be required to exert their authority in support of courses of action recom mended by the user representatives. A key factor in any debate about changes to the design or the requirement is the cost to the project Ð in resources, ® nance or delay. Only the user can evaluate this against the eventual impact on the user organization if the change is not m ade. Users will have to decide, at an appropriate level of authority, what is viable and which is preferable. Mechanisms for promoting a healthy `early-warning’ system include regular meetings of relevant users in a <marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> discussion forum. Availability of experts on key user issues such as job design to inform these discussions is im portant. Conclusions reached in the discussion sessions should be assured of a hearing by top managem ent through appropriate lines of communication.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="140" page="13" column="1">374</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="141" page="13" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Highlight strategic issues: action points. W hat? User to provide an `early-warning’ system for senior user management to ensure: · Identi® cation of potential areas of negative impact. · Discussion and resolution of controversial or critical concerns is prom oted. · The need for design changes is highlighted if serious negative im pact on users appears likely. How? · Provide a resource pool of expertise on key user issues such as job design and work organization. · Provide a forum for discussion of user issues and formulation of policy. · Provide lines of com m unication to convey user concerns to top m anagem ent throughout the development process.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="144" page="13" column="1">5.3. M anaging the user role</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">5.3.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" page="13" column="1">The `user role’ m ay involve just one or two representatives in a small developm ent or whole `user teams’ in large IT applications. W hatever the scale of the system there is a need for planning and controlling the com m itm ent of resources to the project, to the dem ands upon the various user groups and to the dem ands of the QA process. The planning process also applies to the development of appropriate skills by user representatives, by end-users needed to support them and by IT specialists. Often it is seen readily that users require an appreciation of the technology but only rarely is it recognized that IT staff require educating in the reality of existing user practices (formal and informal). Too often the IT specialists design for a theoretical and standardized situation with the result that the product does not m eet the practical realities of the user situation. A major part of the process of m anaging the user role has to be devoted to ensuring the availability of expertise in a number of different areas. These areas include, for exam ple, training, education, environm ental design, workplace lay- out, quality assurance and user analysis techniques. Some of this expertise can be provided by carefully tailored training but some will be suf® ciently specializ ed to require the use of in-house or external consultants.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" confidence="possible" page="13" column="2">Managing the user role: action points. What? · Appropriate planning and control of resources to the project. · Educate the IT specialists in the reality of existing practices (formal and inform al) in the current system. · Learn how to interpret, evaluate and com ment on IT proposals from the IT design team. · Gain necessary training/experience to participate effectively in meetings as user `ambassador’ . · Ensure attention is paid to the ergonom ics of the workplace/equipment. How? · Ensure that thorough analysis of the user situation is conducted by users and conveyed to IT design personnel. · Use rapid prototyping, simulations and pilot studies to develop understanding of IT proposals. · Conduct workshops on user role, effective com munications, etc. · Conduct workshops on ergonom ics associated with screen-based systems. 5.4. Participating in Quality Assurance</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="149" page="13" column="2">Quality Assurance (QA) is de® ned as `all those planned and systematic actions necessary to provide adequate con® dence that a product or service will satisfy given requirements for quality’ . The aim of this section is to encourage the future IT user (a) to recognize the QA process as a powerful tool for gaining in ̄ uence over the design process and (b) to utilise it accordingly. For users to be able to exert appropriate influence through the QA process requires that they understand: · W hat the QA process is about. · The importance of QA to the user. · How the user can m eet his QA responsibilities. <marker type="block"/> 5.4.1. W hat the QA process is about: The QA process is usually structured in a Quality Assurance programm e which aims to ensure that the quality and the appropriateness of the system is established cum ulatively as the system is developed . Project control m ethods such as PROMPT include the QA process as an integral part of every stage in the developm ent life-cycle. In such a process the user is required to carry out two vital functions in QA: Ð Check that products are correct, i.e., that they properly describe the current organization or what is required by the user or proposed by the project.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="150" page="14" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="151" page="14" column="1">375</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Ð `Signing off ’ those products, i.e., certifying that they describe what the user requires from the system .</region>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" page="14" column="1">The QA process involves Quality Reviews which ensure that the user is made aware of what is being developed to m eet the speci® cation. For the IT project developm ent team the review process should provide essential feedback on the acceptability of its products. How to achieve this is discussed next. The QA process requires that the project team submit the products for review and, if they m eet with the users’ approval, that a written assurance is given by the user to the effect that the system is being developed as required and that the next stage of developm ent can be embarked upon. The QA process will vary in size according to the size and com plexity of the project. Some products will need a technical review which requires skills the user is unlikely to possess and will require him to seek expert judgements. Other products can be evaluated by relevant users themselves. In sm all projects these reviews will form a linear progres- sion, with the user reviewing the key product(s) at the end of each stage and seeking assurance that technical reviews have also been carried out. W ithout this type of m ajor review the project should not progress to the next stage, where work and expenditure could be nugatory. A quality assurance programme of this type is the minim um required by PR OMPT methodology. In larger projects a hierarchical programm e of reviews is likely to be required. This should ensure that as various com ponent parts of large products are drafted or com pleted by project m embers they are reviewed by colleagues within the team or associated with the project. This may require IT specialists or users, or both. Products reviewed in this way form the building blocks from which larger docum ents can be assembled with con® dence. These larger products need to be reviewed in their turn to determine whether they are com prehensive and appropriate, and to check that the separate building blocks ® t together appropriately. The evidence of the earlier reviews provides the assurance that the components are technically sound and relevant. It can therefore be seen that a critical document such as the User Requirem ent can be built up of several com ponents which have individually been reviewed and `signed off ’ previously by members of the future user population who have the practical experience of the current system . Typically the com pleted User Requirem ent will need to be reviewed and `signed off ’ as a single entity and in large projects several different groups will have an interest in this at a high level. The sign off at this level will establish a contract between the project and the user. It is therefore important for managers with som e seniority and authority to be involved in the form al review meeting. Further, it is essential for their staff <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> to have spent a substantial amount of time reviewing the product to con® rm that it is a valid and appropriate product from the users’ point of view. Any doubts expressed need to be taken seriously and their foundation examined carefully Ð despite the pressure to conclude the stage and move on to the next.<marker type="block"/> 5.4.2. Importance of QA to the user: The preceding description of the QA process indicates that, in theory, users have considerable power to direct and indeed to halt the developm ent process if they are not convinced of the appropriateness of quality of the work done. In practice this power is rarely seized by users for a variety of reasons. Som e of the reasons relate to lack of seniority and authority of users compared with that of the IT project team m embers. For users to have a clearly de® ned and legitim ate role in QA, as required under PROMPT methodology for example, is essential but not suf® cient to ensure user in ̄ uence. W ithout an understanding of the goals and signi® cance of QA it is often the case that users go through the m otions of reviewing products and signing them off without due re ̄ ection and consideration of the im plications of their actions. The m ost fundamental point for users to understand is that the sign-off procedure is highly signi® cant since it represents a binding acceptance that the product m eets the users’ requirement of it. Too frequently the user feels pressurized into `signing-off ’ because the delay while they deliberate and re ̄ ect is likely to be seen as obstructing the progress of the developm ent. Users are often led to see their function in QA as a `rubber-stamping’ operation and are encouraged to sign-off in order that project sched ules are not disrupted. In reality this can mean that users are facilitating, often inadvertently, the developm ent of the wrong product or of a product with inappropriate features. As it is rare for users, espec ially ® rst-tim e users, to appreciate the signi® cance of QA, careful brie® ng is essential as part of the initial training provided to user representatives.<marker type="block"/> 5.4.3. How the user can meet his QA responsibilities: In order to participate effectively in the QA process the user will need an understanding of the process and training in his role. As part of user training it will be important to include educational techniques which convey an understanding of: Ð The power and signi® cance of QA. Ð The need for technical assurance. Ð The need for the user to review and accept products (at the same tim e or separately from the technical review). Ð The hierarchical approach which m ay be necessary and the im portance of the sign-off at various points. Ð The need to record and control this process. With regard to contributing to the review effectively the<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> user needs a yardstick to m easure the validity and relevance of the product, i.e. he requires evaluation criteria. Relevant criteria need to be form ulated by the user based on data collected in the user analysis process. Acceptance criteria, including acceptability factors, need to be clearly speci® ed in order that each product can be assessed and checked against them. It this way the criteria can be applied to assess acceptability of key products as the project progresses through the prescribed stages of developm ent. IT m em bers of the project team can be helped greatly by worthwhile feedback from users on the products under review. The feedback is only likely to be worthwhile and of value if users have understood the products and been given adequate time and opportunity to digest and explore the contents and their im plications. Techniques for prom oting understanding and discussion include demonstrations, `walk-through’ , pilots, prototypes and visits to sites with com parable system s in use.<marker type="block"/> 5.4.4. Participation in the QA process: action points: W hat? · Gain an understanding of the power and signi® cance of QA for the user. · Formulate acceptance criteria which include user acceptability factors. · Set up a hierarchical programme of quality assurance and reviewers.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="157" page="15" column="1">376</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="158" page="15" column="1">L. Damodaran</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="161" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">How? · Acquire training in the QA process which emphasizes for example the signi® cance of the `sign-off ’ of key products. · Use data from current systems surveys to generate user acceptability criteria. · Select reviewers from appropriate levels in the hierarchy to ensure that valid assessm ent occurs. · For key end-of-stage reviews ensure involvement of an appropriately senior user who is well-briefed on the work com pleted to date.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="162" page="15" column="1">6. Discussion and conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="164" page="15" column="1">The paper provides a practical guide to m eeting the com plex dem ands associated with effective user involvem ent. The rewards of participation are high and so too are the costs of adequately resourcing and managing the process. Given the problematic nature of user involvem ent, fraught with dif® culties and offering uncertain outcom es, it is not surprising that the subject is treated with cynicism and som etimes even derision. However, the cumulative costs of failure to involve users in IT projects on a national scale is <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> probably incalculable. The sense of persistent disappointment with technology can only be eroded gradually by ensuring that user issues are clearly on the agenda for all advanced technological projects. User issues cannot be on the agenda in any m eaningful way without the active involvem ent of users in all stages of the planning and developm ent of technical system s. In particular, user issues need to be addressed at top management level since that is where policy and strategy are decided and resource allocations are agreed (Dam odaran 1994). The requirement for the future is to develop organizational strategies which incorporate user involvem ent principles in all areas of corporate life. The im mediate stepping stones to achieving that future goal are the application and testing of the guidance presented here and elsewhere in order to prom ote genuinely user-centred IT strategies.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="165" page="15" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="166" page="15" column="2">B JERKNES , G. 1993, Som e PD advice, Communications of the ACM, 36, 39.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="167" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">B JORN -A NDERSEN , N. and H EDBERG , B. 1977, Designing information systems in an organisational perspective, in P. L. Nystrom and W. H. Starbuck (eds) Perspective M odels of Organisation. TIM S Studies in the M anagement Sciences (Amsterdam: North-Holland).</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="168" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">C LEMENT , A. and V AN D EN B ESSELAAR . 1993, A retrospective look at PD projects, Communications of the ACM, 36, 29 ±37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L. 1977a, Managerial learning needs for effective employee participation, HUSA T M emo 146.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L., H OCKEY , R. and I DE , C. 1977b, Shoe room study report, HUSAT Memo 135.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L. and E ASON , K. D. 1982, Design procedures for user involvement and user support, in M. Coombs and J. Alty (eds) Computing Skills and the User Interface (London: Academic Press), 373 ±388.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L. 1991, Towards a human factors strategy for information technology, in B. Shackel and S. J. Richardson (eds) Human Factors for Informatics Usability (Cambridge University Press), 291 ±324.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L. 1992, Integrating hum an factors principles into a version of SSADM: the practice and the problems. Invited paper to DTI seminar on Human Factors in the System Design Life Cycle, London, June, HUSAT Memo 592.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">D AMODARAN , L. 1994, Development of a user-centred IT strategy: a case study. HUSAT M emo 604.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">E ASON , K. D. 1988, Information technology and organisational change (London: Taylor &amp; Francis).</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">H ARKER , S. 1993, User participation in prototyping, Communications of the ACM, 36, 77.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">H EDBERG , B. 1975, Computer systems to support industrial democracy, in E. Mum ford and H. Sackman (eds) Human Choice and Computers (Amsterdam: North-Holland).</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">H IRSCHHEIM , R. A. 1983, Assessing participative systems design: some conclusions from an exploratory study, Information &amp; Management, 6, 317 ±327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" confidence="possible" page="15" column="2">L EVIE , H. and M OORE , R. 1984, The Control of Frontiers, W orkers</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="16" column="1">and New Technology: Disclosure and Use of Company Information (Oxford: Ruskin College). M ULLER , M. J. and K UHN , S. 1993, Introduction to participatory design, Communications of the ACM, 36, 24 ±28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">M UMFORD , E. 1983, Designing human systems for new technology (Manchester Business School).</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="16" column="2">R OBEY , D. and F ARROW , D. 1982, User involvement in information systems development: a con ̄ ict model and empirical test, Management Sciences, 28, 73 ±85.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="16" column="1">Users guide to involvement in design</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="181" page="16" column="1">377</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
