<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>15dbce13e372cab32041c50d477fff29e6c2586093d7fd10bb28d43ea9406244</job>
    <base_name>62et</base_name>
    <doi>10.1016/j.apergo.2010.09.006</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect Applied Ergonomics</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx3">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62et.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62et.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/apergo</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">Participatory ergonomics in design processes: The role of boundary objects</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">Ole Broberg</name>
          <aff id="7">*</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Vibeke Andersen</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">Rikke Seim</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <footnote class="DoCO:Footnote" id="19" page="1" column="1">* Corresponding author. Tel.: þ45 4525 6033.</footnote>
      <region class="unknown" id="10">DTU Management Engineering, Technical University of Denmark, Building 425, DK-2800 Lyngby, Denmark a r t i c l e i n f o a b s t r a c t</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="11">Article history: Received 15 April 2010 Accepted 14 September 2010 Keywords: Participatory ergonomics Design processes Boundary objects</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="12" confidence="possible">The aim of this paper is to introduce the concept of boundary objects in order to better understand the role of objects in participatory ergonomics (PE) design processes. The research question is: What characterizes boundary objects in PE processes? Based on two case studies, we identify eight characteristics of boundary objects and their use, which make them particularly useful in PE design processes. These characteristics go beyond the object itself and extend into the context of their use. We argue that the selection of boundary objects in PE processes is of great importance, since different objects enable workers’ participation and collaborative design in different ways. The framework developed may serve to provide criteria to guide practitioners and intervention researchers in the selection of objects to facilitate a PE process. The paper concludes with a list of recommendations for ergonomic practitioners that are based on the framework. Ó 2010 Elsevier Ltd and The Ergonomics Society. All rights reserved.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Introduction">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="13" page="1" column="1">1. Introduction</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="1" column="1">Participatory ergonomics (PE) has become a widespread field of research and practice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Haines et al. (2002)</xref> have developed a conceptual framework for understanding PE. Seven dimensions are identified, each with categories explaining its range. The dimension or topic (e.g. “Focus”) has the following categories: “Designing equipment or tasks”, “Designing jobs, teams or work organization”, and “Formulating policies or strategies”. This framework is very useful for researchers in understanding specific PE schemes. For practitioners it may serve as a reflective tool when designing PE schemes in companies. We argue, however, that the framework would benefit from a clearer distinction between two basic topics addressed in PE. The first topic is problem solving in a current production and workplace, and the second topic is the design and planning of a completely new installation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Kuorinka (1997)</xref> makes this distinction, pointing to the first topic as the most common in PE, but also acknowledging the other one. In an analysis of user-centered design, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="16" class="deo:Reference">Eason (1995)</xref> also widens the topics of PE to include: “.establishing design processes in which the end users themselves can influence the design so that it is compatible with their goals and beliefs, etc.”. This second topic seems more widespread today. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="17" class="deo:Reference">Sundin et al. (2004)</xref> claim that it is not enough to improve workplaces and production systems</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">E-mail addresses: <email id="20">obro@man.dtu.dk</email> (O. Broberg), <email id="21">vian@man.dtu.dk</email> (V. Andersen), <email id="22">seim@man.dtu.dk</email> (R. Seim). 0003-6870/$ e see front matter Ó 2010 Elsevier Ltd and The Ergonomics Society. All rights reserved. doi:10.1016/j.apergo.2010.09.006</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx24">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62et.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62et.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" page="1" column="2">themselves; it is also necessary to involve “the earlier step that affects the production system, i.e. the product design”. They coin the term ‘participatory ergonomics design’ for such activities. In line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Sundin and Medbo (2003)</xref>, we find that the PE framework of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Haines et al. (2002)</xref> would benefit from introducing a “Tools and methods” dimension. Such a dimension should include tools and methods for participatory ergonomics design. The focus on design and planning of new installations or production systems as a goal for PE triggers a new question: How can workers and other workplace end-users participate in setting up measures for ergonomics, when the new workplace does not exist? This question is about representations of workplaces and work processes in design processes. If the ergonomist has the role of guiding the PE process, he also has to consider what kinds of representations are useful in the design process. Studies of PE processes indicate that quite a number of different kinds of objects are used to represent features of the non-existing workplace and work process in design processes. By objects, we initially refer to such different things as written documents, drawings, prototypes, and CAD systems. The representations constitute means of communication and are enablers of participatory design processes. For an ergonomist guiding a PE process, the involvement of objects should make it easier for the workers or workplace users to participate in the design process. This raises the question of whether some objects are better than others for doing this job. In this study, we introduce the concept of ‘boundary objects’, which was originally developed within the Science and Technology Studies field. Boundary objects can translate meaning across different knowledge domains and<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> work practices. This ability is highly sought in PE to facilitate design processes involving workers, designers, and ergonomists. The aim of this paper is to identify and explore the role of boundary objects in PE processes. The question in focus is: What characterizes boundary objects in PE processes? A characterization scheme can be a basis for including tools and methods in Haines et al.’s PE framework. In the following, we first introduce the concept of boundary objects. Second, we report the findings of a search to identify objects in PE processes. Third, objects fulfilling the requirements for boundary objects are placed in one of five categories. Fourth, we present our own empirical findings from two PE case studies in which boundary objects played an important role. Finally, based on a grounded theory approach, we develop a characterization of boundary objects in PE design processes and propose a framework for how the use of boundary objects in PE processes could be conceptualized. We argue that the concept of boundary objects in PE processes is contextual, and that the ergonomist needs to actively consider their selection and the stage at which they are to be used.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="28" page="2" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="29" page="2" column="1">465</outsider>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="31" page="2" column="1">2. The concept of boundary objects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" page="2" column="1">The concept of boundary objects was introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Star and Griesemer (1989)</xref>: Boundary objects are objects which are both plastic enough to adapt to local needs and constraints of the several parties employing them, yet robust enough to maintain a common identity across sites. They are weakly structured in common use, and become strongly structured in individual-site use. They may be abstract or concrete. They have different meanings in different social worlds but their structure is common enough to more than one world to make them recognizable means of translation. The creation and management of boundary objects is key in developing and maintaining coherence across inter- secting social worlds. (p. 393) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (2002, 2004)</xref> analyzed the concept in studies of product development, and for him it describes objects that are shared and shareable across different problem-solving contexts. In line with Star &amp; Griesemer but without using the exact same terms, he operates with three categories of boundary objects in the product development setting: first, repositories, i.e. cost databases, CAD/ CAM databases, and parts libraries; second, standardized forms and methods, i.e. standards for reporting findings, problem-solving methods, or engineering change forms; third, objects, models, and maps, i.e. sketches, assembly drawings, parts, prototype assemblies, mock-ups, computer simulation, Gantt charts, process maps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (2002)</xref> identifies three characteristics of a tool, method, or object that makes it useful in joint problem solving at a given knowledge boundary. A boundary object: 1) establishes a shared syntax or language that individuals can use to represent their knowledge; 2) provides a concrete means for individuals to specify and learn about their differences and dependencies across a given boundary; and 3) facilitates a process where individuals can jointly transform their knowledge. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (2004)</xref> points out that boundary objects with different capacities are required, depending on the type of boundary faced. In a broader view of engineering design, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Boujut and Blanco (2003)</xref> pay particular attention to the interfaces between the actors involved in collaborative design processes. They observe the features of objects, which they, in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Vinck et al. (1996)</xref>, term ‘intermediary objects’, such as mediation, transformation or translation, and representation. Intermediary objects are representations of a final object. “They are supposed to be objects that can be communicated and exchanged between design partners. Their goal is to improve exchanges, enable viewpoints from various<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> trades to be expressed and compromises to be achieved” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Vinck et al., 1996</xref>). In this understanding, objects have an active role in the design process. A prototype is not only a new shaping of what is represented in the drawing; it is a new version of the final product. When introduced into the design process, intermediary objects are meant to communicate the intention of the author. The user of the CAD drawings is not supposed to interpret or transform the designer’s intentions, only to comply with them. The object is regarded as “closed”. On the other hand, if the object can be understood and modified by the various design partners, it is considered to be “open”. Users are not completely trapped by the object but have some degree of freedom in terms of use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Vinck et al., 1996</xref>), and it gives access to the various participants in a collaborative design process. The actors can transform the objects into shared representations. In another field of research, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Wenger (2000)</xref> introduces the concept of boundary objects in social learning theory. He also focuses on boundaries and boundary processes. Boundaries connect different communities of practice and they offer learning opportunities. Boundary objects can be intentionally promoted to help bridging between communities and facilitate learning. In the words of Wenger: “Some objects find their value, not just as artifacts of one practice, but mostly to the extent that they support connections between different practices”. Wenger suggests three different forms of boundary objects: 1) Artifacts, 2) discourses, and 3) processes. Artifacts correspond to Carlile’s second and third categories. Discourses may be the existence of a common language that allows people to communicate and negotiate meanings across boundaries. Processes include explicit routines and procedures in an organization. While boundary objects may be considered part of the daily work in engineering design and product development, it is some- thing new to bring this concept to the field of participatory ergonomics in relation to designing and planning new workplaces. Participatory processes in this area are often a series of discrete events with the aim of influencing the overall design outcome from an ergonomic point of view. Working with boundary objects is not only about representing and transforming knowledge but also about facilitating collaborative design across work practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Suchman, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Button and Harper, 1996</xref>) e collaboration and coordination, not between engineers with different specializations but between workers, management, designers, and ergonomists with very different work practices and organizational positions. This is the challenge that led us to look for objects in PE processes that might qualify as boundary objects.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="45" page="2" column="2">3. Objects in participatory ergonomics processes</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="59" page="2" column="2">The Appendix summarizes our findings across a wide range of PE studies in the literature. We had no intention of identifying all published PE studies in the period 1995 e 2008. The idea was to select a population across a period of approximately 15 years in order to identify the range of objects being used in PE studies. We recorded every object stated in a paper regardless of its importance in the study reported. The listing of PE studies in the Appendix does not distinguish between the two basic PE topics, problem solving in existing production and design and planning of new production. This means that the recorded objects are basically either part of an ergonomisteworkeremanagement or an ergo- nomisteworkeremanagementedesigner relationship. We then sorted the objects into the categories of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Carlile (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Wenger (2000)</xref>. The result is seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>. The objects in this table can be seen as potential boundary objects in PE processes. Ergonomic training and courses occur in several PE studies. This may be taken as part of the category discourses. However, we<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> choose to not consider this an object. Objects may be part of the way ergonomics are taught, but it was not possible from the studies to tell if this was the case. Furthermore, teaching or training ergonomics do not share a common language. In fact, the ergonomist is trying to teach the participants the language of ergonomics. We distinguish between prototypes and prototyping. Prototypes are physical or digital representations of a future artifact. Prototyping refers to the mutual learning process that takes place in a collaborative design setting. During the process, a prototype may be con- structed and manipulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Brodersen et al., 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> presents an overview of objects that in one way or another have been involved in PE processes. The point is that many objects appear in PE processes, but their role, way of functioning and impact are very rarely discussed in the studies. Furthermore, it is not evident whether there have been any considerations about choosing among more possible objects. This may affect their quality as boundary objects in PE processes. Only in studies focusing on computer visualizations do there seem to be deliberate discussions of their role and quality as communication tools in the PE design process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Sundin and Medbo, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Sundin et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Määttä, 2007</xref>). The next section reports empirical findings from two participatory ergonomics design studies in which objects played an important role.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="50" page="3" column="1">466</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="51" page="3" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="52" page="3" column="1">Table 1 Categorization of PE boundary objects.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="53" page="3" column="1">Object type Recorded in PE process Repositories None Standardized forms and methods Documents e Ergonomic “Blueprint” e Questionnaires e Injury reports e Lists of results and problems e Inventory e Layout diagram e Handmade sketches e Drawings e Diagrams e Tables e Meeting reports e Pareto diagram e Relations diagram e Tree diagram Breakthrough Thinking Usability tests Focus group interviews Objects, models, and maps Prototypes Test of workstations and equipment Slideshow with workplace pictures CAD Computer visualization e 2D e 3D e Animation e Mannequin e Virtual environment Scale or full-size mock-ups Production games Fishbone chart Ergonomics bulletin board Discourses Questioning situation Typical Action Situation Auto-confrontation Video recordings of work Dialogue model Processes Prototyping Test of new ways of working Visiting other departments or workplaces</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="60" page="3" column="2">4. Objects in design process interventions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="3" column="2">The two cases are from a research program that developed and tested a framework for participatory design of workplaces during the period 2005e2008. The aim was to develop methods and tools to be applied by ergonomists and other workplace professionals to stage direct participation in design and planning of new installations and production systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Binder and Brandt, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Broberg, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Seim and Broberg, 2010</xref>). The authors were part of this research program. In this retrospective analysis, we present a number of objects taking part in the intervention and the context in which the objects were used. The research program was based on intervention studies in two organizations: an industrial manufacturer and a public administration office. The industrial manufacturer was to implement a new production technology. Engineering designers, workers, management, and ergonomists were involved. In the public administration office, three departments were being merged, moving from cell offices into an open-plan office, and implementing new ways of working. Architects, workers, management, human relations people and ergonomists were involved. The interventions were aimed at facilitating a collaborative design process for the future work and workplace. Special emphasis was placed on developing and testing methods that would make it easy for the workers to articulate their concerns and wishes and to participate in design activities. The format for the interventions was a workshop series in which different interactive methods and tools were applied: workbooks, layout design game, use scenarios, future workplace assessment, photo safari, and the dream office. The researchers, together with ergonomists and other workplace professionals from the two organizations, took on the role of facilitators and workshop leaders. Other researchers in the team evaluated the process of intervention and the outcomes of the workshops. The data for the cases were collected over a 12-month period, and included interviews and observations. We present first a brief overview of the context in which objects were used. Then, we present the objects in detail.</region>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="65" page="3" column="2">4.1. The intervention context</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="69" page="3" column="2">In the industrial manufacturer company, we accomplished two workshop series, each consisting of two workshops. The first series focused on the layout of the production facility in which the new technology was to be installed. The main object was a layout design game. As a warm-up, the workers first did a workbook session. The first workshop series was held in a meeting room in the company. The second series was based on the layout resulting from the first series and focused on work processes and ergonomics that would be used with the new technology operating in the future layout. The main objects were a 1:20 scale model and floor markings in the actual production hall. Both workshops in this second series were held in the production hall where the new technology would be installed. In the public administration office, a similar workshop series structure was used. Here, the focus is on only two objects: a photo safari and sketching the dream office. All participants considered both interventions highly successful. The workshops in the industrial manufacturer case resulted in a new design of the layout and a detailed ergonomics specification list that was agreed to by all involved actors. The public office case resulted in workplace experiments that were implemented in the existing office facilities, as well as a detailed proposal for the layout of the new open space office. The evaluation “highly successful” is based on interviews with participants after the workshops. <marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The production manager from the industrial manufacturer case stated that he was quite sure he had saved a lot of money by redesigning the layout and setting up specific ergonomic requirements. He was also quite satisfied with the methods used to involve the workers in the design process, hereby promoting ownership to the solutions. The workers stated that they really felt they contributed to the design process and that the engineers were listening to them. They found the workshop to be successful because they had a format that allowed them to act as co-designers. The design engineers, a little bit reluctant in the beginning, stated that this was a quite new experience that showed how much the workers could contribute to the design process. In the public administration office, the head of department stated that he made a good investment by letting all the personnel participate in the workshop activities. Contrary to other departments in the administration office, he was sure that his department was very well prepared for the move to the open space office and starting new ways of working. He was glad that he could specify for the architects his personnel’s wishes for the design of their new open space office. The manager of a new-way-of-working project as well as the shop steward and several workers also stated that they found the intervention successful. Another indication was the fact that the workshops resulted in new experiments of layout and collaboration in the existing office.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="67" page="4" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="68" page="4" column="1">467</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="70" page="4" column="1">4.2. Objects in the collaborative design processes</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="77" page="4" column="1">In this section, we briefly present the objects and how they were used in the workshops. Inspired by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Horgen et al. (1999)</xref>, we used workbooks with a selection of pictures from the current workplace, which workers could comment on, using colored pens (Fig.1). A three-color code was used to indicate, for example, good solution, problematic solution, and problem to be solved. The problems and solutions comprised ergonomic topics as well as production optimization topics. Workers presented their workbooks to the participants at the first workshop; they included design engineers, managers, and ergonomists. In the layout design game, a game board with a blueprint of the new facility is in the middle of the room at a workshop meeting.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Moveable bricks in different colors represent machines, equipment, and installations. Each participant in turn manipulates the bricks on the game board and briefly explains the idea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 2</xref>). The game explores different layout possibilities through “what if .” experiments at the game board, and the impact of each on ergonomics and production issues. Use scenarios were applied in two versions. In the first, the work processes and the spatial workplace were simulated with the help of a 1:20 scale model of the new facility, with moveable machine models and LEGO figures. We also used a kind of mock-up based on floor markings in the actual production hall where new machines were to be installed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Fig. 3</xref>). The floor markings indicated machines, walls and doors. Different production episodes were played out, as if the participants were actually working with the new technology in the new facility. All participants were active in reflecting upon what worked and what should be redesigned. In the second version, the same use scenario setup was applied for a future workplace assessment, where the ergonomist went on a virtual walk-through guided by the operators of the projected new facility. This event identified ergonomic and safety and health factors that had not been recognized previously. In a photo safari, four teams of workers from the public administration office, armed with a digital camera, went to visit four organizations with open space offices. They took pictures and conducted short dialogues with people. After returning, each team presented a selection of photos at a workshop and explained what they liked and disliked, and what the impact could be for design of their future workplace. In the dream office session, teams of workers sketched their dream office as a poster, sometimes using allegories to explain the idea. The sketches included ideas of physical layout as well as work organization issues. The sketches were presented to the other workshop participants and discussed.</region>
          <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
            <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62et.page_004.image_03.png" thmb="62et.page_004.image_03-thumb.png"/>
            <caption class="deo:Caption" id="74" page="4" column="1">Fig. 1. A workbook filled in with comments.</caption>
          </region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="4" column="2">5. Characteristics of the boundary objects</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="4" column="2">The five objects presented in the previous section were tested as tools in a kind of participatory design process, which in the future could be guided by an ergonomist. The objects used in the two cases functioned as boundary objects, and according to participant <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> interviews, they were considered by all parties to be doing a good job. In order to find out why they are doing a good job, we will characterize these objects and their context of use. The five objects and their context of use were analyzed with inspiration from a grounded theory approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Corbin and Strauss, 2008</xref>). The data material used for coding were four-fold: 1) Field notes from observations of the objects “in action” in workshops; 2) the researchers’ subsequently written description of the setting and the process that took place in the workshops; 3) video recordings of<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the workshops; and 4) transcripts of interviews with participants after the workshops. This material was selectively coded using the guiding questions: What characterizes the objects and their use context? What are the objects able to do? From this analysis, the following eight characteristics emerged. 1. The objects do not come ready made. They need to be created through the actions of the participants. They are objects-in-the- making. The workbook has no meaning before the workers have drawn and commented on the pictures. The blank blueprint layout<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> cannot be understood before the participants have furnished it with bricks representing machines, walls, equipment and the like in a specific configuration. The use scenarios are inherently actions by the participants. The photo safari forces the participants to think about which pictures from an unknown workplace are interesting and why. A blank piece of paper has no meaning before a team of workers has drawn their dream office. If we compare the objects in this analysis to some of the objects listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>, the latter seem to be more like facts or at least ready-made objects. This applies for example to injury reports, diagrams, tables, drawings, meeting reports, and inventories. These objects may of course be discussed, but they do not in themselves invite to any sort of design action. 2. The objects in the two cases have this capacity. They have built-in affordances to make a design develop or to articulate what is good and bad design. Affordances are the possibilities for action provided by the environment. The bricks in the layout design game are interaction instruments for the participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Kaptelinin and Nardi, 2006</xref>). By manipulating the bricks they make a design action. When a participant places a brick, he is “forced” to explain why this is good design for him. If he moves a brick placed by another participant, he has to explain why it was bad design that has to be changed. 3. Some of the objects e the layout design game, the use scenarios, and the dream office e are flexible and malleable in a way that makes it possible to begin “rapid prototyping” with the new workplace. In the layout design game, it is very quickly possible to explore the question: “What if we place the machines in this way?” In the use scenario, it is possible to illustrate and reflect upon the question: “How about doing the work sequence in this way?” The capacity to test different configurations quickly contrasts with CAD drawings and computer simulations, which require time- consuming programming or other work with the software before an alternative can be presented. CAD technology and computer simulations of workplaces are developing quickly and can of course be used in PE processes. Using such objects, however, will set-up another participatory process that is characterized by a ‘visualiza- tion delay’, when participants make a design move, and by the need for participation by CAD specialists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Pedersen, 2010</xref>). 4. The boundary objects require rules and instructions for their use. For example, the workbook: use the red pen for problems, the green one for good design; the layout design game: manipulate the bricks after turn and give a short explanation when you move bricks; the use scenario: act out specific sequences of work in the new production system, so we can examine ergonomics in the control room, and take part in reflections; the photo safari: take pictures of things you like or dislike, of designs related to how citizens are met in the office etc. 5. A facilitator of the events selected the boundary objects, developed the rules and instructions, and guided the workshops in which the objects were used. 6. The boundary objects are used in discrete events (i.e. workshops), under the guidance of a facilitator who has developed the rules and instructions. This setup establishes a temporary learning space in the organization. The guidance and rules and instructions help this temporary space to some extent to dissolve the daily organizational structures, roles, and politics in which participants are embedded. This setup enables a collaborative design process. It promotes all participants into a “design mode”, rather than a “negotiating mode” based on daily conflicts of interests. The objects become boundary objects in a learning process between different communities of practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="94" class="deo:Reference">Wenger, 2000</xref>). In both organizations, we were aware of minor conflicts and disagreements between management and workers and between different groups of workers. This awareness was based on interviews and our<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> presence in the organization for observations or workshops. The evidence that the “design mode” was prevailing is based on the observation that these conflicts never became an issue during the workshops. There were some minor remarks but never in a way that derailed the collaborative design process. 7. The location of the boundary object needs attention. The layout design game was played out in the company’s meeting room in the administration building. This is a very familiar environment for design engineers and managers, but for the workers it was unfamiliar. In contrast, the use scenarios took place in the production hall. Here, the workers were playing at home and the design engineers away. The location issue leads to a general consideration about whether the use of boundary objects can be embedded in the workplace and in work practices that are to be redesigned. 8. The boundary objects themselves become an output from participatory events. They articulate a piece of design that has been materialized and can then be circulated in the organization, also in the ongoing design process. When all participants agree on the new layout or when a compromise has been reached, it can be seen directly on the game board; the bricks on the game board are frozen in a specific configuration. Such materialized outcomes from participatory events may better support the results being taken into the further design process. They may even have a political character in the ongoing design process. Workers can physically point to the ‘frozen’ boundary object and present it to other actors in the organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Henderson, 1999</xref>). The findings of this analysis are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="80" page="5" column="1">468</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="81" page="5" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62et.page_005.image_04.png" thmb="62et.page_005.image_04-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="83" page="5" column="1">Fig. 2. The layout design game.</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62et.page_005.image_05.png" thmb="62et.page_005.image_05-thumb.png"/>
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="87" page="5" column="1">Fig. 3. A use scenario playing out in the production hall.</caption>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="89" page="6" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="90" page="6" column="1">469</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="96" page="6" column="2">Table 2 Conceptualization</caption>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="97" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">processes.</region>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="98" page="6" column="2">of boundary objects in participatory ergonomics design</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="Tx99">
          <content>
            <h1 class="table"> processes.</h1>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="6">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Attribute</td>
                  <td class="table"> Characteristics</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> The boundary object</td>
                  <td class="table"> Object-in-the-making Built-in affordances Flexible and malleable</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> The context of use</td>
                  <td class="table"> Facilitator stages and guides Rules and instructions Temporary learning space Location of workshops</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> End product</td>
                  <td class="table"> Materialized outcome</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="100" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">Attribute Characteristics The boundary object Object-in-the-making Built-in affordances Flexible and malleable The context of use Facilitator stages and guides Rules and instructions Temporary learning space Location of workshops End product Materialized outcome</region>
        </region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="6" column="2">6. Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" page="6" column="2">Based on two intervention case studies, we have identified eight characteristics of boundary objects and their use. It is an important point that these characteristics go beyond the object itself towards the use context and the outcome of applying the objects in a PE design process. Thus, we have a tentative framework for boundary objects in a PE design process, as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref>. Such a framework may be a contribution to a new “tools and methods” dimension in the PE framework of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Haines et al. (2002)</xref>. The selection of objects as boundary objects in PE processes is of great importance, since different objects enable workers’ participation and collaborative design in different ways. The framework can serve better understanding of the role of boundary objects in PE processes and provide some criteria for practitioners and intervention researchers to guide the selection of objects to facilitate a PE process. Ergonomists taking part in PE design processes have to make sure that all participants are able to contribute to the design process. When it comes to design of new workplaces and production systems, it may be difficult for the future workplace users to contribute, if the representations of the future design are solely in<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> the language of engineers and architects. Boundary objects are needed that can create a common language, which allows all participants’’ knowledge and ideas to be represented. Focusing on PE design, it is also important to identify boundary objects that have the ability to act as design objects. They must be objects-in- the-making. The notion of closed and open objects clearly touches on this. We argue that closed objects are primarily meant to transfer the intention of one designer to another. A CAD drawing is the specification for building a prototype. The drawing is not supposed to be interpreted by the prototype builder; it is supposed to be trans- ferred accurately into a prototype. If a CAD drawing is used as an object in a PE design process, it would only invite the participants to comment on it. The engineer or architect can of course afterwards change it, but in the PE design event, it is only possible to comment on this object. We argue that open objects, on the other hand, are not intended to transfer but to allow a transformation of the participants’ different design ideas. The participants in a PE design process can design with such objects. The participants in a collaborative event can transform an open object into a shared representation of the future workplace or production system. For an ergonomist with the role of facilitating a PE design process, the following guidance on using the framework may be useful: 1. Situational awareness is required when planning a PE design process. What is going to be designed in the technical or architectural design process? Who are the designers? What is open to design or redesign in the process? In what stage of the overall design process is the PE design events placed? What are the goals in setting up PE design events? Who should participate? 2. Organize the PE design approach in a number of inter- connected workshops with participants from management, workers, and designers (engineers, architects and others). Be aware that PE design workshops are just one input to a more technically or architecturally oriented design process continuing for a longer period. Make sure that management is committed to integrate results from the workshops into the ongoing design process. Set-up rules and instructions for the PE design workshops that promote<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> setting the participants in “design mode” instead of “negotiating mode”. 3. Boundary objects in PE design processes should be selected on the basis of the understanding that they also have to act as design objects enabling the participants to design-with and not just comment on. Do not use objects that are only intended to transfer a design specification accurately e and which the participants are only asked to comment on. The objects have to be flexible and malleable in the workshop situation. Even if a trained CAD programmer can change a 2 D drawing, this is not flexible. It does not invite (afford) design moves. The best-suited objects allow playing out “what if .” experiments of the future design. In this way, different scenarios of the future workplace can be tested instantly in a PE workshop. What originally is a closed object may be changed into a more open object. Using transparent paper makes it possible to design a new layout to superimpose on a CAD drawing of a production layout. Or the drawing can be translated into a rougher floor plan in which the equipment and walls are bricks that can be easily moved by the participants. 4. Design objects are manipulated during the workshops, generating a potential new design of the future workplace in a collaborative design process. It is recommended that at the end of PE workshops these design objects are in a tangible design format that can be circulated into the ongoing design process, as a starting point for a more technical architectural design process. Finally, it is very important that the participants in the PE process can subsequently see how their contribution is incorporated into the final solution. When workers are invited to join a PE process, they have legitimate expectations to be taken seriously.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="7" column="1">470</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109" page="7" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="114" page="7" column="1">Authors PE Topic Organizational setting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Garmer et al. (1995)</xref> Automotive assembly plant Co-education as support for user participation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Garrigou et al. (1995)</xref> Design of two printing plants Follow-up group Working groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Nagamachi (1995)</xref> Requisites of PE</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Acknowledgements">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="116" page="7" column="2">Acknowledgments</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" page="7" column="2">We gratefully acknowledge the financial support of the Danish Working Environment Research Foundation for carrying out this work (Grant 19-2004-09).</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="118" page="7" column="2">Appendix 1</h1>
        <region class="unknown" id="119" page="7" column="2">Participants Object Candidates Operators, manufacturing Dialogue model engineers Working groups: Drawings Personnel manager, project Diagrams manager, members of the Questioning situation safety and health Typical action situation committee, operators The future activity Occasionally: engineers, Meeting reports architects, equipment suppliers 2 D mannequin Fishbone chart Pareto diagram Relations diagram Tree diagram Video recordings</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="120" page="8" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="121" page="8" column="1">471</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Appendix (continued ) Authors PE Topic Organizational setting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Wilson (1995)</xref> Crane control room design Design Decision Group Solve ergonomic problems Problem-Solving Group Procedure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Kuorinka (1997)</xref> Review of techniques used n.a. in PE projects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Haims and Carayon (1998)</xref> Public service agency Action research team Implementation of an ‘in-house’, Ergonomic coordinators continuous improvement PE program Develop theoretical model and related design principles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Laitinen et al. (1998)</xref> Engineering company Project groups in each Reduce ergonomic risks by focusing department on tools and materials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Kadefors and Forsman (2000)</xref> Automotive workshop Video recorded. Ergonomic evaluation of complex Operators evaluate work sequences ergonomics at the film <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Haines et al. (2002)</xref> Conceptual framework for understanding PE cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Sundin and Medbo (2003)</xref> Car manufacturer Work group Redesign of kitting area Reduce ergonomic problems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Garmer et al. (2004)</xref> Hospitals Development of user requirements for new medical equipment Purchase of equipment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Sundin et al. (2004)</xref> Product development process in a bus Work group manufacturing company Improve efficiency and ergonomics in chassis assembly <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Seppälä (2006)</xref> Engineering company Project group Development of new manufacturing cells and team-based work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Theberge et al. (2006)</xref> Automotive foam manufacturing plant Labour-management Intervention to reduce biomechanical ergonomic change and psychosocial risk factors team (ECT)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">Participants Object Candidates Four workers, Workers visit similar 1e2 researcher(s) operations Slide show with pictures from current control room Test of seats Workers build and test alternative control and seat setups Experiment with and explore moveable screens, different blinds, black painted card and paper (lighting simulation) n.a. Tables Drawings CAD Scale or full-size mock-ups Tape marks on the floor Production games Auto-confrontation method (based on video recording) Six office employees, two Ergonomic training program specialists, one (lectures and ‘hands-on’) supervisor, three risk Ergonomic coordinator and safety personnel, Survey university researchers Breakthrough Thinking Ò Mock-up workstations Production manager, Training seminars workers’ safety Ergonomics course representative, supervisor, Large wall chart 2e4 workers (posting results) Lists of positive results and remaining problems Video recording of work Layout and workflow diagram (produced by workers) Three workers, two industrial 3 D CAD visualization engineers, two researchers (2D and 3D sketches, no animation) Handmade sketches Zero-Based Analysis Figure 23 nurses, medical engineer, Usability tests researchers Focus group interviews Video recordings of usability tests Ten persons from different Computer manikin design and production visualization engineering departments, Prototypes ergonomics researchers Prototype simulations Video recording of simulations Manufacturing manager, supervisor, Meetings two workers, and the researchers Five managerial and professional Ergonomics training sessions staff, four hourly workers, two Ergonomic “Blueprint” ergonomist-facilitators (stages in ergonomic from research team improvements) Results from interviews based on questionnaire (“One-minute” survey) Computer program (4D Watbak) Injury reports (continued on next page)</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="135" page="9" column="1">472</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="136" page="9" column="1">O. Broberg et al. / Applied Ergonomics 42 (2011) 464e472</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Appendix (continued ) Authors PE Topic Organizational setting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Vink et al. (2006)</xref> General PE framework on design of workplace artifacts and organization Four PE cases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Laing et al. (2007)</xref> Automotive parts Steering committee manufacturing factory Ergonomic change team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="139" class="deo:Reference">Määttä (2007)</xref> Evaluation of new production Safety analysis group machines and procedures before installation (steel plant) Identification of hazards <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Vink and van Eijk (2007)</xref> Design of screwdrivers 11-step participative design program <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Boynton and Darragh (2008)</xref> Hospital sterile processing center New building Prevention of injuries</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="143" page="9" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="144" page="9" column="1">Binder, T., Brandt, E., 2008. The Design:Lab as platform in participatory design research. CoDesign 4, 115e129.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="145" page="9" column="1">Boujut, J.-F., Blanco, E., 2003. Intermediary objects as a means to foster co-operation in engineering design. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 12, 205e219.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="146" page="9" column="1">Boynton, T., Darragh, A.R., 2008. Participatory ergonomics intervention in a sterile proccesing center: a case study. Work 31, 95e99.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="147" page="9" column="1">Broberg, O., 2010. Workspace design: a case study applying participatory design principles for healthy workplaces in an industrial setting. International Journal of Technology Management 51, 39e56.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="148" page="9" column="1">Brodersen, C., Dindler, C., Iversen, O.S., 2008. Staging imaginative places for participatory prototyping. CoDesign 4, 19e30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="149" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Button, G., Harper, R., 1996. The relevance of ‘work practice’ for design. Computer Supported Cooperative Work 4, 263e280.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="150" page="9" column="1">Carlile, P.R., 2002. A pragmatic view of knowledge and boundaries: boundary objects in new product development. Organization Science 13, 442e455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="151" page="9" column="1">Carlile, P.R., 2004. Transferring, translating, and transforming: an integrative framework for managing knowledge across boundaries. Organization Science 15, 555e568.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="152" page="9" column="1">Corbin, J., Strauss, A., 2008. Basics of Qualitative Research 3e e Techniques and Procedures for Developing Grounded Theory. Sage Publications, Los Angeles.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="153" page="9" column="1">Eason, K.D., 1995. User-centred design: for users or by users? Ergonomics 38, 1667e1673.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="154" page="9" column="1">Garmer, K., Dahlman, S., Sperling, L., 1995. Ergonomic development work: co- education as a support for user participation at a car assembly plant. A case study. Applied Ergonomics 26, 417e423.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="155" page="9" column="1">Garmer, K., Ylvén, J., Karlsson, M., 2004. User participation in requirements elici- tation comparing focus group interviews and usability tests for eliciting usability requirements for medical equipment: a case study. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 33, 85e98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="156" page="9" column="1">Garrigou, A., Daniellou, F., Carballeda, G., Ruaud, S., 1995. Activity analysis in participatory design and analysis of participatory design activity. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 15, 311e327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="157" page="9" column="1">Haims, M.C., Carayon, P., 1998. Theory and practice for the implementation of ‘in- house’, continuous improvement participatory ergonomic programs. Applied Ergonomics 29, 461e472.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="158" page="9" column="1">Haines, H., Wilson, J.R., Vink, P., Koningsveld, E., 2002. Validating a framework for participatory ergonomics (the PEF). Ergonomics 45, 309e327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="159" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Henderson, K., 1999. On Line and On Paper. The MIT Press, Cambridge MA.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="160" page="9" column="1">Horgen, T.H., Joroff, M.L., Porter, W.L., Schön, D.A., 1999. Excellence by Design: Transforming Workplace and Work Practice. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="161" page="9" column="1">Kadefors, R., Forsman, M., 2000. Ergonomic evaluation of complex work: a participative approach employing video-computer interaction, exemplified in a study of order picking. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 25, 435e445.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="164" page="9" column="1">Kaptelinin, V., Nardi, B.N., 2006. Acting with Technology. Activity Theory and Interaction Design. The MIT Press, Cambridge MA. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Participants<marker type="block"/> Object Candidates Inventory Prototypes Training of workers Brainstorm sessions Test of new ways of working and workstations Test of new equipment Prototypes Computer simulation Ergonomics training course Ergonomics bulletin board Mock-ups One minute surveys</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="169" page="9" column="2">Virtual environment (VE) computer system <marker type="block"/> Project manager, foremen, designers, safety specialist, operators, the researcher (chair)<marker type="block"/> Designers Professional users Workers, management, supervisors, administration<marker type="block"/> Test of experimental prototype Employee training program Visiting other departments<marker type="block"/> Kuorinka, I., 1997. Tools and means of implementing participatory ergonomics. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 19, 267e270.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="170" page="9" column="2">Laing, A.C., Cole, D.C., Theberge, N., Wells, R.P., Kerr, M.S., Frazer, M.B., 2007. Effec- tiveness of a participatory ergonomics intervention in improving communication and psychosocial exposures. Ergonomics 50, 1092e1109.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="171" page="9" column="2">Laitinen, H., Saari, J., Kivistö, M., Rasa, P.-L., 1998. Improving physical and psychosocial working conditions through a participatory ergonomic process. A before- after study at an engineering workshop. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 21, 35e45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="172" page="9" column="2">Määttä, T.J., 2007. Virtual environments in machinery safety analysis and participatory ergonomics. Human Factors and Ergonomics in Manufacturing 17, 435e443.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="173" page="9" column="2">Nagamachi, M., 1995. Requisites and practices of participatory ergonomics. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 15, 371e377.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="174" page="9" column="2">Pedersen, J.H., 2010. Development and test of a CAD tool for workspace design. Technical University of Demark, Lyngby (MSc thesis).</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="175" page="9" column="2">Seim, R., Broberg, O., 2010. Participatory workspace design: a new approach for ergonomists? International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 40, 25e33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="176" page="9" column="2">Seppälä, P., 2006. How to carry out sustainable change? An analysis of introducing manufacturing cells in a Finnish engineering company. Human Factors and Ergonomics in Manufacturing 16, 17e37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="177" page="9" column="2">Star, S.L., Griesemer, J.R., 1989. Institutional ecology, ‘translations’ and boundary objects: amateurs and professionals in Berkeley’s museum of vertebrate zoology. Social Studies of Science 19, 387e420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="178" page="9" column="2">Suchman, L., 1995. Making work visible. Communications of the ACM 38, 56e64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="179" page="9" column="2">Sundin, A., Christmansson, M., Larsson, M., 2004. A different perspective in participatory ergonomics in product development improves assembly work in the automotive industry. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 33, 1e14.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="180" page="9" column="2">Sundin, A., Medbo, L., 2003. Computer visualization and participatory ergonomics as methods in workplace design. Human Factors and Ergonomics in Manufacturing 13, 1e17.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="181" page="9" column="2">Theberge, N., Granzow, K., Cole, D., Laing, A., 2006. Negotiating participation: understanding the “how” in an ergonomic change team. Applied Ergonomics 37, 239e248.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="182" page="9" column="2">Vinck, D., Jeantet, A., Laureillard, P., 1996. Objects and other intermediaries in the sociotechnical process of product design: an explanatory approach. In: Perrin, J.,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="183" page="9" column="2">Vinck, D. (Eds.), The Role of Design in the Shaping of Technology. European Commission Directorate-General Science. Research and Development, Brussels, pp. 297e320.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="184" page="9" column="2">Vink, P., van Eijk, D.J., 2007. The effect of a participative product design process on user performance. Safety Science 45, 567e577.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="185" page="9" column="2">Vink, P., Koningsveld, E.A.P., Molenbroek, J.F., 2006. Positive outcomes of participatory ergonomics in terms of greater comfort and higher productivity. Applied Ergonomics 37, 537e546.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="186" page="9" column="2">Wenger, E., 2000. Communities of practice and social learning systems. Organization 7, 225e246.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="187" page="9" column="2">Wilson, J.R., 1995. Solution ownership in participative work redesign: the case of a crane control room. International Journal of Industrial Ergonomics 15, 329e344.</ref>
        </ref-list>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
