<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>6ca38929929c02ce8f3e0ff29948741d34038df76469e03fe40bb43d0f156599</job>
    <base_name>62c8</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.2753/mis0742-1222220402</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">The Emergence of Boundary Spanning Competence in Practice:</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="2" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Implications for Information Systems’ Implementation and Use*</h2>
      </section>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Natalia Levina</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Emmanuelle Vaast</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="11" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">The Emergence of Boundary Spanning Competence in Practice: Implications for Information Systems’ Implementation and Use *</h2>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="12" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">This work was sponsored in part by MIT’s Center for Information Systems Research, Cambridge, MA, and by the CRG, Ecole Polytechnique, Paris, France. Natalia Levina is an Assistant Professor in the Information, Operations, and Management Sciences Department at the New York University Stern School of Business. Her current research interests include understanding collaboration practices on multi-party systems development projects, knowledge management in IT service delivery organizations, IT outsourcing strategy and implementation, and technology design principles in heterogeneous environments. Her works have appeared in MIS Quarterly, Applied Intelligence Journal and Reflections: The Society for Organizational Learning Journal. Dr. Levina has a Ph.D. in Information Technology from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and a Master’s in Mathematics from Boston University. Emmanuelle Vaast is an Assistant Professor in Management of Information Systems at the School of Business, Public Administration and Information Sciences, Long Island University. Her research interests deal with situated learning and the construction of intra-organizational boundaries and with IS use as well as with the relationships between representations and practices in the context of IS use. Her work has been published in Information and Organization, Management Communication Quarterly, SIM and Information Research. She earned her Ph.D. in Management of Information Systems from the Ecole Polytechnique, Paris, France and is a former student of the Ecole Normale Supérieure and Sciences Po.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible" page="2" column="3">2</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="14" page="3" column="1">4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible" page="3" column="2">1 2 3</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="16" confidence="possible" page="3" column="3">The Emergence of Boundary Spanning Competence in Practice: Implications for Information Systems’ Implementation and Use</h2>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="17" confidence="possible" page="3" column="3">ABSTRACT Knowledge Management (KM) literature has centrally focused on organization’s ability to build practices that integrate diverse expertise across professional, organizational, industry and other boundaries. In this paper we investigate how an organizational competence in boundary spanning emerges in practice. We draw on the concepts of boundary spanner and boundary object and on the practice-based view of KM in organizations to understand the emergence of boundary spanning in practice, which we define as relating practices from diverse fields. We contrast data from two qualitative, longitudinal field studies to draw our conclusions. We argue that for boundary spanning to emerge in practice a new joint field, which unites agent in a common pursuit, needs to be produced. Engagement of agents in this practice partially transforms their practices in local fields so as to accommodate the interests of their counterparts. Those agents who engage in negotiating the nature of this new field become boundary spanners- in-practice. Through their engagements in the new joint field and diverse local practices boundary spanners-in-practice produce and use objects which become locally useful and acquire a joint identity through their use – boundary objects-in-use. Through data analysis we find, first, that nominated boundary spanners and designated boundary objects do not always become boundary spanners-in-practice and boundary objects-in- use. Second, we outline the conditions necessary for boundary spanners-in-practice to emerge, including the need for them to become legitimate, albeit peripheral, participants in the practices of the fields that they span. Thirdly, we show how boundary spanners-in-practice use their symbolic, cultural, social, and economic resources (capital) to build the new joint field. Finally, we examine the tensions involved in a) the nomination of agents as boundary spanners and artifacts as boundary objects; b) the growth of the new joint field; c) agents’ choice in investing in the new joint field; and d) spanning one at the expense of another kind of boundary. We conclude by drawing implications for IS implementation and use. Keywords: Boundary spanning, boundary objects, boundary spanners, boundaries, practice theory, Bourdieu, Knowledge Management, organizational learning, IS implementation, IS use, client-consultant relationship, intranet, roles. ISRL Categories: AJ; DD06; DD02; DD0301; DD01; CA; HA08; AI0112; AI0803; FD; FD0802; FD07; FB; FB01; AA1202; AF09.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">1 2</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="19" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">The Emergence of Boundary Spanning Competence in Practice: Implications for Information Systems’ Implementation and Use INTRODUCTION</h2>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="24" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">3 4 The ability of an organization to build practices that draw on diverse bases of expertise 5 constitutes one of the key organizational competencies in Knowledge Management (KM). 6 According to the knowledge-based view of the firm, integrating various sources of expertise 7 involves overcoming significant obstacles and doing so better than the competition can become a 8 source of sustained competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Kogut and Zander 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Grant 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Tsoukas 1996</xref>; 9 Dyer and Singh 1998; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Nahapiet and Ghoshal 1998</xref>). Recent studies of organizations such as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" page="4" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">IDEO, General Electric, NASA’s Jet Propulsion Laboratory and other successful innovators have</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27" page="4" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">argued that the success of these organizations is largely due to their ability to engage effectively</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="29" page="4" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">their members in practices that allow them to span boundaries of diverse settings (Orlikowski</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="31" page="4" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">2002; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Hargadon 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>; Cross and Parker 2004; Majchrzak et al. 2004).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="35" page="4" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Beside spectacular successes, however, there are also examples of phenomenal failures.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37" page="4" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">NASA’s recent Columbia shuttle disaster is a case in point. A key conclusion from the accident</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="39" page="4" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="40" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">investigation was that part of the disaster had to do with miscommunication and mass confusion</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="4" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="42" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">among engineers and safety officials from at least three NASA sites. For instance, a manager in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="4" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="44" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">charge of the flight ignored important requests from engineers that did not go up through</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="45" page="4" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="47" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">appropriate channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Verton 2003</xref>). This manager failed to fulfill her role in spanning the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="48" page="4" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">boundaries of organizational units within NASA. Information Technology (IT), which NASA</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" page="4" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="51" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">uses extensively, did not help either: “Problem- and Waiver-Tracking” and “Lessons Learned”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="52" page="4" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="53" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Information Systems (IS), for example, were not used to support boundary spanning in real time,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="4" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">but were used primarily for post-incident analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Verton 2003</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" confidence="possible" page="4" column="3">1</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="71" page="5" column="1">10 <marker type="block"/> 11<marker type="block"/> 12<marker type="block"/> 13<marker type="block"/> 14<marker type="block"/> 15<marker type="block"/> 16<marker type="block"/> 17<marker type="block"/> 18<marker type="block"/> 19<marker type="block"/> 20<marker type="block"/> 21<marker type="block"/> 22<marker type="block"/> 23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="72" confidence="possible" page="5" column="2">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="75" confidence="possible" page="5" column="3">This and other examples of failures raise the question of how organizations not only aspire to, but actually develop and use their KM competence so as to support their members in spanning multiple boundaries. In other words, how does boundary spanning competence emerge in practice? How do individuals, such as the NASA’s manager, actually come to fulfill their boundary spanning roles and how do IS actually become used for boundary spanning? To understand how boundary spanning emerges in practice (i.e., in what people do) as opposed to in theory (i.e., what people aspire to do), this paper uses and extends a practice-based view on KM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>) and data from two qualitative field studies. It contributes to KM literature by developing a dynamic (Griffith et al. 2003) and dialogic (Schultze and Leidner 2002) perspective on the emergence of boundary spanning competence in practice. The rest of the paper is organized as follows: we first review and extend a practice-based perspective on KM in organizations and then tie this perspective to the existing literature on boundary spanners and boundary objects. We then present our empirical approach and our analysis of the two field studies. The discussion section analyzes the processes involved in the emergence of an organizational competence in boundary spanning. Finally, we draw implications from our newly developed understanding for IT implementation and use.</region>
      </section>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="3" page="1" column="1">by</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="6" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">New York University Stern School of Business Information Systems Group/ IOMS 44 West Fourth St, Suite 8-78 (KMC) New York, NY 10012 Office Phone: 212-998-0850 Fax: 212-995-4228 Email: <email id="5">nlevina@stern.nyu.edu</email></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Long Island University School of Business, Public Administration and Information Sciences 1 University Plaza—H700 Brooklyn, NY 11201 Office Phone: 917-306-5348 Fax: 718-488-1125 E-mail: <email id="8">emmanuelle.vaast@liu.edu</email> * The authors have contributed equally to the paper</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="3">1</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="76" page="5" column="3">THEORETICAL DEVELOPMENT: A PRACTICE-BASED PERSPECTIVE ON BOUNDARY SPANNING IN ORGANIZATIONS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" confidence="possible" page="5" column="3">The proposition that spanning boundaries of diverse professional and organizational settings can become a key organizational competence has received increasing theoretical support for fome time now (von Hippel 1988; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Kogut and Zander 1992</xref>; Nonaka 1994; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Grant 1996</xref>). More recently, a few researchers have investigated empirically what kinds of organizational practices actually allow firms to claim such competence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="80" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>). We draw on 2</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="82" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">1 these recent developments in KM literature and on original ideas from Bourdieu’s theory of 2 practice (Bourdieu and Wacquant 1992) to understand how such practices actually emerge. 3 A Practice-based Perspective on Knowledge Management in Organizations 4 Sociologists use the concept of practice to understand the dynamics of societies based on 5 what people do (Bourdieu 1977; Certeau 1984; Giddens 1984). 6 materially bounded and situated action engaged in by members of a community” 7 2002: 256). Through practice, reflexive agents engage to produce, reproduce, or transform 8 structures which, in turn, enable and constrain their actions (Bourdieu 1977; Giddens 1984). In 9 the KM literature, this perspective supports the claim that “knowing is an ongoing social</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83" page="6" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">accomplishment, constituted and reconstituted in everyday practice” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>: 252-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="86" page="6" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">253). Thus, a practice view on KM is necessarily a dynamic view (Griffith et al. 2003).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" page="6" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Practice is bounded in a specific material, historical and social context that shapes what</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" page="6" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">agents do and gives meaning to habitual actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="91" class="deo:Reference">Suchman 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="92" class="deo:Reference">Lave 1988</xref>). This view allows</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="94" page="6" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">us to see where boundaries in practice come from. As agents engage in practice, they develop a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="96" page="6" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">continuity in their local practices, which allows them to act knowledgeably in a given context but</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98" page="6" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="99" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">also distinguishes them from others who do not engage in this practice or engage in it only</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" page="6" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">peripherally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>: 103). Practice theorists have conceptualized this phenomenon as the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="103" page="6" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">emergence of fields (Bourdieu and Wacquant 1992: 96-120) . By engaging in fields, agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="105" page="6" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">pursue a joint interest (an inclination and ability to succeed in a given endeavor), but also</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="107" page="6" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="108" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">differentiate themselves from outsiders who do not pursue the same interest. At any given time,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="109" page="6" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="110" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">agents are engaged in multiple, nested fields. Within each field, agents are distinguished based</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="111" page="6" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="114" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">on their attainment of stakes offered by this field (into “haves” and “have-nots”) (ibid). 1 We rely on the concept of “fields” instead of “communities of practice” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Lave and Wenger 1991</xref>), because the latter is limited in addressing the power dynamics involved in boundary spanning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Contu and Willmott 2003</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" confidence="possible" page="6" column="3">Practice is a “recurrent, (Orlikowski</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="116" page="6" column="3">1</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" confidence="possible" page="6" column="3">3</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="131" page="7" column="1">10 <marker type="block"/> 11<marker type="block"/> 12<marker type="block"/> 13<marker type="block"/> 14<marker type="block"/> 15<marker type="block"/> 16<marker type="block"/> 17<marker type="block"/> 18<marker type="block"/> 19<marker type="block"/> 20<marker type="block"/> 21<marker type="block"/> 22<marker type="block"/> 23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="132" confidence="possible" page="7" column="2">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" confidence="possible" page="7" column="3">Through their engagement in fields, agents produce different kinds of resources (capital) that they can accumulate and use as bases of power in a field. Bourdieu distinguishes four key species of capital: economic capital (e.g., money, time, IT), cultural capital (e.g., professional expertise, education, ownership of information), and social capital (which social networks an agent can draw on); in addition, symbolic capital is defined as the ability to name any other resource as valuable—the power to name and classify things. Agents in every field are engaged in producing a unique sub-specie of one of these species of capital (1992: 119). Discontinuities in practice (boundaries of fields) create opportunities for organizations to develop a knowledge-based competitive advantage. For example, as engineers engage in their professional practice, a boundary between their field of practice and the field of practice of marketing people emerges and grows. Organizations that successfully engage engineers and marketing specialists in relating practices from these fields (what we will refer to as boundary spanning) develop a knowledge-based competence in product development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Dougherty 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>). In addition to spanning boundaries of professional fields, organizations may develop competencies in spanning boundaries of organizational (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Powell 1990</xref>; Dyer and Singh 1998), academic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="136" class="deo:Reference">Liebeskind et al. 1996</xref>), national socio-economic (Lam 1997), and other fields. Such competencies are produced through the engagement of agents in practices that agents produce to navigate and negotiate multiple boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="137" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>: 267). These practices must be different from practices within specific fields that contributed to the production of the boundary in question; otherwise, agents would only reproduce the boundary. Whatever repertoire of practices agents rely on in spanning boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="138" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>: 267), they produce these practices in the context of prior actions and relationships and in pursuit of a common interest, that is, in the context of a field. We propose that the emergence of a boundary spanning 4</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">1 competence in practice is associated with the emergence of a 2 in pursuit of a common organizational interest, but also distinguishes them from others who are 3 not engaged in such pursuit. In practice theory terms, developing an organizational competence 4 in boundary spanning means producing a specific type of organizational capital ("social capital" 5 according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Nahapiet and Ghoshal 1998</xref>) by using and relating capital produced in other fields 6 ("transforming knowledge boundaries" according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>). 7 The concepts of field and capital allow us to engage in a dialogical discourse on KM by 8 offering a way of “tracing power and domination to claims of expertise”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="143" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">9 2002: 217). While Orlikowski’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="144" page="8" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="145" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">competence in spanning boundaries is embedded in the everyday practice of its members, our</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" page="8" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">interest is in investigating how a new joint field where such practices are produced emerges. To</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="148" page="8" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="149" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">achieve this, we draw on two prominent concepts in the organizational literature on KM:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="150" page="8" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">boundary spanners and boundary objects. We argue that currently the literature has developed a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" page="8" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="153" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">rather static view of these concepts, focusing on either what these “mechanisms” are supposed to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="154" page="8" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">achieve in theory, or on what happens in practice. What is missing is an understanding of how</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156" page="8" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="157" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">the aspirations behind “boundary spanning mechanisms”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="158" page="8" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="159" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">practice.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162" page="8" column="1">18 <marker type="block"/> 19</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="161" page="8" column="1">Boundary Spanners in Theory and in Practice</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="163" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">The literature on KM has emphasized the importance of relying on individuals performing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="164" page="8" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">boundary spanning roles (Hargadon and Sutton 1997; Davenport and Prusak 1998; Swan and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="166" page="8" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Scarbrough 2001</xref>; Cross and Parker 2004; Pawlowski and Robey 2005). Cross and Parker (2004)</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" page="8" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="170" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">characterized boundary spanners</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" page="8" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">linking two or more groups of people who are separated by location, hierarchy, or function.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="173" page="8" column="2">new joint field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="174" page="8" column="2">(2002) work has demonstrated</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="175" page="8" column="2">become</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="176" confidence="possible" page="8" column="2">as vital individuals who facilitate the sharing of expertise by</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" confidence="possible" page="8" column="3">which unites agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="178" confidence="possible" page="8" column="3">(Schultze and Leidner</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="180" page="8" column="3">that an organizational <marker type="block"/> or do not become enacted in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="181" confidence="possible" page="8" column="3">5</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="195" page="9" column="1">10 <marker type="block"/> 11<marker type="block"/> 12<marker type="block"/> 13<marker type="block"/> 14<marker type="block"/> 15<marker type="block"/> 16<marker type="block"/> 17<marker type="block"/> 18<marker type="block"/> 19<marker type="block"/> 20<marker type="block"/> 21<marker type="block"/> 22<marker type="block"/> 23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="196" confidence="possible" page="9" column="2">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="202" confidence="possible" page="9" column="3">Managers of R&amp;D groups, sales representatives, HR specialists, and IT professionals are prime examples of professionals expected to span inter and intra-organizational boundaries (Allen and Cohen 1969; Tushman 1977; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="197" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>; Pawlowski and Robey 2005). The literature on boundary spanners has taken two disjoint directions. First, numerous research studies have identified and classified the roles that boundary spanners are expected to perform (e.g., Aldrich and Herker 1977; Leifer and Delbecq 1978; Tushman and Scanlan 1981; At-Twaijri and Montanari 1987; Ancona and Caldwell 1992; Friedman and Podolny 1992; Cross and Parker 2004). For example, the boundary spanner’s roles have been distinguished into representative vs. gatekeeper, advice vs. trust broker (Friedman and Podolny 1992) as well as scout, ambassador, sentry, and guard (Ancona and Caldwell 1992). Second, other studies have focused on individuals involved in boundary spanning in practice. These studies indicated that the multiple roles of boundary spanners are often in conflict, which leads to stress and burnout (Lysonski and Johnson 1983; Baroudi 1985; Lysonski 1985; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="198" class="deo:Reference">Singh and Rhoads 1991</xref>; Dubinsky et al. 1992; Singh et al. 1996). It is also hard to find individuals to perform these roles as they should be sensitive to social cues (Caldwell and O'<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="199" class="deo:Reference">Reilly 1982</xref>) and competent in multiple domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="200" class="deo:Reference">Nochur and Allen 1992</xref>). Even qualified individuals may choose to avoid the uncomfortable feeling of dual, often conflicting, identification and marginalization within each field spanned (Bourdieu 1977; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="201" class="deo:Reference">Tajfel 1978</xref>) and may stick to one side rather than span boundaries (Wiesenfeld and Hewlin 2003). One of the recommendations from the literature is to assign different boundary spanning roles to different individuals thus preventing role conflicts (Friedman and Podolny 1992). In organizational practice, however, boundary spanners tend to occupy managerial positions (Wiesenfeld and Hewlin 2003) and may be reluctant to part with any of their roles, especially since the information and accumulated social capital can be used to 6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="205" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">1 their own personal advantage (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="203" class="deo:Reference">Keller and Holland 1975</xref>; Baroudi 1985; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="204" class="deo:Reference">Katz et al. 1995</xref>). In 2 short, there is enough evidence from examples like NASA’s Columbia accident as well as from 3 academic studies to suggest that agents nominated into boundary spanning roles may fail to 4 perform these roles in practice. 5 To clarify this discrepancy, we introduce a distinction between</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="206" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="207" page="10" column="1">2 spanners and boundary spanners-in-practice</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="208" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">7 the process of nomination (or “designation by name”), agents who occupy dominant positions in 8 a field, such as top leadership or KM groups in organizations, use the symbolic capital of their 9 own positions to appoint (name) themselves or others to various positions endowed with</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="209" page="10" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="210" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">symbolic capital (Bourdieu 1998: 51). Through this nomination, organizational leaders try to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="211" page="10" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="213" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">foster the emergence of a new joint field across a particular boundary. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="212" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214" page="10" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="215" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">lack of boundary spanning-in-practice when only nominated boundary spanners are present.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="216" page="10" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="217" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Formal structures such as roles, however, may not coincide with actual practice, which</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="218" page="10" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="219" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">involves diverse interests and in which actions (e.g., such as nomination) have unexpected</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" page="10" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="222" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="221" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>: 80). In contrast to nominated boundary spanners, boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="223" page="10" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="224" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">spanners-in-practice must actually engage in boundary spanning, that is, in relating practices in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="225" page="10" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="226" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">one field to practices in another field by negotiating the meaning and terms of the relationship.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="227" page="10" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="228" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">They engage in building a new joint field “in-between” the two fields. To understand the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="229" page="10" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="230" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">emergence of an organizational competence in boundary spanning, we need to investigate how</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="231" page="10" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="232" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">agents become boundary spanners-in-practice by drawing on their nomination or, possibly,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="233" page="10" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="234" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">independently from their expected roles. In other words, we need to understand how agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="235" page="10" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">actually develop and sustain a new joint field. 2 This distinction was (inspired by the practice theory-based distinction between a technological artifact and a technology-in-practice Orlikowski 2000: 403).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="237" confidence="possible" page="10" column="2">. According to Bourdieu’s practice theory, through</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="238" page="10" column="3">nominated boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="239" confidence="possible" page="10" column="3">7</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" page="11" column="1">10 <marker type="block"/> 11<marker type="block"/> 12<marker type="block"/> 13<marker type="block"/> 14<marker type="block"/> 15<marker type="block"/> 16<marker type="block"/> 17<marker type="block"/> 18<marker type="block"/> 19<marker type="block"/> 20<marker type="block"/> 21<marker type="block"/> 22<marker type="block"/> 23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="254" confidence="possible" page="11" column="2">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="261" confidence="possible" page="11" column="3">Boundary Objects in Theory and in Use Star and Griesemer (1989) introduced the concept of boundary object to address the limitations implied by the reliance on boundary spanners who may promote self-interest, have a limited social network, and face temporal and physical constraints. Examples of boundary objects include physical prototypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="255" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>; Bechky 2003), design drawings (Bødker 1998), use scenarios (Bødker 2000), engineering sketches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="256" class="deo:Reference">Henderson 1991</xref>; Bechky 1999), accounting ledgers (Briers and Chua 2001), and standardized reporting forms (Star and Griesemer 1989; Bowker and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Star 1994; Bowker et al. 1996</xref>; Briers and Chua 2001). The term “boundary object” thus refers to a broad range of artifacts that “are plastic enough to adapt to local needs and constraints of the several parties employing them, yet robust enough to maintain a common identity across sites” (Star 1989: 393). This concept is useful in understanding how IT-based artifacts can support the development of a boundary spanning competence. The IS literature provides many examples of boundary objects, from document archives to ERP systems (Ackerman and Halverson 1999; Briers and Chua 2001; Pawlowski and Robey 2005). Researchers in this tradition have focused more on practice-based studies of organizations than their counterparts studying boundary spanners. They initially catalogued various boundary objects and, later, investigated their properties such as modularity, abstraction, accommodation, and standardization (Star 1989; Star and Griesemer 1989; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="258" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>; Pawlowski and Robey 2005), as well as the purposes behind the use of different kinds of objects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="259" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>). Studies suggest that boundary objects should be tangible (Carlile 1997), concrete (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="260" class="deo:Reference">Henderson 1991</xref>; Bechky 2003), accessible, and up-to-date (Carlile 1997). Such lists of characteristics and aspirations behind artifacts are useful to identify boundary objects in practice. Yet, they are not necessarily helpful to figure out how an organizational 8</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="265" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">1 competence in boundary spanning actually emerges from the use of these objects. In many cases 2 objects that have been designated as useful for boundary spanning and that possess desired 3 characteristics remain unused or were used superficially (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="262" class="deo:Reference">Levina 2001</xref>). There are many 4 examples of IS that were designated to support organizational members in spanning boundaries, 5 but that were eventually used in practice to guard and reinforce these boundaries (Goodman and 6 Darr 1998; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="263" class="deo:Reference">Schultze and Boland 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="264" class="deo:Reference">Newell et al. 2001</xref>). 7 Drawing on recent theorizing about artifacts in practice, we argue that it is impossible to tell 8 whether an artifact would acquire a common identity or would satisfy varied local needs outside 9 its use, because outside its use an artifact does not have any meaning or structural property</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="266" page="12" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="267" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">(Orlikowski 2000). Recent practice-based accounts of boundary objects have supported our</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="268" page="12" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="269" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">claim that boundary objects’ characteristics and performances are embedded in the situated</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="270" page="12" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="272" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">practices of the agents that use them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>; Bechky 2003), but they did not examine how</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="273" page="12" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="274" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">boundary objects emerge in practice. We, thus, distinguish between</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="276" page="12" column="1">14 and boundary objects-in-use. <marker type="block"/> 15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="277" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">who hold positions of power in a field designate certain objects as valuable for accomplishing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="278" page="12" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="279" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">boundary spanning in practice. They do so by using their own symbolic capital to name an</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="280" page="12" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="281" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">artifact as symbolically valuable. These designated boundary objects may not, however, become</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="282" page="12" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="283" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">boundary objects-in-use: they may not be usefully deployed in the practices of each field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="284" page="12" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="285" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">involved, nor have a common identity in their use across fields (following Star's1989 original</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="286" page="12" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="287" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">definition). Artifacts that become boundary objects-in-use become both locally useful (they are</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="288" page="12" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="289" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">meaningfully and usefully integrated into local practices) and acquire a joint identity across</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="290" page="12" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="291" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">fields. A joint identity in this case refers to having a structure that “is</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="292" page="12" column="1">23 than one world to make them recognizable”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="293" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">In a way that is similar to nominating boundary spanners, agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="294" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">(Star and Griesemer 1989: 393). In practice theory</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="295" page="12" column="3">designated boundary objects</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="296" confidence="possible" page="12" column="3">common enough to more 9</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="298" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">1 terms, “common identity” refers to the association of some symbolic capital (particular value) 2 with the boundary object, which can only happen in the context of a joint practice. Thus, the 3 development and use of boundary objects-in-use must be situated in a new joint field. 4 We summarize the differences between the nominated boundary spanners and designated 5 boundary objects and boundary spanners-in-practice and boundary objects-in-use in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="297" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref>.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="299" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="300" page="13" column="1">Table 1: Comparing Nomination/Designation and Enactment in Boundary Spanning</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="13">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Nomination and Designation</th>
                  <th class="table"> Enactment</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Nominated Boundary Spanners: Refers to</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> Boundary Spanners-in-Practice: Refers to agents</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> agents who were assigned by the empowered</td>
                  <td class="table"> who, with or without nomination, engage in</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> agents in a field to perform certain roles in</td>
                  <td class="table"> spanning (navigating and negotiation) boundaries</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> spanning boundaries of diverse fields.</td>
                  <td class="table"> separating fields.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Designated Boundary Objects: Refers to</td>
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects-in-use: Refers to artifacts that,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> artifacts, that, due to their design and properties,</td>
                  <td class="table"> with or without designation, become usefully</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> were named as valuable in spanning boundaries of</td>
                  <td class="table"> deployed in the practices of diverse fields and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> diverse fields.</td>
                  <td class="table"> acquire a joint identity in practice</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="301" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">Nomination and Designation Enactment Nominated Boundary Spanners: Refers to Boundary Spanners-in-Practice: Refers to agents agents who were assigned by the empowered who, with or without nomination, engage in agents in a field to perform certain roles in spanning (navigating and negotiation) boundaries spanning boundaries of diverse fields. separating fields. Designated Boundary Objects: Refers to Boundary objects-in-use: Refers to artifacts that, artifacts, that, due to their design and properties, with or without designation, become usefully were named as valuable in spanning boundaries of deployed in the practices of diverse fields and diverse fields. acquire a joint identity in practice</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="303" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">7 The distinction between the four concepts depicted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="302" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> helps us see the difference 8 between boundary spanning in theory and boundary spanning in practice and moves us closer to 9 understanding how an enacted competence in spanning the boundaries of particular fields</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="304" page="13" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="305" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">emerges. The purpose of our fieldwork and data analysis was to understand the dynamics</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="306" page="13" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="307" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">through which agents and artifacts become boundary spanners-in-practice and boundary objects-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="308" page="13" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="309" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">in-use. Such an analysis helps us understand better why in certain cases IT-based artifacts</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="310" page="13" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="311" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">become boundary objects-in-use, while in others they do not, and draw implications for IS</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="312" page="13" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="313" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">implementation and use for supporting this kind of KM.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="315" page="13" column="1">15 <marker type="block"/> 16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="316" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">The goal of our empirical approach was to use practice theory to interpret data from our</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="317" page="13" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="318" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">cases and to understand the emergence of an organizational competence in boundary spanning,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="319" page="13" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="320" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">especially in the context of IT implementation and use. Prior works (Barley 1986; Orlikowski</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="321" page="13" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="324" confidence="possible" page="13" column="1">1992; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="322" class="deo:Reference">Schultze and Boland 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="323" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>) have demonstrated such way of using</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="325" page="13" column="2">METHODOLOGY</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="326" page="13" column="3">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="328" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">1 practice theory in data analysis. Because we wanted to study agents’ production of practices as 2 well as their aspirations, our investigation relied on direct empirical observations of what people 3 did and on interviews with key participants regarding their intentions and perceptions of practice. 4 We compared two qualitative longitudinal case studies to address our research questions. 5 Cases were considered as specific instances of several fields-of-practice, following Bourdieu’s 6 (1998: 2) guide for empirical research. To further our understanding of the phenomenon and to 7 address the questions that arose from the theoretical development, we used grounded theory 8 techniques (Glaser and Strauss 1967; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="327" class="deo:Reference">Strauss 1967; Strauss and Corbin 1998</xref> The conclusions presented in 9 this paper were based on the comparative analysis of practices involved in boundary spanning</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="329" page="14" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="330" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">within (longitudinal analysis) and across cases (cross-case analysis).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="332" page="14" column="1">11 <marker type="block"/> 12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="333" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Each of us separately collected data on one of the cases. One case focused on the emergence</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="334" page="14" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="335" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">of practices supporting boundary spanning associated with the implementation of intranet</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="336" page="14" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="337" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">applications in an insurance company—Insura . This case was well-suited for investigating</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="338" page="14" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="339" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">boundary spanning because the stated objective behind intranet implementation at Insura was to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="340" page="14" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="341" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">improve “knowledge sharing” between Insura’s headquarters and its geographically distributed</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="342" page="14" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="343" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">sales agents, as well as among sales agents. The other case focused on the emergence of practices</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="344" page="14" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="345" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">supporting boundary spanning in an inter-organizational IS development project conducted by an</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="346" page="14" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="347" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Internet consulting firm, Eserve, and its client, Pubco. This case was also relevant for examining</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="348" page="14" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="349" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">the research questions because Eserve managers insisted that the strength of their organization</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="350" page="14" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="351" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">was in integrating diverse professional expertise (in strategy, technology, and graphic design) as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="352" page="14" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="353" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">well as their clients’ business expertise on project teams. Pubco, as a client, was chosen because 3 Names of organizations, their members, and specific practices are disguised</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="354" page="14" column="2">Data Collection</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="355" page="14" column="2">3</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="356" page="14" column="3">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="358" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">1 Pubco managers expressed an interest in improving communication with consultants. Eserve had 2 also put in place an intranet-based KMS to facilitate boundary spanning among its professional 3 groups and with clients. Both Insura and the Eserve-Pubco project granted us necessary access 4 for conducting sustained on-site observations, interviews, and archival data analysis. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="357" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> 5 outlines how each researcher independently collected data.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="359" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">6</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="360" page="15" column="1">Table 2: Cross-Study Comparison of Methods</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="2" page="15">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Methods</th>
                  <th class="table"> Insura</th>
                  <th class="table"> Eserve-Pubco</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Field Observation</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> 4 months, 3 days a week. Insura’s</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> 9 months, 4-5 days a week. Mostly</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> headquarters and local teams.</td>
                  <td class="table"> at Eserve, but some at Pubco.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Access to the field</td>
                  <td class="table"> Negotiated access through</td>
                  <td class="table"> Negotiated access through Eserve.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> headquarters.</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Semi-structured interviews</td>
                  <td class="table"> 31—recorded and transcribed.</td>
                  <td class="table"> 41 (23—Pubco, 19—Eserve)— recorded and transcribed.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Informal contacts</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Follow ups visits</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Documents and Archives</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                  <td class="table"> Yes</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Key Boundaries</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1) Professionals in Departments at</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1) Consulting Firm—Business</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Headquarters—Sales Reps</td>
                  <td class="table"> Clients</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> 2) Among Geographically</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2) Requirements Team—Graphic</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Distributed Sales Teams</td>
                  <td class="table"> Designers</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Key Technologies</td>
                  <td class="table"> Email, Telephone, intranet</td>
                  <td class="table"> Email, Telephone, intranet</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Other</td>
                  <td class="table"> - 3 focus groups of 5 sales reps</td>
                  <td class="table"> - Coding of email archives and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> - Statistics of use of the intranet</td>
                  <td class="table"> records in Eserve’s HR System</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="361" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Methods Insura Eserve-Pubco Field Observation 4 months, 3 days a week. Insura’s 9 months, 4-5 days a week. Mostly headquarters and local teams. at Eserve, but some at Pubco. Access to the field Negotiated access through Negotiated access through Eserve. headquarters. Semi-structured interviews 31—recorded and transcribed. 41 (23—Pubco, 19—Eserve)— recorded and transcribed. Informal contacts Yes Yes Follow ups visits Yes Yes Documents and Archives Yes Yes Key Boundaries 1) Professionals in Departments at 1) Consulting Firm—Business Headquarters—Sales Reps Clients 2) Among Geographically 2) Requirements Team—Graphic Distributed Sales Teams Designers Key Technologies Email, Telephone, intranet Email, Telephone, intranet Other - 3 focus groups of 5 sales reps - Coding of email archives and - Statistics of use of the intranet records in Eserve’s HR System</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="362" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">7 8 Longitudinal and Cross-Case Analyses 9 The integration of ideas based on data from field studies conducted by researchers separately</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="363" page="15" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="364" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">is somewhat unusual in the IS literature, but it has been fruitfully deployed for inductive theory</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="365" page="15" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="367" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">development in organizational literature (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="366" class="deo:Reference">Tyre and Orlikowski 1994</xref>; Staudenmayer et al.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="368" page="15" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="369" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">2002). This approach appealed to us because we shared the same sociological tradition (reflexive</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="370" page="15" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="371" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">sociology as outlined in Bourdieu and Wacquant 1992) and unit of analysis—an organizational</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="372" page="15" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="373" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">practice targeted at boundary spanning—when we performed separate data collection and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="374" page="15" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="375" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">analysis, yet each of us emerged from the field with a different understanding of key concepts:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="376" page="15" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="377" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">One of us concluded that the nomination of people to boundary spanners’ roles created only</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="378" page="15" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="379" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">obstacles in practice, while the other one observed how a nominated boundary spanner was</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="380" page="15" column="3">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="381" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">1 crucial in fostering the emergence of a boundary spanning competence. By going back to our 2 notes and interviews we developed a common viewpoint that illuminated observations in both 3 settings. The steps we have taken are described below. 4 First, each of us went through our qualitative data to write individual case descriptions, based 5 on interlinked stages of data reduction and interpretation (Agar 1980; Becker 1998). This process 6 resulted in a series of gradually refined monographs (Pettigrew 1990) that constituted our 7 independent interpretations of data—“boundary spanning stories.” Next, using a comparative 8 method, we contrasted our stories within and across sites (Glaser and Strauss 1967). The contrast 9 between the two cases helped each of us practice the “radical doubt” (Bourdieu and Wacquant</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="382" page="16" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="384" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">1992: 235) or “suspicion” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="383" class="deo:Reference">Klein and Myers 1999</xref>): we challenged each other’s conclusions and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="387" page="16" column="1">11 <marker type="block"/> looked for confirming and<marker type="block"/> 12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="388" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">explanations. Next, we identified noticeable intentional and emergent shifts in practices over</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="389" page="16" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="390" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">time within each case—new stages. For example, in the Insura case, we identified a new stage of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="391" page="16" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="392" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">IS implementation based on a significant increase in the system’s usage. The factors defining</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="393" page="16" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="394" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">each stage were then contrasted within and across cases. Through this analysis, we developed the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="395" page="16" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="396" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">notion of a new joint field. We could then explain key differences in the cases by distinguishing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="397" page="16" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="398" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">between nominated boundary spanners and agents who actually engaged in building new joint</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="399" page="16" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="400" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">fields as well as between designated boundary objects and objects that were actually used for</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="401" page="16" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="402" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">boundary spanning. Then we went back and re-interpreted the data using these new concepts.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="403" page="16" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="404" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">After the inductive analysis, we used the theory and literature on KM as an additional lens to re-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="405" page="16" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="406" confidence="possible" page="16" column="1">interpret our findings, as suggested by Glaser and Strauss (1967).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="409" page="16" column="2">discomforting evidence to support <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> or reject our emergent<marker type="block"/> 13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="410" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">1</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="411" page="17" column="1">BOUNDARY SPANNING-IN-PRACTICE: TWO CASES</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="412" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">2 We identified three stages in the evolution of each case based on shifts in boundary spanning 3 practices. Each case description is presented separately and followed by an analytical summary. 4 Insura Case: How the Implementation and Use of Intranet Applications 5 Helped Develop a New Boundary Spanning Competence 6 Insura was an autonomous arm of a French insurance company that sold financial services to 7 households. Insura’s four thousand employees worked in the headquarters or in local sales teams. 8 Four hundred people at headquarters created new and updated existing financial services as well 9 as the company’s marketing strategy. Sales agents worked in local teams of about twenty sales</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="413" page="17" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="414" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">agents and one sales manager each. A substantial part of the sales agents’ work consisted of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="415" page="17" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="416" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">scheduling and preparing visits using clients’ files, information on services and markets, and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="417" page="17" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="418" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">each team’s marketing and advertising strategies. When a new sale had been contracted, agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="419" page="17" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="420" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">keyed their sales information into the reporting system on their laptops to validate the deal.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="421" page="17" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="422" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Subsequently, the HR department issued them paychecks. As their tasks were geographically</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="423" page="17" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="424" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">spread out, sales agents from different teams did not have the opportunity to interact directly.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="425" page="17" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="426" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">Traditionally, there was a lack of mutual understanding between local teams and people at</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="427" page="17" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="428" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">headquarters. Members of headquarters complained that, while their work was directed at</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="429" page="17" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="430" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">helping sales agents, sales agents did not value the tools they provided. For instance, members of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="431" page="17" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="432" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">the marketing department created posters advertising new products. They also visited a few local</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="433" page="17" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="434" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">offices to advocate the use of these posters. Yet, they were aware that these posters were not</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="435" page="17" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="436" confidence="possible" page="17" column="1">integrated into sales practices. The following excerpt from field notes illustrates this point: Marie works in the marketing department. She shows her peers her new promotional poster. As her colleagues congratulate her on the poster, she comments, ironically: “Well, yes, it [the poster] is good. Too bad they [i.e., sales agents] will not have the same opinion about it. And next week, I have to go defend the poster. I will be lucky if they do not throw tomatoes at me!”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="438" page="17" column="1">22 23 24 25 26 <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="439" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">1 Members of local teams, on the other hand, maintained that headquarters’ policies and 2 recommendations were not suitable for the realities of their trade. They argued that the posters 3 provided by headquarters were too “abstract” to be persuasive to clients. Members of local teams 4 created their own posters to address what they considered to be clients’ specific needs. 5 Stage 1: Limited Joint Field Production between Local Teams and Headquarters</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="440" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">6 Insura’s general manager</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="441" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">7 headquarters in order to improve Insura’s overall performance. He decided to develop various 8 intranet-based applications that would be shared by headquarters and local teams. The general 9 manager nominated Dominique to lead the project and become the future webmaster. Dominique</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="442" page="18" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="443" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">had a unique background which combined twenty years of experience as a sales agent and as a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="444" page="18" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="445" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">team manager as well as an IT specialist at the MIS department at headquarters in the last five</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="446" page="18" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="447" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">years. Assisted by a small team of IT professionals, Dominique designed and implemented</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="448" page="18" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="449" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">intranet applications in six months. During this period, he did not consult his former colleagues</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="450" page="18" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="451" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">in local teams about the project, but relied primarily on the input from marketing, HR, and legal</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="452" page="18" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="453" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">departments at headquarters. Dominique explained: “I did not ask local teams what they thought about the future intranet, because I knew they would not think anything about it. So I designed the intranet in-house.”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="454" page="18" column="1">16 17 18 19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="455" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Implemented in December 1999, the intranet became available to all members of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="456" page="18" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="457" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">headquarters and local teams. It included applications such as an interface to the sales reporting</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="458" page="18" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="459" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">system, a personnel directory, and official documentation on services. In addition, a folder</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="460" page="18" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="461" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">entitled “commercial initiatives” allowed agents to share best practices. Sales agents could</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="462" page="18" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="463" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">access the intranet from their laptops or from their local offices.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="464" page="18" column="1">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="465" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">During the first six months of its availability, however, sales agents hardly used the intranet</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="466" page="18" column="1">25</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="467" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">for anything but the interface to the sales reporting system. Agents’ lack of competence with the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="470" page="18" column="2">wanted to foster relationships <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> between local teams and<marker type="block"/> 15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="471" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">1 technology partially accounted for their limited use. More importantly, however, sales agents 2 seldom used the intranet because they considered that headquarters had created the applications 3 without considering their practices.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="473" page="19" column="1">4 A sales agent: “Why use the intranet? There is nothing much in it that is of real use to what is 5 truly important to me, that is to say, dealing with clients on a daily basis. It’s incredible, we are 6 working for the whole Insura, but they [at headquarters] do not seem to be aware of it.” 7 8 This statement was typical of sales agents’ opinion that headquarters were not providing 9 useful tools for them and did not acknowledge the value of sales agents’ hard work. 10 Stage 2: The Nominated Boundary Spanner Becomes a Boundary Spanner-in-Practice <marker type="block"/> 11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="474" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">By accessing web logs, Dominique soon learned that sales agents seldom used the intranet.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="475" page="19" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="476" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">He decided to take action and embarked on what he called his “Tour de France,” which consisted</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="477" page="19" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="478" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">of visiting about 40 local teams. During visits, he presented the project, explained how to use the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="479" page="19" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="480" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">intranet, and received direct feedback from agents. Visits were well received and stories about</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="481" page="19" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="482" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">them were gradually shared with other teams by word of mouth. With Dominique’s visits, sales</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="483" page="19" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="484" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">agents perceived that members of headquarters paid attention to their practices and provided</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="486" page="19" column="1">17 <marker type="block"/> 18 19 20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="487" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">tools that could concretely help them in their work. A sales agent commented: “The intranet (...) was launched by [headquarters] and it really shows that they care about how we deal with clients.” Moreover, as Dominique talked to sales agents, he learned ways of improving the intranet’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="488" page="19" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="489" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">functionality and applications. Sales agents talked freely to Dominique because they considered</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="490" page="19" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="491" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">him to be “one of them” as his former fame as a successful sales agent was still fresh in people’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="492" page="19" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="493" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">minds. Sales agents told Dominique that the intranet did not provide them with specific answers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="494" page="19" column="1">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="495" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">to some of their daily concerns. Dominique then introduced a new “Frequently Asked Questions”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="496" page="19" column="1">25</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="497" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">(FAQ) application that agents could use to ask questions (related to new services, HR, or legal</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="500" page="19" column="1">26 <marker type="block"/> matters) and to get focused<marker type="block"/> 27</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="501" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">departments—marketing, HR,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="502" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">answers from headquarters.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="506" page="19" column="2">and legal affairs—and Dominique <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> The heads of the concerned<marker type="block"/> jointly assigned six<marker type="block"/> 16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="507" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">1 headquarters’ members to answer these questions as part of their jobs. Moreover, during this 2 period, Dominique asked—mostly though e-mail and phone calls—some of the sales agents who 3 used to be his closest colleagues from various local teams to contribute to the “commercial</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="508" page="20" column="1">4 initiatives” folder by sharing some</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="509" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">5 Dominique also created a link from this folder to the intranet homepage that showed pictures of 6 the contributing agents. 7 Stage 3: Intranet Applications Become Boundary Objects-in-Use and Their Use 8 Encouraged the Emergence of New Boundary Spanners-in-Practice 9 From late fall 2000, Dominique had returned to the company headquarters and had scaled</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="510" page="20" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="511" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">down his direct involvement in the relationships between local teams and headquarters. Sales</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="512" page="20" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="513" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">agents and members of headquarters made substantial and active use of the FAQ applications.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="514" page="20" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="515" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Members of local teams used the FAQ to ask questions that really mattered to them. The</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="516" page="20" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="517" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">designated members of headquarters responded to these questions by following two rules that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="518" page="20" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="519" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Dominique had decreed: 1) the answer had to be short (two paragraphs) and, 2) the answer had to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="520" page="20" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="521" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">be put online within twenty-four hours, which forced members of headquarters to take into</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="522" page="20" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="523" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">account sales agents’ needs for straightforward and fast answers.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="524" page="20" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="525" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">Moreover, sales agents started putting their best practices online in the “commercial</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="526" page="20" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="527" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">initiatives” folder. Traditionally, among sales agents, the “best” professionals were considered to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="528" page="20" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="529" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">be the ones who were the most successful at selling financial services, as identified by the sales</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="530" page="20" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="531" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">volume rankings published in a newsletter. When the intranet commercial initiatives feature</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="532" page="20" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="533" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">became available, at first, sales agents remained reluctant to share their best practices with</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="534" page="20" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="535" confidence="possible" page="20" column="1">colleagues through the intranet, as they considered that contributing would equate to giving away</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="536" confidence="possible" page="20" column="2">of their best practices.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="538" page="20" column="3">To encourage contributions, <marker type="block"/> 17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="539" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">1 their source of competitiveness. After Dominique contacted his ex-colleagues and recognized 2 contributions through pictures, initial contributors gained immediate publicity: 3 Sales agent: “The ‘commercial initiatives’ folder, for sure, I use very often. Just to tell 4 you, there was a colleague of mine who has posted a way of treating new clients. You 5 can see his picture on the site! This is fame! More seriously, it is very useful, because 6 one has the occasion of knowing what the others do. Others that we do not know but 7 who deal with the same issues as we do. Before the intranet, we did not do that.” 8 9 Sales agents became gradually more willing to contribute to the folder. Dominique received</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="540" page="21" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="541" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">potential contributions via e-mail, and usually contacted the author to add details about the story</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="542" page="21" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="543" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">(e.g., the methods for identifying prospects) or to get rid of unnecessary details (e.g., names of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="544" page="21" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="545" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">clients) before posting them online. Now being a good professional</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="546" page="21" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="547" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">being able to sell a lot of contracts, but also contributing to the commercial initiatives folder.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="549" page="21" column="1">14 Analytical Summary <marker type="block"/> 15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="550" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Insura as a whole constituted a field that engaged agents in practices through which they</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="551" page="21" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="552" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">related various species of cultural capital produced by diverse professional fields (e.g., HR, legal,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="553" page="21" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="554" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">finance, sales, and marketing) to produce a unique organizational competence in developing and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="555" page="21" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="556" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">delivering financial products</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="557" page="21" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="558" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">professional sales practice which produced a unique cultural capital—a competence in selling</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="559" page="21" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="560" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">products. The headquarters’ leadership within the Insura field held the power of “nominating”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="561" page="21" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="562" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">agents to specific officially acknowledged roles.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="563" page="21" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="564" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">The first stage of the case revealed limited boundary spanning in practice. Headquarters’</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="565" page="21" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="566" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">marketing agents were nominated boundary spanners, but were not boundary spanners-in-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="567" page="21" column="1">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="568" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">practice. They engaged in the practices of their own professional field, but were not engaged in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="569" page="21" column="1">25</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="570" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">negotiating the meaning and terms of the relationship of their field to that of sales agents’. Not</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="571" page="21" column="1">26</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="572" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">surprisingly, the posters that they produced remained merely designated boundary objects.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="573" page="21" column="2">to consumers. Sales agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="574" confidence="possible" page="21" column="3">at Insura included not only</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="576" page="21" column="3">also belonged to the field of <marker type="block"/> 18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="577" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">1 Insura’s general manager then nominated Dominique to develop intranet-based applications as 2 boundary objects between local teams and various departments at Headquarters. During the 3 development and the first six months upon launch, Dominique remained a nominated boundary 4 spanner and various intranet applications, designated boundary objects. Sales agents’ limited use 5 of these applications reinforced the boundary between sales agents and headquarters. 6 Dominique became concerned by this situation as it threatened the symbolic capital he had 7 acquired through his nomination as a boundary spanner. He then changed his actions to become a 8 boundary spanner-in-practice. During his “Tour de France”, he engaged in relating what sales 9 agents were interested in obtaining and producing (their capital and practices), to the capital and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="578" page="22" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="579" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">practices of agents at headquarters. Dominique then designed and modified various objects</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="580" page="22" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="581" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">(applications such as the FAQ folders) that started acquiring a joint identity in the Insura field as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="582" page="22" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="583" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">objects representing the relation between sales agents and headquarters’ agents. These objects</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="584" page="22" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="585" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">became boundary objects-in-use for agents in local teams and agents in the headquarters.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="586" page="22" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="587" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">During the third stage, Dominique reduced his active engagement in the newly established</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="588" page="22" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="589" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">joint field. The specific contents of the FAQ applications became useful in the context of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="590" page="22" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="591" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">practices in local teams and in the headquarters’ departments. Moreover, through use, a common</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="592" page="22" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="593" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">identity of the FAQ application emerged as that of signifying the relation between sales agents as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="594" page="22" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="595" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">advice seekers and various headquarters agents as advice givers. As Dominique scaled down his</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="596" page="22" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="597" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">involvement in this practice, FAQ contributors and users started taking on more or less active</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="598" page="22" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="599" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">roles in negotiating and sustaining the joint field.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="600" page="22" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="601" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Similarly, a new joint field emerged surrounding the use of the commercial initiatives folder.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="602" page="22" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="603" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Here, the joint field was a sub-field of the sales agents’ professional field rather than the Insura</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="604" page="22" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="605" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">field and involved spanning boundaries of various geographically distributed socio-economic</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="606" page="22" column="3">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="607" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">1 fields in which local sales agents’ practices were embedded. Dominique used his symbolic 2 capital as a boundary spanner to encourage the production of a new joint field by giving 3 symbolic recognition to those agents who contributed to building the practice. He also used his 4 social capital to mobilize participation. The commercial initiatives folder became for agents who 5 could learn from others how to improve their practice and accumulate professional capital. The 6 folder also acquired a common identity signifying the relationship among geographically 7 distributed economic fields as that of partial collaboration rather than strict competition. 8 Eserve-Pubco Case: How Project Management Structures Inhibited Boundary 9 Spanning- in-Practice and Limited IT Use</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="608" page="23" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="609" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Eserve was a young, successful, and rapidly growing professional services firm engaged in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="610" page="23" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="611" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">the production of Business-to-Consumer (B2C) applications. Although there were no formal</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="612" page="23" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="613" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">titles at Eserve, project teams comprised of an client partner, a project manager (PM), and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="614" page="23" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="615" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">strategy, graphic design, and technology consultants who defined, designed, and built the system.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="616" page="23" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="617" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Projects generally went through</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="618" page="23" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="619" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Eserve’s service delivery model and other practices emphasized that clients knew little about</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="620" page="23" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="621" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">“the web space” and needed to be heavily guided by innovative, young consultants. On the other</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="622" page="23" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="623" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">hand, Eserve leadership put great emphasis on building a strong collaborative culture among</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="624" page="23" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="625" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">consultants and, to this end, implemented a state of the art intranet-based KMS system (E-share),</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="626" page="23" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="627" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">which included, among other things, a repository of consulting tools as well a separate project</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="628" page="23" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="629" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">space for each project participant to share their work-in-progress and completed documents.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="630" page="23" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="631" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Pubco was a division of a well-established publishing company, with headquarters located</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="632" page="23" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="633" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">within a thirty-minute walk from Eserve offices. Pubco relied on strong hierarchical and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="634" page="23" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="635" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">departmental distinctions Historically, Pubco was cautious in dealing with consultants, but, in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="636" confidence="possible" page="23" column="2">three phases—Planning,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="638" page="23" column="3">Prototyping, and Development. <marker type="block"/> 20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="639" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">1 fall 1999, Pubco’s executives decided to hire a consulting firm to revamp their current web site</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="640" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">2</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="641" page="24" column="1">and boost their e-brand.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="642" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">3 development and strategy expertise and that consultant could help prioritize and integrate various 4 grassroots web initiatives that were developed at Pubco in the last five years. It was agreed that 5 the project would be conducted in close collaboration between Eservers (the consultants) and 6 Pubco employees (the clients). 7 Stage I: Too Many Nominated Boundary Spanners: No Boundary Spanners-in-Practice 8 The key objective of the Planning phase of the project was the determination of a business 9 vision for the website. Frank, a seasoned Eserve strategy consultant, became the project’s client</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="643" page="24" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="644" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">partner. Frank usually explained that the definition of his role was to represent the client’s needs</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="645" page="24" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="646" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">to the Eserve team, but he invariably added, “I will always represent [Eserve] team’s needs.”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="647" page="24" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="648" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">In the initial weeks of the project, Pubco participants struggled to understand Eserve’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="649" page="24" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="650" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">approach to the project. It was up to Frank to educate Pubco participants, but in his explanations</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="651" page="24" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="652" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Frank relied heavily on what Eservers themselves referred to as “consulting speak.” In addition,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="653" page="24" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="654" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Frank was often unavailable, due to multiple business obligations. Bob, Eserve’s PM, who was</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="655" page="24" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="656" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">new to Eserve and not yet accustomed to its methods, was the other manager who interfaced with</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="657" page="24" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="658" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">clients. His role expectations included coordination of the work of the team and coordination</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="659" page="24" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="660" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">with clients on specific tasks. Bob, however, considered Pubco a slow-moving bureaucratic</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="661" page="24" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="662" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">organization, not suited for the Internet age, and gave little credit to clients’ opinions.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="663" page="24" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="664" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Simultaneously, Eservers were trying to learn about Pubco’s business through Pubco’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="665" page="24" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="666" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">project coordinator Maya, who was entirely devoted to the project. Maya had no previous</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="667" page="24" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="668" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">experience with the web, but she was a natural choice for a project coordinator because she was a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="669" page="24" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="670" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">professional consultant who had been involved with Pubco for several years, analyzing its</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="671" confidence="possible" page="24" column="2">Pubco’s executives argued that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="672" confidence="possible" page="24" column="3">Pubco lacked advanced web</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="673" page="24" column="3">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="674" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">1 marketing strategy, which was of direct relevance to the Eserve-Pubco project. Pubco’s 2 executive said: “We felt we needed a consultant type to round out our team”. In addition, to 3 Maya, a VP-level project sponsor was involved in the relationship, but he lacked domain 4 expertise and still had to perform his everyday job at Pubco. 5 Yet, the relationship between Maya and Eservers did not work out, to a large degree because 6 Maya initially tried to act “too much like Eservers.” This was not acceptable to Eservers because 7 she “did not know the web space.” Disrespect for Maya grew so far as to be openly expressed 8 during Eserve-Pubco joint meetings. Behind closed doors, Eservers referred to her as “the Queen 9 of Darkness”. Initially, Maya tried to help Eserve communicate with Pubco in terms that Pubco</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="675" page="25" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="676" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">would understand. She provided paper-based versions of documents like Pubco’s strategic plan</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="677" page="25" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="678" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">and market analysis. Frank and Bob, however, discounted these documents as “useless pieces of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="679" page="25" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="680" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">paper” without passing them on to line consultants. Maya also advised Eserve on how to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="681" page="25" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="682" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">approach the project in “a Pubco way.” Eservers complained that Maya tried to impose things on</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="683" page="25" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="684" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">them that did not make sense. At this time, Maya started collecting complaints from Pubco’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="685" page="25" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="686" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">participants about Eserve’s processes and delivering them to Eserve’s top management.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="687" page="25" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="688" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Tensions among the managers on the project grew while Eserve’s and Pubco’s team</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="689" page="25" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="690" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">members continued to rely on the managers to learn about each other’s practices and concerns.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="691" page="25" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="692" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Although Eserve made promises that Pubco people would be able to contribute and access</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="693" page="25" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="694" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">project documents through E-share, the Eserve’s PM and client partner argued that a firewall</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="695" page="25" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="696" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">prevented them from granting Pubco access to the system. This kind of problem, however, had</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="697" page="25" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="698" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">been resolved in the past (and was resolved in the next phase of this project). Moreover, until it</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="699" page="25" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="700" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">became clear that clients would not be able to access E-share, consultants were advised to share</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="701" page="25" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="702" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">their work-in-progress through internal email rather than through E-share. Despite email and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="703" page="25" column="3">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="704" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">1 telephone availability in both firms, small face-to-face group meetings among the managers were 2 the primary mode for issue discussion and decision-making. There were also several scheduled 3 workshops in which all project members participated. 4 Pubco participants viewed the relationship as dysfunctional and feared that their interests 5 would be compromised if they left it up to Eservers to analyze potential web site initiatives. 6 Pubco team members, therefore, came up with top priority initiatives and passed them on to 7 Eserve in a “must have” list. Eservers were not convinced of the strategic value of these 8 initiatives, but interpreted the list as sign of Pubco’s insistence on gaining full control over the 9 intellectual substance of the project. With Pubco threatening to withdraw funding for the next</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="705" page="26" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="706" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">phase, they recommended these initiatives as the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="709" page="26" column="1">11 Stage II: The Emergence of Boundary Objects-in-Use and Boundary Spanners-in-Practice <marker type="block"/> 12 and the Obstacles Created by Nominated Boundary Spanners<marker type="block"/> 13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="710" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">The relationship started slowly mending when line consultants began engaging directly with</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="711" page="26" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="712" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">line Pubco’s members upon the acceptance of the “must have” list. With the most contentious</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="713" page="26" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="714" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">issue out of the way, two junior Eserve strategy consultants started interacting directly with three</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="715" page="26" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="716" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">of Pubco’s team members in face-to-face meetings, further detailing the selected initiatives. This</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="717" page="26" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="718" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">direct relationship became formalized in the Prototyping phase of the project when the work was</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="719" page="26" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="720" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">broken down so that clients and consultants worked together in the “requirements,” “technical,”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="721" page="26" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="722" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">and “design” sub-teams. Members of the requirements sub-team met frequently and created</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="723" page="26" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="724" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">requirements called “Pubco’s Use Cases.” Eserve’s strategists produced initial documents based</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="725" page="26" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="726" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">on their market research and insight (e.g., what makes Amazon.com effective), Eserve’s Use</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="727" page="26" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="728" confidence="possible" page="26" column="1">Case templates stored in E-share, and Pubco’s current web site. Then members from both</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="729" confidence="possible" page="26" column="2">best strategy for the new website.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="730" page="26" column="3">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="731" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">1 organizations discussed the documents in meetings. Through this interaction, they started 2 learning each other’s business language and practical concerns. 3 The hierarchical project management structure, however, was still reinforced on the project 4 with Maya and Eserve’s new project manager Wendy, who replaced Bob, attending every 5 meeting. Maya and Frank, at this point stopped following the details of the work, yet Maya 6 insisted that any significant issue had to be resolved through meetings among project leaders. 7 Meanwhile, through interactions of the requirements team, Eserve consultants became deeply 8 concerned about the strategic value of the initiatives that they recommended. Risking their own 9 careers, they approached Pubco’s requirement team members with whom they had developed a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="732" page="27" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="733" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">good working relationship, and raised their concerns. Pubco participants, however, reported this</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="734" page="27" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="735" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">interaction to Maya according to the established process for resolving significant issues. Maya</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="736" page="27" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="737" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">reprimanded consultants for going outside established ranks.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="739" page="27" column="1">13 The very same Pubco team member who elevated the issue to Maya: Something 14 happened in the communication from our core group to [Maya] and [John] back over to 15 [Eserve]. I think that if there were less process, or it was less formal without having 16 these leaders and project leaders and bearing everything through them, that in all cases 17 early on that were difficult in communication, we would not have had those problems. 18 19 Stage III: Emergent New Joint field Marginalizes Non-spanners <marker type="block"/> 20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="740" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">With the designation of the requirements, technology, and design sub-teams, communication</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="741" page="27" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="742" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">among different professionals</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="743" page="27" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="744" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Increased email and face-to-face communication between Eserve and Pubco took place primarily</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="745" page="27" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="746" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">within these sub-teams; only major completed pieces of work were now posted in E-share.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="747" page="27" column="1">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="748" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">Once Use Cases were finalized, they were placed in E-share and printed for graphic</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="749" page="27" column="1">25</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="750" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">designers to develop designs for the website. The graphic designers, who mostly entered the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="751" page="27" column="1">26</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="752" confidence="possible" page="27" column="1">project during the Prototyping phase and were not interfacing with clients much, lacked an</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="753" confidence="possible" page="27" column="2">within the Eserve team on key project issues became less frequent.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="754" page="27" column="3">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="755" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">1 understanding of Pubco’s business practices and terminology. They did not know how to utilize 2 Use Cases or, if necessary, suggest changes to them. 3 Eserve designer commented: I was looking at them [Use Cases] but I could not 4 understand them. I would read through them, but it seemed like they were not making 5 sense, and it just kept on ...They [requirements sub-team] were sending out a lot of 6 documents. 7 8 For several weeks, designers who received Use Cases did not use them, sometimes throwing 9 the documents into the trashcan. Work on the site design stagnated and strategists blamed the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="756" page="28" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="757" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">designers for their lack of contributions. All designers were re-assigned to other projects after the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="758" page="28" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="759" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">Prototyping phase—a loss to their careers since they could no longer include Pubco’s website in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="760" page="28" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="761" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">their portfolios. Yet, Eserve strategists’ careers got a big boost at Eserve after this project.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="763" page="28" column="1">13 Analytical Overview <marker type="block"/> 14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="764" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">Eserve and Pubco constituted fields, much like Insura, each engaged in the production of a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="765" page="28" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="766" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">specific cultural capital using and transforming species of cultural capital produced in various</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="767" page="28" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="768" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">professional fields. Simultaneously, Eserve and Pubco also held institutionalized positions within</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="769" page="28" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="770" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">the larger field of the consulting practice, which contributed to the development of antagonistic</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="771" page="28" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="772" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">expectations between their respective members. During the first stage of the project, Eserve and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="773" page="28" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="774" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">Pubco had each nominated two agents as boundary spanners, but none of these four agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="775" page="28" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="776" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">actually became a boundary spanner-in-practice. The four nominated boundary spanners</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="777" page="28" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="778" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">remained unable or unwilling to use various designated boundary objects (e.g., the strategic plan,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="779" page="28" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="780" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">market research document, “must have” list) in a way that related practices of the two fields. In</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="781" page="28" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="782" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">addition, they limited others’ direct use of IT (email or KMS) and, hence, prevented the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="783" page="28" column="1">24</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="784" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">emergence of alternative boundary spanners-in-practice.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="787" page="28" column="1">25 <marker type="block"/> In the second stage<marker type="block"/> 26</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="788" confidence="possible" page="28" column="1">communication among line consultants and Pubco members on smaller scale issues. Eserve</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="789" page="28" column="2">of the project, nominated boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="790" confidence="possible" page="28" column="3">spanners allowed direct</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="791" page="28" column="3">25</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="792" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">1 strategy consultants were the first to emerge as boundary spanners-in-practice: they started 2 reflecting upon objects produced in various fields (e.g., strategy group within Pubco produced 3 the strategic plan and KMS group within Eserve produced an archive of Use Case templates) and 4 negotiating the relationship between the fields by creating and using new objects such as Pubco’s 5 Use Cases. Pubco’ Use Cases became boundary objects-in-use and were used and co-produced in 6 the new joint field (constituted by the members of the requirements team). In the new joint field, 7 a common identity for Pubco’s Use Cases emerged which signified that Eservers would draw on 8 their expertise (cultural capital) in the wider web space, while Pubco would draw on their 9 expertise in the publishing business. The symbolic capital associated with the participation in this</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="793" page="29" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="794" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">joint field, however, had limited value within Pubco as Maya used the symbolic capital of her</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="795" page="29" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="796" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">role as a nominated boundary spanner to preserve her privileged position and limit boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="797" page="29" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="798" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">spanners-in-practice ability to fully engage in practices in both fields.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="799" page="29" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="800" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">In the third stage, boundaries among professional fields within Eserve were re-enforced</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="801" page="29" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="802" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">through practice. Eserve strategists as well as Wendy had become boundary spanners-in-practice</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="803" page="29" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="804" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">for the boundary between Eserve’s and Pubco’s fields thereby distinguishing designers as “non-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="805" page="29" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="806" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">spanners.” Use Cases were thus boundary objects-in-use between Eserve and Pubco but</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="807" page="29" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="808" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">remained designated boundary objects among Eserve’s sub-teams. This had different impacts on</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="809" page="29" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="810" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">the respective careers of Eserve’s strategists as opposed to designers.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="812" page="29" column="1">19 20 <marker type="block"/> 21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="813" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">In this section, after contrasting the two cases, we examine how agents become boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="814" page="29" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="815" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">spanners-in-practice and how artifacts become boundary objects-in-use. In line with Bourdieu’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="816" page="29" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="817" confidence="possible" page="29" column="1">theory of practice, our discussion stresses the dilemmas and conflicts experienced by agents who</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Discussion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="818" page="29" column="2">DISCUSSION</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="819" page="29" column="3">26</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="821" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">1 occupy various positions in multiple fields and are expected to perform different roles in diverse 2 fields. 3 The Emergence of New Joint Fields: Cross-Case Comparison 4 A cross-case comparison reveals key differences in settings summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="820" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="822" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">5</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="823" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">Table 3: Comparing the main dimensions of the two cases</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="3" page="30">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Dimensions of</th>
                  <th class="table"> Insura case</th>
                  <th class="table"> Eserve-Pubco case</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> analysis</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundaries</td>
                  <td class="table"> HQ Among Departments/Local Local Teams teams.</td>
                  <td class="table"> Eserve/Pubco Eserve Strategists vs. Designers</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Material context of</td>
                  <td class="table"> Geographically Distributed</td>
                  <td class="table"> Co-located or located at close distance</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> practice</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Stages in boundary</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 1: no joint field</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 1: no joint field</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> spanning in practice</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 2: two new joint fields emerge</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 2: a new joint field emerges</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 3: New agents engage in the</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 3: a few select agents are</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> production of the new joint field</td>
                  <td class="table"> engaged in the production of the new joint field</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Emergence of a</td>
                  <td class="table"> Two new joint fields emerges</td>
                  <td class="table"> A new joint field emerges distinguishing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> joint field</td>
                  <td class="table"> distinguishing those who do and</td>
                  <td class="table"> Eserve agents who understand</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> those who do not contribute to the</td>
                  <td class="table"> Pubco’s business and Pubco’s agents</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> FAQ and commercial initiatives</td>
                  <td class="table"> who understand Eserve’s business and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> folders respectively.</td>
                  <td class="table"> those who do not</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Nominated</td>
                  <td class="table"> Marketing agents from headquarters.</td>
                  <td class="table"> Frank, Bob, Maya, and Pubco’s VP,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary spanners</td>
                  <td class="table"> Dominique, the webmaster.</td>
                  <td class="table"> and later Wendy.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary spanners-</td>
                  <td class="table"> Dominique, in the 2 nd and 3 rd stages.</td>
                  <td class="table"> Eserve’s and Pubco’s members of the</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> in-practice</td>
                  <td class="table"> Some sales agents and rd members of</td>
                  <td class="table"> requirements team including Wendy.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> headquarters, in the 3 stage.</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Designated-</td>
                  <td class="table"> Paper-based posters and</td>
                  <td class="table"> Pubco strategic plan, Eserve’s Use</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> boundary objects</td>
                  <td class="table"> newsletters, homepage, occupational</td>
                  <td class="table"> Case templates, and “must have” list</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> documentation on the intranet.</td>
                  <td class="table"> shared in person.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Boundary objects-</td>
                  <td class="table"> Intranet-based FAQ and “commercial</td>
                  <td class="table"> Pubco’s Use Cases shared in</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> in-use</td>
                  <td class="table"> initiatives” folder.</td>
                  <td class="table"> meetings, email, and through E-share.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> IT use practices</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 1: Limited use.</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 1: Not used</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 2: A boundary spanner-in-</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 2: Boundary spanners-in-</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> practice creates and shares objects</td>
                  <td class="table"> practice create and share objects using</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> using the intranet</td>
                  <td class="table"> an e-mail list.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 3: The development of the joint</td>
                  <td class="table"> Stage 3: Boundary spanners-in-</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> field through the use of objects on the</td>
                  <td class="table"> practice create and share objects using</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> intranet.</td>
                  <td class="table"> email and E-share intranet.</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="824" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">Dimensions of Insura case Eserve-Pubco case analysis Boundaries HQ Departments/Local teams. Eserve/Pubco Among Local Teams Eserve Strategists vs. Designers Material context of Geographically Distributed Co-located or located at close distance practice Stages in boundary Stage 1: no joint field Stage 1: no joint field spanning in practice Stage 2: two new joint fields emerge Stage 2: a new joint field emerges Stage 3: New agents engage in the Stage 3: a few select agents are production of the new joint field engaged in the production of the new joint field Emergence of a Two new joint fields emerges A new joint field emerges distinguishing joint field distinguishing those who do and Eserve agents who understand those who do not contribute to the Pubco’s business and Pubco’s agents FAQ and commercial initiatives who understand Eserve’s business and folders respectively. those who do not Nominated Marketing agents from headquarters. Frank, Bob, Maya, and Pubco’s VP, Boundary spanners Dominique, the webmaster. and later Wendy. nd rd Boundary spanners- Dominique, in the 2 and 3 stages. Eserve’s and Pubco’s members of the in-practice Some sales agents and members of requirements team including Wendy. rd headquarters, in the 3 stage. Designated- Paper-based posters and Pubco strategic plan, Eserve’s Use boundary objects newsletters, homepage, occupational Case templates, and “must have” list documentation on the intranet. shared in person. Boundary objects- Intranet-based FAQ and “commercial Pubco’s Use Cases shared in in-use initiatives” folder. meetings, email, and through E-share. IT use practices Stage 1: Limited use. Stage 1: Not used Stage 2: A boundary spanner-in- Stage 2: Boundary spanners-in- practice creates and shares objects practice create and share objects using using the intranet an e-mail list. Stage 3: The development of the joint Stage 3: Boundary spanners-in- field through the use of objects on the practice create and share objects using intranet. email and E-share intranet.</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="826" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">6 7 In addition to differences noted in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="825" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref>, some key difference had to do with the relation of the 8 new joint field to other fields in the setting. In the Insura case, the new joint field surrounding the 9 FAQ use was a sub-field of an organizational field of Insura and the new joint field surrounding</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="827" page="30" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="828" confidence="possible" page="30" column="1">the commercial initiatives folder use was a sub-field of the sales agents’ professional field. In the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="829" page="30" column="3">27</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="830" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">1 Eserve-Pubco case, the new joint field was situated in the field of management consulting 2 practice. From prior literature, we know that it is possible that new joint fields become sub-fields 3 of other kinds of fields such as the field of labor negotiation (Friedman and Podolny 1992). 4 Despite these differences, we identified a conceptually similar scenario of emergence of new 5 joint fields in both cases. A critical aspect of this emergence is that boundary spanners-in- 6 practice engage in producing new kinds of practices in each setting. By producing these practices 7 they and other agents from diverse fields develop an interest in pursuing unique new stakes 8 involved in relating practices produced in diverse fields. As part of the negotiation of the 9 relationship between diverse fields, involved agents become willing to change the way they</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="831" page="31" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="832" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">practice in their local fields so as to participate in the new joint field (e.g., Insura’s sales agents</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="833" page="31" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="834" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">contributing and reading FAQs or commercial initiatives folders’ postings). The new joint field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="835" page="31" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="837" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">helps agents develop a new distinction (identity according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="836" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>) as “participants in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="838" page="31" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="840" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">these new joint fields” (e.g., as a member of Eserve-Pubco requirements team). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="839" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref></region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="841" page="31" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="842" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">demonstrates the emergence of a new joint field. By engaging in this new joint field, agents both</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="843" page="31" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="844" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">draw on organizations’ competence in boundary spanning and contribute to its development.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="847" page="31" column="1">16 <marker type="block"/> 17</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="846" page="31" column="1">Becoming a Boundary Spanner-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="848" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">In the two cases, a significant number of agents were nominated to perform different</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="849" page="31" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="850" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">boundary spanning roles (a solution advocated by Friedman and Podolny 1992), but only a few</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="851" page="31" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="852" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">of them became boundary spanners-in-practice. Based on practice theory and on our data</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="853" page="31" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="854" confidence="possible" page="31" column="1">analysis, we found three necessary, but not necessarily sufficient, conditions for an agent to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="856" page="31" column="1">21 become a boundary spanner-in-practice. <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 28</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="857" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">1 2 In order to become a boundary spanner in practice, an agent must develop an interest (ability 3 and inclination) in negotiating relationships between fields. The first two necessary conditions 4 we outline relate to developing an ability to span boundaries, while the second one has to do with 5 having an inclination to do so. No set of conditions can be sufficient, though, because becoming 6 a boundary spanner-in-practice involves developing a practice that involves other agents and 7 associated unforeseen consequences of actions. 8 First, becoming a boundary spanner-in-practice requires becoming a 9 peripheral, participant in the practices of both fields. Because boundary spanning requires an</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="858" page="32" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="859" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">ability to negotiate the relationship between the involved practices, it requires the development</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="860" page="32" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="862" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">of an at least peripheral understanding of each practice. Drawing on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="861" class="deo:Reference">Lave and Wenger (1991)</xref>, a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="863" page="32" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="864" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">legitimate peripheral participant (LPP) gains access to the practices and artifacts of a field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="865" page="32" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="866" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">(legitimacy) and takes stakes in the field and in the reproduction of its practices (participation).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="867" page="32" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="868" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">This is not an easy condition to satisfy as it involves perturbing relations of power within settings</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="869" page="32" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="870" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">and serving “as a source of power or powerlessness, in affording or preventing articulation and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="871" page="32" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="873" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">interchange among settings” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="872" class="deo:Reference">Lave and Wenger 1991</xref>: 36). Thus, to become LPP, agents may</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="874" page="32" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="875" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">need to draw on their economic, cultural, social, and symbolic capital. For example, as Eservers</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="876" page="32" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="877" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">guarded the boundary of their field very diligently, Maya did not have enough symbolic capital</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="878" page="32" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="879" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">to become seen as legitimate,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="880" page="32" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="881" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">the project late and did not have enough economic capital (time) to participate in Pubco’s</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="882" page="32" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="883" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">practice. On the other hand, Dominique used his cultural capital (the understanding of sales</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="884" page="32" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="885" confidence="possible" page="32" column="1">agents’ practices), economic capital (time and money to take “Tour de France”), social capital</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="886" page="32" column="2">Necessary conditions</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="887" confidence="possible" page="32" column="2">even peripheral, participant at Eserve. Eserve’s designers joined</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="888" confidence="possible" page="32" column="3">legitimate, but possibly</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="889" page="32" column="3">29</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="890" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">1 (his contacts with the sales network), and symbolic capital (his old fame as a prominent sales 2 agent) to become LPP in sales agents’ field. 3 Second, on top of being LPP in both fields, boundary spanners-in-practice must have 4 legitimacy not only as participants, but also as 5 example, at first, Eserve’s strategy consultants, even upon becoming LPP in both fields, did not 6 have enough legitimacy as negotiators of the relationship due to their junior status at Eserve. 7 Dominique, on the other hand, used the symbolic capital of his webmaster’s position to gain such 8 legitimacy within the fields that he spanned. It is not necessary for these agents to be full 9 participants in both fields to gain the legitimacy as negotiators as such legitimacy can come</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="891" page="33" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="892" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">through nomination or evolve through object use, for example.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="893" page="33" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="894" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">Third, agents engage in boundary spanning because they develop an inclination to do so.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="895" page="33" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="896" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">This inclination may be based on perceiving greater advantages within their organizational or</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="897" page="33" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="898" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">professional fields from spanning a given boundary than from not doing so. Frank, for instance,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="899" page="33" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="900" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">articulated clearly that he had no inclination to represent Pubco’s interests, as he felt he had a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="901" page="33" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="902" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">strong interest in being seen as representing only Eserve’s side. By contrast, Wendy and strategy</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="903" page="33" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="904" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">consultants were relative newcomers to Eserve. They did not have such strong stakes in their full</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="905" page="33" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="906" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">association with Eserve, and were more inclined to engage in spanning the boundary with Pubco.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="908" page="33" column="1">18 <marker type="block"/> 19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="909" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">As boundary spanners-in-practice engage in relating diverse fields, they become different</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="910" page="33" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="911" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">from others within these fields—they develop a distinction as “boundary spanners.” To</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="912" page="33" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="913" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">overcome the marginalization of this potentially negative distinction, boundary spanners-in–</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="914" page="33" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="915" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">practice develop an interest in separating their practices from the practices of others and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="916" page="33" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="917" confidence="possible" page="33" column="1">developing an “enclave” for themselves and others like them. They also start negotiating the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="918" confidence="possible" page="33" column="2">negotiators on behalf of others in a field. For</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="919" page="33" column="2">Investing in the New Joint Field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="920" page="33" column="3">30</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="921" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">1 status of their distinction as a potential source of power in the larger fields to which they belong 2 —producing a capital. In this way, boundary spanners-in-practice start producing a new joint 3 field. For this field to be sustained, being seen as “boundary spanners” becomes a symbolic 4 capital that boundary spanners-in-practice can use for advancement. For instance, Eserve’s 5 strategists used their position as boundary spanners with Pubco to advance within Eserve and, 6 possibly later, within the profession (say, through good recommendations). Similarly, agents at 7 Insura who used and contributed to the “commercial initiatives” folder became seen as boundary 8 spanners and were symbolically recognized at Insura. Some of those who used the folder gained, 9 first, professional, and then, economic capital as sales agents. Finally, some professionals, such</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="922" page="34" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="923" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">as IS managers (Pawlowski and Robey 2005) like Dominique, actually develop a permanent</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="924" page="34" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="925" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">identity as boundary spanners among different fields. Building a joint field becomes fully aligned</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="926" page="34" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="927" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">with their interests in professional advancement.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="930" page="34" column="1">13 <marker type="block"/> 14</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="929" page="34" column="1">Emergence of Boundary Objects-in-Use</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="931" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Boundary objects-in-use were defined as acquiring both a local usefulness and a common</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="932" page="34" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="933" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">identity in practice. Below we outline certain conditions necessary for their emergence.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="935" page="34" column="1">16 <marker type="block"/> 17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="937" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Consistent with prior studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="936" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>; Bechky 2003), we found that for artifacts to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="938" page="34" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="939" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">acquire a local usefulness, agents must use and make sense of them in the context of each field.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="940" page="34" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="941" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">For example, Pubco’s Use Cases were not used by designers and did not make sense to them.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="942" page="34" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="943" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">From Bourdieu’s practice theory, we also consider what it takes for an artifact-in-use to acquire a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="944" page="34" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="945" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">common identity. We view common identity as a shared symbolic capital – a way of naming or</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="946" page="34" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="947" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">referring to an object that makes it recognizable in practice. To develop this symbolic capital,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="948" page="34" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="949" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">there must be a joint field in which agents jointly recognize and value the artifact. Thus, many</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="950" page="34" column="2">Necessary Conditions</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="951" page="34" column="3">31</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="952" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">1 designated boundary objects that had acquired a local usefulness, such as Pubco’s “must have 2 list”, did not emerge as boundary objects until a joint field emerged. 3 Boundary Spanners-in-Practice Producing and Using Boundary Objects-in-Use 4 To establish local usefulness of boundary objects-in-use in each practice and to establish 5 their common identity as jointly recognized symbolic capital, we found that organizations rely on 6 boundary spanners-in-practice. Only the agents who are centrally engaged in the negotiation of 7 the relationship between practices and thus posses a significant amount of symbolic capital can 8 establish an object as symbolically valuable across contexts (Bourdieu 1998: 57) 9 We now turn to discussing how boundary spanners-in-practice engage in establishing and co-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="953" page="35" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="954" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">producing boundary objects-in-use. First, boundary spanners-in-practice reflect on objects from</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="955" page="35" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="956" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">each field (which they accessed by being LPP) and interpret them in terms of their own practices</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="957" page="35" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="958" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">in the new joint field, thereby relating the objects to each other. For instance, Eserve strategists</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="959" page="35" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="960" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">reflected on the Use Case templates they found in E-share and on Pubco’s old website and tried</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="961" page="35" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="962" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">to understand the relationship between the two.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="963" page="35" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="964" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Second, upon reflection, boundary spanners-in-practice create new artifacts (or adopt</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="965" page="35" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="966" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">existing artifacts) and establish a new identity for these artifacts in the context of a new joint</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="967" page="35" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="968" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">field. For instance, Dominique reflected on sales agent’s feedback about the Intranet as well as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="969" page="35" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="970" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">on documents produced at headquarters to design the FAQ applications that signified the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="971" page="35" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="972" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">relationship between agents at headquarters as advice givers and sales agents as advice seekers.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="973" page="35" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="974" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Third, boundary spanners-in-practice use various species of capital that they accumulated to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="975" page="35" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="976" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">establish the local usefulness and negotiate the symbolic value of the artifacts that they promote 4 To be clear, this is not to say that every relationship has to be symbolically represented through the use of an artifact (Bourdieu 1977: 183-197); nor that a boundary spanner must continue being involved in the joint practice and negotiate the joint meaning of the artifact. We discuss situations in which this needs or does not need to happen elsewhere [Reference Suppressed].</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="977" page="35" column="3">4</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="978" page="35" column="3">32</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="979" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">1 as boundary objects. Dominique masterfully used various species of capital that he accumulated 2 to do so for various Intranet applications. He used his symbolic capital to obtain economic 3 capital from department heads at headquarters to assign agents to answer questions posted in the 4 FAQ folders. He also used his social capital (old contacts); cultural capital in the MIS field 5 (knowing how to build an FAQ application), cultural capital in the professional field (knowing 6 sales agents’ work practices), cultural capital in the Insura field (knowing that Insura wanted 7 sales agents to use certain information from headquarters); and various types of symbolic capital 8 (as a webmaster in the Insura field and as a distinguished sales agent in the professional sales 9 field) to prove usefulness and stimulate contributions to the commercial initiatives folder.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="980" page="36" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="981" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Finally, as artifacts emerge as boundary objects-in-practice, boundary spanners-in-use use them</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="982" page="36" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="983" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">to further signify their positions in the new joint fields and the position of their field vis-à-vis</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="984" page="36" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="985" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">other fields. Eserve strategists used Pubco’s Use Cases for this purpose.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="988" page="36" column="1">13 <marker type="block"/> 14</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="987" page="36" column="1">Tensions in Building Organizational Competencies in Boundary Spanning</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="989" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">In line with practice theorizing, we now illuminate key tensions that are inherent in the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="990" page="36" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="991" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">emergence of the new joint practice and the associated organizational competence in boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="992" page="36" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="993" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">spanning. We highlight four types of tensions: 1) between the acts of nomination and designation</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="994" page="36" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="995" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">and the practical enactments; 2) between agents’ investing in attaining stakes in local fields</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="996" page="36" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="997" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">versus attaining stakes in new joint fields; 3) between growing or restricting the growth of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="998" page="36" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="999" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">joint field; and 4) between organizational investments in developing competencies in spanning</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1000" page="36" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1001" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">one vs. another type of boundary.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1002" page="36" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1003" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">We have started by distinguishing between boundary spanning in theory and in practice. We</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1004" page="36" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1005" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">found that the acts of nomination and designation by agents empowered in organizational fields</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1007" page="36" column="1">23 are neither sufficient, nor necessary for the intended practices to emerge; rather, they serve a <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> 33</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1008" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">1 kind of “mediating” role in practice. 2 with the nominated role helps agents who are interested in spanning boundaries in practice to 3 foster the emergence of a new joint field as it helps them access local fields, obtain other 4 necessary resources, and be seen as legitimate negotiators. On the other hand, owning this 5 symbolic capital also helps those agents who decide not to take stakes in developing a new joint 6 field to prevent others from doing so. Such agents use their symbolic capital to contest the 7 legitimacy of others who want to engage in boundary spanning or to deny them access to local</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1009" page="37" column="1">8 practices. A similar situation</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1010" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">9 conceptually similar to the roles of nominated boundary spanners. The ownership of the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1011" page="37" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1012" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">symbolic value associated with these objects is used to either foster or inhibit the emergence of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1013" page="37" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1014" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">new joint fields (e.g., Pubco’s strategic plan vs. Insura’s commercial initiatives folder).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1015" page="37" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1016" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">The second tension involved in this emergence is experienced by agents who are or consider</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1017" page="37" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1018" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">engaging in the joint field. On one hand, engaging in such practice may help agents advance in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1019" page="37" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1020" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">their “local” fields if the capital associated with their engagement in the joint field can be</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1021" page="37" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1022" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">converted into something of value in their local fields. On the other hand, engaging, especially</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1023" page="37" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1024" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">fully, in the joint field, like investing in a start-up company, requires using one’s capital. This</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1025" page="37" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1026" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">capital could be usefully applied to advance in local fields. Moreover, accumulating the new kind</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1027" page="37" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1028" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">of capital in a joint field may be highly risky: agents may loose it entirely if the joint field</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1029" page="37" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1030" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">becomes stigmatized in the fields being spanned. If Eserve-Pubco project had been declared a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1031" page="37" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1032" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">failure, requirements team members would risk loosing their accumulated capital. A professional</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1033" page="37" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1034" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">who invests in building organizational competence in boundary spanning as opposed to in their</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1035" page="37" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1037" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">own professional competence may be making a firm-specific investment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="1036" class="deo:Reference">Lepak and Snell 1999</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1038" page="37" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1039" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">There are professions (like IS management) for which these two investments are not in conflict.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1040" confidence="possible" page="37" column="2">On the one hand, having the symbolic capital associated</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1043" page="37" column="2">is observed with designated <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> boundary objects, which are<marker type="block"/> 34</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1044" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">1 Beyond these “classical” considerations, there is a third, related, tension faced by boundary 2 spanners-in-practice. On one hand they have an interest in growing the practice and encouraging 3 others to engage in co-defining and using boundary objects so as to get symbolically recognized 4 in the organizational field for their efforts in spreading a valuable practice as well as to develop a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1045" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">5 possibly permanent distinction.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1046" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">6 development of the Intranet and took credit for the spread of Intranet use at Insura. On the other 7 hand, as more agents start engaging in the new joint field and start taking credit for evolving it, 8 participation in the joint field may stop serving as a valuable distinction. As these agents start 9 taking part in co-defining the boundary objects-in-use, the joint recognition of these objects as</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1047" page="38" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1048" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">valuable may disappear. If, for example, all Insura’s sales agents started contributing to the best</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1049" page="38" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1050" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">practice database, contributors would no longer be positively distinguished (as evidenced in the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1051" page="38" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1054" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">cases described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="1052" class="deo:Reference">Schultze and Boland 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="1053" class="deo:Reference">Garud and Kumaraswamy 2004</xref>).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1055" page="38" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1056" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">Fourth, as agents engage in the joint field, they produce a new boundary between boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1057" page="38" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1058" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">spanners and “non-spanners,” which creates a tension between growing one or the another kind</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1059" page="38" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1063" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">of competence in boundary spanning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="1060" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>: 141; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="1061" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>: 442; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="1062" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>:</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1064" page="38" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1065" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">269). Through our theorizing, we further unpack this tension. As organizational leadership</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1066" page="38" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1067" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">invests resources in spanning one kind of boundary, they foster the emergence a new boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1068" page="38" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1069" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">between agents who are engaged in the new joint field and agents who are not engaged, or</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1070" page="38" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1071" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">engaged only peripherally. The more Eserve leadership, for example, invested in building</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1072" page="38" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1073" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">“Eserve culture”, the harder it became for others (like Maya) to engage in boundary spanning</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1074" page="38" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1075" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">with Eserve agents. At the same time, the more Eserve strategists engaged in boundary spanning</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1076" page="38" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1077" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">with the client, the harder it became for them to relate to their Eserve colleagues (designers and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1078" page="38" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1079" confidence="possible" page="38" column="1">people working on other projects).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1080" confidence="possible" page="38" column="2">Thus, Dominique involved</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1082" page="38" column="3">several other agents in the <marker type="block"/> 35</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1083" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">1 2</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="1084" page="39" column="1">IMPLICATIONS FOR IS IMPLEMENTATION AND USE IN SUPPORTING KNOWLEDGE MANAGEMENT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1085" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">3 IT-based artifacts have long been viewed as boundary objects intended to support the 4 integration of expertise situated in diverse fields (Star 1989; Boland and Tenkasi 1995; 5 Pawlowski and Robey 2005). We contribute to the IS literature by discussing how system 6 sponsors, who are in positions of power and supervise the introduction, implementation, and use 7 of IS, can take into consideration the practical tensions associated with the emergence of IT- 8 based artifacts as boundary objects-in-use . We look at two key decisions that such agents 9 typically influence: 1) how to choose agents to be nominated into boundary spanning roles; and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1086" page="39" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1087" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">2) how to grow or restrict the growth of practices surrounding IS use.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1088" page="39" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1089" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">We argued that the reliance on boundary spanners-in-practice is crucial for the emergence of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1090" page="39" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1091" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">IT artifacts as boundary objects-in-use. We also argued that nominating agents to particular</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1092" page="39" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1093" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">boundary spanners’ roles and designing IT artifacts for particular boundary spanning purposes</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1094" page="39" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1095" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">may hurt or help the development of a boundary spanning competence depending on whose</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1096" page="39" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1097" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">hands these titles and objects fall into. In IS implementation efforts, IS project managers or KM</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1098" page="39" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1099" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">group members are typically nominated to perform boundary spanning roles. Our findings</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1100" page="39" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1101" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">suggest the importance of paying close attention to the positions of nominated agents within each</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1102" page="39" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1103" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">field involved. Are these agents able and willing to become at least peripheral participants in the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1106" page="39" column="1">19 <marker type="block"/> practices of the fields they<marker type="block"/> 20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1107" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">marginalization within these fields to gain the benefits of building the new joint field? These</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1108" page="39" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1109" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">considerations may imply that, rather than promoting—and it is often a promotion—a person</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1110" page="39" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1111" confidence="possible" page="39" column="1">who is most distinguished in a given field to a boundary spanning position, building an 5 We view IS as an infrastructure supporting the use of IT-based artifacts, which may be specific IT applications.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1112" page="39" column="2">5</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1115" page="39" column="2">are supposed to span? Are <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> they willing to risk possible<marker type="block"/> 36</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1116" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">1 organizational competence in boundary spanning may require promoting somebody who is less 2 distinguished. Beyond the classical considerations of “let professionals do what they are good at 3 doing”, our investigation shows that “stellar professionals” or “strong local team players” may be 4 unwilling to become even partial participants in the practices of the other field. On the other 5 hand, this consideration needs to be balanced with the concern for legitimacy of a nominated 6 boundary spanner as a negotiator on behalf of a field. Our data shows that through the 7 “supremely mysterious power” of nomination (Bourdieu 1998: 51), even peripheral participants 8 in a given field can be seen as legitimate negotiators. 9 Beyond the initial nomination of boundary spanners, system sponsors also have to follow</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1117" page="40" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1118" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">what happens in practice. They need to see if nominated boundary spanners actually engage in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1119" page="40" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1120" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">building the joint field or, instead, if they are using their position to prevent the emergence of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1121" page="40" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1122" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">alternative boundary spanners-in-practice. Designing of an IT-based artifact as a boundary object</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1123" page="40" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1124" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">“for everybody to use” (for example, by granting everybody proper permissions to develop and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1125" page="40" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1126" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">use these artifacts) as opposed to “for nominated boundary spanners to decide how to use them”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1127" page="40" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1128" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">may lead to the later scenario. In this case, the geographical proximity may be detrimental to the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1129" page="40" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1130" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">emergence of a joint field as nominated boundary spanners can advocate avoidance and put</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1131" page="40" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1132" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">restrictions on IT use. In distributed contexts, there is greater incentive even for nominated</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1133" page="40" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1134" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">boundary spanners to use IT as economic capital to reduce the costs of transporting artifacts.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1135" page="40" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1136" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">The second key area of influence for system sponsors concern how they use their symbolic,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1137" page="40" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1138" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">economic, cultural, and social capital to influence a wider adoption of IS. From our discussion, it</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1139" page="40" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1140" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">follows that investing in a wider adoption may be problematic for several reasons. First, as IT-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1141" page="40" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1142" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">based artifacts get widely adopted (e.g., beyond agents involved in their development), they may</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1143" page="40" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1144" confidence="possible" page="40" column="1">stop being boundary objects-in-use by either failing to be useful in local practices or losing their</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1145" page="40" column="3">37</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1150" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">1 common identity. It is well documented that wider uses of IS are often in conflict with local 2 practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="1146" class="deo:Reference">Suchman 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="1147" class="deo:Reference">Star and Ruhdeler 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="1148" class="deo:Reference">Nidumolu et al. 2001</xref>). Our work emphasizes 3 the need to pay continuous attention not only to local usefulness, but also to the development and 4 maintenance of a common identity for IT-based artifacts designed to support KM across 5 boundaries. Failure to do so may lead to IS use that merely reifies existing boundaries (as was 6 demonstrated in an example of a KMS implementation described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="1149" class="deo:Reference">Newell et al. 2001</xref>). As 7 agents from new and different practices start using a given IS, boundary spanners-in-practice 8 need to emerge for these new boundaries. 9 The second tension associated with wider adoption of IS intended to support boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1151" page="41" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1152" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">spanning in practice is that, through such growth, boundary spanners’-in-practice “value added”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1153" page="41" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1154" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">(symbolic capital) gets eroded if other agents engage in the joint field and start participating</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1155" page="41" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1156" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">more fully in the negotiation of the relationship among fields. This happened in the case</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1157" page="41" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1158" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">described by Schultze and Boland’s (2000) and resulted in boundary spanners-in-practice</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1159" page="41" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1160" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">resisting wider adoption of a KMS so as to preserve their position as the only boundary spanners-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1161" page="41" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1162" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">in-practice in a given organization. Thus, when investing resources in growing the practice,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1163" page="41" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1164" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">system sponsors should consider the possibility of such resistance.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1165" page="41" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1166" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">Finally, system sponsors need to be careful when providing incentives for systems’ growth,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1167" page="41" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1168" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">such as symbolic distinctions and monetary rewards. If rewards are widely accessible to many</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1169" page="41" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1170" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">agents in the organizational field, then the wide adoption and contribution to the system may lead</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1171" page="41" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1173" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">to information overload (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="1172" class="deo:Reference">Garud and Kumaraswamy 2004</xref>). On other hand, if these distinctions</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1174" page="41" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1175" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">are hard to obtain and are seen as valuable in practice, then agents who contribute to and use the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1176" page="41" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1177" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">system may start protecting their prerogative as the only system users (boundary spanners-in-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1178" page="41" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1179" confidence="possible" page="41" column="1">practice) vs. non-users (non-spanners). Thus, the development of a strong group of active users</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1180" page="41" column="3">38</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1181" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">1 who see themselves as “elite” boundary spanners may be critical for fostering an organizational 2 competence in boundary spanning (as we saw in the Insura case) but it may also be detrimental 3 to it (as in the case of Eserve designers).</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1182" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">4</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="1183" page="42" column="1">CONTRIBUTIONS TO KNOWLDEGE MANAGEMENT</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1185" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">5 The practice-based view on KM in organizations draws on practice theory and on the notion 6 of situatedness to argue that organizational competencies (knowledgeability) are embedded in 7 practice. Whereas earlier works on this topic focused on how to build competencies within 8 particular domains of expertise (communities of practice) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="1184" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid 1991</xref>), more 9 recent works argued that another critical aspect of such competencies is in agents’ ability to span</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1186" page="42" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1189" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">multiple boundaries in practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="1187" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>; Bechky 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="1188" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>). The key</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1190" page="42" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1191" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">contribution of our work to this literature is in examining how an organizational competence in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1192" page="42" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1193" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">boundary spanning actually</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1194" page="42" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1195" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">engagement of agents in a new joint field—“a space between”—through which agents develop a</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1196" page="42" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1197" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">new interest in spanning boundaries of multiple fields and eventually “transforming knowledge”</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1198" page="42" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1200" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1"> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="1199" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>). We show how the emergence of a new joint field is facilitated by agents who</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1201" page="42" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1202" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">become boundary spanners-in-practice and by the use of artifacts that become boundary objects-</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1203" page="42" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1204" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">in-use. In this way, we integrate more closely extensive streams of research on boundary</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1205" page="42" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1206" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">spanners and objects into a practice-based view on KM.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1207" page="42" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1208" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">The second contribution of this paper to the literature on KM is in providing a theoretical and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1209" page="42" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1210" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">empirical examination of the specific tensions involved in fostering the emergence of a new joint</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1211" page="42" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1212" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">field. The existence of tensions involved in developing an organizational competence in</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1213" page="42" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1214" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">boundary spanning has been acknowledged before. Prior research points out that individual</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1215" page="42" column="1">23</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1216" confidence="possible" page="42" column="1">agents may struggle to achieve knowledge transformation across boundaries (specifically across</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1217" confidence="possible" page="42" column="2">emerges in practice. Such emergence is associated with the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1218" page="42" column="3">39</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1224" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">1 "pragmatic" boundaries according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="1219" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="1220" class="deo:Reference">Carlile 2004</xref>); that formal organizational 2 mechanisms (like roles and rules) may not translate into the development of intended situated 3 practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="1221" class="deo:Reference">Brown and Duguid 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="1222" class="deo:Reference">Wenger 1998</xref>); and that organizations may develop inertia 4 associated with building joint fields (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="1223" class="deo:Reference">Orlikowski 2002</xref>). This paper views these different kinds of 5 tensions through a single theoretical lens which draws on Bourdieu’s theory and in light of the 6 emergence of a new joint field. 7 Finally, we draw on IS literature to clarify how IT-based artifacts can support the 8 development of an organizational competence in boundary-spanning by becoming boundary 9 objects-in-use. Various types of IS, and KMS in particular, are often designated as tools to</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1225" page="43" column="1">10</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1226" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">support KM across the boundaries of professional communities and distributed groups (Alavi</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1227" page="43" column="1">11</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1228" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">and Leidner 2001; Pan and Leidner 2003). In practice, however, the implementation and use of</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1229" page="43" column="1">12</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1231" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">this systems often fails to fulfill these expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="1230" class="deo:Reference">McDermott 1999</xref>; Schultze and Boland</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1232" page="43" column="1">13</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1233" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">2000). Specifically, many IT-based artifacts are used solely in local contexts and do not promote</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1234" page="43" column="1">14</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1236" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">the emergence of organizational competence in boundary spanning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="1235" class="deo:Reference">Newell et al. 2001</xref>; Currie</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1237" page="43" column="1">15</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1239" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="1238" class="deo:Reference">Kerrin 2004</xref>). It has been argued that IT use for KM is more likely to succeed when the</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1240" page="43" column="1">16</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1241" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">system is integrated into practices of particular communities (Goodman and Darr 1998;</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1242" page="43" column="1">17</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1244" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="1243" class="deo:Reference">McDermott 1999</xref>) as illustrated by the successful implementation of Xerox’s “Eureka” system,</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1245" page="43" column="1">18</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1246" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">for example (Bobrow and Whalen 2002). Our paper illuminates how IT can be implemented and</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1247" page="43" column="1">19</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1248" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">used to support KM across boundaries</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1249" page="43" column="1">20</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1250" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">field (a new “organizational community”). This view allow us to highlight specific tensions that</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1251" page="43" column="1">21</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1252" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">IS project sponsors need to pay attention to when nominating project managers and growing</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1253" page="43" column="1">22</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1254" confidence="possible" page="43" column="1">organizational competencies in boundary spanning.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1255" confidence="possible" page="43" column="2">by focusing on fostering the emergence of a new joint</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1256" page="43" column="3">40</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1257" confidence="possible" page="44" column="1">1</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1258" page="44" column="1">2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1261" confidence="possible" page="44" column="1">Ackerman, M., and Halverson, C. "Organizational Memory: Processes, Boundary Objects, and Trajectories," 32nd Annual Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences, HICSS-32, IEEE, Maui, HI, USA, 1999, pp. 43-55. Agar, M. The professional stranger: an informal introduction to ethnography Academic Press, New York, NY, 1980, pp. xi, 227. Alavi, M., and Leidner, D.E. "Review: Knowledge management and knowledge management systems: Conceptual foundations and research issues," MIS Quarterly (25:1), Mar 2001, p 107. Aldrich, H., and Herker, D. "Boundary Spanning Roles and Organization Structure," Academy Management Review (2:2), Apr. 1977, pp 217-230. Allen, T.J., and Cohen, S.I. "Information flow in Research and Development laboratories," Administrative Science Quarterly (14:1), March 1969, pp 12 - 19. Ancona, D., and Caldwell, D. "Bridging the boundary: External activity and performance of organizational teams," Administrative Science Quarterly (37) 1992, pp 634-665. At-Twaijri, M.I.A., and Montanari, J.R. "The Impact of Context and Choice on the Boundary- Spanning Process: An Empirical Extension," Human Relations (40:12), Dec 1987, p 783. Barley, S.R. "Technology as an Occasion for Structuring - Evidence from Observations of Ct Scanners and the Social-Order of Radiology Departments," Administrative Science Quarterly (31:1), Mar 1986, pp 78-108. Baroudi, J.J. "The Impact of Role Variables on IS Personnel Work Attitudes and Intentions," MIS Quarterly (9:4), Dec 1985, p 341. Bechky, B. "Sharing Meaning Across Occupational Communities: The Transformation of Understanding on a Product Floor," Organization Science (14:3), May-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="1259" class="deo:Reference">June 2003</xref>, pp 312-330. Bechky, B.A. "Crossing Occupational Boundaries: Communication and Learning on a Production Floor," Stanford University, CA, USA, 1999, p. 116. Becker, H.S. Tricks of the Trade: How to think about your research while you're doing it The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="1260" class="deo:Reference">University of Chicago Press, Chicago and London, 1998</xref>, p. 232. Bobrow, D., and Whalen, J. "Community Knowledge Sharing in Practice: The Eureka Story," Reflections: The SoL Journal (4:2) 2002, pp 47-57. Bødker, S. "Understanding representation in design," Human-Computer Interaction (13:2) 1998, pp 107-125. Bødker, S. "Scenarios in user-centred design - setting the stage for reflection and action," Interacting with Computers (13:1) 2000, pp 61-75. Boland, R.J., Jr., and Tenkasi, R.V. "Perspective making and perspective taking in communities of knowing," Organization Science (6:4) 1995, pp 350-372. Bourdieu, P. Outline of a theory of practice Cambridge University Press, Cambridge ; New York, 1977, pp. viii, 248. Bourdieu, P. Practical reason: on the theory of action Stanford University Press, Stanford, Calif., 1998, pp. xi, 153. Bourdieu, P., and Wacquant, L.J.D. An invitation to reflexive sociology University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1992, pp. xiv, 332. Bowker, G., and Star, S.L. "Knowledge and Information in International Information Management: Problems of Classification and Coding," in: Information Acumen: The</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="1262" page="44" column="2">REFERENCES</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1263" page="44" column="3">of</ref>
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1265" page="45" column="1">1 Understanding and Use of Knowledge in Modern Business, L. Bud-Frierman (ed.), 2 Routledge, London, 1994, pp. 187-213. 3 Bowker, G., Timmermans, S., and Star, S.L. "Infrastructure and Organizational Transformations: 4 Classifying Nurses' Work," in: Information Technology and Changes in Organizational 5 Work, W.J. Orlikowski, G. Walsham, M.R. Jones and J.I. DeGross (eds.), Chapman and 6 Hall, London, UK, 1996, pp. 344-369. 7 Briers, M., and Chua, W.F. "The role of actor-networks and boundary objects in management 8 accounting change: A field study of an implementation of activity-based costing," 9 Accounting, Organizations and Society (26:3) 2001, pp 237-269.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1266" page="45" column="1">10 Brown, J.S., and Duguid, P. "Organizational Learning and Communities-of-Practice: Toward a 11 Unified View of Working, Learning, and Innovation," Organization Science (2:1) 1991,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1267" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">12 pp 40-57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1268" page="45" column="1">13 Caldwell, D.H., and O'Reilly, C.A.I. "Boundary Spanning and Individual Performance: The 14 Impact of Self-Monitoring," Journal of Applied Psychology (67:1), Feb 1982, p 124. 15 Carlile, P.R. "Understanding Knowledge Transformation In Product Development: Making</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1269" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">16 Knowledge Manifest Through Boundary Objects," University Of Michigan, USA, 1997,</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1270" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">17 p. 188. 18 Carlile, P.R. "A Pragmatic View of Knowledge and Boundaries: Boundary Objects in New 19 Product Development," Organization Science (13:4), July-August 2002, pp 442-455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1271" page="45" column="1">20 Carlile, P.R. "Transferring, Translating, and Transforming: An Integrative Framework for 21 Managing Knowledge Across Boundaries," Organization Science (15:5), Sep-Oct 2004, 22 pp 555-568. 23 Certeau, M.d. The practice of everyday life University of California Press, Berkeley, 1984, pp.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1272" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">24 xxiv, 229 p. 25 Contu, A., and Willmott, H. "Re-embedding Situatedness: The Importance of Power Relations in 26 Learning Theory," Organization Science (14:3), May-June 2003, pp 283-296. 27 Cross, R.L., and Parker, A. The hidden power of social networks : understanding how work</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1273" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">28 really gets done in organizations Harvard Business School Press, Boston, Mass., 2004, 29 pp. xiii, 213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1274" page="45" column="1">30 Currie, G., and Kerrin, M. "The limits of a technological fix to knowledge management: 31 Epistemological, political and cultural issues in the case of intranet implementation," 32 Management Learning (35:1) 2004, pp 9-29. 33 Davenport, T.H., and Prusak, L. Working knowledge : how organizations manage what they 34 know Harvard Business School Press, Boston, Mass, 1998, pp. xv, 199 p.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1275" page="45" column="1">35 Dougherty, D. "A Practice-Centered Model of Organizational Renewal Through Product 36 Innovation," Strategic Management Journal (13:Special Issue) 1992, pp 77 ,16 pages. 37 Dubinsky, A.J., Michaels, R.E., Kotabe, M., Lim, C.U., and Moon, H.-C. "Influence of Role</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1276" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">38 Stress on Industrial Salespeople's Work Outcomes in the United States, Japan, and 39 Korea," Journal of International Business Studies (23:1), 1st Qtr. 1992, pp 77-99. 40 Dyer, J.H., and Singh, H. "The relational view: Cooperative strategy and sources of</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1277" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">41 interorganizational competitive advantage," Academy of Management Review (23:4) 42 1998, pp 660-679. 43 Friedman, R.A., and Podolny, J. "Differentiation of Boundary Spanning Roles: Labor</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1278" confidence="possible" page="45" column="1">44 Negotiations and Implications for Role Conflict," Administrative Science Quarterly 45 (37:1) 1992, pp 28-47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1280" page="46" column="1">1 Garud, R., and Kumaraswamy, A. "Viscous and Virtuous Circles in the management of 2 Knowledge: The Case of Infosys Technologies," in: New York University Working 3 New York, NY, 2004, pp. 1-46. 4 Giddens, A. The constitution of society: outline of the theory of structuration University of 5 California Press, Berkeley, 1984, pp. xxxvii, 402. 6 Glaser, B.G., and Strauss, A.L. The discovery of grounded theory; strategies for qualitative 7 research Aldine Pub. Co., Chicago, IL, 1967, pp. x, 271. 8 Goodman, P.S., and Darr, E.D. "Computer-aided systems and communities: Mechanisms for 9 organizational learning in distributed environments," MIS Quarterly; (22:4) 1998, pp</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1281" confidence="possible" page="46" column="1">10 417-440. 11 Grant, R.M. "Toward a knowledge-based theory of the firm," Strategic Management Journal 12 (17:Winter) 1996, pp 109-122.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1282" page="46" column="1">13 Griffith, T.L., Sawyer, J.E., and Neale, M.A. "Virtualness and knowledge in teams: Managing 14 the love triangle of organizations, individuals, and information technology1," MIS</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1283" page="46" column="1">15 Quarterly (27:2), Jun 2003, p 265.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1284" page="46" column="1">16 Hargadon, A. How breakthroughs happen : the surprising truth about how companies innovate 17 Harvard Business School Press, Boston, Mass., 2003, pp. xvi, 254. 18 Hargadon, A., and Sutton, R.I. "Technology brokering and innovation in a product development 19 firm," Administrative Science Quarterly (42:4) 1997, pp 716-749.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1285" confidence="possible" page="46" column="1">20 Henderson, K. "Flexible Sketches and Inflexible Data Bases: Visual Communication 21 Conscription Devices, and Boundary Objects in Design Engineering," Science, 22 Technology, &amp; Human Value (16:4) 1991, pp 448-473.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1286" page="46" column="1">23 Katz, R., Tushman, M., and Allen , T.J. "The influence of supervisory promotion and network 24 location on subordinate careers in a dual ladder RD&amp;E setting," Management Science 25 (41:5), May 1995, p 848.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1287" page="46" column="1">26 Keller, R.T., and Holland, W.E. "Boundary-Spanning Roles in a Research and Development 27 Organization: An Empirical Investigation," Academy of Management Journal (18:2), Jun. 28 1975, pp 388-393.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1288" page="46" column="1">29 Klein, H.K., and Myers, M.D. "A Set of Principles for Conducting and Evaluating Interpretive 30 Field Studies in Information Systems," MIS Quarterly (23:1) 1999, pp 67-92.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1289" page="46" column="1">31 Kogut, B., and Zander, U. "Knowledge of the Firm, Combinative Capabilities, and the 32 Replication of Technology," Organization Science (3:3), August 1992, pp 383-397. 33 Lam, A. "Embedded firms, embedded knowledge: Problems of collaboration and knowledge 34 transfer in global cooperative ventures," Organization Studies (18:6) 1997, pp 973-996.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1290" confidence="possible" page="46" column="1">35 Lave, J. Cognition in practice: mind, mathematics, and culture in everyday life Cambridge 36 University Press, Cambridge ; New York, 1988, pp. xv, 214.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1291" page="46" column="1">37 Lave, J., and Wenger, E. Situated learning: legitimate peripheral participation Cambridge 38 University Press, Cambridge, England, 1991, p. 138. 39 Leifer, R., and Delbecq, A. "Organizational/Environmental Interchange: A Model of Boundary 40 Spanning Activity," Academy of Management Review (3:1), Jan. 1978, pp 40-50.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1292" page="46" column="1">41 Lepak, D.P., and Snell, S.A. "The human resource architecture: Toward a theory of human 42 capital allocation and development," Academy of Management Review (24:1) 1999, pp 43 31-48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1294" page="46" column="1">44 Levina, N. "Multi-party Information Systems Development: The Challenge of Cross-Boundary 45 Collaboration," in: Sloan School of Management, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 46 Cambridge, MA, 2001, p. 300. <marker type="column" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> Paper,</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1296" page="47" column="1">1 Liebeskind, J.P., Oliver, A.L., Zucker, L., and Brewer, M. "Social networks, learning, and 2 flexibility: Sourcing scientific knowledge in new biotechnology firms," Organization 3 Science (7:4), Jul/Aug 1996, pp 428-443. 4 Lysonski, S. "A Boundary Theory Investigation of the Product Manager's Role," Journal of 5 Marketing (49:1), Winter 1985, p 26. 6 Lysonski, S.J., and Johnson, E.M. "The Sales Manager as a Boundary Spanner: A Role Theory 7 Analysis," The Journal of Personal Selling &amp; Sales Management (3:2), Nov 1983, p 8. 8 Majchrzak, A., Cooper, L.P., and Neece, O.E. "Knowledge Reuse for Innovation," Management 9 Science (50:2), Feb 2004, p 174.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1297" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">10 McDermott, R. "Why Information Technology Inspired But Cannot Deliver Knowledge 11 Management," California Management Review (41:4) 1999, pp 103-117.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1298" page="47" column="1">12 Nahapiet, J., and Ghoshal, S. "Social capital, intellectual capital, and the organizational 13 advantage," Academy of Management Review (23:2), Apr 1998, pp 242-266.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1299" page="47" column="1">14 Newell, S., Scarbrough, H., and Swan, J. "From global knowledge management to internal 15 electronic fences: Contradictory outcomes of intranet development," British Journal of 16 Management (12:2) 2001, pp 97 - 111.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1300" page="47" column="1">17 Nidumolu, S.R., Subramani, M., and Aldrich, A. "Situated learning and the situated knowledge 18 web: Exploring the ground beneath knowledge management," Journal of Management 19 Information Systems (18:1), SUM 2001, pp 115-150.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1301" page="47" column="1">20 Nochur, K.S., and Allen, T.J. "Do Nominated Boundary Spanners Become Effective 21 Technological Gatekeepers?," IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management (39:3) 22 1992, pp 265-269. 23 Nonaka, I. "A dynamic theory of organizational knowledge creation," Organization Science (5:1)</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1302" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">24 1994, pp 14-37. 25 Orlikowski, W.J. "The Duality of Technology: Rethinking the Concept of Technology in</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1303" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">26 Organizations," Organization Science (3:3), August 1992, pp 398-427. 27 Orlikowski, W.J. "Using technology and constituting structures: A practice lens for studying</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1304" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">28 technology in organizations," Organization Science (11:4) 2000, pp 404-428.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1305" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">29 Orlikowski, W.J. "Knowing in practice: Enacting a collective capability in distributed 30 organizing," Organization Science (13:3), May/Jun 2002, p 249. 31 Pan, S.L., and Leidner, D.E. "Bridging Communities of Practice with Information Technology in</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1306" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">32 Pursuit of Global Knowledge Sharing," Journal of Strategic Information Systems (12:1), 33 March 2003, pp 71-88. 34 Pawlowski, S.D., and Robey, D. "Bridging User Organizations: Knowledge Brokering and the</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1307" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">35 Work of Information Technology Professionals," MIS Quarterly (29:forthcoming) 2005. 36 Pettigrew, A.M. "Longitudinal Field Research on Change: Theory and Practice," Organization</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1308" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">37 Science (1:3), August 1990, pp 267-292.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1309" page="47" column="1">38 Powell, W.W. "Neither Market nor Hierarchy: Network Forms of Organization," Research in 39 Organizational Behavior (12) 1990, pp 295-336.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1310" page="47" column="1">40 Schultze, U., and Boland, R.J. "Knowledge management technology and the reproduction of 41 knowledge work practices," Journal of Strategic Information Systems (9:2-3), SEP 2000, 42 pp 193-212. 43 Schultze, U., and Leidner, D.E. "Studying knowledge management in information systems</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1311" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">44 research: Discourses and theoretical assumptions," MIS Quarterly (26:3), Sep 2002, p</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1312" confidence="possible" page="47" column="1">45 213.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1314" page="48" column="1">1 Singh, J., and Rhoads, G.K. "Boundary Role Ambiguity in Marketing-Oriented Positions: A 2 Multidimensional, Multifaceted Operationalization," JMR, Journal of Marketing 3 Research (28:3), Aug 1991, p 328. 4 Singh, J., Verbeke, W., and Rhoads, G.K. "Do organizational practices matter in role stress 5 processes? A study of direct and moderating effects for marketing-oriented boundary 6 spanners," Journal of Marketing (60:3), Jul 1996, p 69. 7 Star, S.L. "The Structure of Ill-Structured Solutions: Boundary Objects and Heterogeneous 8 Distributed Problem Solving," in: Readings in Distributed Artificial Intelligence, M. 9 Huhn and L. Gasser (eds.), Morgan Kaufman, Menlo Park, CA, 1989, pp. 37-54.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1315" page="48" column="1">10 Star, S.L., and Griesemer, J.R. "Institutional Ecology, 'Translations' and Boundary Objects: 11 Amateurs and Professionals in Berkeley's Museum of Vertebrate Zoology 1907-39," 12 Social Studies of Science (19) 1989, pp 387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1316" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">13 Star, S.L., and Ruhdeler, K. "Steps toward an ecology infrastructure: Design and access for large 14 information spaces," Information Systems Research (7:1) 1996, pp 111 - 134. 15 Staudenmayer, N., Tyre, M., and Perlow, L. "Time to Change: Temporal Shifts as Enablers of</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1317" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">16 Organizational Change," Organization Science (13:5), September-October 2002, pp 583-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1318" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">17 597.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1319" page="48" column="1">18 Strauss, A.L., and Corbin, J.M. Basics of qualitative research : techniques and procedures for 19 developing grounded theory, (2nd ed.) Sage Publications, Thousand Oaks, 1998, pp. xiii,</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1320" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">20 312. 21 Suchman, L.A. Plans and situated actions : the problem of human-machine communication 22 Cambridge University Press, Cambridge Cambridgeshire ; New York, 1987, pp. xii, 203. 23 Swan, J., and Scarbrough, H. "Knowledge, Purpose and Process: Linking Knowledge</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1321" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">24 Management and Innovation," Proceedings of the 34th Hawaii International Conference 25 on System Sciences, Hawaii, USA, 2001, pp. 1-10.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1322" page="48" column="1">26 Tajfel, H. Differentiation between social groups: studies in the social psychology of intergroup 27 relations Published in cooperation with European Association of Experimental Social 28 Psychology by Academic Press, London ; New York, 1978, pp. xv, 474.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1323" page="48" column="1">29 Tsoukas, H. "The firm as a distributed knowledge system: A constructionist approach," 30 Management Journal (17:Winter), Winter 1996, pp 11-25. 31 Tushman, M.L. "Special boundary roles in the innovation process," Administrative Science</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1324" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">32 Quarterly (22:4) 1977, pp 587 - 605. 33 Tushman, M.L., and Scanlan, T.J. "Boundary Spanning Individuals: Their Role in Information 34 Transfer and Their Antecedents," Academy of Management Journal (24:2), Jun 1981, p</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1325" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">35 289.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1326" page="48" column="1">36 Tyre, M.J., and Orlikowski, W.J. "Windows of opportunity: Temporal patterns of technological 37 adaptation in organizations," Organization Science (5:1), February 1994, pp 98-118.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1327" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">38 Verton, D. "Inadequate Systems Play Role in Columbia Disaster, Report Finds," in: 39 Computerworld, September 1, 2003. 40 von Hippel, E. The sources of innovation Oxford University Press, New York, 1988, pp. xi, 218.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1328" page="48" column="1">41 Wenger, E. Communities of practice: learning, meaning, and identity Cambridge University 42 Press, Cambridge, U.K. ; New York, N.Y., 1998, pp. xv, 318. 43 Wiesenfeld, B., and Hewlin, P. "Splintered Identity and Organizational Change: The</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1329" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">44 Predicament of Boundary Spanning Managers," in: Research on Managing Groups and 45 Teams, Elsevier Science Ltd., 2003, pp. 27-52.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1330" confidence="possible" page="48" column="1">46 47</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="1331" page="48" column="3">Strategic</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1264" page="44" column="3">41</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1279" page="45" column="3">42</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1295" page="46" column="3">43</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1313" page="47" column="3">44</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1332" page="48" column="3">45</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1333" page="49" column="1">Nominated Boundary Spanners Only B A A B B A A A B B A B</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1335" page="49" column="1">Field A Field B Field A <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="1334" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>: No Boundary Spanning in Practice Nominated boundary spanners , marked by diamonds , are distinguished from the rest of the field agents , but are not engaged in boundary spanning . They or other agents pass designated boundary objects produced in one field to another field without relating them or establishing a common identity for them .</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1336" page="49" column="1">1. Emergence of Boundary Spanners-in-Practice</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1337" page="49" column="1">A B New Joint Field A AB AB A B A A B B Field A Field B</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1338" page="49" column="1">-- A and B represent agents in fields A and B respectively. -- AB represent boundary spanners -in-practice -- Ab and aB represent agents joining the field, who are not necessarily boundary spanners -- AB object represents a boundary object-in-use by both fields</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="1339" confidence="possible" page="49" column="1">Figure 2: Emergence of a New Joint Field</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1340" confidence="possible" page="49" column="1">1. Boundary spanners -in-practice emerge by engaging in the negotiation of the relation between practices in fields A and B . They engage in reflecting on and relating artifacts produced by A and B separately . 2. A new common identity for a boundary objects -in-use emerges with the help of boundary spanners -in-practice and new agents joint the boundary practice through by using and co -producing boundary objects -in-use; some of them may become boundary spanners -in-practice. 1</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1341" confidence="possible" page="49" column="2">Designated Boundary Objects Only B A A B B A A’s object B A A’s object B A A’s object B Field B 2. New Agents Join the New Joint Practice A New Joint Field AB a B Ab AB AB a B A AB Object A b Field A</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1342" page="49" column="3">-- Letters A and B represent agents in fields A and B respectively.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1343" page="49" column="3">B</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1344" page="49" column="3">B</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="1345" page="49" column="3">Field B</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="1346" confidence="possible" page="49" column="3">46</region>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
