<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>8428ca188ffb4e89bcbe80e4e5465fbcf45b4642c62eee030d4812b791f0d2b4</job>
    <base_name>62qe</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/016224399802300201</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">The Role of Material Objects in the Design Process: A Comparison of Two Design Cultures and How They Contend with Automation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx2">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62qe.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">The Role of Material Objects in the Design Process: A Comparison of Two Design Cultures</name>
          <aff id="4">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">How They Contend with Automation Author(s): Kathryn Henderson Source: Science</name>
          <aff id="6">:</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Technology</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">Human Values</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">Vol.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="10">No. 2 (Spring</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="11">)</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="12">pp. 139-174 Published by: Sage Publications</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="13">Inc. Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/690180 . Accessed: 27/08/</name>
          <aff id="14">:</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="15">of Use, available at .</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="17">Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="16">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="18">discover, use, and build upon a wide range of increase productivity and facilitate new forms</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="20" confidence="possible">. JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="19">support@jstor.org</email>.</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="21">.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22">Sage Publications, Inc. is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Science, Technology, &amp;Human Values.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx23">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62qe.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="25"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="24">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="26">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">The Roleof MaterialObjectsin the DesignProcess: A Comparison of Two DesignCultures and HowTheyContend withAutomation</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible">Kathryn Henderson TexasA&amp;MUniversity</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="29">This article engineeringdesign, one flexible and interactive, the other rigid and hierarchical.It examinesthe practices of design engineers who use a paper documentsand computergraphics systemsand contraststhese with the practices of workers reengineeringtheir own work process and its technological supportsystem,usingpredesignedsoftware.Based on the that objectsparticipate in the shaping of new technologiesand the networksthat build them,the that (1) design culturesare to the way in which are constructed because prototypes-are the heart of design work; (2) such design tools can engage or restrict participationin the designprocess; (3) politics in of management prerogatives can be builtinto a design tool, influencingthe range of and innovation a given sociotechnologicalsetting.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="62">This articlecomparestwo culturesof engineeringdesign, one flexible and interactive, the other rigid and hierarchical.It examines the practices of design engineers who use a mixture of paper documents and computer graphicssystems and contraststhese with the practicesof workersreengi- neeringtheir own work process and its technologicalsupportsystem, using predesignedsoftware. Design culturesor styles are intrinsicallytied to the way in which each constructs representationsof their ideas. Such repre- sentations-sketches, drawings, prototypes-are the heart of design work and constitutethe space in which ideas are defined, refined,and negotiated. Comparisonof the mannerin which differentdesign tools both engage and restrictparticipation in diversesettingsrevealsthe importance not only of the tools, butalso of the culturethey helpbuild.The studyalso shows thatpolitics in the form of managementprerogativescan be built into a design tool, <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> influencingthe rangeof creativityandinnovationin a given sociotechnologi- cal setting. Actor networktheory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Callon 1986a</xref>, 1986b; Latour 1987; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Law 1987a</xref>, 1987b) lets us treat design documents-sketches, drawings,diagrams-as participants in the interactions that constructnew technologies. Such documents are actantsenlisted into and constructedby a heterogeneousnetwork of people and things which jointly contributeto the constructionof a new technology. Visual representations are also the holding ground for collectively negotiateddesign ideas.Theyserve as recruiting devices andgatekeep- ers. As I have shownelsewhere,visualrepresentations, includingprototypes, used in the design of new technologiesareconscriptiondevices, objects that both enlist and constrain participationin design. Anyone who wants to participate in thedesignprocessmustdo so by interacting with them.Because they representa design group's negotiatedideas, and hence its distributed cognition, they also structurehow work gets done in groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Henderson 1991, 1995a</xref>). Consequently,their form and format affect the nature of interactionsand the culture of the designing group. Art historian <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Alpers (1983)</xref> has shown that how members of a given culture see the world is reciprocallyinfluencedby the way they renderthis world. In his discussion of visualizationand cognition,Latour(1986, 9-10) refersto this relationship as "definingboth what it is to see and what there is to see." I have shown, similarly,that engineeringdraftingconventionsand theircontext help con- structthe visual cultureof engineers,thatin turninfluencesthe conventions of renderingthat world (Henderson1995b). Clearly,the implementation of new representational tools (such as computergraphicssystems) changesthis culture,while the existing conventionsinfluence how the new tool may be used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Henderson 1993, 1994, 1995b</xref>). Because visual representations can facilitateor restrictgroupinteraction,they are primaryplayersin the social constructionof the design culture or design style of the designing group, whetherits membersareperiodartists,mechanicalor otherdesign engineers, reengineering workers,or any othertypes of designers. This study adopts the STS perspective that views technology and its design as both socially constructedand society shaping.This perspectiveis compatiblewith design studies thatcomparedifferencesand similaritiesin variousdesign cultures.Whereasthe role of visual renderingsin design has been often acknowledged,science and technology studieshave been paying attentionto the role of visual representations not only in design but also in laboratory work1 and in the heterogeneousengineeringof technology (Fer- guson 1976, 1992; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Hindle 1981</xref>;Mukerji1984; Latour1986,1992; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Fyfe and Law 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Bowker 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Henderson 1991, 1995a, 1995b</xref>;Turnbull1993; Gormanand Carlson 1993). Historical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Vincenti 1990</xref>) and ethnographic<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> studiesby engineersthemselves(Bucciarelli1994) also documentthe importance of visual documentsin technology design development.Observations of engineeringpractice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Ullman, Stauffer,and Dietterich 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Bly 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Tang and Leifer 1988</xref>; Henderson1991, 1995a) have pointed out that more is going on in sketchinganddrawingthanthe workingout of a single design. Fromthe psychological perspective,Arnheim,who has long recognizedthe importanceof visual thinking(1969), has more recently (1993) pointed out the dialectic natureof sketches for the individualworkingout design ideas. From the sociological perspectiveadoptedhere, such a dialectic is manifest at the grouplevel when engineersanddesignersuse interactivesketches and drawings on white boards and paper to work out and negotiate various perspectives and to draw in, literally and figuratively, a wealth of tacit knowledge (Henderson1991, 1995a, 1998). The new perspectivesin design studies are somewhatanalogousto those in science and technology studies. Sociological perspectiveson science no longer acceptthe myth of linearscientific progressnor embracethe myth of scientific objectivityand detachmentin researchmethods.Similarly,design studiesaremoving away frompositivistand functionalist views thatprescribe the one rightway to do design (such as formfollows functionideology). They tendto advocateexamination of the varietyof design processesandacknowl- edge no preferredright way to do design and no single correctmeaning of the designed object in a pluralisticsociety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Margolin 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Margolin and Buchanan1995; Buchananand Margolin 1995</xref>). Accordingto Margolin,in the continuing debate over the definition of design, more positivist views such as those of HerbertSimon, who defined design as the science of the artificial, compete with ideas such as those of the civil engineer Petroski (1985), who describeddesign as the disassemblingand reassemblingof the partsof nature,and with the perspectivesof those who suggest thatdesign is a new formof practicalartor communication (Margolin1989). Most relevant to this study arethe ideas of ItaliandesignerVitta,who sees a design culture as embracing"thetotalityof disciplines,phenomena,knowledge, analytical instruments and philosophiesthatthe design of useful objectsmust takeinto account,inasmuchas those objectsareproduced,distributed, and used in the context of economic and social models thatare even more complicatedand elusive" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Vitta 1989</xref>, 31). Vitta's inclusion of such heterogeneouselements moves his positioncloser to the perspectiveof actornetworktheory,although he emphasizesthe consumptionratherthan productionside of the network. The overall theme that design is an activity defined by the social milieu in which it occursis compatiblewith the perspectivetakenhereandagreeswith those in science studies who argue that neither design nor science and technology are value free.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> The contingenciesof automationin work worlds thathad been tradition- ally dependenton paper-based practiceshave also drawncross-disciplinary attention.Researchers have shownthatin manyworksettings,practicesusing paperareso integralto the way workis done andknowledgeis generatedthat they cannotsimply be replacedby automatedsystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Harper, Hughes, and Shapiro 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Luff, Heath,and Greatbatch 1992</xref>). Despite nationalisticU.S. hope and hype, implementationof computergraphicsin all types of engineering design-from civil to mechanical to electronic-has not led to a smoothertransitionfrom design to manufacturing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Downey 1992a</xref>, 1992b, 1995). It has also not led to a paperlessworld,butratherto a world of mixed practicesthatcombinethe assets of boththe paperandthe electronicworlds. Initial ideas are often capturedon paper, whereas analysis and problem solving are often accomplished individually and/or collaboratively using computer-generated hard copies (Henderson,1993, 1994, 1998).2Hence the flexibility of collaborative practices around visual documents is crucial, whether the representations are hand-drawnsketches on paper and white boards,orcomputer-generated hard copies,redlinedby hand.Moreimportant thanthe differencebetweenelectronicrepresentational formats is the difference betweenflexible andnegotiablevisual representations (and the situated interactionsaroundthem) and the rigid andreified formats.Both the work- place context and the particular representational mode used arerelevant. The article begins with an overview of my findings from ethnographic researchconductedin industrial engineeringdesign settingsandfocusing on the crucialrole of visual representations in thecollaborativelysharedknowl- edge of team design work.I thendescribethe participation action researchat a national call center and present the situated practice of one of the jobs to be integratedthroughreengineering.Finally,I comparemy observations of the reengineers'practicesusing printoutsfrom their company-provided software with my earlier findings regardingdesign engineers' interactive practices on, around, and through visual documents. The contextual elements, includingthe way automationis handled,are analyzedalongside the choices of the mode of visual representation.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="31">Science, HumanValues,Vol. 23 No. 2, Spring 1998 139-174 ? 1998 Sage PublicationsInc. 139</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx32">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62qe.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="33">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="34">140 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx46">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62qe.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="47">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="48">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 141</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx56">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62qe.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="57">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="58">142 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="63" confidence="possible">Visual Documents and Situated Practice in Design Engineering</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="80">The visual culture of design engineering that has been built around drafting conventions constructs the manner in which engineers see their world. My earlier research revealed the crucial role visual documents (sketches, drawings, schematics) play not only in the constructionof new <marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> technologies but also in the constructionof shared and individual work practices and knowledge (Henderson1991, 1995a, 1995b). For instance, a case studyat a site thatbuildsturbineengines revealedthatvisual documents wereused individuallyandcollectively as thinkingandnote-taking tools. The importance of sketches as individualthinkingtools is illustrated by a drafter who hadmoved throughthe ranksto become a design engineer(still possible in some old-line, heavy industries). When she was promotedto engineerthey took away her draftingboard,but she askedfor it back, stating"Ican't think withoutmy draftingboard."She describedthe way drawinghelps her think:<marker type="block"/> Thus, as individualthinkingtools, sketches help to captureconcepts in a tangibleand communicableform which then facilitatesindividualand com- munal critical analysis. Pairs and groups use sketches as an interactive communication tool for further refiningof ideas.Collaboration over sketches is one of the best methods for accessing and sharingtacit knowledge. On several occasions at the same site I observed seasoned design engineers engaged in collaborativesketching conversations.One engineer described such activity:<marker type="block"/> Duringa study at a high-precisionmedical optics firm I observedeven more synchronouscollaboration-two engineersdesigning a new surgicalinstru- mentwere so engagedin sharedvisual thoughtthatthey werejointly drawing<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> a sketchwith one implement,each alternatively taking the pen fromthe hand of the otheras they drew and talkedsimultaneously. Moreover,throughout my observationsI found, as have others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Ullman, Stauffer,and Dietterich 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Bucciarelli 1994</xref>), thatdesignersdo not actually follow design school protocolsthatdictateworkingfrom overall design to finer and finer detail in a linearfashion,developing one areaat a time. In practice,designersworkbackandforthfromgenerallayoutto specific detail. Nor do they concentrateon one area alone and develop it. They work on different portions of the design, all over the drawing, both serially and simultaneously, developingit as a whole while they collaborate with others- a nonlinearpracticethattakes advantageof multipleresourcesand perspectives by negotiatingdistributed cognition. Productivemechanicalengineeringdesignersoften takeearly sketches to the shop floor and show them to machinistsand welders. The combination of the visual representation and the interactionregardingit serves both to elicit information that improvesthe design and to make explicit information that might be ambiguous in the drawing. As objects serving to facilitate sharedcognition, sketchescapturepertinentknowledgefrom many sources. Cap, the senior designer on the turbinepackage project, pointed out the crucialrole thatsketchesanddrawingsplay not only in collaboration between design engineersbut in eliciting tacit knowledge in consultationwith those in the productioncycle. He describedhis methods:<marker type="block"/> Because he knows from experiencethatdrawingscan be misinterpreted on the shop floor, this engineeris out on the productionfloor duringthe first assemblyof his designs. This way he can provideadditionalvisual informa-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx65">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62qe.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="67">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 143</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="69">Whenyou do draftingby hand,a lot of the thoughtprocesscomes when you're out. So it's like you can't think.... Youcan't sit thereandwait until you've got it up here,becauseit comes And as soon as you start drawingit, you andimproving it. You'rejust feeling for it. Youknow,you'rejust get a size, understand it-to get anunderstanding of the up your self-confidenceso you know the task you've been assigned. Then, as soon as you have something,you can take it to someone else and say, "Look,this is what I have, how can I it?"or "Did you have a this area too?" Withoutthe drawing,you know, it's just talk. But when you out, that'swhere,you know,80%of the out, when you start drawing it and you start realizing what you've got. . . you've always got hand. (Henderson1991, 159-60)</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="71">I don't think you ever get two designers who just sit down andjust talk. It's "give me a pencil, and I'll each other; [it's] "Youknow, this is whatI'm tryingto do here,let me show you." ... They say thatthe best they makeall theirmistakes.... out there.They're looking at it. They're visually checking it and improvingupon it. (Henderson 1991, 460-61 )</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx73">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62qe.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="75">144 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="79">doing the work you have to be very awareof all the people to workwith yourdesign problems. You've gotta leave room for the to put their stuff, you have to know how to put a package togetherso it... can be built in the cheapest, most inexpensive way that you can possibly do it. An' to do that you are in contact a good portion of the time with other departmentsespecially, eh, structures, which actuallyweld the thing together. I usuallytakemy layoutsrightafterI've started, after I do my initiallayouts, beforethey're ever dimensionedor, you know,just be a I'll go over and I'll sit andtalk with them and say, "Look,eh, here's what I wanna do and here's the types of materialI wanna use, here's what I've gotta have cut out." . . . And it's just a matterof: "is this the best possible way to do this particular thing?" And usually it's peripheral, but a lot of times they'll say, ah, "Well,gee, if you did this, over here, this would save one weld." (Henderson 1991,460)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx81">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62qe.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="82">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83">Henderson / Roleof Material Objects 145</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible">tion when needed. Referring to the plan, profile, and section drawings from which the initial assembly workers must build the first prototype, Cap acknowledges:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="85" confidence="possible">They still may not make as much sense in one area, so you circle a line on it andmakea little handsketchoff to one side thereto clarifythe thing. [Pointing to a vague areain a layout] For instance,like where its black here in this area, they see a dotted line coming down and say "what'sreally going on there?" I'm liable to just go off with the pencil andgo an'just makea little handsketch off to one sidejust to makeit clearerto the guys doing it at the time. (Henderson 1991,461)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="87" confidence="possible"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Latour (1986)</xref> points out that such cascades of sketches cumulatively build up knowledge for the ultimate transformation from paper to machine at centers of calculation that are necessarily centers of power. My observations ethnographically document the larger complexity of this process as information is accumulated in a continual progression back and forth from paper to machine to paper until all the myriad design details reach closure through negotiation of the multiple heterogeneous social and technical elements and players. For instance, at the medical optics site prototypes played an important role in the development of the new surgical tool. They were interspersed between the iterations in the cascade of drawings that transformed the design idea into a producible product. As the project engineer put it:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="88" confidence="possible">It [a drawing]helps in termsof, "Ohit looks pretty" or "Howdoes this [work]," or "I think my finger could work really well on this." But until you actually get your hands on it, it's still not even close. There's a big, big difference in drawingit andmakingit. That'swherethe mainchangecomes over, when you get the prototype.... I would say you cannotmake anythingunless you make prototypes, urn, andunderstand it andworry out thebugs.(Henderson, 1995a, 283)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89" confidence="possible">Prototypes were especially useful for soliciting tacit knowledge, which was then incorporated back into new iterations of the drawings. This eliciting of tacit knowledge was seen as very useful play by the engineers involved:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="90" confidence="possible">I'm basicallythe personwho comes in and says, "Ah,this isn't workingright" and then I say, "Let's change this and see if this will fit and get rid of that problem."... Or I bring them into my office and play with the instruments. That'swhen thingsget accomplished... when I'm grindingat thebit andthat's just the next thing on the list-one of the criticalthings to know is thatif you keep working on the thing all the time it doesn't get any better .... You can work super hard on it. But it just doesn't improve. Going every time with a</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx91">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_008.image_09.png" thmb="62qe.page_008.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="92">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93">146 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="94">fresh approach,with a fresh look and not being afraidto change it is just as important. (Henderson1995a, 286)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="98">Such play with the prototypewas greatlyadvancedby the engagementof others,especiallynew membersof theprojectteamwhojoined the designers' meetings when the new tool neared production. The research and devel- opmentteam's strategyof handinga prototypeof theirinstrument, designed for physicians'use, to newcomers(myself included)and soliciting feedback about the appropriateness of its size, shape, smoothness, and comfort of function served not only to garnertacit knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Polanyi 1958</xref>, 1967; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Collins 1974</xref>). Politically,it also workedto facilitatesupportfor the designers' "technologicalframe"in Bijker's terms (1995), "jumpingon the band- wagon" in Fujimura'sterms (1988), or "buying into the project" in the commercialterms of my corporateinformants.Hence prototypesserved as devices for eliciting and capturing-conscripting-tacit knowledge and as devices for conscriptingsupportnetworks. They share the capacity of paper documentsto be read on several levels at once, as boundaryobjects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Star 1989</xref>; Star and Griesemer 1989).3But this capacity too has political possibilities becausemultiplereadingscan bothfacilitatecollaborativework and contribute to conflict amongcollaborators. As Bucciarelli(1994) points out, the shareduse of visual representations can help participants negotiate differences,given theirdifferentexperientialbackgrounds and expectations for the design. Negotiationcan also be facilitatedwhen participating engi- neersreadthe design drawingsfromthe perspectivesof theirspecializations (for example, from the perspectiveof fluids flows, electrical, or structural engineering). However, diverse orientationscan also potentially lead to out-and-outconflict when readingsare based not only on differentspecialty orientationsand backgroundexperience, but also on departmental politics and distrustbetweenresearchanddevelopmentandmanufacturing. My data from the practiceof design engineersshow thatbecause of the potentialfor such conflict, visual documentsplay a gatekeepingrole as agentscontrolling who is permittedto have inputinto the new design. Designers at more than one site told me that they did not show early iterationsto superiors,so that certain decisions were alreadyclosed by the time managementinput was given. The way in whichdesignershadto contendwithmanagement prerogatives in the reengineering project was very differentandmuch moredifficult to circumvent.Before discussingthe work of the designersin thatproject,it will be necessary to understand the context of the reengineers'contrasting design culture.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx99">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_009.image_10.png" thmb="62qe.page_009.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="100">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="101">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 147</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible">Reengineering a Call Center</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="113">The site of this studywas one of severalcall centersthatprovidessupplies and service for a multinational companythatmakescopy machines.41was a memberof a team of sociologists engaged in action researchto participate along with workers in reengineeringtheir work. The project plan was to integrate three specialty areas-service, supplies, and billinginquiry call-taking- into one moregeneralistcall-taking job. Initially,calls for service came in on separate800 toll-freelines to telephonerepresentatives in the threerespective areas.Underthe reengineering initiative,suchcalls wouldcome in on a single 800 line, requiring the TeleRepto become knowledgeablein the multitudeof policies and practicesfor all three areas.New softwarewould facilitatethe integratedfunctions.In the first phase of the researchour team documented existing practiceso thatthe reengineered computertools andwork processes would be groundedin actualways of doing work. This phase of our researchpaid close attentionto the total context of the TeleRep'sinteractionswith people, work setting, and machines.Our observations focused on the interdependence of conversationstructure, the use of paperdocuments,the dictatesof the technology,the role of tacit knowledge, and the physical involvementof the TeleRep'sbody. We found the driving forces for interaction and the locus of the knowledgeto be multiple,shifting, and mutating.Knowledge was not singularlyconstructedinto the "smart" system that supportedthe work alone, nor only into the heads of TeleReps, singly or collectively. Nor was it located in the posted documentsalone, nor only in the TeleRep'sfingertipsor visual memory;it was in all these places, elicited interactivelyand in consort,sometimesorchestrated simultaneously and other times sequentially( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Whalen,Henderson,and Whalen 1995</xref>). This has been called distributedcognition by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Hutchins (1991)</xref>. Hutchins now terms it cultural cognition (1995). Suchman(1987) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Lave (1988)</xref> call it situatedpractice; it is knowledge in practice.The important points are that (1) the knowledge that TeleReps command was complex and distributed throughouttheir tacit, technical,and physical work environment,including collaborationwith peers; and that (2) the menu-drivengraphicmethods the companyprovidedfor representingand redesigningthe work, coupled with a structured, management-driven quality assuranceprocess, workedagainst capturingthis complexity in a mannerthatwould allow creativeinnovation. In all three areasof specialization(service, sales, billing inquiries)to be combinedby reengineering,the TeleRep,almost cyborglike,sits suspended between one machine-the telephone-and another-the computersystem.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> Headphones connect her or him to the computerizedtelephone system, fingers hovering at-the-readyover the keyboard,and eyes set to scan the computer screen. Also withinat-a-glance range arenumerous paper documents andpad andpencil. On the surfacethe worklooks simple:answerthe phone, place the requestin the system. However,thejob is made more complex by the myriadvariationsin types of service,purchase,andlease contracts, time zones, prioritycodes, supplies used by various models of copiers,quantity discounts, availability,and special offers, to namejust a few details that the TeleRep must maneuver.To keep trackof much of this informationalong with its constant updates and the coding for the various screens of the database of an aging system, TeleReps, especially new ones, paper their space with posted and bounddocuments.I mentionthem here only as part of the context;the detailsof theiruse is an articlein itself. To understand fully the complexity and knowledge involved in actually doing this work, I participated in the standard training classes in serviceandsuppliessales given to new employees.I spenttwo weeks takinglive calls in the CustomerService Call Center.Because thatjob was generallyregardedas the simplest of the three to be integrated,I will draw on that area to illustratethe attentionto detail andtacitknowledgeinvolved in the work of the TeleRepsat its locally<marker type="block"/> The CustomerService Call Centersegment of the convertedwarehouse in which the national call center resided was broken up by clusters of two-personworkspaces,separated by cubicle walls risingabouta foot above the work surface.Higherwalls compartmented work areastowardthe rearof the large space, makingit quieterthanthe ongoing call-takingchatterof the main floor. Sets of clocks on threewalls of the centralspace displayedtime zones across the continentalUnited States, while red LED screens above them reportedthe numberof callers waiting on hold and how long they had been waiting. A light on the telephoneconsole on each desk also indicated urgency,turningfrom green to yellow to red as the caller queue lengthened. The console's standardtelephone keypad was amplified with additional largernodes thatlit to indicatewhetherthe TeleRepwas on an 800-line call, an internal,company line, or an outside line; and in "wrap-up," "ready," or "idle." The telephone system is computer controlled, but a human monitor surveys the display,showing who is off the system, or, if on, which type of line they are using. All of this is recordedand checked against statistical norms and expected on hours. The results are posted monthly, a form of employee monitoringand discipline. This is anotherexample of the politics built into artifacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Winner 1985</xref>, 1995). Even though management has recentlyinformedemployees thatthese statisticsare less important than the</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx107">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_010.image_11.png" thmb="62qe.page_010.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="108">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="109">148 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="111">perceived minimum.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx114">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_011.image_12.png" thmb="62qe.page_011.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="115">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="116">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 149</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="117" confidence="possible">quality of service they give customers, TeleReps tend not to believe this rhetoric, because the monitoring devices are built into the technology and have not been removed. My own experience supports the TeleReps' percep- tions, as shown in this account from my field notes while I was taking calls:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" confidence="possible">Mara,my trainerand the floor facilitatorcomes by and asks thatI sign off the telephonesystem when I am takingnotes and asking questions because I am staying in wrap-upmode on the phone too long, causing the computermoni- toring system to highlight the designationfor my telephone line connection, upsetting their process. Once signed on to the phone, TeleReps are really hooked in like partof the machine,every action monitored.I ask a neighbor TeleRepif I would have been reprimanded for this, were I a regularemployee and she says, "Yes."5</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119" confidence="possible">Although the work of taking and recording service calls can eventually become monotonous, learning the tacit knowledge required both to use the technology and to manage the callers takes time and experience, as illustrated by this excerpt from my first day on the phones:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="120" confidence="possible">I plugmy headset into thephoneconsole in my assignedcubicle,next to Sandy, an experiencedTeleRep.She helps me log on, but a screen message indicates a PC problemso she rebootsthe machine.Wechoose the appropriate programs from the programmanager,Rhumbaand FWSS. I type in "logon impf," hit enter, then the ctlc22 button twice, as I have been instructed,but the screen tells me: "your logon is alreadyin use." We have to call the trainerback. It turnsout someone else has been given this numbersince I used it yesterday.I get a new numberand we do it all over again.Finally I am readyto take calls. I punch the ready buttonon the phone console. A recordedvoice tells me "incomingcall." I respondas I have been taught,"[companyname] customer service, this is Kathryn, How may I help you?"The customeridentifieshimself and his company,saying he wants to place a service call. I say, "MayI have your serial number,please?"He is used to the protocol,has his serial number handy and rattlesit off so fast I have to ask him to repeatit so I can type it. I make a couple of typos and the numberturnsred. Finally when I have the correctnumberit turnsgreen andthe datascreenfinally comes up. I verify the caller's and his company'sname and addressbut Sandy has to remindme to verify the telephone number.Its field is buried in the middle of the screen among many others and I missed it in my visual scan. The customertells me he has lines and streaks on his copies so I enter "poorcopy quality"in the problem field. Sandy tells me later I could have just entered"cq."I tell the customerI will place the call andhe hangs up. I hit the enterbuttonto register the service order.The purchaseorderfield turnsred and I have to enterN for "no purchaseorderrequired" before the system will let me enter the order.I hit enteragain and the screen for solving machineproblemscomes up. Sandy has to help me get out of it. I should have hit the returnkey, located rightnext to the enterkey. I also forgot to verify the customerhours, importantfor the service technicianto know, Sandy remindsme. This field is in the uppermost</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx121">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_012.image_13.png" thmb="62qe.page_012.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="122">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="123">150 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="124">rightcomer of the screen,which I also missed in my visual scan as I readdown the page, vertically,to verify the name and address.Sandy also tells me not to use the hyphen in telephonenumbersbecause it sometimes messes up pager calls-a glimpse of TeleReptacit knowledge. I take two more simple requestsfor service calls but keep forgettingto ask the caller for the condition of the machine:totally down, partiallydown, or routineservice check, for which I should enter a 0, 1, or 2 in the appropriate field. A new call comes in, but when I ask for the serialnumberthe caller says they on hold andwill transfer to room.Too muchtime cannot get outof hold,on the help button and get a recordingstatingthat all my calls are on hold, and to call a supervisor. Her line is busy andso is I sit feeling dumbandfrustrated, afraid to punch any more buttons that might make mattersworse. Finally, Sandy is free and tells me to the several lit up on the phone console. This is my first piece of informationthat the buttons are active not static, more tacit knowledge absorbed.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="127">The opening protocol for any service call requireseliciting the machine serial numberfrom the caller to access the databaserecords.The database was designed in the 1970s. Some but not all TeleRepshave personalcom- puterswith a Windowsinterfacethroughwhich to access the database.Many terminals,however,have the old green-on-black display, andall information in the database, even with new PC color choices, appears in old style, squarish,difficult-to-read computerprint.Whateverthe customermay wish to convey about a nonworkingcopier, no informationcan be recordedfor potential action until the machine serial numberis recited and enteredinto the system. If the entered serial number is valid, the computer system proceedsto the next screen.The information fields on this screenareso dense they fill the entirepage, often leaving only one- and two-digit spaces to be filled in. The visual field is so crowded that it is easy for a novice to miss details. Only after the TeleRep verifies the name, address, and telephone numberof the corporate customer,along with the name of the client contact personandcompanyhoursof operation,is the customerto be askedwhatthe <marker type="block"/> a two-line problemfield is availablefor the description,so the TeleRepmust usuallyrewordand shortenthe description.If a tiny field at the bottomof the screenis markedMC for maintenance contract,the call is enteredby simply pressingthe appropriate key, andthe TeleRepinformsthe customerthattheir call has been placed. If the field is markedTM for time-and-materials, the TeleRep must informthe customerthatthey will be billed a certainamount for the first half hour and anotheramountfor each subsequentquarter hour, depending on the size and complexity of theirparticular copier and whether the customerwants the service call duringor after regularbusiness hours.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="126">TeleRep can do for them. Whatever a caller replies about their machine, only</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx128">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_013.image_14.png" thmb="62qe.page_013.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="129">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="130">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 151</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="131" confidence="possible">The most current billing rates are posted on paper nearby so that TeleReps can verify that they are quoting the most recent price updates. But not all calls are so straightforward, as these examples from my field notes show:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="132" confidence="possible">The next call is a legitimateENOF [equipment not on file]. The serialnumber the customerhas providedturnsred when I attemptto enter it. I have double checked for typos on my partand had the customergo back to theirmachine to check the numberthey gave me against that on the copier's silver serial numberplate. This in itself is an ordeal.Many times customersdo not know theirserialnumberandmust go look for it. It is not in the same place on every machine. Each TeleRep has a small but thick reference volume with a line drawingof each model of the company'scopier,typewriter, and fax machines and their accessories. An arrowpoints to the location of the serial number, which is sometimes inside the machine. Sandy can tell customerswhere it is on the most common models without looking it up; she has worked for the company for twelve years. I write down the company and caller's name, address,telephone and serial numberson a pad of paper.Sandy says to wait until we come back from lunch to handlethis because we will have to make a phonecall andhave someoneget backto us so we can tell the customerwhether the call is billable or covered on a service contract. The data screen for the next caller has "XFS in conversion,customersaid was convertingfrom time and materialsto ser.cont."in the billing field. We never discussed anythinglike this in trainingso I ask Sandywhat I should do. She says to put the service call throughbecause it was alreadychangedat the top of the screen and was internalanyway.I am learningthatthe literalrules we weretaughtin trainingas the one-and-only-way-things-are-done are indeed more open to interpretation, even in an automatedsystem.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="133" confidence="possible">One of the forms of tacit knowledge I had to develop as a TeleRep was learning to see the data screen. I had to discipline my visual scan to include the small two-digit fields pertinent to what I was doing at the time while glancing over other fields not relevant to the customer on the line. This meant training my gaze to include the far upper-right corner of the screen where the clients' hours were posted instead of reading down the screen, vertically, as if it were a list. Learning to scan all the relevant fields took some practice:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="134" confidence="possible">I get call from an elementaryschool thathas "donot service, no renewalPC," an 800 number,and a name to call, so I tell the woman that there is some problem on the account and she needs to call the 800 number.I have now trainedmy visual scan to notice the billing field at the bottomof the screen as well as those things I have to verify. Sandy tells me a lot of schools have problemsgetting service becauseof billing problemsbecause they often have really old equipmentwithoutservice contractsor have to get purchaseorders from theirdistrictor state. I get severalcalls thatI handleOK,thenone fromthe Stateof Massachusetts Department of MotorVehicles on which I missed the "PC[purchasecontract]</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx135">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62qe.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="136">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="137">152 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="138" confidence="possible">required" until afterthey hung up. Sandy says to just put "if billable " in that field. I get a call from CarmellaEastinat InvestmentBankersof Americawho said she had called yesterdaybut received no ETA[estimatedtime of arrival] andfelt she shouldhave by now, Sandytells me that[readingthe screenbetter thanI] the service technicianhas alreadybeen out there. A bit after2:00 p.m. [CST] Sandyremindsme to ask customerson Eastern Standard Time whetherthey want to pay for after-hours calls. This involves not only noticing where and in what time zone the customeris located and whetherthey have a service contract,but also if the service contractcovers after-hours calls.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="139" confidence="possible">Although I had been through training, I felt very dependent on my paper cheat sheets, which listed the various computer codes to move through the database or protocols for exceptional, but common, breaks from simple calls, like the one below.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140" confidence="possible">I do my first CCE [customercourtesyescalation],the processfor impatientor iratecustomers.The caller was irritated that the technicianhad not yet come. I designateit a"+1"rather than a "+2"becausethe tone of the customer'svoice is not out-and-outanger,but mild irritation.I must send two messages from the screen, one to the area service technician supervisor and one to the designated technician.With my cheat sheets near-byI feel confident that I know the process but then get confused about how to designate the service team numberbecausethe exampleused in trainingwas unclear.Workingwith the datascreenrather than my memoryandthe cheatsheet,I realizethatthough we have to enterthe same message twice, it is the second box on the message screen thatactuallysends the message to the technicianvia employee number when I put"CCE+ teamandsectionnumber" into the CCP[customercourtesy process] screen.I make the usual mistakeof using the enterbuttonto end this which means the technician got paged twice. Sandy reminds me I should have used the pflO key, adding,"Thenshe would not have been paged twice." The service area was local so Sandy knew who the technician was by the employee number.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="141" confidence="possible">My second day on the phones, paper cheat sheets at hand, I felt more self-assured and resolved to try to use the on-line system (CCA; customer call assistance) designed to help customers fix simple problems with their copy machines themselves without having to place a service call. I had heard Sandy give instructions to customers from memory. I would be dependent on the system. After a delay because the whole system went down, forcing us to scurry around getting paper documents to record calls, I finally had a chance to try out the technology-assisted helper role:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="142" confidence="possible">I take a call from an Army Base in their CareerResource Mgt. Center.The caller says their machine is "jammingin the output area"and give[s] me a complicatedset of hours,differentfor each day of the week. In additionto the</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx143">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_015.image_16.png" thmb="62qe.page_015.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="144">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="145">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 153</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="146" confidence="possible">PO [purchaseorder]numberthe caller wants to give me a very long "BPA" number.I write all the hoursand the BPAnumberdown on my tablet and ask thecaller,"Areyou willing to trysome thingsthatmight fix the problem?" She says, "Yes."I type "paper jams" in the "problem" field and the right number in the CCA field but nothinghappens.So I look up the code for paperjams on my CCA paper cheat sheet. I finally get into CCA by using the right alpha- numericcode for paperjams. I scan the list of questions that appearson the screenandask the callerthe firstone: "Howmanycopies have you been doing at a time?"since the instructionssay twenty-five is the limit. The caller says people areonly allowed to do five at a time since the machineis for publicuse. I readoff a suggestionfor adjustingthe feed trayand the next one which asks if the papercould be damp. The caller responds,saying they have had very dampweather,and I tell her to try a new reamof paperand recall thatI have often heardSandy mentionthis to customers.There is anothersuggestion on the list, but this seems like a good one, so I do not readthe final suggestion. I do readsomethingaboutpressingthe startbuttontwice to the customer,but it was not worded clearly and neither of us is quite sure of the step-by-step process. Keeping the conversationnatural-sounding while wording the "Do this,do that"commandsin a way thatdoes not soundcondescendingis difficult. I tried to word my instructionsas I had heard other TeleReps do, in an "of course you've done this" tone of voice, because the CCA instructionscome from customermanualsand are mostly common knowledge for anyone who has worked regularlywith copiers or electronic equipment.After telling the caller to try changing the paperI tell her to call back and cancel the service orderif thatworks andthankher for tryingthe steps as I have heardSandydo. When I returnfrom lunch, the small screen on my phone console says, "4 calls waiting."The overheadLED screen which shows numberof customers waiting and their averagetime of wait had displayedall O'searlier.Now it is lit up with numberswhich keep escalating. A bell rings and everyone drops whateverthey are doing to get on the phones and bring the numbersdown. Everyone, including me, ignores CCA, turningall calls as much as possible into vanilla service calls to get the backlog down as fast as possible. The numbersarenot so severe now, my peakhadbeen 14 waiting,just after I got on, now it shows only 6. I take two more calls but neitherwants to try CCA. A third doesn't even know what area her jam is in: input, output, whatever,so I try nothing. Customersdo not want to try things to fix their machine very often. They would rather just call the technicianto fix it, even whenjust changingthe paperor turningthe machineon andoff mightget them backup andrunning. Getting peopleto attempt to fix theirown copieris another level of TeleRep knowledge. The TeleRep has to read the customer's mood, probetor contextualclues, such as whetherthe copier is nearbyand carefully word the suggestions so thatthe customerdoes not feel thatthey arehaving to do what their service contractshould provide.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="147" confidence="possible">During my two weeks on the phones, I remained dependent on my posted documents for less frequently used codes but did acquire some tacit knowledge. Doing the work myself, but dependent on the expertise of my experi- enced neighbor, Sandy, I became particularly aware of her level of tacit</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx148">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_016.image_17.png" thmb="62qe.page_016.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="149">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="150">154 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151">knowledge,includingnotjust themechanicsof takingservicecalls, including work-arounds, but also her extensive knowledgeof all the variousmodels of copiers and how to fix them over the phone. Some of this knowledge was gained from her husband,who was a service technician,some from experience; but none of it was includedin companytrainingprograms. By the end of the two weeks I had severalsuggestionsfor the reengineering design team about how to improvetraining.I also had suggestions for changes to the antiquated system which would makethe workpracticemore efficient,as the threejobs becameintegrated into one. However,sharingwhat I learned with the reengineeringdesign team during our regular design meetings was not to be. The structure of the design meetings focused on the workat an abstract level andused a menu-driven process thatwouldnot allow the discussion of work details to take place. At the beginning, it certainly appearedto our team of sociologists, concernedwith knowledge situatedin practice,that having the workerswho actuallydid the work design the new integratedwork process and its supportingtechnology was an excellent insight on the partof management. Indeed, the worker-reengineers knew the work in depth and in detail. However,whethermanagementintendedso or not, the design practice itself and the documents for capturing it were hamperedby management-driven imperativesfor following a rigid process. This ultimatelytook the formof a piece of softwarein which everythingwas preordained, and the designersonly filled in the blanks-another exampleof buildingpolitics into artifacts.This, of course, workedagainstthe flexibility crucial to innovative design work. Significantly, the introductionof this software and the translationof the project into prespecified terminology occurredwhen it lost its autonomyas a singularinitiative and was put, by management, under a corporate-wide reengineeringinitiative.At thatpoint, which happenedto coincide with the arrivalof our team of sociologists, the whole projectwas rewritten in the largerinitiative'slanguage,the company's versionof total qualitycontrol (TQC).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" confidence="possible">The "Quality Process": Quality or Control?</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="170">In contrastto the engineeringdesign world of negotiation,collaboration, and/orpotentialconflict, negotiationover the documentsfor the redesignof theactualworkhardlyever occurred at thereengineering site. Theexceptions occurredwhen our research team raised questions about details of work practice,althoughwe were often silenced for being "at the wrong level."6 The design process was constrainedboth by the design documentsand the formatof the meetings.Management perspectivesintervenedin the process, <marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> not by their presence per se, but by the dictatedformatof design meetings and design documents.Management-directed corporateculturedictatedand constrainedinteractionthroughits TQC conventions.These includedman- dated step-by-step prescribedprocess for runningmeetings, documenting what took place, and what action would follow. A menu-drivenprocess formuladictatedstaying at a high level of abstraction before details of work practicecould be considered.The formalismwas compoundedby the software templates used to create visual documents. Such documents were supposedto represent work processandwereconstantlyemployedas a means of shorthand communicationin meetings. Anyone making a presentationin the corporatesetting uses overhead slides composed of boxes andbullets andpictograms.This computer-generated format has become the correct medium of corporatetalk; one is not professional if one cannot reduce the message to sound bites, icons, and bullets.7The requisiteexecutive summaryis intendedfor managerswho do not have time to addressdetails. Concreteexamples of work practice that supportsummarystatementsare left out. This detail is what broadergener- alizations should be built on, so acceptanceof the broaderabstractionsis dependenton trust that the person making these generalizationshas paid attentionto the detail. However, all too often the abstractionscome down from management'sgeneral impressions ratherthan being built up from concretedata because the details of work practiceare associatedwith low- status workers. A reengineeringteam must pay attention to the level of practicaldetailthatcannotbe easily reducedto abstractions. The workhas to be thoroughlyunderstoodbefore it can be redesigned.However, so much time was spenton documentsat the high level (theirterm)of abstraction (my addition)thatwhen attentionfinally turnedto detail,little or no time was left because it had been eaten up in numerous two-day meetings devoted to high-level discussions aroundhigh-level documents. The structuredinteractionwas the result of the applicationof management's interpretationof the so-called total quality process introduced by W. EdwardsDeming via Japanesemarketsuccess.8This concept of quality is based on the idea thatbusiness must anticipatethe needs of its customers, transformthese needs into a useful and dependableproductthat meets or exceeds customer expectations, and in so doing create a process that can producetheproductatthe lowest possible cost so thatqualityandprofitability become synonymous.Deming recommendeda cyclical perspectivepromot- ing ongoing change and improvement, not only of the productproduced,but also of the structureand processes of the firm. Cooperation among all departments was intendedto facilitateredefinitionof the customer's needs in a changing environment.Although corporateadaptationsof Deming's<marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> ideas vary,any good idea can always be reified andformula-izedas it moves from originatorto management-mandated applications.Deming also advocated commitmentto long-termstrategies;eliminationof numericalgoals and quotas that focus managementattention on ends ratherthan means; driving out fear so thatpeople can work effectively; leadershipthat guides ratherthan polices; collaborationwith suppliersratherthancontractsbased only on lowest price;employee duties thatare meaningful,accompaniedby programsfor educationand self-improvement; eliminationof mass inspec- tion, emphasison teamwork instead of individualism and competitionamong employees, includingon-the-jobtraining in which managersparticipate; and eliminationof the individualmeritsystem and the numericmeasurement of job productivity.Deming maintainedthat if a system is functioning with quality processes in place, it will not generatewaste or faulty products.He also advocated the eradicationof slogans and exhortationsbecause they imply thatreformlies with the employeesrather than in a functioningsystem. According to Deming, change must be holistic, encompassingevery aspect of the organization. The structure to facilitatesuchtransformation must come from top management(Townsendand Gebhardt1992). Deming's TQC process recommendations may or may not have been the primary reasonsfor Japaneseascendancein a competitivemarket.American business has incorporatedDeming's perspective in many different ways, some more successful than others. In many cases, managementhas taken some ideas and not others, abstracting,reinterpreting, and reifying them, using some of the very perspectivesand processes of which Deming was critical.Too often, management-mandated workshopsthroughout corporate Americahave institutionalized slogans, acronyms,and variousprocess formulas and checklists promotingquality processes and attemptsto measure quality. Contraryto Taylor's original ideas, just as scientific management came to dictateto laborthe one rightway thatwork should be done, so also managementhas all too often selected some, but not all, of Deming's ideas and applied them piecemeal from a top-down perspectivethat missed the holistic character of the nonhierarchical teamworkDeming advocated. This was the case in the companywheremy researchwas conducted.The TQC process, initiated in the early 1980s, was conceived as a top-down corporate culture change.Eachlevel of management was supposedto master an abstracted and truncated version of Deming's ideas, "cascadingit down- ward"in companyjargon. TQC was handeddown the managementchain, starting each time with managersandtheirstaff,who thentaughtit to the next level, downward, and eventually to employees. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="161" class="deo:Reference">Pace and Argona (1991)</xref> reportthe conflict between this top-downperspectiveand a joint union and management project to improvethe qualityof work life (QWL) in the same<marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> company.They also point out, to the company'scredit,thatit allowed QWL representatives to modifythe TQCcurriculum and deliverit to the workforce. In the past decade, furthermodificationsof Deming's concepts have taken place.9The companyhas won nationalqualityawardsand has implemented Deming's ideas such as employee self-improvementprogramsand an emphasis on teamwork.And yet it maintainspracticesantithetical to Deming's TQC. The company still uses quantitativemeasures for everything from numberof minutes spent per customertelephonecall to the setting of sales goals. It still maintainsindividually based meritevaluationanda proliferation of empty slogans that promote the idea that delivering quality is the sole responsibilityof the worker.The following analysis traces this company's version of its TQC formula in the structureand language of the design documentsprovidedto the reengineersin softwaretemplates. Ourteamjoined the NationalDesign Program Team afterits membershad completed the initial conceptual stage of the reengineeringproject. The design meetings we attendedbegan with large stacks of paper documents being passedout to all present.Sometimesthese were blackandwhite copies of multicoloredslides. Othertimes they were sets of paperdocumentsalone. The personwho was responsiblefor the TQC action item for a subjectarea would presentthe documentby readingthroughit. Others,whose specialty area was the same, would respond. There was no sense of innovation or creativity. There was no playing with the designedobjectas describedby the engineers who designed the surgical instrument.There was no room to explore related areas. The contents of the document set the agenda for discussion, and little deviationwas made from it. The documentsserved as a checklist for things alreadyknown. Representations of work stayed at a very abstractlevel. No unrepresented tacit knowledge was elicited. If more concretesuggestions or observationswere made, the speakerwas often told they were at the wronglevel. The team was said to be workingat a very high level, butthatmeanta very low level of understanding of the actualwork.As participants engaged in documentingthe work practicethatwas being reengineered, our team members attemptedto make comments about actual practice. But we also were told that we were at the wrong level. In other words, our input was too concrete in a discussion where things were to be kept very general and abstract.After being repeatedly reprimanded,all participants, includingourresearchteam,learnednot to mentionsuchdetails. We awaitedthe appropriate time to raise detailedwork practiceissues. As time passed, the National Design ProgramTeam worked from high into medium levels. When flowchartswere finally broughtout to discuss process, it appearedwe were finally at a level to addresswork practice.But the company'sand hence the design team'sdefinitionof process was not the<marker type="page" number="21"/><marker type="block"/> same as practice.Process was formalizedand prescribedso thateven here it was hardto introduceattentionto detail. Time was short,the pilot initiation deadlinewas approaching, and manyothertopics hadto be covered.So much time had been spenton documentsat a high level thatwhen the time came to addressthe details of practice,therewas very little time left to do so.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx154">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_017.image_18.png" thmb="62qe.page_017.image_18-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="155">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="156">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 155</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx158">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_018.image_19.png" thmb="62qe.page_018.image_19-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="159">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="160">156 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx163">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_019.image_20.png" thmb="62qe.page_019.image_20-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="164">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="165">Henderson / Roleof Material Objects 157</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx167">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_020.image_21.png" thmb="62qe.page_020.image_21-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="168">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="169">158 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" confidence="possible">The "Design Documents"</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="172">A series of documents illustrates the company's and the design program</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="176">team's notion of moving from a very high level to a detail level. The representation of the business profile of the overalljob integration-plan is a good example of a very high level document(see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" id="173" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>) composed for broad dissemination at the managementlevel with figures expressed in millions andbillions.i? The second example (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" id="174" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref>) is a working document used by the programdesign team. It presentsthe componentpartsof the new integrated job, dividedinto blocks thatrepresent actual job descriptions. This is a design process document, a detailed representation of the actual processes to be incorporated into the new integrated job, designatedby numbersthat index official writtenjob descriptions.At the next level down (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="175" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>), each process is furtherdetailed. A designated specialist who had actually per- formed the job being analyzed worked on the document to be sure that it includedall the pertinent information and thenpresentedit backto the design team for furtherreview. Feedbackgenerally came from those on the team who had the samejob expertise. The thirddocument(Figure3) shows how one of the business subproc- esses of technicalservice management(9.0), the so-called service call man- agement(9.3), can be brokendownfurther into two subsubprocesses: service call handling(9.3.1.1) and service dispatch(9.3.1.2). Althoughthe number- ing system seems to imply thatwe aremoving into a very detailed area,the job practicesare abstracted into the preformulated jargon of the company's dictated process abstractions:objective, process owner, inputs, outputs, documents.To make sense of this language use, one must know the company's specializedcodes andhave some experiencewith thejob itself. In this respect, the documentresemblesthe design documentsin mechanicalengi- neering that are intended for specialty engineers. The electrical engineer contributesone set of codes to a particular segmentof the design documents while the fluids engineer andthe structural engineerconstructothersegments using theirparticular sets of symbols. Despite the fact thatthe reengineering documentuses English, its languageis neitheruniversalnor transparent. In</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx177">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_021.image_22.png" thmb="62qe.page_021.image_22-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="178">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="179">|Integrated</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180">Customer Service</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="181">BUSINESS PROFILE</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="182">|</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="183">SUPPL</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="184">|BUSINESS | | CUSTOMER CARE, PROBLEM RESOLUTION, TELEMARKETING, CUSTOMER SERVICE</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="185" confidence="possible">PROCESS |</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="186">r r</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="187">'</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="188">SUB-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="189" confidence="possible">SUPPLY ^ MARKETING</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="190" confidence="possible">TELE- ? MARKETING</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="191" confidence="possible">PROCESS l l</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="192" confidence="possible">r CUSTOMER SERVICE SUPPORT</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="193">FROM</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="194">~-</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="195" confidence="possible">S N REVENUE ~AND GROWING LEADS GENERATED</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="196">CALLS 'UBUD CLST CUSTOMSET</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="197" confidence="possible">-$ ORDERS I - ^WERS. ^^^^^H f l - CALIJMAIL CONTACTS WITH T CUSTOMERS</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="198">- ^ I</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="199" confidence="possible">11 W \^T - CUSTOMER CNAT</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="200">- CUSTOMER CONTACTS</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="201">personnel,</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="202">customers an</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="203">KEY MESSAGE: * There are million customer contacts done by today's functionally oriented processes and technologies. * Each of these customer contacts represents a 'Moment of Truth' to satisfy of Business Priorities.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="204">Figure 1</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_022.image_23.png" thmb="62qe.page_022.image_23-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="205">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="206">Process</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="207">Sub- Process</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="208">Figure 2</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_023.image_24.png" thmb="62qe.page_023.image_24-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="209">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="210">USCOBUSINESS AREA: TECHNICAL SERVICE MANAG KEYBUSINESS PROCESS:SERVICE CALL MANAGE KEY WORK PROCESS:SERVICE DELIVERY (9. &amp;|k SERVICE CALLHANDLING 9.3.1.1 . E SERVICEDISP</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="211">Objectve:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="212">Ensure timelydispatch analystfserviceengineer.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="213">and hand</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="214" confidence="possible">Providefront.endproductsupport to customers through accurate rvice entlement Identification, problem Identiflca Remon CallAshtance, and prompt ecalation to *nelylthwrvlceengineer.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="215">Process O w n er</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="216" confidence="possible">Customer Services Support</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="217">WorldwideCustomerServices Support</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="218">a</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="219" confidence="possible">mpins.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" confidence="possible">*Service Requests *OutboundSeviCe Alerts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="221">*Pending Ser *PendingSoftwareCalls</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="222">ice Calls</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="223">*.HrdwareService *Soltwar Service</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="224">Calldispatc Callhanded-</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="225">Outputs:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="226" confidence="possible">*Hardwace Sertice Callneed Identified *Softwne,Service Callneed Identified *Co atlon Callscheduled *AccountProfileupdatd *RemoteCallAssistance successfully completed</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="227">Documents</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="228" confidence="possible">*Service CaJl Record .*SofwareCallRecord Remot CallA$$1stlnceSolve Record *Accountprofileupdates</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="229">*Service CallRecord *SoftwareCallRecord *RemoteCallAssistance *Accountprofileupdates</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="230">Solve</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="231">Figure 3</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_024.image_25.png" thmb="62qe.page_024.image_25-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="232">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="233">162 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="234" confidence="possible">WORK PROCESS: SERVICECALL HANDLING9.3.1.1</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="235">Objective:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="236">Provide Front-endproduct support to customers through accurate service entitlement Identification,problem identification, Remote CallAssistance, and promptescalation to analystlservice engineer.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="237">Process Owner: Customer Services Support</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="238">Inputs*</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="239">Service Requests Outbound Service Alerts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="240">Key ProcessSteps:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="241">&gt;^ \</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="242">Confimatio s cheduld A t Remote profl C a Dttermloe *ny i^^^^ Csil AsiistaBce\ \, reuiirmenti sSBQS\ Dispstch procesi</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="243">Oupt: pUS</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="244">Hardware Service call need idenftifed, Software call need Ideneified, Confirmnation caSI scheduled, Account profile update, Remote aill Assistance successfully completed</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="245">C</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="246">ustomer</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="247">, Field Technicians, Analysts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="248">Documents: Service Remote Call CallA.istance Record,Software Solve Call Record, Record, Account Profile updates</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="249">Benefits: Quality Cost - Reduced on4ite service calls Del'verv - Customer downtimereduced</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="250" confidence="possible">Figure4</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" confidence="possible">this document, the representation of the detail is constrained by the inflexi- bility of the company's formalized interpretation of process components. This interpretation dictates what can be expressed and prohibits descriptions of actual practice. The next level document (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" id="251" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>) represents the redesigned job, but it does not take us much closer to practice either. Three quarters of it is identical to the document in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" id="252" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref>. What has been added are the customer, benefits,</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx254">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_025.image_26.png" thmb="62qe.page_025.image_26-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="255">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="256">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 163</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="257">and a visual representation of key process steps. A practice-oriented action researcher trying to participate in this design process inevitablyexperiences frustration.Every time my colleagues and I tried to clarify practice or contributeinformationon knowledge in practice,we were told we were at the wrong level. This document can be read as an actual picture of our frustration: Each circle in the key process steps identifies the sequence of events the TeleRepgoes throughin takingandplacing a service call request. However,the circles literallycircumscribe the spaceavailablefor the descrip- tion of steps,makingit very clearthatthis is still the wronglevel for capturing actualpractice.Furtherproof of how little design manipulation occurredat these levels is providedby the comparisonof the originaldocumentfrom 25 January1995 (Figure4) with ones from 8 February1995 (Figure5) and 16 February1995 (Figure6). The only differencebetweenthe first two of these documents is that process owner has been changed, the quality line under benefits has been filled in, and the borderlines have been removed. In the next iteration,the only change is computer-generated aesthetics, the document has been moved to landscapeconfiguration,and the background shad- ing has been removed. But I still hoped that, at the most detailed level, the process flow chart (Figure 7) representingthe job as redesigned would finally address the contingencies of the work itself. Time was runningout. Plans for the pilot were being made anddesign teammemberswere being called away to other responsibilities.On the day when we finally discussed things at the level of work practices,only some of the National Design ProgramTeammembers were presentand the projectmanagerwas not there.The flowchartthatwas passed around,dated7 February, was no differentfrom its predecessorfrom 25 January. Fortunately, those presentdid include areaexpertswith service- call experience.When I startedaskingquestionsaboutthe actualwork, they listened andresponded.Ourinteractionsgeneratedchanges to the chartthat arehandwritten in Figure8. At least some of the messiness and ambiguityof the work got discussed, although even there, little was captured in the documents.The whole sequenceof eventsthatoccurred when a TeleRepused remotecall assistance(RCA),11 that requiredknowledge of how to coax the caller to turn their machine off and on or run some copies, as well as familiaritywith machinetypes and common problems,has been reducedto a flowchart decision. Although the flowchartcould be used as a centering device for discussion of the detailsof this workthatcould be improvedin the redesign, time and energy for examinationof how the work really got done had run out. Had our researchteam not interrupted the structureddesign sequence earlier,with our own workshop, our suggestions relevant to the details of the work would hardlyhave been discussed.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx258">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_026.image_27.png" thmb="62qe.page_026.image_27-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="259">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="260">164 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="261" confidence="possible">XVORK PROCESS: SERVICECALL HANDLING9.3.1.1</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="262">Objective:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="263">Provide Front-end product support to customers through accuraet service entitlement identification, problem identification, Remote Call Assistance, and prompt escalation to analyst/service engineer.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="264">Process Owner: 8erviceCallHandling Process Owner</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="265">Inputs:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="266">ServiceRequests Outbound Service Alerts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="267">Key Process Steps:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="268">J Cutomer\ t k, | Account *nd 5h|_ &amp; PrblemB8iB_ sai InormtbnA t _SS rob</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="269">01 Mianose Proble</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="270">4Perform 4. Remote' Detennine.ny Call Asi,stnce \ requlremenU/ follow-up / ~fl % Dlispatch (exit fedd to Service process</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="271">Outputs:</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="272">Harowarcservice call need Idenfified, Software call need identified, Confirmation cell scheduled, Account profilc updated. Remote Call Assistance successfully completed</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="273">Customer: Customer, Field Technicians, Analysts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="274">nArnm-4o Service Call Record, 8offwarn Call Record, Remote Call Assistance Solve Record, Account Profile uDdates</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="275">Benefits: Quality ,Accuracy of Informationgiven to customer (.e., Cuebase Info.) Cost -Cost per telephone Call Dellewv - Response to customer phone call</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="276" confidence="possible">Figure5</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="277" confidence="possible">Because of this change of communication format, some innovations based on attention to practice were made in the pilot. Among these were (1) awareness of the importance of at-a-glance support documents so that some paper documents, already in use, were captured and expanded; (2) awareness of the significance of TeleRep interaction and sharing of information and, hence, the importance of cubicle wall height for both easy communication between work groups and some level of sound buffer, also applied in the pilot;</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx278">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_027.image_28.png" thmb="62qe.page_027.image_28-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="279">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="280">WORKPROCESS:SERVICE CALL HANDLING 9.3.1.1</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="281">| Ob Ujec ve:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="282" confidence="possible">tii* i</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="283">|</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="284" confidence="possible">!</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="285" confidence="possible">| problemidentification,Remote ProvideFront-endproductsupportto CallAssistance, customers and through promptescalation accurate service to</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="286" confidence="possible">Process Owner: c.ll Proc Ownj OutboundService Alerts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="287">tomer.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="288">t&amp;ece andllng -npu8: Inputs' 11~I I1 Service Requests| KeyProcessSteps: , ! y</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="289" confidence="possible">^ -'^l</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="290" confidence="possible">Obt.l Cu Account ,nd</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="291">)</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="292" confidence="possible">f Verify customer ~ sUtisfctloni nd close ]</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="293">\^ nicrvcall</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="294">y</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="295">[ \</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="296" confidence="possible">&gt; \\</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="297" confidence="possible">&lt;r 4 &gt; Detetme ny 1 % fo.ljw-up /</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="298">'^ reqnlrement p^</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="299">f Perform R f Aufista . Selrice sjroces I</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="300" confidence="possible">I I Outputs: * I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="301">Hardware Service call need need t Account profileupdated, Remote CallAssistance successfully</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="302">identified, Confir completed</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="303">| ^ustomer,</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="304" confidence="possible">| Customer:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="305" confidence="possible">FieldTechnicians,Analysts</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="306">I)ocumenc.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="307" confidence="possible">se* | Assistance Ince CallRecord,SoftwareCallRecord, Solve Record, Account Profileupdates Remote Call</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="308">Benefits:</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="309">info.)</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="310" confidence="possible">QuarAy - Cost Delivery</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="311">Accuracyof informationgiven to customer (i.e., Casebase - Cost per telephone Call :Response to customer phone call</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F6">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="312">Figure 6</caption>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_028.image_29.png" thmb="62qe.page_028.image_29-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="313">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="314">3</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="315">U1 ? s</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="316">3 o~ O X :$</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="317" confidence="possible">oE f</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="318">O)</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="319">'0</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="320">0 CfJ</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="321">0 . :- 0</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="322">! ]</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="323">I 0 QC. 3 s;</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="324">0 o</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="325">..</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="326">' -</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="327" confidence="possible">s</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="328">UZ</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="329">- K</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="330">E e</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="331">a</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="332">_ -</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="333">j</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="334" confidence="possible">gE3</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="335">' 8 X w</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="336">rI</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="337">2~</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="338">166</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx339">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_029.image_30.png" thmb="62qe.page_029.image_30-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="340">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="341">EU</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="342">I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="343">L) '- -</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="344">I oo o X</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="345">L) ) o: X 2 o C 3? ; *..C I</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="346">on s</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="347">? l} i t i</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="348">180 5</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="349">l00</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="350">o,</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="351">167</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx352">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_030.image_31.png" thmb="62qe.page_030.image_31-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="353">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="354">168 Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="359">(3) awarenessthatthe"smartsystem"for solving machineproblemsover the phone was not being used in practiceas it was designed to be, which was addressedin existing practiceby soliciting morefeedback fromusers andby a company-sponsored, month-longcompetitionamong users for the highest numberof solves (solutions).The updatedsystem was used in the pilot. Issues thatwere not addressedin design meetingsbecause the discussion of actualpracticewas putoff for so long includedthe omission of knowledge in practiceresidingin the sequenceof customer-TeleRep interactions during the use of RCA. In the flowchartmodel of customer-TeleRep interaction, the juncture at which the TeleRepinitiatedsolving the machineproblemon the phone is shown as a simple yes/no decision tree.However, in practice,much skill in handlingthe customerwas necessary to get them even to try to fix their own machine;in fact, many refused. Successful skills involved using the right language and tone along with holding out the potential that the customer's copier could be back up and runningright away. Another tech- nique, useful if the caller's telephone was remote from the copier, was informingthe customerthatthe service call was being placed, as usual, and asking them to call back and cancel if the recommendedsteps solved the problem. In all cases, judgment of the customer's mood, their kind of business, along with the level of difficulty of the problemrequiredas much skill and knowledge as knowing the various machinemodels, their typical problems, and the right recommendationsfor solving those problems, whetherfound in the databaseand read from the screen in a mannerto keep conversationflowing or recitedfromthe TeleRep'smemory.Such skills and knowledge were neitheracknowledgedby managementnor taughtin training. The assumptionwas that TeleReps knew little and were dependenton the smartsystem to accomplishsuch solves.12Discussion of how TeleReps actually solve machine problemsover the phone would have revealed the mistakennatureof such assumptionsand would have shown the shortcom- ings of the smartsystem. Had this taken place early in the design process, less emphasis could have been put into trying to make the ill-suited, case- basedsmartsystemwork,andmoreemphasiscouldhave beenputon training TeleReps in machine-problem-solving skills. Our IRL team's participation in the design and constructionof trainingcurriculum broughtemphasis on learningthroughpractice with expertpeers as tutors,facilitatingsome tacit knowledge transfer.However, the mind-set that credited the technology ratherthanthe workerdid not change.It mighthave at least been challenged had such practice-oriented discussion takenplace in the design meetings. Anotherexampleof the resultsof ignoringpracticewas the destructionof useful resources because they were put on-line with no awarenessof their use in practice.The inclinationto have technicianssimply put paperdocu- <marker type="page" number="32"/><marker type="block"/> ments on-line withoutunderstanding how they are actuallyused in practice is a common pitfall in the use of computersystems. The particular example here applies to supplies sales ratherthan service calls. Indiscriminate digi- talizationof existing paperresourceshadresultedin the destructionof useful documentssuch as the one used for floor (lowest allowed) prices in supplies sales. As a paperdocument,referred to as the hible, it had been individually customizedwith highlightingandbook-marking for often-usedsections, and handwritten margin notes for specialcases andupdates.Althoughinteractive technology was capable of incorporating such functions,the documentwas put on-line in a form thatmadeit impossiblefor people to customizeto their use, andit became a deaddocument.As a compilationof unuseddata,it was a waste of technology and of a previouslyvaluableresource.We were able to addressthis issue in memos fromthe IRLteamduringthe pilot period,but it would have been preferable,however, if the importanceof designing on-line documentsto emulatetheiruse in practicewere discussed earlierin the process with the whole team of designer-users. Althoughsome attention was given laterto which documentsshouldbe put on-line, when the technicians responsible for this task requestedthat our team give them a list of documentsto be digitalized,they expected that we would provide a yes/no type of list ratherthan an answer demonstratingawareness that how the informationcontainedin the paperdocumentwas used in practicemattered for the format in which it should be made available electronically.When earlieruse practiceis not emulated,the assets of the original-such as speed of access facilitated by at-a-glance structureand location, and its custo- mizable flexibility-are lost.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx356">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_031.image_32.png" thmb="62qe.page_031.image_32-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="357">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="358">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 169</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="360" confidence="possible">Conclusion</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="361">The comparisonof the two design cultures-industrial designengineering practice and this particularreengineeringpractice-reveals a contrast in termsof flexibility and innovation. The mechanicaldesign engineerssketchedto one anotheron scrappaper and in the marginsof official drawingsto convey meaning.The reengineers were boundby predefinedtemplatesand icons in theircomputerprogram. Industrialdesign engineers did not follow design school protocols in practice,preferring to work on differentlevels and differentsegments of the design simultaneously.The reengineershad to work using dictated steps, controlledby management-mandated structure of theTQCprocess,deviation from which was quickly pointedout. The work was a lock-step hierarchical process that stayed at a high level of abstraction to the extent thatlittle time</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx362">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_032.image_33.png" thmb="62qe.page_032.image_33-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="363">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="364">170 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="365" confidence="possible">was left for the crucial details of work practice that could make or break the project's effectiveness. The industrial design engineers used mixed electronic world and paper world practices to create visual representations, choosing the format most appropriate for a given context. The reengineers used only the computer software templates and, given the conventions of presentation and the de- mands of management, had no other choices. Corporate management has created a myth that it is handing over crucial decisions to empowered work groups, stepping aside so that workers can redesign their own work practice and its technical support. However, corporate programs to ensure quality through uniformity of practice also ensure that little innovation takes place. To its credit, this is not what management is trying to do. It is trying to give guidance and structure. However, just like Taylor's ideas that have come down to us through scientific management, what might have been a good idea to start with in one particular application, when reified and made into a formula, results in the loss of the creative flexibility and of the innovative informal processes that are the cornerstones of doing things well. The real dangers are less the software packages that create concepts and visual representations of work than the assumptions that one idea will work for every application and that the formalization of good ideas will produce standardized good work. Such reifications cause the loss of the necessary messy, informal detail and patched-together character of real work and knowledge in practice that made them fit the situation in the first place. Streamlined and abstracted knowledge in executive summaries and prepackaged formats may serve the purposes of review for busy executives, but such standardization can result in slippage and misfit between plans, appropriate action, and anticipated outcomes.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="366">Notes</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="370" confidence="possible">1. See,forinstance, Rudwick (1976,1992),Mukerji (1984), Lynch (1985a, 1985b,1988), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="367" class="deo:Reference">Latour and Woolgar (1979)</xref>, Lynch and Woolgar (1988a, 1988b),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="368" class="deo:Reference">Amann and Knorr Cetina (1988)</xref>,andKnorr Cetina (1990). 2. See<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="369" class="deo:Reference">Allwood and Kalen (1994)</xref> forareview of theliterature on thelimitations of computer assisted design (CAD). 3. Star and Griesemer (1989, 393)define boundary objects as "objects that arebothplastic enough to adapt to localneedsandconstraints of theseveral parties employing them, yetrobust enough to maintain a common identity across sites." 4. Thiswasa teamproject in action research sponsored through theInstitute for Research on Learning (IRL) and fundedby the unnamed corporation at whose site the studywas conducted. 5. All individual and company names arepseudonyms.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx371">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_033.image_34.png" thmb="62qe.page_033.image_34-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="372">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="373">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 171</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="375" confidence="possible">6. Once the members of our team realized we would not be able to convey the crucial informationwe needed to get across to the design team because of the structureof the design meeting format,we introduceda differentinteractional structure in the form of a workshopto presentour findings. However, this was an exception introduced by our presence, and was not partof the usual process. 7. The use of slick corporatepresentationslides is similar to the art history example of Alberti(1404-1472), who had to presenthis arguments regardingthe importance of perspective in paintingin Ciceronianrhetoric,regardlessof its inappropriateness for the subject,to be taken seriouslyby the Medici court,because such rhetoricwas the respectedmode of discourseof the day. Overheadslides presentingmaterialin boxes, icons, and bullets is the Ciceronianrhetoric of today's corporateculture. 8. Quality became the corporatefetish of the 1980s and 1990s, anotherby-productof shrinkingsingle company marketshares due to increasedinternational competition.In many sectors, the focus has been deemed the new battleground for corporatesurvivaland prosperity. Deming, originator of the conceptand a U.S. citizen, founda receptiveaudiencefor his quality philosophyin the desperateeconomy of postwarJapan,his ideas having been rejectedby the then-booming U.S. business community. Declines in U.S. market shares due to Japanese competitionin the 1970s broughtrenewedattentionto Deming's ideas. 9. Marcia Porterfield,"The Quality Philosophy and One Corporation'sInterpretation" (unpublished manuscript, n.d.). 10. This representation also includestelemarketing that was to be incorporated, althoughthe National Design ProgramTeam was working on integrationof supply marketing,customer service support,and customeradministration. 11.This is an updated term to includenew supportsystemsto help customersfix theircopiers with database-supported advice from TeleReps.CCA, the older system, is discussed earlierin the field notes. 12. How such solves were actuallyaccomplishedis discussed in Vinkhuyzenand <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="374" class="deo:Reference">Whalen (1996)</xref> and Whalenand Henderson(1996).</region>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="376" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="377" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Allwood, Martin,andThomasKalen.1994. Usabilityin CAD: A psychologicalperspective.The International Journalof HumanFactors in Manufacturing 4 (2): 145-65.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="378" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Alpers, Svetlana. 1983. The art of describing.Chicago:Universityof Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="379" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Amann, Klaus, and KarinKnorrCetina. 1988. The fixationof visual evidence. HumanStudies 11:133-69.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="380" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Arnheim,Rudolf. 1969. Visualthinking.Berkeley:Universityof CaliforniaPress. . 1993. Sketchingand the psychology of design. Design Issues 9:15-19.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="381" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Bijker,Wiebe. 1995. Of bicycles, bakelites,and bulbs. Cambridge,MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="382" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Bly, Sara. 1988. A use of drawingsurfacesin differentcollaborativesettings.Paperpresentedat the Second Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work, Portland, Oregon, September.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="383" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Bowker,Geof. 1988. Picturesfrom the subsoil, 1939. In Picturingpower,visual depictionsand social relations,editedby GordonFyfe andJohnLaw,221-54. London:Routledge&amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="384" confidence="possible" page="34" column="1">Bucciarelli,Louis L. 1994. Designing engineers.Cambridge,MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="388" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Buchanan,Richard,and VictorMargolin,eds. 1995. Discovering design. Chicago:University of ChicagoPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="389" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Callon, Michel. 1986a. The sociology of an actor-network: The case of the electric vehicle. In Mappingthe dynamicsof science and technology,edited by Michel Callon,John Law, and Arie Rip, 19-34. Basingstoke,UK: Macmillan. . 1986b. Some elementsof a sociology of translation: Domesticationof the scallops and the fishermenof St. BrieuxBay. In Power,action and belief:A new sociology of knowledge ? edited by John Law, 196-229. London:Routledge&amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="390" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Collins, HarryM. 1974. The TEA set: Tacitknowledgeandscientific networks.Science Studies 4:165-86.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="391" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Downey, Gary. 1992a. CAD/CAMsaves the nation?Knowledgeand Society9:143-68. . 1992b. Humanagency in CAD/CAMtechnology.Anthropology Today 8:2-6. . 1995. Steeringtechnologydevelopmentthroughcomputer-aided design. In Managing technologyin society, editedby A. Rip, T. Misa, and T. Schot, 83-110. London:Pinter.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="392" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Ferguson,Eugene. 1976. The mind'seye: Nonverbalthoughtin technology.Science 197:827. . 1992. Engineeringand the mind'seye. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="393" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Fujimura,Joan. 1988. The molecular biology bandwagonin cancer research:Where social worlds meet. Social Problems35:261-83.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="394" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Fyfe, Gordon,andJohnLaw,eds. 1988. Picturingpower: Visualdepictionsand social relations. London:Routledge&amp; KeganPaul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="395" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Gorman, Michael, and BernardCarlson. 1993. Invention as re-representation: The role of sketchesin the developmentof the telephone.Paperpresentedat the PrincetonWorkshop on Cognitive Approachesto Visualizationin Science and Technology,February.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="396" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Harper,R. R., J. A. Hughes,and D. Z. Shapiro.1991. Workingin harmony: An examinationof computertechnology in air traffic control. In Studies in computersupportedcooperative work: Theorypractice and design, edited by J. M. Bowers and S. D. Benford, 225-34. Amsterdam: Elsevier.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="397" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Henderson,Kathryn.1991. Flexible sketches and inflexible databases. Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues16:448-73. . 1993. Mixed practicesin the visual cultureof design engineering.Paperpresentedat the PadisWorkshop on Social Science Research,TechnicalSystems and CooperativeWork, April. . 1994. How and why changes from one visual cultureto anothercause restructuring in design engineering.Paperpresentedat the Conferenceon VisualRepresentations in Scien- tific Practice,Galveston,Texas,April. . 1995a. The politicalcareerof a prototype: Visual representation in design engineering. Social Problems42:274-99. . 1995b.The visual cultureof engineers.In Culturesof computing, edited by Leigh Star, 196-218. Oxford,UK: Blackwell. . 1998. On line and on paper: Visual representations, visual culture, and computer graphicsin design engineering.Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="398" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Hindle,B. 1981. Emulationand invention.New York:W. W. Norton.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="399" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">Hutchins,Edwin. 1991. The social organizationof distributedcognition. In Perspectives on socially sharedcognition,editedby LaurenResnickandJohnLevine, 283-304. Washington, DC: APA. . 1995. Cognitionin the wild. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="400" confidence="possible" page="35" column="1">KnorrCetina,Karin. 1990. Imagedissection in naturalscientific inquiry.Science, Technology, &amp; HumanValues15:259-83.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="404" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Latour,Bruno. 1986. Visualizationand cognition:Thinkingwith eyes and hands. Knowledge and Society: Studiesin the Sociology of CulturePast and Present6:1-40. . 1987. Science in action: How to follow scientists and engineers through society. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UniversityPress. . 1992. Where are the missing masses? The sociology of a few mundaneartifacts.In Shapingtechnology,buildingsociety, edited by W. Bijkerand J. Law, 225-58. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="405" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Latour,Bruno, and Steve Woolgar.1979. Laboratorylife: The constructionof scientificfacts. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="406" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Lave, Jean. 1988. Cognitionin practice. Cambridge, MA: Cambridge UniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="407" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Law, John. 1987a. On the social explanationof technicalchange: The case of the Portuguese maritimeexpansion.Technologyand Culture28:227-52. . 1987b. Technology and heterogeneousengineering:The case of Portugueseexpan- sion. In The social constructionof technological systems, edited by W. Bijker,T. Hughes, and T. Pinch, 111-34. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="408" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Luff, P., C. Heath, and D. Greatbatch.1992. Tasks-in-interaction: Paper and screen based documentation in collaborative activity.In Proceedings,10thInterdisciplinary Workshop on "Informatics in Psychology": CognitiveAspectsof VisualLanguageand VisualInterfaces, Sharding,Australia,May 1991.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="409" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Lynch,Michael. 1985a. Art and artifactin laboratoryscience. London,Beverly Hills: Sage. . 1985b. Discipline and the materialform of images: Analysis of scientific visibility. Social Studiesof Science 15:37-66. . 1988. The externalizedretina:Selection and mathematization in the visual documentation of objects in the life sciences. HumanStudies 11:201-34.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="410" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Lynch, Michael, and Steve Woolgar,eds. 1988a. Introduction: Sociological orientationsto representational practice in science. HumanStudies 11:99-116. . 1988b. Representation in scientific practice.Special issue on Representation in Scien- tific Practice.HumanStudies 11 (2-3).</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="411" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Margolin, Victor. 1989. Introduction. In Design discourse, edited by Victor Margolin, 3-28. Chicago:Universityof Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="412" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Margolin,Victor,and RichardBuchanan,eds. 1995. The idea of design. Cambridge,MA: MIT Press.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="413" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Mukerji,Chandra.1984. Visual language in science and the exercise of power: The case of cartography in early modem Europe.Studiesin VisualAnthropology10:30-45.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="414" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Pace, Larry,and DominickArgona. 1991. Participatory action research.In Participatoryaction research,edited by WilliamFoote Whyte, 56-69. NewburyPark,CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="415" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Petroski,Henry.1985. Toengineer is human.New York:St. Martin's.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="416" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Polanyi, Michael. 1958. Personal knowledge: Towardsa post-critical philosophy. London: Routledge&amp; Kegan Paul. . 1967. The tacit dimension.London:Routledge&amp; KeganPaul.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="417" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Rudwick,Martin.1976. The emergenceof a visual languagefor geological science 1760-1840. Historyof Science 14:148-95. . 1992. Scenesfrom deep time. Chicago:Universityof Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="418" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Star,SusanLeigh. 1989. The structure of ill-structured solutions:Heterogeneousproblem-solv- ing, boundaryobjects and distributed artificialintelligence. In Distributedartificial intelli- gence 2, edited by Michael Huhns and Les Gasser, 37-54. Menlo Park, CA: Morgan</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="419" confidence="possible" page="36" column="1">Kauffman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="423" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Star,Susan L., and James R. Griesemer.1989. Institutional ecology, "translations," and coher- ence: Amateursandprofessionalsin Berkeley'sMuseumof Vertebrate Zoology 1907-1939. Social Studiesof Science 19:387-420.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="424" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Suchman,Lucy. 1987. Plans and situatedactions: The problemof human-machine communication. Cambridge, MA: CambridgeUniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="425" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Tang,J., and L. Leifer. 1988. A frameworkfor understanding the workspaceactivity of design teams. In Computer-supported cooperativework. San Mateo, CA: MorganKauffman.</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="426" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Townsend,Patrick,andJoanGebhardt.1992. Qualityin action. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="427" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Turnbull, David. 1993. The ad hoc collective workof buildingGothiccathedralswithtemplates, string,and geometry.Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues18:315-40.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="428" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Ullman,D., L. Stauffer,and T.Dietterich.1987. TowardexpertCAD. Computers in Mechanical Engineering 16:56-63.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="429" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Vincenti,WalterG. 1990. Whatengineers know and how they know it. Baltimore,MD: Johns HopkinsUniversityPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="430" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Vinkhuyzen, Erik, andJackWhalen. 1996.Machineintelligenceandhumaninteraction: Solving problemswith documentmachines over the telephone.Paperpresentedat the meetings of the AmericanSociological Association,New York,August.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="431" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Vitta,Maurizio. 1989. The meaningof design. In Design discourse, editedby VictorMargolin, 31-41. Chicago:Universityof ChicagoPress.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="432" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Whalen, J., K. Henderson,and M. Whalen. 1995. On line, on paper,and on the phone: The choreographyof work. Paper presented at the meetings of the American Sociological Association,Washington, DC, August.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="433" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Whalen, Marilyn,and KathrynHenderson.1996. Outstanding smart systems. Paperpresented at the meetings of the AmericanSociological Association,New York,August.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="434" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Winner,Langdon. 1985. Do artifactshave politics? In The social shaping, of technology,edited by Donald MacKenzieand Judy Wajcman, 26-38. Philadelphia: Open UniversityPress. . 1995. Political ergonomics. In Discovering design, edited by R. Buchanan and V. Margolin, 146-70. Chicago:Universityof Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="435" confidence="possible" page="37" column="1">Kathryn Henderson earned her Ph.D. in sociology and M.EA. in art criticism at Universityof California,San Diego. She is currentlyan assistantprofe.vssor in sociology at TexasA&amp;M University(College Station,TX77843-4351). Her latest book is On Line andon Paper:VisualRepresentations, Visual Culture,andComputer Graphicsin Design Engineering (MIT Press, 1998). She is currently writing aboutthe use ofpaper documents in computer-supported work and researching the actor networks of the grassroots sustainablebuildingmovement.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx385">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_034.image_35.png" thmb="62qe.page_034.image_35-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="386" page="34" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="387" page="35" column="1">172 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx401">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_035.image_36.png" thmb="62qe.page_035.image_36-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="402" page="35" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="403" page="36" column="1">Henderson/ Role of MaterialObjects 173</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx420">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_036.image_37.png" thmb="62qe.page_036.image_37-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="421" page="36" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="422" page="37" column="1">174 Science, Technology,&amp; HumanValues</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx436">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62qe.page_037.image_38.png" thmb="62qe.page_037.image_38-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="437" page="37" column="1">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.141 on Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:09:47 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
