<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>1283dc61c029fa77a3664f79c7817ad6a21e17c17e493f89db6a2143591d1925</job>
    <base_name>62is</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible">http://dx.doi.org/10.1287/orsc.9.2.123</doi>
    <warning>Original PDF was found to be an image-based/possible OCR document. Output quality may be degraded.</warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62is.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="2">Organization Studies</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="3">the New Pragmatism: Positivism</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Anti-Positivism</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="5">the Search for Ethics Author(s): Andrew C. Wicks</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="6">R. Edward Freeman Source: Organization Science</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="7">Vol.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="8">No. 2 (Mar. - Apr.</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="9">)</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="10">pp. 123-140 Published by: INFORMS Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/2640349 . Accessed: 19/11/</name>
          <aff id="11">:</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="13" confidence="possible">Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp" id="12">http://www.jstor.org/page/info/about/policies/terms.jsp</ext-link></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="16" confidence="possible">JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact <email id="15">support@jstor.org</email>.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="17">.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="18">.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="19">INFORMS is collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve and extend access to Organization Science.</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx20">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62is.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.jstor.org" id="21">http://www.jstor.org</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="23">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="24">Organization Studies and he New Pragmatism: Positivism, Anti-positivism, and he Search or Ethics</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="25">Andrew C. Wicks R. Edward Freeman</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="26" confidence="possible">* University of Washington, Graduate School of Business Administration, Seattle, Washington 98195 The Darden School, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="27">In</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible">this articlethe authorsoffera way outof the circulardebatebetweenthepositivistandanti-positivist positionsin ourliterature. In the contextof the criticalissues of ethics,the authors raise thepragmatist alternative and suggestthatthis commongroundmightprovidea place for the field to not only meet, but also a place wherewe can productively collaborate. The perspectives outlinedin this articlearewhat the field needs:a hopefulandproductive setting for proactivescholarship. Bart Victor</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="29">Introduction</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="30" confidence="possible">Abstract The central claim of this paper is that organization studies needs to be fundamentally reshaped. Such change is needed to provide room for ethics and to increase the relevance of research. We argue that the new pragmatism provides critical resources for this change. Pragmatism is a particularly helpful tool to use in that it highlights the moral dimensions of organizing (is this useful for our purposes?) while at the same time avoiding en- trenched epistemological distinctions that marginalize ethics and make research less useful. The paper begins by discussing the relative absence of ethics within the mainstream of organization studies, indicates why this relative absence is problematic, and proceeds to show how pragmatism offers a preferable approach. Epistemology specifically the debate between positivists and anti-positivists becomes a central issue because the framework of positivism is overtly hostile to ethics (and other nonquantitative approaches to studying organizations), rendering it a marginal subject. While anti-positivism holds promise for overcoming this hostility towards ethics, it retains some of the destructive elements of positivism that create new and equally troubling difficulties. The paper claims, in contrast to the proposals of others (e.g., Zald' s 1993 position) that the preferredalternative is not to split the difference, but to move beyond the positivism vs. antipositivism debate and work from an alternative framework. Pragmatism allows researchers to put this debate to the side and, in the process, develop research that is focused on serving human purposes i.e., both morally rich and useful to organizations and the communities in which they operate. (Pragmatism; Ethics; Epistemology)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="218">While organization studies has a long and distinguished history, recent contributions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>) raise fundamental questions about the nature of research in the field (e.g., what constitutes relevant research questions, foundational assumptions, viable methodologies, compelling evidence, and larger objectives for inquiry?). We agree with Zald that it is time to reconsider the foundations of organization studies. We share his view that there needs to be an increase in interdisciplinary work, including a prominent role for the humanities, as a way to enrich the literatureand help charta different course for the field. However, the primary aims of this paper are to create a viable place for ethics and increase the relevance of research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Hambrick 1994</xref>). The new pragmatism (the terms "pragmatism"and "the new pragmatism" are used inter- changeably) focuses on serving human purposes, and thus simultaneously highlights the moral dimensions of organizations and the need for research to have practical value. Indeed, as we will attempt to show, existing conceptual barriers to consideration of ethics also make research less relevant. Why ethics? First, research suggests that ethics is critical to the practice of capitalism. Several prominent thinkers, including economists such as Adam Smith, have held that a broad array of moral agreements are necessary for markets to function well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Arrow 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="34" class="deo:Reference">Fukuyama 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Smith 1981</xref>, Werhane 1991). Others have held that capi-<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> talism may "implode" if its central moral foundations erode or are lost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Caeldries 1993</xref>, analyzing work of Shumpeter, Smith, Heilbroner, and others). This thesis suggests not only that ethics is critically relevant to business and the success of the market, but that systematic attention to the moral dimension of business is necessary to a coherent and constructive notion of organization studies. A second and related point is that ethics is an essential part of the very foundations of organization studies. The domain of ethics spans both the ends and means of human (and corporate) activity. Ethics raises the issue of whether a given activity can be justified. Since the goal of the field is to both understandand evaluate organizations with the larger purpose improving their function, ethics is an in- extricable element of this effort-particularly when research contains implications for practice (e.g., how managers of firms should behave). Any attempt to provide direction to corporations (e.g., firms should do x and not y) are at some level moral endeavors. The key-and to this point unanswered-question is whether such directives can be ethically justified (i.e., can we give defensible and ethically sound reasons for them?). Taking this next step would require the explicit identification and systematic analysis of such issues, the sine qua non of ethics. Our claim is that epistemology is a critical factor ex- plaining why ethics has been largely absent from mainstream research and why work in organization studies hasn't been as useful as it might be. Epistemology helps shape whether-and how-ethics (i.e., concern for advancing human purposes) is part of research. Avoiding discussion of ethics and trying to remain agnostic on the subject does not allow positivist researchers to make organization studies value-free. Such a strategy entails that they, in effect, do ethics badly. By not exploring the value assumptions and implications of their work researchers have sidestepped this responsibility and, in the process, risked making their work "a naive tool for advancing an unquestioned administrative conception of social order and function" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Weaver and Trevino 1994</xref>, p. 132; citing Barley et al. 1988; Sullivan 1983). At the same time, while anti-positivists provide a critical advance beyond positivism by being cognizant of the value assumptions and implications of organization studies research, they do not offer a viable alternative. By retaining key positivist assumptions, anti-positivists embrace a moral relativism that precludes the integration of ethics. Unlike Zald, we do not think that it is possible to simply "combine" positivism and anti-positivism or split the difference between them in order to create a compelling alternative to the current situation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>, p. 516). Rather, researchers must find a way to move beyond both<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> views and put the field on a tenable epistemological foot- ing if ethics, in particular, is to have a viable place in organization studies. Changing the epistemology is necessary, but it is only a first step. Other conceptual inno- vations discussed below are needed to refocus and re- structure inquiry before it is possible to "build bridges" between ethics and the mainstream organization studies literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>). Thus, while we agree with the spirit of Zald's paper, we see the problems outlined by him as more fundamental and complex than he does, requiring a careful and comprehensive rehabilitation of the existing literature. This paper advocates a different approach to organization studies which we term "pragmatic experimentation." Researchers doing this type of work would see organization studies as a vehicle to help people lead better lives. It would he characterizedby a focus on the practical relevance of research as well as a desire to search for novel and innovative approaches ("experimentation") that may help serve human purposes. Ethics would have a central role-given the centrality of advancing human purposes-but a variety of quantitative and qualitative methodologies are also critical to realizing the objectives of research. To advance this argument the paper is broken into two major parts. The first part focuses on epistemology. This topic is pursued in detail to both support a central claim of the paper-that ethics has been largely isolated from mainstream management research-and to explore how ethics can play an integral role in organization studies. Part one lays the foundation for exploring a specific research agenda wherein ethics and organization studies are interconnected and directed at the task of serving human purposes. Part two develops a pragmatic approach to organization studies ("pragmatic experimentation") built around the pragmatist criterion of usefulness.<marker type="block"/> Presuppositions of what constitutes legitimate research questions and methods go a long way in determiningwhat kinds of research scholars will undertake. We will try to show how the reigning epistemology within the field makes ethics a marginalized topic. This discussion focuses less on a systematic analysis of specific thinkers to show that they are either positivists or anti-positivists. It is instead devoted primarily to showing the implications of the conceptual framework in which positivism and anti-positivism are the primary forms of epistemology.<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Thus, to support the claim that these two camps provide the primary intellectual anchors within organization studies, we rely on prominent authors who make similar claims in their published writings. We begin by focusing on positivism. At its core, positivism assumes the marginality of ethics to organization studies. It posits that the study of organizations can occur through a value-free scientific approach which is qualitatively superior to nonscientific methods. Astley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Astley 1985</xref>, Astley and Zammuto 1992) casts additional light on this issue by suggesting that positivism is characterizedby "a conventional model of scientific progress as a cumulative discovery of objective truth"and the belief that "knowledge grows linearly as new data are added to the existing stock of research findings" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Astley 1985</xref>, p. 497). Flew's definition of positivism reinforces the basic qualities we ascribe to it.<marker type="block"/> Flew's definition makes explicit the positivists' inherent and systematic bias against ethics: it is both distinct from science and incapable of generating anything worthy of the title of "knowledge." Other researchers have noted the pervasive influence of positivist epistemology within organization studies, either in the form of positivism or of neo-positivist approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Astley, 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Bettis 1990</xref>, Daft and Lewin 1990, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="62" class="deo:Reference">Deetz, 1996</xref>). Recent work (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Pfeffer 1993</xref>) highlights the value of normal science and greater paradigm consensus to scholarly reputation and resource al- location, suggesting that more rigorous adherence to positivism may be an increasingly important goal for researchers. Neo-positivism may soften the edges of positivism, but the basic features and underlying distinctions of the positivist world-view are retained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Astley 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Deetz, 1996</xref>). Thus, while many or most positivist researchers may not feel any hostility or opposition to ethics (indeed, they may want to see more of a role for ethics), the content of their epistemology entails the systematic exclusion of ethics from the mainstream of research. Indeed, many critics agree that mainstream positivist and neo-positivist social scientific research has stripped away the moral components of research concepts as impurities which might undermine the validity of their findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Eastman and Bailey 1994</xref>, p. 319; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>, p. 524).<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> To better understandthe foundation of the positivist hostility toward ethics, and to offer an alternative approach, we explore three distinctions which positivists assume are essential and categorical. Finding and Making. The underlying premise of the conventional view is that the task of researchers is to find reality rather than to create or interpret it. There is an underlying objective reality, or at least a set of laws and principles governing how things "work," which can be discovered (e.g., why a rock falls when a hand lets it go; what gives a firm a competitive advantage). The techniques of science are the mechanism to penetratethrough the world of subjective human perceptions and biases to determine what is really going on in a given context. This is to be sharply contrastedwith the approachof "making." Making the world challenges the idea that there is a de- terminate underlying objective reality-at least in a sense that transcends human perception (i.e., reality is socially constructed). Making asserts that all inquiry, including science, is shaped and limited by culture, history, tradition, and perception even with science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Kuhn 1970</xref>). Makers view the world as not telling us how to describe it, but as having a variety of reasonable possibilities of which we are the "makers." Descriptive and Prescriptive. Positivism creates a sharp distinction between prescribing and describing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Flew 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson 1992</xref>). Descriptive work involves talking about things as they exist. Researchers stand as neutral observers, using scientific techniques that allow them to get beyond human biases so that they can make contact with "reality"and document facts. The results of such studies do not tell corporatemanagers what it is they ought to do, or why they ought to do it; it simply reports in an unbiased way what empirical forces are to be reck- oned with in a given context. In contrast, prescriptive writing is the domain of the philosopher or literary critic and it focuses on what ought to be the case. Prescriptive writing explores such questions as "How can we make organizations more humane or better serve the interests of an array of stakeholders?" Prescriptive writers talk about how the world can be if one adheres to certain ideals. Science and Nonscience. According to positivists, scientifically grounded study is the only way to gain genuine knowledge. One of the key distinguishing characteristics is the scientific method which allows researchers to test their hypotheses and rely on objective measures (data) to support their findings. The scientific method is vital for resolving disputes among scientists regarding ri- val theories and provides a critical foundation for the claim that it is hierarchically superior to other methods of analysis. Nonscience refers to any of an array of other<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> modes of inquiry which do not rely on the methods and techniques of scientific research (e.g., the humanities, including ethics). For the positivist, such approaches are, at best, speculative and biased.<marker type="block"/> While the above descriptions are a simplistic rendering of what are often complex and intricateviews, we suggest that they capture the basic logic and outlook of the positivist position. Pragmatism offers a very different inter- pretation. In agreement with the anti-positivists, it rejects the privileged status of science. Science is simply one more technique (albeit very useful and powerful) for cop- ing with the world. Pragmatistsreject the attempt by positivists to create sharp or categorical separations between the terms outlined above (i.e., "the three distinctions"). There is no Archimedean point or underlying reality which we can get at by trying to be objective. The World Is "Out There" but Not "Objective." It would be foolish to suggest that reality or the world is simply an illusion in which people can do whatever they choose within it. There are brute forces people encounter in the world: when an elbow hits the corner of a table, or when someone tries to fly by jumping off the Sears Tower and flapping their arms. In this sense reality is undeniable as well as unavoidable. Pragmatists, like many postmod- ernists, would distinguish between causality and description. While causality may not be in question, description and interpretationare. Following Davidson (1984, 1990) and others, pragmatists hold that there is not one privileged description of events, and thus, no way to find a truly objective account of a situation. Pragmatists would not go so far as to suggest that we can't isolate pragmatic differences between types of evidence and arguments (e.g., natural sciences, social sciences, humanities-based) which facilitate coherent discourse. However, pragmatist do hold that these different types are not fundamentally or categorically distinct-ultimately each are narratives of how we make sense of the world. Facts and Sentences Are Inexorably Intertwined. As soon as one tries to formulate sentences to describe any events or "facts," it becomes evident that any emergent views are embedded in human experience, language, and culture. In short, the pragmatist thesis is that there is no way of linking any of these "factual events" to the truth of a term or a sentence. As Richard Rorty has claimed,<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The brute forces of reality can't make us have "correct" beliefs about them. The bruteness of facts is irreducibly separatedfrom the truth of the sentences about them. The variance across interpretivecommunities about the meaning of a particularevent or fact-the separationof sensory input and the linguistic attempts to encapsulate its mean- ing-is highlighted when viewed through the span of history and the multitude of human vocabularies. All Inquiry Is Fundamentally Interpretive or Narrative. The basic mistake people have made since the En- lightenment is believing that science offered us an anar- rative and purely factual way of looking at the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>). It was felt that with science one could get beyond the prejudice of the individual, and the subjectivity of "story telling" and enter the realm of objectivity. This, however, was precisely the wrong conclusion to draw. The positivist obsession with the scientific method is a "confusion between a pedagogical device-the de- vice of summarizing the upshot of one' s narrativein pithy little formulae-and a method for discerning truth" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Rorty 1985</xref>, p. 3). Science (including social science) is simply a cleverly disguised narrativewhich people some- how took to be a discourse that transcended narrative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="87" class="deo:Reference">McCloskey 1990</xref>). Science as a Language Game. From a pragmatist view, science is simply a language game with a set of ground-rules that one accepts before playing the game. The agreement across cultures from experiments in bio- chemistry and particle physics speaks more about the logical consequences of a language game choice than it does about the necessity of a set of beliefs and descriptions. Rorty suggests the following.<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> The "progress" of science is defined with respect to advances in terms of a particular paradigm, not progress toward Truth or Reality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Kuhn 1970</xref>, p. 126). The boundaries of the three distinctions become increasingly blurred when we look carefully at Kuhn's notion of paradigms and notice that symbolic generalizations (a fundamental element of the disciplinary matrix) serve a definitional (descriptive) and legislative (prescriptive) role simultaneously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Kuhn 1970</xref>, p. 183). The effect of this argument is to unmask the objectivity people so often assign to science and reveal it to be similar to the more mundane and "subjective" discourse science sought to get beyond. With the language game of science, necessity is real in terms of certain discoveries, but this has to do with already held views about the meaning of, for example, litmus paper turning blue. In this sense data that we document can "cause us to hold beliefs, but it cannot suggest beliefs for us to hold. It can only do things which our practices will react to with preprogrammed changes in beliefs" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Rorty 1985</xref>, p. 7). Science is simply another narrative account of how things within the world relate to each other. This critique does not suggest that science is either useless or danger- ous. Quite the contrary, science has been of great assis- tance in harnessing the brute forces of the world to fill basic human needs and advance our larger aspirations (e.g., exploration, self-knowledge). To the extent that it continues to serve these purposes ratherthan direct them, science is a healthy and important tool. It becomes dan- gerous only when the myths become Truthand when people forget that science is simply another vehicle for interpreting the world and implementing human purposes, not for obscuring or defining them. Tolstoy's words are refreshing in this regard:"Science is meaningless because it gives no answer to our question, the only question important for us: 'What shall we do and how shall we live?' " Positivism obscures this most basic question when people think about organizations, and it creates an epistemic context which prevents it from being taken seriously. Even among social scientists who are sympathetic to this mode of inquiry, ethics is seen as something to be "added on" or fit in after the law-like generalizations of positivist science are found. Researchers may hope empirical studies establish that acting in a socially respon- sible manner "pays," or that the most efficient forms of organizations are also humane places to work, but this is contingent on the outcome of scientific studies. Fundamentally, organization studies, like all good social science, is structuredto remain agnostic about ethics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Zald 1993</xref>). Unless the normative discourse of ethics can be built into the fabric of organization studies, then it isn't<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> likely to have a meaningful role to play-ethics will remain something "tacked on" and extraneous rather than incorporated and essential. Recent work suggests that the marginality of ethics is no accident. Rather, it is the result of long-standing assumptions about the nature of business which tend to isolate the ethics "parts"from business "parts":a view that Freeman calls the separationthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Freeman, 1994</xref>). The separation thesis posits that society has come to see business and ethics as distinct and separate realms with their own relevant concepts, categories, and language. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Sen (1987)</xref> argues that, over the past 60 years, the mainstream economics literature has come to embrace an outlook very much like Freeman's separation thesis. Given the way these two realms are shaped and distinguished, there is not much room for ethics (seen primarily as altruism) to play a role in business (seen primarily as strict self- interest) except as an overarching external critique. In this context, business ethics becomes, by definition, an oxy- moron. This conceptual divide closely parallels the three distinctions characteristicof positivism. Indeed, the thesis of this paper is that positivism plays a critical role in making the separation thesis a plausible-perhaps even necessary-way to think about business activity. An ini- tially promising alternative to this positivist view lies in antipositivism.<marker type="block"/> The Relativist Dilemma of Anti-positivism Anti-positivists take great pains to criticize the "positivism" present in management research (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Astley 1985</xref>, Astley and Zammuto 1992, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="105" class="deo:Reference">Martin 1990</xref>, Morgan 1983). Anti-positivists unmask the alleged objectivity of science and see instead the ultimate subjectivity of all forms of research, including science. The scientist is not a neutral observer but an active participantand creatorin collecting data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="106" class="deo:Reference">Morgan 1980</xref>, p. 610-612). The objective of research becomes tapping into the great power within the human imagination to reinvigorate organization studies. By rejecting the epistemologically privileged position of science, the anti-positivist position appearsto hold a great deal of promise for introducing creativity and legitimiz- ing a broad arrayof approaches within organization studies, including ethics. However, the assumptions behind the positivist posi- tion-which anti-positivists so vehemently attack-are unwittingly retained. Rather than moving beyond the basic distinctions outlined in the previous section on positivism, anti-positivists simply invert them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="107" class="deo:Reference">Deetz 1996</xref>). That is, while positivists try to be "finders,""descriptive," and "scientific," anti-positivists represent "makers,""pre- scriptive," and "non-science." For example, the prominent anti-positivist Gareth Morgan argues,<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Morgan continues to accept the positivist view of the world as split into "objective" (finding) and "subjective" (making) parts. His attack on positivism is merely an attempt to create a profound skepticism about the ability to realize the ends of such inquiry. Anti-positivist researchers emphasize the complexity of the world and underscore the limits on the ability to "know" things. In this context, science is not necessarily preferable to the tools of the humanities for getting a good look at the world. Graham Astley's writings also indicated a similar view.<marker type="block"/> For anti-positivists, researchers are caught-even with science-in a web of subjective activities where they only get a partial and distorted glimpse of reality. Thus, organization studies is "an essentially subjective enterprise" where multiple perspectives are important for better grasping the objective world. Antipositivist researchers continue to be troubled by their inability to fully know reality and apologize for the "bias" and "subjectivity" of their work rather than rejecting positivist notions of objectivity altogether (and thereby removing the basis of their angst).1 The Quest for Liberation: A False Hope. The implications of anti-positivism generate a profound sense of liberation, but it is ultimately false and problematic. By claiming that science and all organization studies paradigms are reducible to metaphor-"a partial and one- sided view of the phenomenon to which it is applied" as well as a "partialtruth"-the emphasis shifts from finding the "right"paradigm (and/or metaphor) to finding lots of new and different paradigms and metaphors. Indeed, by claiming that each metaphor is one-sided, partial, and subjective, anti-positivists have no real way to limit how many or what kinds of metaphors are used. An example follows.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> If all metaphors are partial truths, given that antipositivists offer researchers no way outside of a given metaphorto evaluate its "validity"or superiority,how can one determine which theory or metaphor to use? What counts as a good theory? How does one know when to stop looking for metaphors? Aren't there bad metaphors? These are questions which many anti-positivists are aware of, but for which they ultimately have no real answer (e.g., Morgan 1983, p. 407).2 The focus among anti-positivists on meaning-creating activity within organizations has similar problems. Though anti-positivists play up its importance, there is a vacuum of meaning at the center of this activity. As creators of metaphors and interpretationsthat are general and ambiguous, researchers act as "lay theologians," "applied metaphysicians," and "witch doctors" (Astley and Zammuto 1992). As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson (1992)</xref> suggests, they help managers to understandand legitimize their actions. Yet, should any action of management be legitimized? What is the value of talking about organization studies researchers acting as theologians and metaphysicians if researchers systematically avoid discussion of the con- tent-the normative ideas-inherent in any theological or metaphysical view? Presupposed in all three metaphors is some larger normative meaning which should shape and inform the activity of meaning creation (e.g., Johnson and Johnson's credo). Yet, Astley and Zammuto-as well as other anti-positivists-systematically avoid identifying and discussing what this normative meaning might be, thereby implicitly denying its significance. Under scrutiny, the admirable commitment of antipositivists to diversity and novelty crumbles into noth- ingness. It does so, ironically, because these researchers retain the basic positivist distinctions even as they rail against the implications of positivism. It is from this perspective that relativism (the idea that all methods, insights, points of view-as well as moral values-are equally valid) becomes a fundamental problem. It is precisely for this reason that Zald's (1993) attempts to find a compromise between the two camps will not work- both are caught up in a conceptual framework where ethics is marginalized. In this context, there is no way to determine what constitutes "better" forms of meaning creation, either epistemologically or morally. Toward the larger goal of incorporatingethics into organization studies, anti-positivism offers few meaningful contributions while creating a substantial new problem (i.e., relativism). In Part One we have cast a broad net, suggesting that<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> the vast majority of researchers-despite the diversity of viewpoints and methodologies-fall into one of the two camps (or variations of them). This section demonstrates that both positivism and anti-positivism are significant influences within organization studies and that pragmatism provides a preferable epistemological framework. The paper now shifts to outlining a pragmatist approach to organization studies.<marker type="block"/> To construct an alternative vision of management theory, the authors will rely on the new pragmatism. Key figures within pragmatism include John Dewey, William James, and the contemporary philosopher Richard Rorty. James, and especially Dewey, opened up a distinctly American approach to philosophy: Turning the skills of the philosopher to bear on social and political problems so that people (as individuals and as a community) may live<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> richer and more fulfilling lives. Both men saw pragmatism as a way to move beyond the vexing and seemingly irresolvable philosophical questions of metaphysics and epistemology. James and Dewey argued that people should use philosophy as a "forum in which people can talk about how to fulfill their needs, which beliefs work to get them what they want, without running into Platonic and Cartesian impasses" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Rorty 1985</xref>, p. 5). In this connection, it is important to note that both men saw pragmatism as imploring people to act as agents of social and political change. Dewey, in particular, wanted to unseat "the notion, which has ruled philosophy since the time of the Greeks, that the office of knowledge is to uncover the antecedently real, ratherthan, as is the case with our practical judgments, to gain the kind of understandingwhich is necessary to deal with problems as they arise" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Dewey 1988</xref>, vol. 4, p. 14) The key question for pragmatists is whether or not information (scientific data, a novel, a trea- tise on ethics) is useful-useful in the sense of helping people to better cope with the world or to create better organizations. It is important to be clear on this point: the pragmatic criterion of value is not a pseudonym for utilitarianism. Rather, it contains a broad injunction that is adaptable to a wide range of value-systems that may differ substantially from utilitarianism. Instead of offering specific and detailed content to the term, the pragmatic value of usefulness simply requires those engaged in research or decision-making to scrutinize the practical relevance of a set of ideas as defined by their purposes and those shared by their community (e.g., within a country, a corporation, a research stream). There are a number of challenging problems that emerge from this approach, particularly sorting out which values or purposes can be morally de- fended and (especially in a pluralistic society) which values can be used to guide the interactions of people in organizations. The pragmatist criterion accomplishes the broad goal set out in the paper: it shifts attention onto the ethical dimensions and practical relevance of organization studies. A pragmatist approach fosters an environment in which people see the relevance and importance of values to the study of organizations and the need to engage in discussion about which purposes are advanced and why. Once researchers establish that the question of purpose is relevant, the ethics literature-particularly in business ethics-can provide them with an arrayof research which can help to facilitate detailed analysis of these questions. Donaldson and Dunfee's (1994) Integrative Social Contracts Theory (ISCT) and Gilbert's (1992) Strategy Through Convention (STC) each offer procedures and<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> constraints which help communities-specifically business organizations-to manage the process of developing objectives and practices which are morally legitimate. In addition, there are a variety of other resources that provide content-based criteria and give more specific meaning to "usefulness" when it is applied in particular contexts, especially in evaluating firm objectives and activities. One rich stream is in stakeholder theory, where particular normative frameworks are developed, including personal projects (Freeman and Gilbert 1988), Kantian capitalism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Evan and Freeman 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Bowie 1994</xref>), feminist approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Wicks et al. 1994</xref>), and property-based arguments for stakeholder rights (Donaldson and Preston 1995). There are also other de- velopments of moral theory tailored to a business context to help address questions of purpose and managing values: Aristotelian approaches to business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Solomon 1992</xref>), rights and justice approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="151" class="deo:Reference">Werhane 1985</xref>), and an emerging stream of work dealing explicitly with these questions in an international context (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="152" class="deo:Reference">De George 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson 1989</xref>). There are numerous other sources which could be utilized, including standardsand criterion from various religious and philosophical traditions. For the pragmatist, the criterion of usefulness applies across two dimensions that the positivist views as sharply distinct: epistemological (is this information credible, well-founded, reliable?) and normative (does this help advance our projects?). This criterion allows the pragmatist to make judgments about research where the positivist and antipositivist could not. In the service of this revised agenda, pragmatists shift the object of philosophy from the quest for foundational knowledge to the generation of hope: hope as an opti- mism about the possibilities for the future and a dispo- sition to experimenting with alternative ways of living that hold some promise to better realize human aspirations. This version of pragmatism would make inquiry driven by the quest to fulfill human aspirations and the desire to live better lives in community with others. Key resources for carrying out this project are language, history, and culture, as they provide a backdrop for people to understand:their projects, how they fit with the broader discursive communities of which they are a part, and what has worked in the past.<marker type="block"/> The theme of creativity and imagination is prominent among anti-positivists and pragmatists. Pragmatism emphasizes the importance of experimenting with new ways of living, searching for alternative and more liberating vocabularies, and opening up an arrayof possibilities for<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> human action (Rorty 1989). Once researchers drop the notion that organization studies needs to model reality and search for essentialist underlying structures via scientific study, they can embrace a more diverse and interpretive approach. Pragmatism provides a framework that opens up possibilities for such research and gets beyond the problems of relativism found in antipositivism. This non-positivist approachto experimentation can be contrasted with that of anti-positivists. While much of anti-positivism is still valuable, it lacks a connection to particular persons and communities with specific values and goals. Organization studies ceases to be an abstract discipline written for other academics and becomes instead a way of connecting the insightfulness and skill of the intellectual with the needs and challenges of those engaged in the practice of business in a given socio- political context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="158" class="deo:Reference">Hambrick 1994</xref>). Such inquiry offers a genuine prospect of liberation precisely because it con- nects the creative and aspirational with a clear sense of identity and purpose-the models and metaphors are cho- sen by and for us with the expectation that they will enable people to lead better lives (Rorty 1989, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Freeman 1994</xref>). Liberation comes not from the playful exercise of seeing the world differently, but from seeing things differently in ways that are useful to individuals and communities. The spirit of experimentalism is necessary to challenge conventional wisdom and ask questions about "what if ?" but it is tempered by the pragmatist's own commitment to finding alternatives which are useful. Thus, the pragmatist alternative is not a suggestion that "anythinggoes" (a la anti-positivists such as Morgan, Astley, and Zammuto) or that researchers simply sit aroundand come up with fairy tales about how life in organizations might look in the land of make believe. While such a creative spirit might prove an important starting point, theorists must always shape their thought so that it can be opera- tionalized in a specific organization in a particularcom- munity at a given time in history. We take seriously the concern raised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="160" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson (1992)</xref> and other positivists that academic research needs to have tangible results and shape human activity in constructive ways. Pragmatists put as much emphasis on usefulness as they do on novelty, such that a concern with the practical must shape and channel the spirit of experimentation. Thus, different kinds of evidence and research, including empirical studies, can be helpful in grasping the implications of alternative ways of thinking and acting in the world, and serve as a useful source of evidence to complement other insights. Given the perception that opening up moral conversation is a recipe for chaos and divisiveness (Bird and<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Waters 1989</xref>), it becomes essential to indicate how such discussion could occur without undermining effective action within organizations.<marker type="block"/> Ethics in Organizing: The Priority of the Political Pragmatism emphasizes the priority of the political. This insight helps guide conversations about ethics so that they can be both manageable and constructive ratherthan de- stabilizing and destructive. The focus of discussions should be on the concerns of managers, communities, and other key stakeholders, ratherthan the abstract and often obtuse discourse of philosophers. With respect to political philosophy, particularly in a liberal democratic society where people have a wide range of theological and philosophical beliefs, people are best served observing the "Jeffersonian compromise" and debate public policy using shared terms and concepts from American political culture (Rorty 1988, p. 257). Starting with metaphysics and theology not only unnecessarily clouds the issues, it seems to violate the spirit of democracy. Thus, in terms of collective efforts, it is best to start by asking what set of goals can be agreed upon, what kinds of agreements people require to create community, and how they can be implemented. Rather than focusing on whether the theological support for capitalism found in Protestantism is superior to that of Catholicism, people should start by asking whether people can agree to a specific set of rules to govern economic activity-or to abide by the outcome of democratic debates on these questions. The implications of this interpretationof organization studies are that emphasis on the allegedly vague, amor- phous, and contentious issues of ethics does not have to mire one in irresolvable philosophical questions or require that one adopt any specific philosophical or theological worldview to ground those agreements. Ethics in the context of business is about what the corporation strives to be (its goals or ends), how the corporation relates to its stakeholders, how managerial responsibilities are defined, and what ground rules will be used to limit and guide people's behavior. Managers, as well as academic researchers, either implicitly or explicitly make choices on all these issues. Taking the pragmatist approach involves seeing these matters as of primary importance, as "moral," and as to a significant degree, up for grabs; thus, they need to be negotiated within the community of stakeholders who constitute a given corporation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Freeman 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="169" class="deo:Reference">Freeman and Gilbert 1988, Donaldson and Dunfee 1994</xref>, Donaldson and Preston 1995). The process of coming to answers should, wher- ever possible, focus on what people can agree about on these specific issues while trying to avoid bringing in un- necessary philosophical and theological notions. Sharing<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> purposes at the corporation doesn't have to involve shar- ing an entire worldview and philosophy. Adopting this as basic wisdom makes the search for relevant standardsless daunting and seem much closer to the kind of conversations managers engage in daily.<marker type="block"/> The paper now shifts to explore more specific implications of a pragmatist view. Part of this task involves illustrating how research in organization studies would proceed if it were driven by the pragmatic experimentation model. This exploration occurs on two levels-one micro, the other macro: first (micro), exploring how a particular theory or stream of research can be reshaped along pragmatistlines, and second (macro) by examining a broader view of how a diverse array of research in organization studies might unfold under the rubric of pragmatic experimentation. The first part is accomplished by examining and reinterpretingKarl Weick's research. His work offers a particularly attractive framework in which to develop a distinctively pragmatist approach to organization studies. This reinterpretationbuilds on the pragmatist elements in his research and indicates how a more thoroughgoing pragmatism can help address a number of underlying problems and tensions therein (especially antipositivist leanings). We begin by highlighting and re- interpretingsome of the central features of Weick' s work. Equivocality. Weick suggests that the phenomena people encounter in the world are fundamentally equivocal; that is, they do not tell us what to say about them. They are open to multiple interpretations.The image of the world is not that there is some underlying reality wait- ing to be discovered, but that people retain a large degree of freedom to interact with those phenomena and create meaning:<marker type="block"/> Organizations as Social. If Weick is correct, and the raw experience of sensory input is equivocal, then it is natural for research to focus on how individuals and organizations interpretequivocality. Weick argues that this process is, and organizations in general are, fundamentally social. Thus, he turns our attention away from the search for underlying structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Weick, 1979</xref>, p. 11), such as those found in authors like Henry Mintzberg<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> (1994) and toward the activity of organizing-"consen- sually validated grammar for reducing equivocality by means of sensible interlocked behavior" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="183" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>, p. 3). That is, we cease to think about organizations as rei- fied entities and focus on the underlying processes, shared understandings,and interactions that enable them to function. Where Weick's approach underplays the social and contextual richness which shapes the activity of organizing, pragmatism highlights these features (especially language, culture, and history) and sees them as vital elements in thinking about our actions in the world (organizing, interpreting, enacting, etc.). Thus, it would see naturallinkages to an arrayof literatures,particularly on culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="184" class="deo:Reference">Davis 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="185" class="deo:Reference">Frost et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="186" class="deo:Reference">Martin 1992, Schneider 1990</xref>), which could be used to further enrich Weick's framework. Enactment. Weick argues that people enact their environment rather than discover it. He relies heavily on William James to illustrate how people make choices when they confront equivocality, particularlyJames' idea of breaking sensory input into discrete elements, that enable them to impose order and meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="187" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>, p. 148). While this is reminiscent of antipositivism with its claim that reality is a social construction, Weick makes a stronger claim and emphasizes the centrality of human action, suggesting that people are active agents who shape and give meaning to these constructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="188" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>, p. 5 and 1993, p. 635). He emphasizes that our lives, stories, and organizations have particularsubstance as a result of the choices and meanings which we, as individuals and collectives, ascribe to them over time. The choices and created structuresin turn shape and give substance to the context in which people operate and the domain of op- tions for action which appear sensible (i.e., his notion of circular causation and feedback loops). The focus on en- actment enables human agency to play a central role in how people understandreality, thereby providing inroads to tackling the problem of relativism (i.e., "any metaphor will do.") While Weick highlights the dynamic force of the individual in isolation from context, pragmatism would underscore the extent to which these actions are intelligible in terms of a broad and rich context. Language, meanings, and culture (to a greater or lesser extent) are shared and enable organizing and enacting to occur (e.g., they give sense to terms like "balls,""strikes," and "umpires.") Justification. Even though the world is equivocal and enacted, there are limitations placed on the creation of meaning that prevent an "anything goes" approach. Weick suggests that efforts at "sense-making" are social and bound by a given language community:<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Thus, while there is room to introduce change-both re- formist and radical-new forms of interpretationand new ideals must be understood and evaluated in terms of what is (or could be) shared by the community in question. In this sense, the emphasis on justification reinforces the notion that while people have freedom to choose and create, they don't do so arbitrarilyor in a vacuum-a significant move away from the antipositivist camp and toward pragmatism. This approach to organization studies provides some important new resources. Most basically, it offers a role for narration,for human characters, for human choice. It allows for the centrality of human beings as creators and interpretersof meaning at the corporation-for narration and storytelling as valid and valued parts of organization studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="192" class="deo:Reference">Gilbert 1992</xref>, Rorty 1989, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="193" class="deo:Reference">Daft 1983</xref>). While we have used some of Weick's central concepts to give human choice and narrationa central place in organization studies, he has not capitalized on this potential. In particular, the level of evaluation-why people organize, what counts as good or bad organizing-is woefully underde- veloped. There are some references to creating "good conversation" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="194" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>, p. 240 and 1989, p. 242) and developing approaches that are "useful" (Weick 1989, p. 242)-both terms that are prominent in pragmatist thought-but these themes are not systematically developed. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Lane (1986)</xref> has argued, this creates a rather substantial vacuum at the center of the organizing model. Without attention to such matters, Weick's work risks slipping back into the relativism of anti-positivism, where any form of organizing is as good as the next. If human choice and narrationare going to be central, there should be ways of informing, limiting, and justifying it, in order to avoid the dire-and hyperbolic-image of fascism that Lane suggests as a potentially viable form of Weick's organizing model. More importantly, researchers need to find ways to celebrate the "why" of organizing: the significance of human interaction and the pursuit of specific purposes at the corporation. A related problem, also underscored by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="196" class="deo:Reference">Lane (1986)</xref>, is that Weick's notion of sense-making is largely retro- spective. Lane argues that Weick, in his efforts to shed the constraining structures of previous thinkers, goes too<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> far and creates an image of organizing that evolves in a haphazardand random manner. He contrasts Weick's approach sharply with the thought of Barnard, Selznick, Peters, Waterman, and others who argue that centralized notions of purpose are vital for shaping organizations. For Lane, this compounds the problem of purpose, since the priority of action makes questions about purpose "insig- nifican[t]" and "enslaved-merely reactive to and prod- ucts of behavioral action" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="202" class="deo:Reference">Lane 1986</xref>, p. 117). The authors agree with Lane that this is a substantial problem, but disagree with his claim that it can't be ad- dressed within a Weickian framework. Future work must create more room for projected purposes, intentions, and meanings in the organizing model. Weick need not give up the notion that much of sensemaking occurs retrospectively. Indeed, Weick argues causation in his model is circular rather than linear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="203" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>). Thus, even where purpose is defined retrospectively, future action is thereby shaped and defined in part by that sensemaking activity, providing a legitimate place for purpose to be evaluated and gain added significance. Reinterpreted within a pragmatistframework, it becomes possible to see traces of intention and purposeful action in the creative and interpretive actions of persons. Some larger, though loose, sense of purpose shapes organizing activity, whether it is the orchestra(e.g., the score), the jazz quartet (e.g., chords, the score, one's style), or a production fa- cility (e.g., a strategy or routine). To this extent, it is not incompatible to have some basic principles shaping or guiding an organization within a Weick model. People can have some larger strategy, mission statement, or pur- posefully derived shared notions that reduce equivocality, yet still retain minimalist structures that leave room for creativity, interpretation,and dynamic action. The model of metaphor creation outlined by Astley and Zammuto (1992) captures this balance nicely. It is especially useful that they draw on the example of the Johnson &amp; Johnson credo, as it provides a vivid illustration of the role ethics can play in their model, even though they leave aside the normative questions raised by it (i.e., Is this a good code? Does it improve the moral behavior of the firm? Is it morally defensible?). What is particularlyvaluable about Weick' s approach, which isn't present in Barnard, is the importance of al- lowing a broad array of organizational actors to play a role in defining, shaping, and interpretingthe purposes of the firm (Freeman et al. 1988, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="204" class="deo:Reference">Gilbert 1992</xref>). Whereas for Barnard,people need the powerful and charismatic leader to impose meaning onto the corporation, with Weick an array of members in an organization can collaborate to create and shape shared meanings over time. This latter<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> approach is far more compatible with the pragmatist emphasis on the worth and importance of particularpersons and their need for both deriving and creating meaning at the corporation. It also captures the notion of the firm as a context for the realization of the ends of a community of stakeholders prominent in the writings of several important works by ethicists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="207" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson and Dunfee 1995, Freeman and Gilbert 1988, Gilbert 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="208" class="deo:Reference">Solomon 1992</xref>). A more thoroughgoing integration of ethics, specifically pragmatism, can serve as a natural compliment to Weick's work and provide the resources to address these underlying problems. This interpretationof Weick' s writings provides an approach to organization studies that is grounded in the idea that the firm is both malleable and a mere means in the larger project of satisfying human ends: ends which include, but extend beyond, efficiency, profit, and productivity. The positivism of the conventional view would make these "soft" and particularends invisible or irrelevant to discussions of what organizations can and should be.<marker type="block"/> This reinterpretationof Weick creates a way of studying organization studies that is distinctively pragmatist, but accepting the thesis of the paper need not entail that this become the sole or dominant voice in organization studies. Indeed, taking a pragmatic view of organization studies writ large entails that research be diverse and multi- faceted, adapted to the array of purposes people have for organizations. In terms of a grand view of the field (our macro perspective), the authors share Zald's (1993) as- piration for organization studies that is more integrative, draws more from ethics and the humanities, and redefines its raison d'etre as something like his enlightenment model. Pragmatism, because of its improved epistemology and attention to the purpose of organizing, provides a context which is more hospitable to the pursuitof Zald's (1993, p. 523-525) proposed research agenda-focusing on worker participation; systems of domination and justice; ethics, conformity and crime; and corporate citizenship and control. This agenda, at the macro level, is salient and helps create bridges between mainstream management and ethics/humanities. However, pragmatism provides key resources not only for creating a more palatable epistemology which is necessary for conducting such research, but also for helping to overcome existing conceptual barriersto this type of work which still remain even after the positivism versus anti-positivism debate is put aside. The final section of the paper outlines a macro view of the field, highlighting the distinctive features of a pragmatic orientationto organization studies and further<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> illustrating the practical significance this has for how organization research is conducted.<marker type="block"/> 1. Pragmatic Understanding of Multiple Interpretations. Pragmatists share, with a wide array of antipositivists, the view that there are multiple interpretations of events and different concepts and classificatory schemes which could be used to describe phenomena. In this sense, no one description is privileged over others. However, pragmatism does not attempt to take this insight to the extreme of valuing the simple proliferation of viewpoints or descriptions for their own sake. The pragmatic criterion of value-usefulness-helps to remind people that they can and should see different interpretations as having more or less value (i.e., better or worse), depending on their ability to serve given purposes and enable people to accomplish relevant goals.</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx37">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_002.image_03.png" thmb="62is.page_002.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="38">1047-7039/98/0902/0123/$05.00 Copyright(C 1998, Institutefor OperationsResearch and the ManagementSciences</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="39">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998 123</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="41">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx46">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_003.image_04.png" thmb="62is.page_003.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="49">Part 1. Conceptual Barriers to the Integration of Ethics: The Importance of Epistemology</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="51">124</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="52">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="53">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="54">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="59">The term "positive" has here the sense of that which is given or laid down, that which has to be accepted as we find it and is not furtherexplicable; the word is intended to convey a warning against the attempts of theology and metaphysics to go beyond the world given to observation in order to inquire into first causes and ultimate ends. All genuine human knowledge is con- tained within the boundaries of science . .. Whatever questions cannot be answered by scientific methods we must be content to leave permanently unanswered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Flew, 1979</xref>, p. 283)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx69">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_004.image_05.png" thmb="62is.page_004.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 9, No. 2, March-April1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="75">125</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="76">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="77">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="79">A Pragmatist Critique of the Three Distinctions</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="81">The way in which a blank takes on the form of the die which stamps it has no analogy to the relation between the truth of a sentence and the event which the sentence is about. When the die hits the blank something causal happens, but as many facts are brought into the world as there are languages for describing that causal transaction . . . Facts are hybrid entities; that is, the</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx82">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_005.image_06.png" thmb="62is.page_005.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="84">causes of the assertability of sentences include both physical stimuli and our antecedent choice of response to such stimuli. To say that we must have respect for facts is just to say that we must, if we are to play a certain language game, play by the rules. To say that we must have respect for unmediated causal forces is pointless. It is like saying that the blank must have respect for the impressed die. The blank has no choice, nor do we (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Rorty 1985</xref>, p. 4).</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="90">We construct games in which a player loses or wins if something definite and uncontrollable happens. In some Mayan ball game, perhaps, the team associated with a lunar deity automatically loses, and is executed, if the moon is eclipsed during play ... In the laboratory, a hypothesis may be discredited if the litmus paper turns blue, or the mercury fails to come up to a certain level. A hypothesis is agreed to have been "verified by the real world" if a computer spits out a certain number. The hardness of fact in all these cases is simply the hardness of the previous agreements within a community about the consequences of a certain event. The same hardness prevails in morality or literary criticism if, and only if, the relevant community is equally firm about who loses and who wins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Rorty 1985</xref>, p. 3).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91">126</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="92">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="94">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx100">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_006.image_07.png" thmb="62is.page_006.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="109">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="110">127</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="112">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="114">[t]he scientist on this score, like others in everyday life, draws upon symbolic constructs to make concrete the relationships between subjective and objective worlds, in a process which captures only a pale and abbreviated view of either (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Morgan 1980</xref>, p. 610).</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="117">No theory can simply "describe" empirical reality in neutral linguistic terms; all theoretical perspectives are infused by the biases inhering in particular world views.... In contrast to the conventional model, this paper represents administrative science as a fundamentally subjective enterprise. Because researchers adhere to different world views, they generate a variety of alternative perspectives as they impose different meaning and interpretations upon data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Astley 1985</xref>, p. 497).</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="119">Interpretive social science certainly offers a brand of insight that positivism cannot achieve, but on the other hand, positivism can also generate forms of knowledge that elude the interpretive approach. A more relativistic view of the research process en- courages us to see these different approaches as doing different</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx120">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_007.image_08.png" thmb="62is.page_007.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="121">things and to attempt to assess their contributions with this in mind (Morgan 1983, p. 397).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="124">128</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="125">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="126">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="127">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="128" confidence="possible">Table 1</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="129">Differences Between Positivism/Antipositivism and Pragmatism</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="130">Positivism</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="131">Sharp and categorical divisions across three distinctions (making v. finding; descriptive v. prescriptive; science v. nonscience) Science as the only basis for generating knowledge Concepts/Terms as Value-Neutral (stripped of moral content) Reality as Unequivocal</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="132">Anti- Positivism</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="133">Relativizes, but retains, the categorical distinctions of positivism No basis for determining which accounts are better than others Concepts/Terms as Value-Neutral (stripped of moral content) Reality as Equivocal</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="134">Pragmatism</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="135">Rejects the categorical distinctions of positivism (no privileged status, as such, to science) Can draw useful (pragmatic) distinctions among methods and forms of evidence in terms of what is useful (e.g. between "descriptive" and "prescriptive," "science" and "nonscience"; better and worse metaphors) Concepts/Terms as Value-Laden Reality as Equivocal, but grounded in terms of language, history, culture.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="137">Part 2. Exploring Pragmatist Possibilities: Organization Studies as Pragmatic Experimentation</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx139">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_008.image_09.png" thmb="62is.page_008.image_09-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="143">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="144">129</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="145">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="146">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="155">ManagementTheory as Pragmatic Experimentation</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx157">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_009.image_10.png" thmb="62is.page_009.image_10-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="162">130</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="163">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="164">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="165">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx171">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_010.image_11.png" thmb="62is.page_010.image_11-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="173">OrganizationStudies and Taking Human Agency Seriously</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="176">Thus, when we assert that organizations confront equivocality, we mean that organizations live in an environment of puns [i.e., multiple plausible meanings to ascribe to a given display]. The image we want to capture is not that of an environment that is disordered, indeterminate, and chaotic. Instead, we want to capture the image of an environment that is rich in the possible connections that could be imposed on an equally rich assortment of possible punctuated variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="175" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>, p.174).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="179">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="180">131</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="181">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="182">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx190">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_011.image_12.png" thmb="62is.page_011.image_12-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="191">Perhaps the structure that is most basic to the organizing argument is the structure that arises when people choose to take public, irreversible actions, become bound to these actions because of this committing context, and then write plausible stories justifying why these commitments occurred and why others should treat these stories and their reason as a fragment of reality ... Organizations are embodied in the reasons and rationales that become articulated when decisions are justified (Weick 1989, p. 245).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="198">132</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="199">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="200">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="201">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx206">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_012.image_13.png" thmb="62is.page_012.image_13-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="210">A Different Approach to OrganizationStudies</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="212">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="213">133</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="214">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="215">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="217">A Macro View</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T2">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="219">Table 2</caption>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="220">Differences Between Pragmatism and Zald's Critiqueof OrganizationStudies</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="221" confidence="possible">Epistemology Zald: Researchers need to splitthe difference between the positivists(P) and the anti- positivists(AP)(humanities-based work) Pragmatism: Cannotsplitthe differencebetween P and AP; Conceptualframework of P remainswithAP therebykeeps ethics marginal (as underP) and; AP also makes it relativistic (and therefore irrelevant) Mustget beyond P-AP debate to findan epistemologywhich doesn't posit an "Objective" reality thatwe tryto "mirror" (i.e., get right)and doesn't drawthe three sharp distinctions. Concepts of Organization Studies (OS) Zald: We can findways to make the sciences better humanities and vice versa; We can findways to buildbridges between the two disciplines. Pragmatism: Concepts of OS and business more generally are currently grounded in the separation thesis; Need more thanfavorableepistemology- must findways to rethink concepts and categories before meaningful"bridge building" can occur (i.e., no bridged can be developed and maintained in the current climate).</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx222">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_013.image_14.png" thmb="62is.page_013.image_14-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="282">2. The Importance of Conceptual Framing/Catego- rization. A central focus of the critique of epistemology within the field was to highlight not only the relative value of ethical inquiry as compared to social scientific inquiry, but to highlight the (moral) significance of the language and terminology used in describing phenomena. Being aware of both the assumptions and implications of these choices, and then opening up the critical analysis and defense of them, is a vital part of making ethics an overt and systematic part of organization studies. Several examples highlight the significance of how researchers conceptualize phenomena, and specifically the potential linkages between ethics and organization studies. 2a. Behavioral Assumptions and the Building Blocks of Business. Much of the richest ethics research has been devoted to exploding and reconstructing core assumptions of researchersthat undergirdfoundational concepts of business. This has proven to be a particularly important strand of research precisely because these core assumptions-for example, the nature of self-interest, the relative presence or absence of conflicts among contract- ing parties at the corporation, the meaning of competi- tion-fundamentally shape how people see the world. There is significant evidence in the areas of cognitive framing or "schemas" that how people see the world has a profound impact on what they see as rational behavior and on the actual behavioral choices they make ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="223" class="deo:Reference">Beach 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="224" class="deo:Reference">Dees 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="225" class="deo:Reference">Lee and Mitchell 1994</xref>, Lee et al 1996). Weick' s work on self-fulfilling prophesies reinforces this same point: if I assume, for example, that the person with whom I am negotiating with is "out to get me," then it is very likely that through my resultantbehavior during discussions based on this expectation, the other party will become hostile to me (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="226" class="deo:Reference">Weick 1979</xref>). Economics has been an especially influential area for shaping the assumptions used in business. Frank (1988, p. 226-227) cites several studies that show that economists tend to exhibit the op- portunistically self-interested behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Williamson 1975</xref>) that emerges out of neoclassical (positivist) economic models. In one study, economics students were significantly more likely to defect in prisoner's dilemma scenarios than any other group. Another study found that commerce students made one-sided offers in ultimatum bargaining games more often than other groups. Ethicists have long made a target of economists' assumptions because of these kinds of behavioral implications. Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="228" class="deo:Reference">Solomon (1992)</xref> and Gilbert (1996) have argued that while it is a powerful heuristic, the prisoner's dilemma has created more problems that it is worth because of what it conveys to people about human beings and their<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> interactions in business-namely that people are in con- flict, abstracted from particular relationships and inter- personal ties, and they should think solely in a rationally calculating manner. Such assumptions, they argue, come to shape students views about what it means to design a rational plan of action and become, in turn, self-fulfilling prophesies. Similar charges have been made against "agency theory" and "transaction cost economics" (Bowie and Freeman 1992, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="234" class="deo:Reference">Ghoshal and Moran 1996</xref>)- once one sees the world through the lens of agency theory, it is amazing how many issues in business can be seen as "agency problems." The great irony in this is that while both economists and ethicists seem of one voice in arguing for the moral and economics benefits of trust in business-to markets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="235" class="deo:Reference">Arrow 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="236" class="deo:Reference">Noreen 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="237" class="deo:Reference">Smith 1981</xref>), countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="238" class="deo:Reference">Fukuyama 1995</xref>), and even individual firms/persons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="239" class="deo:Reference">Frank, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="240" class="deo:Reference">Jones 1995</xref>)-that many of the basic assumptions of economics, including those outlined, create a conceptual framework in which trust is less and less likely to exist among persons, particularlywithin business (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="241" class="deo:Reference">Ghoshal and Moran 1996</xref>). While there may be sound rejoinders to these claims and a useful place for such heuristic devices, this work underscores the importance of consciously addressing these questions-scrutinizing the assumptions and implications of key metaphors and assessing their usefulness. Many ethicists are engaged in this type of work, but given the cross-disciplinary nature of many of these concepts and the different purposes for which they are used, it is essential that the search for alternatives occur across disciplinary boundaries (e.g., by both ethicists and social scientists). Other notable examples of this research in ethics include: Werhane's (1991) discussion of Adam Smith's concept of self-interest where she argues, contra mainstream economic thought, that Smith saw it as a moral concept shaped and constrained by other moral values rather than as an open-ended injunction to pursue one's interests (i.e., "greed");Solomon's (1992) deconstruction and reconstruction of such concepts as competition and the profit motive; and Gilbert's (1992) deconstruction and reconstruction of the concept of corporate strategy. Indeed, McCloskey's (1990) work provides one of the most effective critiques of economics in this vein, unseating its mystique as "science." He reveals that despite its pre- tenses to being anarrative,the stock in trade of economics is metaphor and concept creation: activities which require the kind of exploration and criticism offered in this paper before given economic analysis should be viewed as useful or good. Sen's (1987) and Etzioni's (1988) work strike a different but complimentary note, as they lament the<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> influence of positivism which has helped to systematically sever economics from ethics and search for ways of reconstructing economics where these linkages are more overt and systematic. 2b. Worker Participation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="244" class="deo:Reference">Zald (1993)</xref> lists worker participationas an area that deserves greaterattention,but these authors would expand the category to include an arrayof stakeholders. If organization studies is committed to an enlightenment model or a pragmatist agenda, then how various stakeholders are treated becomes a central consideration. Given the importance of participation to overall human well being (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="245" class="deo:Reference">Gini and Sullivan 1987</xref>), this becomes a critical issue. Linking the issue of participation to larger themes such as citizenship, alienation, what it means to live a "good life" are all important and deserve closer attention. Certainly studies which look at the effects of worker participation on the organization are important (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="246" class="deo:Reference">Cotton et al. 1988</xref>, 1990; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="247" class="deo:Reference">Leana et al. 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="248" class="deo:Reference">Wagner 1994</xref>), but the current controversies over these studies highlight the problems inherent in such work. First, they are couched in terms of the separation thesis (does participation pay or not?), thereby accepting and perpetuating the division between ethics and business. Second, researchers are coming to realize that what constitutes participation is quite complex and difficult to measure, and that its effectiveness (broadly speaking) is linked to an array of factors such as the type of organization, the competitive environment, management commitment, management-labor relations, etc. Linking the work in democratic theory, ethics, collaboration with the empirical studies promises to help enrich and reframe the issues-both to get around simplistic attempts to show that participationpays (or doesn't) and to complicate our conceptions of participation. Finally, researchers also need to be able to see participation as part of a system of values or "value-dynamics" which can drive an organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="249" class="deo:Reference">Paine 1994</xref>) and help define its operations (e.g., within a TQM system). In this context, certain forms of participation may be critical to the success of the firm (as defined by its mission), but their impact on "the bottom line" may be very difficult to quantify. Future research needs to explore the significance of worker participation (as well as other stakeholders) and search for richer un- derstandings of how it can play a role in creating successful organizations. 2c. Total Quality Management. Traditional approaches may lead managers to see TQM as the latest fad in how the firm can maximize profits or productivity-a set of instrumentaltechniques that can be used to advance their already defined economic interests. TQM is developed because, and to the extent that, it creates increased<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> profits for the firm. However, there are several other possible ways to conceptualize TQM which profoundly affect how it is implemented, how people treat each other, and may substantially affect how successful it is in practice. For instance, TQM could be seen as a way of improving organization and individual learning. Sitkin and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="255" class="deo:Reference">Sitkin et al. 1994</xref>) highlight the profound differences that arise when one takes this view of TQM rather than more tradition interpretations of TQM (e.g., they discuss a "control" orientation as the foil to "learning"). More relevant to the focus on ethics of this paper, TQM could be seen as driven by an interrelated set of concepts which are simultaneously management concepts and moral values. That is, its core elements establish norms of behavior for the firm which extend beyond self- interest and require ongoing commitment by relevant parties to maintain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="256" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson 1989</xref>, p. 12). Thus, for example, contra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Anderson et al. (1994)</xref>, the focus on customer service in TQM should be seen not as a purely instrumental commitment but as a basic value- commitment of the firm, which it will abide by and not violate even when opportunism would seem appealing. Similar arguments could be developed for other aspects of TQM such as empowerment, cooperation, transfor- mational leadership, and continuous improvement. If they are seen as genuine commitments of the firm-moral values it stands behind-then managers must transcend the focus on profit-maximization, alter their decision-making processes, and broaden the conception of how the firm creates value over time. While this account has an intui- tive moral appeal, there are several parts of the literature that suggest that precisely such commitments may capture what some TQM advocates envisioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="258" class="deo:Reference">Deming 1994</xref>) and highlight what enables firms to create sustainable advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="259" class="deo:Reference">Frank 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="260" class="deo:Reference">Jones 1995</xref>, Pfeffer 1994). 3. Strengthen the Theory/Practice Link. While pragmatism is sometimes questioned for being focused on the applied, it is clearly not a-theoretical or anti-theoretical. Pragmatism offers a helpful check to ensure that the debates and discussions of academics do not become so es- oteric that they are irrelevant-arguments over differences that don't make a difference-and don't help us live better lives. Pragmatism reminds us that academic speculation and theorizing must ultimately-not necessarily in the short or even medium term-prove to be of use in how people live their lives. However, it does see the importance and value of theory as a mechanism to help explain and predict phenomena, to order and direct human actions, and shape practice to create sustainable benefits. The mixture of practice and time combine to form a particularlyhelpful way to help sort out the value of theory. Theoretical wisdom or insights which survive<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> the test of time and create "best practices"-ways of living or structuring organizations which prove especially valuable-provide model forms of good theory. 4. Multiple Methods and Forms of Evidence. Pragmatism creates a fundamental shift in how researchers should think about studying organizations. Rather than inverting the status of privilege from positivist social science to deconstruction, ethnography, and more qualitative work, pragmatism focuses on an entirely different question. It shifts attention away from epistemological status and onto how scholars can best address useful research questions. That is, researchersshould look for methods best suited for providing a compelling answer to a given question. Particularly when the epistemology grounding moves away from an inherentfavoring of law-like generalizations grounded in natural-science based models of social science, the questions which may seem relevant become more diverse and complex, span- ning issues that require an arrayof quantitative and qualitative methods. Pragmatists would focus on utilizing the best and most appropriatetool or method for providing a compelling and reliable answer to a given question. 4a. A GAS Approach. Weick's (1979) GAS (Gen- eral, Accurate, Simple) model is perhaps the most compelling description of different modes of research-both quantitative and qualitative-because it makes explicit the trade-offs and limitations of using any approach and doesn't create an epistemological hierarchy among them. Weick argues that all methods fall somewhere on the spectrum of these three guides-he uses a clock on which general, accurate, and simple are situated equidistant from each other. This in turn, helps to sort out the relative strengths and limitations of a given approach, while also enhancing the ability of researchers to ascertain how ap- propriate a given method is to address a particularques- tion. 4b. Research Standards. unlike those concerned by the influence of anti-positivism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="263" class="deo:Reference">Donaldson 1992</xref>) and its alleged "any account is as good as the next" relativism, pragmatism doesn't entail that researchersdrop standards of scholarly rigor nor that they cease utilizing different standards which are relevant to the different modes of inquiry. There is still a place for rigor, thoroughness, detail, careful argumentation as well as normative criteria (e.g., is this a useful way to talk about organizations?) to help guide and evaluate research. There is also room for imagination and creativity, but it is legitimate to expect detail and rigor in scholarly work when assessing its con- tribution (e.g., how useful or appropriateare various metaphors when researcherstalk about using them in specific contexts?). Acknowledging that all scientific studies are paradigm-dependent and emerge out of particular ways<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> of looking at the world does not mean that social scientists should stop using control groups, double-blind studies, regression analyses, and other techniques that are associated with good social scientific research. While pragmatists reject an essential and fundamental distinction between objective and subjective, they can accept for pragmatic reasons, that there are differences between facts and values and different methods of inquiry appro- priate to each. This is not because facts are value-free and "objective," or that this distinction needs to be maintained to avoid committing the "naturalistic fallacy" objection of inferring an "ought" from an "is" (Donaldson and Dunfee 1994). Rather, differences in the mode and pattern of discourse make direct inferences across these two areas not particularlyuseful. That is, when scholars try to create generalizable statements about the world as seen by a community of persons, they utilize methods suited to that task and they are usually not particularlyuseful or directly applicable-by themselves-for drawing ethical inferences (and vice versa). However, paragraph4d highlights some innovative ways in which the two can be more closely connected. 4c. Reinforcing the Importance of Concepts and Assumptions. Recognizing that scientific studies don't provide access to Truth and that they have other limitations, reminds scholars that other types of questions are important to raise-particularly about the significance of the assumptions made, the categories used, and their implications. Creating this new epistemological framework makes it easier to raise nonquantitative questions (because science is no longer epistemologically privileged) and to use both ethics and humanities based approaches to address them. 4d. Moving Toward a Closer Linking of Normative and Empirical. There are some promising approaches to research, particularly recently, illustrating how normative and empirical discourse can be more directly and consciously interconnected. One promising avenue of research is Donaldson and Dunfee's (1994, p. 254) Integrative Social Contracts Theory (ISCT), in which they place the normative and empirical in "symbiotic har- mony." They adapt social contract thinking to the study of business ethics and develop a model in which different communities (particularly individual business organizations, but also industries and countries) develop basic norms relevant to their interactions (e.g., what objectives the firm pursues, how people are treated within the firm, etc.). The symbiosis comes from requiring that any proposed norms for the group emerge from the distinctive values and practices of persons in that community (e.g., empirically established cultural values; patterns of business interaction, friendship, gift giving; negotiation practices). These values and practices are then, in turn, used<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> to establish the norms which should govern their shared activities. Donaldson and Dunfee require that all such norms be scrutinized for legitimacy (e.g., through consis- tency with hypernorms and macrosocial contracts, by assessing their authenticity) so that the "is"-while important and foundational-doesn't end up being the complete and sole basis for creating the "ought"(1994, p. 259,262- 263). While ISCT provides an interesting and specific case, there are other ways in which normative and empirical can meaningfully interact symbiotically. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Weaver and Trevino (1994)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="272" class="deo:Reference">Victor and Stephens (1994)</xref> both ad- vocate interactive relationships between normative and empirical inquiry. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="273" class="deo:Reference">Weaver and Trevino (1994)</xref> provide an overview of what constitutes a symbiotic interaction and offer some supporting examples. Such a relationship involves some form of collaboration and interaction between normative and empirical without requiring that there be a merging of theoretical principles, methodologies, and metatheoretical assumptions (1994, p. 132- 133). Both take cues from the other on such matters as the delineation of research agendas and the applicability of theory. Symbiosis may even involve direct coordina- tion across normative and empirical to address different dimensions of a common problem. As Victor and Stephens (1994, p. 148) suggest, facts are not value- neutral, and values are empirically based. Symbiosis is especially important because it is a method of ensuring that good (i.e., useful) research occurs across both dimensions, that the underlying premises and implications of empirical work be normatively sound, and that the empirical grounding and relevance of normative research is also established. However, more elaborate linkage of normative and empirical work is possible, namely theoretical integration: "proactively creating a new breed of theory by consciously commingling the cores of the two disciplines" (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="274" class="deo:Reference">Weaver and Trevino 1994</xref>, p. 135-136). In short, such work develops both evaluative claims and categories within empirical work and press forcefully against the idea of there being a distinction between normative and empirical claims. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="275" class="deo:Reference">Weaver and Trevino (1994)</xref> cite three distinct ways of achieving this theoretical integration: conceptual importation, which involves one field using concepts derived from the other in its theoretical foundations; theoretical reciprocity, in which a theory that has both normative and empirical dimensions requires both normative and empirical support to establish its legitimacy (e.g., as found in Kohlberg and Gilligan); and theoretical unity, where researchersreject any significant distinction between normative and empirical on methodological and metatheoreticalgrounds (e.g., Burrell<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="281" class="deo:Reference">Morgan, 1979</xref>). The first two forms of integration are promising, while this paper has maintained that the last position may go too far and oversimplify some of the methodological and discursive difficulties of merging normative and empirical found in the theoretical unity position. The pragmatist critique offered in this paper-both in its rejection of the positivist vs. anti-positivist debate and in its attention on the moral dimensions of research- provides a detailed rationale for researchers to reject the separate but (un)equal view of normative and empirical research (what Weaver and Trevino (1994, p. 130) call "parallelism") and to work systematically for, at a mini- mum, various forms of symbiosis. Beyond this basic threshold, it does not follow that greater levels of interaction would correspondingly have greatervalue (i.e., integration is to be preferred to symbiosis, higher levels of integration are to be preferred to lower levels, etc.). Indeed, consistent with a pragmatist view, such questions are best answered in the context of what researchers de- cide are good questions. That is, does fundamental conceptual and methodological interaction help to better address these questions? It is by answering this question that scholars can discern what levels of interaction are to be preferred. 5. Direct Linkage of Ethics and Mainstream Management Literature. The pragmatic criterion of value provides the fundamental link between the two camps. It reminds management scholars that the driving force behind their work has an inherently moral quality which must be identified and discussed. It reminds ethicists that the methods and insights of management researchershave an established value to improve our lives, specifically to better understand business activities and offer guidance as to how to make business better serve human purposes. The newly created epistemological context also indicates that both parties need each other-their wisdom, insights, methodological capabilities-to address salient research questions. Business ethics is primarily about how to understand and conceptualize business activity-searching for better and more defensible ways of doing this-rather than an external critique of business. If researchersbegin with this understandingof business ethics, then their work will be enriched substantially from systematic involve- ment with management (including empirical) research.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="230">134</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="231">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="232">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="233">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx243">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_014.image_15.png" thmb="62is.page_014.image_15-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="251">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="252">135</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="253">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="254">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx262">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_015.image_16.png" thmb="62is.page_015.image_16-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="265">136</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="266">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="267">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="268">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx270">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_016.image_17.png" thmb="62is.page_016.image_17-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="277">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="278">137</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="279">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="280">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="283" page="17" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="286" page="17" column="1">This paper provides a beginning to an important and ex- citing challenge for organization studies. If researchers are to get past the debilitating effects of the positivism versus anti-positivism debate and find meaningful ways <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> of incorporating ethics and the humanities into mainstream management research, then something like pragmatic experimentation is required. To that end this paper indicates why such a change is needed and specifies how this change might provide a constructive and preferred alternative. This was accomplished by outlining the basic characteristics of pragmatic experimentation, indicating how a particularstream of research could be reshaped to embody this approach, and identifying a number of specific directives for how research in organization studies ought to proceed. While the authors' recommendations pose some daunting challenges for scholars in organization studies, it is equally demanding of ethicists: both must find ways to reconceptualize inquiry and find integrative and complex ways to think about business. There may be substantial obstacles to this agenda, but if our basic argument is sound, then overcoming them would appear to be a necessary part of a commitment to pro- ducing good research.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx285">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_017.image_18.png" thmb="62is.page_017.image_18-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="287" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Acknowledgment The authors would like to thank Bart Victor, three anonymous review- ers, Steve Layman, and Amy Wicks for their efforts to help improve this paper.</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="290" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Endnotes 'Deconstructionism falls under the broad heading of anti-positivism precisely because it shares the same basic inversion of epistemic privilege and the endless proliferation of narratives. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="288" class="deo:Reference">Martin (1990)</xref> defines it, deconstructionism is an "analytic strategy that exposes, in a systematic way, multiple ways a text can be interpreted."It is used to help unmask dominant ideologies, power structures, and forms of op- pression which are masked within ordinary forms of discourse. Deconstructionism helps create room for multiple interpretations and alternative descriptions, yet it too suffers from an internal inability to get beyond exposing the subjectivity and partiality of different points of view. 2There is an analogous problem with deconstructionism. As a tool in the service of advancing a particularcriterion of value (e.g., feminism), deconstructionism is useful for highlighting potential meanings within a given text that the author wants to challenge (e.g., hidden or masked forms of misogyny). However, the only way that deconstructionists are able to criticize the exposed ideology as flawed or problematic is by appealing to some external criterion of value-not by relying on deconstructionism (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="289" class="deo:Reference">Martin 1990</xref>, 341 uses feminism). Indeed, Martin is well aware of the fact that deconstructionism could be turned on her text to expose the ideology it contains, thus continuing a potentially endless, and ultimately pointless, process (1990, 341). Without resort to a set of values (which lie outside of decontructionism), the process of deconstruction is empty and meaningless.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="291" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="292" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Anderson, J., M. Rungtusanatham,and R. Schroeder (1994), "A Theory of Quality Management Underlying the Deming Management Method," Academy of Management Review, 19, 472-509.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="297" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Arrow, K. (1974), The Limits of Organization, 1st ed., New York: Norton.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="298" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Astley, G. (1985), "Administrative Science as Socially Constructed Truth,"Administrative Science Quarterly, 30, 497-513. and R. Zammuto (1992), "Organization Science, Managers, and Language Games," Organization Science, 3, 443-460.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="299" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Beach, L. R. (1990), Image Theory: Decision Making in Personal and Organization Contexts, New York: Wiley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="300" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bettis, R. (1990), "Strategic Management and The Straightjacket:An Editorial Essay," Organization Science, 2, 315-319.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="301" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bird, F. and J. Waters (1989), "The Moral Muteness of Managers," California Management Review, 32, 73-87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="302" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bowie, N. (1994), "A Kantian Theory of Capitalism," presented at the 1994 Ruffin Lectures at the Darden School, University of Virginia. and R. Freeman (1992), Ethics and Agency Theory, New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="303" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Burrell, G. and G. Morgan (1979), Sociological Paradigms and Organizational Analysis, London, UK: Heinemann.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="304" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Caeldries, F. (1993), "On the Sustainability of the Capitalist Order: Schumpeter's Capitalism, Socialism and Democracy Revisited," The Journal of Socio-Economics, 22, 163-185.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="305" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Cotton, J., D. Vollrath, K. Froggatt, J. Lengnick-Hall and K. Jennings (1988), "Employee Participation: Diverse Forms and Different Outcomes," Academy of Management Review, 13, 8-22. and (1990), "Fact: The Form of Participation Does Matter-A Rebuttal to Leana, Locke, and Schweiger," Academy of Management Review, 15, 147-153.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="306" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Daft, R. (1983), "Learning The Craft of Organizational Research," Academy of Management Review, 8, 539-546. and A. Lewin (1990), "Can Organization Studies Begin To Break Out of The Normal Science Straitjacket? An Editorial Essay," Organization Science, 1, 1-9.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="307" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Davidson, D. (1984), Inquiries Into Truth and Interpretation, New York: Oxford University Press. (1990), Essays on Actions and Events, New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="308" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Davis, S. (1984), Managing Corporate Culture, Cambridge, MA: Bal- linger.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="309" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Dees, G. (1992), "Principals,Agents, and Ethics," in Ethics andAgency Theory, N. Bowie and R. Freeman (Eds.), New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="310" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Deetz, S. (1996), "Describing Differences in Approaches to Organization Science: Rethinking Burrell and Morgan and Their Legacy," Organization Science, 7, 191-207.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="311" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">De George, R. (1993), Competing WithIntegrity in International Business, New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="312" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Deming, W. E. (1994), The New Economics, 2nd ed., Cambridge, MA: MIT Center for Advanced Engineering Study.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="313" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Dewey, J. (1988), The Middle Works of John Dewey, Carbondale, IL: SIU Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="314" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Donaldson, L. (1992), "The Weick Stuff: Managing Beyond Games," Organization Science, 3, 461-466.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="315" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Donaldson, T. (1989), The Ethics of International Business, New York: Oxford University Press. and T. Dunfee (1994), "Toward a Unified Conception of Business</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="317" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Ethics: Integrative Social Contracts Theory," Academy of Management Review, 19, 252-284. and L. Preston (1994), "The Stakeholder Theory of The Corpo-</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="318" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">ration: Concepts, Evidence, and Implications," Academy of Management Review, 20, 65-91.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="319" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Eastman, W. and J. Bailey (1994), "Examining the Origins of Management Theory: Value Divisions in the Positivist Program," Journal of Applied Behavioral Science, 30, 313-328.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="320" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Evan, W. and R. E. Freeman (1983), "A Stakeholder Theory of the Modem Corporation: Kantian Capitalism," in T. Beauchamp and N. Bowie (Eds.) Ethical Theory and Business, 75-93, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="321" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Etzioni, A. (1988), The Moral Dimension: Toward a New Economics, New York: The Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="322" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Flew, A. (1979), A Dictionary of Philosophy, 2nd ed., New York: St. Martin's Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="323" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Frank, R. (1988), Passions WithinReason: The Strategic Role of Emo- tions, New York: Norton.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="324" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Freeman, R. (1994), "The Politics of Stakeholder Theory: Some Future Directions," Business Ethics Quarterly, 4, 409-422. and D. Gilbert, Jr. (1988), Corporate Strategy and The Search for Ethics, Engelwood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall. , and E. Hartman (1988), "Values and The Foundations of Strategic Management," Journal of Business Ethics, 7, 821-834.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="325" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Frost, P., L. Moore, M. Louis, L. Lundberg, and J. Martin (Eds.) (1991), Reframing Organizational Culture, Newbury Park, CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="326" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Fukuyama, F. (1995), Trust: The Social Virtues and The Creation of Prosperity, New York: The Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="327" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Ghoshal, S. and P. Moran (1996), "Bad for Practice: A Critique of the Transaction Cost Theory," Academy of Management Review, 21, 13-47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="328" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Gilbert, D., Jr. (1992), The Twilight of Corporate Strategy, New York: Oxford University Press. (1996), "The Prisoner's Dilemma and the Prisoners of the Prisoner's Dilemma," Business Ethics Quarterly, 6, 165-178.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="329" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Gini, A. R. and T. Sullivan (1987), "Work: The Process and The Per- son," Journal of Business Ethics, 6, 649-655.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="330" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Hambrick, D. (1994), "1993 Presidential Address: What if The Academy Actually Mattered?"Academy of Management Review, 19, 11-16.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="331" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Jones, T. (1995), "Instrumental Stakeholder Theory: A Synthesis of Ethics and Economics," Academy of Management Review, 20, 404-437.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="332" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Kuhn, T. (1970), The Structure of Scientific Revolutions, 2nd ed., Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="333" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Lane, L. (1986), "Karl Weick's Organizing: The Problem of Purpose and The Search for Excellence," Administration and Society, 18, 111-135.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="334" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Leana, C., E. Locke, and D. Schweiger (1990), "Fact and Fiction in Analyzing Research on Participative Decision Making: A Critique of Cotton, Vollrath, Froggatt, Lengnick-Hall, and Jennings," Academy of Management Review, 19, 137-146.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="335" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Lee, T. W. and T. Mitchell (1994), "An Alternative Approach: The Unfolding Model of Voluntary Employee Turnover,"Academy of Management Review, 19, 51-89. L. Wise and S. Fireman (1996), "An Unfolding Model of Voluntary Employee Turnover,"Academy of Management Journal, 1, 5-36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="340" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Martin, J. (1990), "Deconstructing Organizational Taboos: The Sup- pression of Gender Conflict in Organizations," Organization Science, 1, 339-359. (1992), Cultures in Organizations, New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="341" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">McCloskey, D. (1990), If You're So Smart: The Narrative of Economic Expertise, Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="342" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Mintzberg, H. (1994), The Rise and Fall of Strategic Planning, New York: The Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="343" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Morgan, G. (ed) (1980), "Paradigms, Metaphors, and Puzzle Solving in Organization Theory," Administrative Science Quarterly, 25, 605-622. (ed.) (1983), Beyond Method: Strategies for Social Research, Beverly Hills, CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="344" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Noreen, E. (1988), "The Economics of Ethics: A New Perspective on Agency Theory," Accounting, Organizations and Society, 13, 359-369.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="345" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Paine, L. S. (1994), "Managing for Organizational Integrity,"Harvard Business Review, 2, 106-117.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="346" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Pfeffer, J. (1993), "Barriersto The Advance of Organization Science: Paradigm Development as a Dependent Variable," Academy of Management Review, 18, 599-620. (1994), Competitive Advantage Through People, Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="347" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Rorty, Richard (1985), "Texts and Lumps," New Literary History, 17, 1-15. (1988), "The Priority of Democracy to Philosophy," The Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom: Its Evolution and Consequences in American History, M. D. Peterson and R. C. Vaughan (Eds.), Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press. (1989), Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity, New York: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="348" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Schneider, B. (ed.) (1990), Organizational Climate and Culture, San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="349" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Sen, A. (1987), On Ethics and Economics, New York: Basil Blackwell.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="350" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">Accepted by Bart Victor; received October 1995. This paper has been with the author for two revisions.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="352" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Sitkin, S., K. Sutcliffe, and R. Schroeder (1994), "Distinguishing Con- trol From Learning in Total Quality Management: A Contingency Perspective," Academy of Management Review, 19, 537-564.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="353" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Smith, A. (1981), The Wealth of Nations, R. H. Campbell and A. S. Skinner (eds.), Oxford, U.K.: Oxford University Press (reprinted Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Classics).</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="354" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Solomon, R. (1992), Ethics and Excellence, New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="355" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Victor, B. and C. Stephens (1994), "Business Ethics: A Synthesis of Normative Philosophy and Empirical Social Science," Business Ethics Quarterly, 4, 145-156.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="356" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Wagner, J. (1994), "Participation's Effects on Performance and Satis- faction: A Reconsideration of Research Evidence," Academy of Management Review, 19, 312-330.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="357" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Weaver, G. and L. Trevino (1994), "Normative and Empirical Business Ethics," Business Ethics Quarterly, 4, 129-144.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="358" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Weick, K. (1979), The Social Psychology of Organizing, 2nd ed., New York: McGraw Hill. (1989), "Organized Improvisation: 20 Years of Organizing," Communication Studies, 40, 241-248. (1993), "The Collapse of Sensemaking in Organizations: The Mann Gulch Disaster," Administrative Science Quarterly, 38, 628-652.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="359" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Werhane, P. (1985), Persons, Rights, and Corporations, Engelwood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall. (1991), Adam Smith and His Legacy for Modern Capitalism, New York: Oxford Univ. Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="360" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Wicks, A., D. Gilbert, Jr. and R. Freeman (1994), "A Feminist Rein- terpretation of The Stakeholder Concept," Business Ethics Quarterly, 4, 475-499.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="361" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Williamson, 0. (1975), Markets and Hierarchies, New York: The Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="362" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Zald, M. (1993), "Organization Studies as a Scientific and Humanistic Enterprise: Toward a Reconceptualization of The Foundations of The Field," Organization Science, 4, 513-528.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="293" page="17" column="2">138</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="294" page="17" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/VOl. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="295" page="17" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="296" page="18" column="1">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx316">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_018.image_19.png" thmb="62is.page_018.image_19-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="336" page="18" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="337" page="18" column="2">139</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="338" page="18" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="339" page="19" column="1">ANDREW C. WICKS AND R. EDWARD FREEMAN Organization Studies and the New Pragmatism</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx351">
          <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62is.page_019.image_20.png" thmb="62is.page_019.image_20-thumb.png"/>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="363" page="19" column="2">140</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="364" page="19" column="2">ORGANIZATION SCIENCE/Vol. 9, No. 2, March-April 1998</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="365" page="19" column="2">This content downloaded from 148.88.244.135 on Tue, 19 Nov 2013 11:04:33 AM All use subject to JSTOR Terms and Conditions</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
