<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>cc4f553be01de5ac215fa2ed97d0c8e3798bdb73ee18d018a3beeff72c11d9fb</job>
    <base_name>62jt</base_name>
    <doi confidence="possible" alt_doi="http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/074793602317355738">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0142-694x(91)90027-t</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="1">The myths of imagery 1</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="2">Terry Liddament, University of London,</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="3">Department of Design Studies, Goldsmiths College, New Cross, London SE14 6NW, UK</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="4">The imagist conception is It is generally taken as may develop a design materials from the mind’s models etc. which can then in turn be used to description is misleading imagery and design phenomena and also fails we disentangle these design activity which puts perception, sketching, perspective. k c 2000</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="5">Keywords: creativity;</outsider>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="6" confidence="possible">popularly linked to descriptions of designing. ‘seeing with the mind’s eye’. Thus, a designer through an iterative procedure; the imagistic eye form the basis for sketches, drawings, then feed back to furnish more images which can further develop the design work. However, this in that it invites a comparison between which both mislocates the significance of these to give an insightful account of them. When misconceptions, we can construct a model of the notions of imagery, observation, drawing and modelling into a more illuminating Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved. design cognition; epistemology; perception</abstract>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">1999 and received positive reviews before we heard of the sudden in June 1999. He did not know of the paper’s acceptance, and was publication. With the permission of Terry’s widow, Ann, we have decided to</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="8">1 This paper was received in March, death of the author, Terry Liddament, not able to revise it for final publish the paper posthumously.</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="9">I</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="10">1 ‘Sketching and the psychology of design’, in</outsider>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="11">Arnheim</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="12">R V Margolin</name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="13">R Buchanan</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="14">(eds) The idea of design MIT Press, Cambridge MA pp 70– 74 (1996) 2 Goldschmidt, G ‘On visual design thinking’ Design Studies 15(2) (1994) pp 158–175 3 Design and Technology Working Group (UK) National curriculum: design and tech- nology Department of Education and Science, London (1988)</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="18" page="1" column="1">maging, imagery and the imagination enjoy a certain status among designers generally, and also among those who theorise design 1,2 . Designers presumably cultivate the faculty of ‘imaging’, but it is also referred to by those advocating design as a pedagogically valuable activity 3 where it is frequently viewed as a ‘distinctive aspect’ of the ‘creative thinking’ of designers, the development of which should be an ‘important aim’ of education, particularly in areas of the (school and university) curriculum such as design education. Discussions of imaging and imagery generally tend to go along with discussions of creativity and they are often thought of as, in some sense, mainsprings of insight and originality in design activity. Often characterised as kinds of ‘mental faculty’, they are typically linked to notions of intentionality; to ‘image’ or to ‘imagine’, is to actively engage this mental faculty in the creation of mental images of one kind or another. In designerly terms, such imagery is usually conceived of as being (primarily) visual which, upon being entertained in ‘the mind’s eye’, <marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> can be captured through conventional means such as sketching or drawing. This is typically thought of as a ‘dialectical process’ which is supposed to go on between the ‘mind’s eye’ and the activity of drawing, sketching, modelling etc. and which leads ultimately to a completed piece of design work. This dialectical process is between an activity ‘in’ the mind, which is ‘private’ to the individual and cannot itself be ‘directly’ observed by others, and the ‘public’ domain of the drawing etc. We have here as it were, a ‘picture’ of how it is that we operate with these phenomena and it is this picture that will be at the centre of the ensuing discussion; but it is, as we shall see, a picture which is largely mythical.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="16" page="1" column="1">589</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17" page="1" column="1">www.elsevier.com/locate/destud 0142-694X/00 $ - see front matter Design Studies 21 (2000) 589–606 PII: S0142-694X(00)00003-X © 2000 Elsevier Science Ltd All rights reserved Printed in Great Britain</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="19" page="2" column="1">1</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="20" page="2" column="1">Imagery: the research terrain</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="25" page="2" column="1">From a research perspective, the territory that is (roughly speaking) marked out by these notions is criss-crossed by different (and often differing) disci- plines, and it is as well to tread with care. The centre-ground tends to be occupied by experimental psychology, with the extremes of the territory bounded on the one hand by work in the fields of the cognitive sciences (merging into work in artificial intelligence) and on the other hand by work in the more speculative areas of philosophical psychology, epistemology, and metaphysics. Not surprisingly, such a broad terrain makes for ambiv- alences and ambiguities; work on ‘visual’ cognition, particularly towards the ‘hard’ end, in computation and artificial intelligence assimilates ‘imagery’ to perception and thence to problems in ‘modelling’ perception via vision systems in machines, while much work on visual cognition in cur- rent philosophy in this area focuses on attempts to explicate the key concepts of imaging, perception, and more generally, of cognition, shading off into wider topics in the philosophy of mind such as intentionality, consciousness and the will. <marker type="block"/> The main focus of this discussion is towards the latter end of this spectrum. Yet philosophy gets drawn into many of the issues of clarification and exposition that inevitably arise within the former, and I will occasionally need to make detours, as it were, since at least some of my remarks here will aim at drawing our attention to the need not only for a clear taxonomy (the terrain is particularly prone to category mistakes), but also to the need to separate conceptual from empirical modes of enquiry in order, partly at least, to get clear about just what kind of enquiry into ‘imaging’ and ‘imagery’ might be of interest to researchers into design theory. Although I will offer a specific set of remedies which will aim at clarification, my task, as I see it, will be largely to persuade us to avoid certain kinds of temptation which tend to arise when we try to address the issues under discussion and which, it must be said, are somewhat easy to fall prey to, all the more so since it is often, if not generally, not noticed that we are<marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="block"/> victims. These temptations are, as we shall see, in some ways rather natural, since they are lent support by the ‘picture’ I remarked on above, of how these psychological ‘phenomena’ are to be described and explicated. But it is a picture which, as it were, ‘lies in our language’ 4 and which prevents us from attaining a clear view of them. It is this picture that I will be targeting in this discussion.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="23" page="2" column="1">590</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="24" page="2" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="26" page="3" column="1">2</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" page="3" column="1">Imagery: some distinctions</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="36" page="3" column="1">‘Imaging’, ‘imagining’, ‘picturing’, ‘seeing’, ‘looking’, ‘perceiving’, ‘observing’ and so on all form part of a larger ‘family’ of phenomena which, in one way or another, are typically conceived as ‘mental’. What is thought to mark off imagery from the others is its voluntary nature and its relatively untrammelled freedom in that we appear to be able, in the imagination, to both entertain and to mix ideas at will, although empiricists such as Locke 5 and Hume 6 claimed that such ‘freedom’ was apparent rather than real. In their view, perception was a process which was largely passive and from which all knowledge of the world was ultimately derived. Imag- ing could only be accomplished from ‘mental’ resources which were themselves derived from perception. Thus imagery could in itself lead to no ‘new’ knowledge. Given the empiricist’s view of what ‘perception’ consists in, it is not surprising that they should have come up with this rather restrictive view of the operation of the faculty of imagination, and it is one that we will need to challenge later. <marker type="block"/> 2. 1 Imagery and the mental Imagery is generally thought of as a conjuring up of various impressions ‘in the mind’, which may be ‘visual’, although this need not be the case. (For example, mental images might be auditory, olfactory, verbal, or tex- tual, or of a musical score, etc.) Indeed, the idea that ‘imagination’ is restricted to visualisation is a misnomer since, for example, hearing also evidently has connections with the imagination as well as (although perhaps to a lesser extent) other senses such as the olfactory and tactile, while imaging the ‘Grace of God’, or ‘Socrates’ last thoughts’ doesn’t obviously rely on ‘sensory’ images of any kind. Thus the concept of ‘imagery’ covers a wider field than that of the merely visual, or indeed the merely sensory.<marker type="block"/> In contrast to perception, conceived as passive or receptive, the voluntary aspect of imagery emphasises it as a ‘doing’ and links it to creativity. But such distinctions between imaging and seeing or perceiving, are not always as clear cut as might be imagined. ‘Seeing’, for example, as the early empiricists stressed, implies a certain passivity it’s true, but ‘looking’ on the other hand involves an often quite strenuous activity, and to ‘perceive’<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> with shrewdness or insight, for example when looking (say) at the outcome of some experimental procedure, is often regarded as a highly ‘creative’ act. Such reflections prompt in us the idea that there may be significant connections between phenomena such as imagining and perceiving. Indeed there are, but they do not by any means conform to the Lockean and Humean notions alluded to above. As we’ll see, the ‘tie-up’ between them consists neither in relative degrees of vivacity, nor in similarity 7 .<marker type="block"/> This indicates that possible difficulties in distinguishing between imagery and perception may have some connection with the appropriate application of these concepts, and we’ll see too, that there is some truth in this. But of course, we can normally distinguish between imaging and perception. If someone were to claim that, for example, they weren’t sure whether they were seeing their friend over there, or having an ‘image’, we would either suppose they meant that they might have fancied they saw their friend but weren’t certain, or really be quite mystified, since we would say that under normal circumstances at least, one can have no difficulty in distinguishing one’s ‘imaging’ from one’s ‘fancying’ or perception or, (in such a case) misperception (Wittgenstein 7 § 634). One cannot wonder whether one is having an image; the possibility of such confusion doesn’t arise here. Also, the fact that ‘imaging’ seems so clearly a voluntary act, must mean that (unlike perceptions) they do not inform us about reality, or not in any direct perceptual sense. 2. 3 Reporting on imagery First-person reports of ‘imagings’ are normally accepted as decisive evi- dence, to third parties, of the possession of such images, whereas first person reports of perceptions are often subject to a host of qualifying criteria that simply wouldn’t apply in the case of imagery. That is, when comparing perceptions, either one’s own, or with those of others, we normally refer to the seen object. This is the common basis of such comparisons; but what is the criterion for ‘sameness of image’? Well, in your case, for me, it’s what you say concerning your images; but for you yourself? Here, it’s very tempting to think of one casting a ‘mental eye’ over one’s ‘images’ as it were. But this treads the brink of regress and incoherence since it implies the existence of an ‘inner eye’ checking the contents of an ‘inner eye’! This ought to make us suspicious; the criteria of ‘same’ in the case of perception seem to be lacking in the case of imaging (Wittgenstein 4 , § 377–8). These differences of treatment in terms of ident- ifying criteria indicate important distinctions in the application of the concepts of perceiving and imaging, and we need to bear such differences in mind.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="30" page="3" column="1">2. 2 Imagery and perception</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="31" page="3" column="1">4 Wittgenstein, L Philosophical investigations Blackwell, London (1953) 5 Locke, J An essay concerning human understanding Fon- tana Books, London pp 233–238 (1967 edn) 6 Hume, D Enquiries concerning human understanding Oxford University Press, Oxford pp 17– 19 (1969 edn)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="33" page="3" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="34" page="3" column="1">591</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="37" page="4" column="1">7 Wittgenstein, L Zettel Blackwell, London (1967)</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="38" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Again, ‘images’ are sometimes likened to perceptions in that both can be</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="39" page="4" column="1">592</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="40" page="4" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" page="5" column="1">seen as a kind of ‘inner picture’. Here, one is tempted to think of perceiving as having a visual image which one has in one as it were. But let’s consider this more carefully; actual pictures can be checked against reality, and such comparisons are often (or can be) the yardstick of their appropriateness. Likewise, if we want to check on what we’ve seen, we can look again; this is generally what ‘comparison’ means in the case of perceptions or ‘visual impressions’. We also have a use for expressions making comparisons of the imagined with the real, e.g. ‘When I met her she was not at all as I had imagined’. But note what import checking, comparing etc. have here though; we can be puzzled (by a picture, as by a visual impression) and maybe even, not recognise what we see, at least not straight off, and this makes us look again. Of course, we might be tempted to say that in doing this we are ‘checking’ an ‘inner picture’ against ‘outer criteria’. But even if we could give a clear sense to that notion, none of this could intelligibly be applied to one’s images. We can neither be puzzled nor surprised by them; it is part of the employment of the whole panoply of ‘mental imagery’ that surprise, puzzlement and so on do not find their expression in this way at all. If we are surprised in the case of imagery– reality comparisons it is merely with respect to the way that ‘reality’ turns out, not with respect to the content of any images we might have had. The criteria normally associated with visual phenomena such as perception seem to get no grip in the case of imagery. The notion of an ‘inner picture’ is in any case misleading and ought to make us suspicious; indeed, it is a notion that can lead to intractable difficulties, as I will now show.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="42" page="5" column="1">3</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="43" page="5" column="1">Imagery and the ‘mind’s eye’</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" page="5" column="1">What emerges thus far, is that we do indeed have a role for concepts such as ‘imagery’, ‘imaging’ and so on, and can distinguish between them and other concepts such as perception. The role that imagery plays, together with its distinguishing features, is readily noted in terms of its differing uses, a difference which manifests itself most clearly in the different forms of expression we employ with respect to them. Yet it is when we try to explicate or clarify these concepts, that we start to stumble. As I remarked earlier, the ‘picture’ which is supposed to explicate them and illuminate their application is at fault. To begin with, it relegates imagery and other mental items to a domain which is essentially private and not ‘directly’ accessible to others. <marker type="block"/> The attempt to apply this picture leads to confusion and mystification. Let’s take a closer look: according to it, I ‘call up’, or ‘bring before me’ a mental image, let us say of a room—we’ll call it the ‘image-room’ (Wittgenstein 4 , § 398–400). The ‘image-room’ is something you or I ‘have’; but of course, I can’t see your image nor you mine. According to this picture, we each<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="block"/> have these images, but they are private to us. But might my ‘image-room’ correspond, as it were, to a sketch I have before me, of the room on paper? Let us suppose that I make the sketch according to my ‘image-room’. Here, the picture tempts us to think in terms of a method of projection according to which the mental image and the sketch are related; the sketch represents the image. Now, think of where, in actual cases, such a notion of ‘projection’ is employed; perhaps between objects on a drawing, in order to construct different views, as in orthographic projection. Or again, perhaps in the development of a model or mock-up from a drawing; here, the model can be though of as a projection too.<marker type="block"/> Now try to apply this to the ‘image room’ case; here, the picture tells us that the projection goes from one to the other, from ‘image-room’ to sketch. Now, isn’t this as if we each had a portfolio of ‘images’, but only we can see into this portfolio; no-one can look into anyone else’s portfolio. I only get to know your ‘image-room’ indirectly (if at all) via your description of it, your sketch, or words etc. and vice versa. But now, suppose the expression ‘my image-room’ is to be used in terms of this picture—how could it actually ever name anything? For example, everybody’s portfolio might quite possibly have a different ‘image-room’ or even be completely empty—so the expression ‘my image-room’ could name anything—or nothing!!<marker type="block"/> Consider in particular, what implications this has for the notion of ‘projection’ here: the situation is like this; we might each agree that a sketch we have before us accords with our own ‘private’ image, but in fact (and of course unbeknown to each other—essentially so) be employing very different modes of ‘projection’. That is, if we assume that the grammar of an expression such as ‘my image’ is cashed out in terms of its designating an essentially private object, then this ‘object’ simply drops out of consideration; it becomes irrelevant. Another way of putting this would be to say that the completely private ‘thing’ to which the expression supposedly refers couldn’t actually have a use in our (ordinary) language. We could only say of such a ‘thing’ that it’s a ‘something’ that s/he says s/he has, but it could, after all be an ‘anything’—we don’t know what, though! (Wittgenstein 4 , § 304).<marker type="block"/> What we should note here, is that no attempted ‘projection’ from a supposed domain of essentially private mental entities to the public and essentially shared domain of sketches, drawings, models etc can work, because any and every such possible ‘projection’ will suffice. The notion of a ‘projection’ becomes vacuous; the ‘projection’ never in fact reaches from the one domain to the other; it always falls short, ‘hangs in the air’ as it were,<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/> since the ‘institution that gives it its use (i.e. its publicly accessible shared use) is lacking.’ (Wittgenstein 4 , § 380) The picture that ‘forces itself on us here’ (Wittgenstein 4 , § 305) does no work, it fails to explicate our intuitions. If mental imagery, or indeed any kind of mental phenomenon is construed as an essentially private entity, then this is tantamount to slap- ping a label ‘unusable’ on it. In general, if ‘x’ is a projection of ‘y’, or any kind of representation of ‘y’ then ‘y’ must in some sense belong to a domain we can all share. We could say that what we need in other words, is another way of unpacking the logic of ‘inner’ with respect to mental items such as ‘image-rooms’. What this other way might be is something I’ll come to presently.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="46" page="5" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="47" page="5" column="1">593</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="52" page="6" column="1">594</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="53" page="6" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="55" page="7" column="1">4</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="56" page="7" column="1">Reductionism and mental imagery</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="64" page="7" column="1">But first, it might seem that a way out of this apparent impasse is to construe ‘mental’ items such as my ‘image-room’ as belonging to the same domain as sketches, models etc. Thus if ‘mental entities’ are construed as ‘brain-states’, they can be put on the same ‘level’ as other physical phenomena. This then makes it possible to think of them as ‘processes’ in the brain rather than as mysteriously unreachable mental entities. Such processes can then be investigated in terms of empirical physical sciences such as neurobiology. Of course, this physicalist research programme is well established 8 , resulting at one extreme in ‘hard line’ approaches such as eliminativism 9 which seeks the complete replacement of mentalistic concepts with the categories of a mature or ‘final’ science of neurobiology. More commonly, the aim of eliminativism is to show that the mental is, though not strictly eliminable in terms of physicalist categories, neverthe- less supervenient on them in the strict sense that if all physical phenomena were to be ‘removed’ from the universe, there would be nothing left over— no ‘mental states’. <marker type="block"/> This may look suspiciously like behaviourism, a doctrine popular earlier on in the 20th century 10 . Indeed, it has similarities with behaviourism; but with eliminativism, the ‘commonsense’ psychological concepts of our everyday language, sometimes referred to as ‘folk psychology’ 11 , will be, rather than ignored (as with behaviourism) replaced by a completed science (e.g. of neurobiology). The presupposition is that these everyday psychological concepts amount to a primitive ‘theory’ which is at the least inad- equate and quite possibly incoherent, thus must be replaced. But it isn’t at all clear that our everyday psychological concepts do constitute any such theory; indeed, there are good reasons for seriously doubting this. The basic reason for this is that a theory is, typically, an interpretative framework. But in third-person contexts qua psychological states, although one may sometimes surmise or infer someone else’s pains or sadness, for<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> example on the basis of their behaviour, one generally makes no such inferences; one’s grasp of other people’s psychological states is not based on any kind of interpretative theory. In normal cases you see the suffering or the fury or the delight of another as plainly as if it were in your own breast (Wittgenstein 7 , p 220). And in first-person contexts, it makes no sense to suppose that I either surmise or infer that I am (say) in pain, or sad. I simply am in pain or sad, and I make no such inferences or interpretations. Neither first-person nor third-person employment of psychological concepts rests on a basis of interpretation, thus cannot constitute a theoretical framework of any kind. And if ‘folk psychology’ isn’t a theory then it cannot credibly be held to be false or replaceable in the sense that eliminativism requires.<marker type="block"/> The physicalist theoretical framework is by definition geared to explain those everyday observables such as ‘water’ etc. and it does this by postulat- ing a ‘transperceptual’ (i.e. not observable) domain of theoretical entities and processes ‘in’ which such observables can take on a new and enhanced role. Thus, for example, our pre-theoretical concept ‘water’ may be extended by science so that we come to understand it as having the con- stituents hydrogen and oxygen whose combination can be explained by the concept of valency. It is an important fact that the theory here is accepted at least partly because it explains many of the physical properties and behaviour of water (such as incompressibility or evaporability) in terms of the theoretical entities (hydrogen, oxygen etc.) it introduces. Neurophysiol- ogy (or some future replacement science) similarly postulates a domain of theoretical entities (e.g. brain-states). But there is a lack of symmetry here; for on this physicalist model of explanation, the ‘ordinary’ counterparts of the theoretical entities (brainstates) are, in fact (roughly speaking) squishy (and in principle directly observable) bits of matter constituting the brain, not mental items such as imagery or other phenomenal qualities.<marker type="block"/> Another way of putting this is to say that theories of what items such as water ‘really’ are form part of an established and sophisticated explanatory network by means of which we can give an enriched and above all useful account of the role ‘water’ occupies in our lives. But knowing (what is undoubtedly the case) that mental states have in some sense an underlying substrate of ‘processes-in-the-brain’ we still ask: yes, but what role do mental phenomena actually play in our lives? Put briefly, we can point out that they play an essential role. It is a condition of being human that we exist in the ‘epistemic space’ of conscious states, and these states are (epistemically) quite distinct from ‘brain-states’, whatever the latter may be. this being so we must reject the eliminativism and reductionism that physicalism entails.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="58" page="7" column="1">8 Dennett, D Consciousness explained Penguin Books, London (1994) 9 Churchland, P M Matter and consciousness MIT Press, Cambridge MA (1988) 10 Skinner, B F Beyond freedom and dignity Peregrine Books, London (1971) 11 Greenwood, J D (ed) The future of folk psychology Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (1991)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="60" page="7" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="61" page="7" column="1">595</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="65" page="8" column="1">596</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="66" page="8" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="67" page="9" column="1">5</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="68" page="9" column="1">Empiricism and mental imagery</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" page="9" column="1">Physicalist reduction is part of a wider empirical research programme into mental states such as imagery. However, empiricism enters this discussion in another significant way, via work in empirical psychology which among other things focuses on investigations of subjects’ abilities concerning the employment of mental imagery and in particular the ‘manipulation’ of mental images 12 . Now, this brings out another kind of problem, and it’s a methodological one; in starting from the ‘givenness’ of mental states, the basic assumptions about the nature of ‘inner’ experience, including the supposed facilities of ‘mental manipulation’ remain unexamined. That is, it is assumed that such ‘experience’ is taken as a datum against which a range of experimental procedures can be tested. But how valid is such an assumption? If we consider the experiments with subjects’ supposed powers to ‘rotate’ and otherwise ‘manipulate’ mental images, then what we should note is that if one talks here of ‘movements’ such as ‘rotating’ something in the ‘imagination’ or the ‘mind’s eye’ then one hasn’t as yet given a clear meaning to terms such as ‘rotating’ in such cases. For what kind of ‘doing’ is this? Well, if we are asked to rotate or by some means physically manipulate a physical object in a certain way and report on what we see, then we, and, importantly someone else, can also check on whether this has been carried out correctly, and can also check on the results; the possibility of the application of such criteria is constitutive of the notion of ‘rotation’ ‘manipulation’ and so on here. But since no such checking can occur in the ‘imagery’ case it is not clear what ‘rotating’ can actually mean; the concept ‘rotation’ and its cognates simply drops out of consideration; it has no clear application (Wittgenstein 7 , § 641–3). An empirical psychologist might counter this by claiming that a new use was hereby being introduced by these terms; we simply use them to ‘label’ our mental phenomena. But then, we would be back with our earlier problem; as we have seen, it is not at all clear how any intelligible use could be given for expressions supposedly referring to ‘inner’, essentially private mental items of the type assumed. <marker type="block"/> Thus, in the case of the experimental scenario enacted by empirical psychology in the investigation of mental phenomena such as ‘rotating images’ the wrong move has already been made, since the concept ‘to rotate’ is presupposed as having an unproblematic application in this scenario, whereas it is this application here which is the very point at issue. We could say: there is an experimental procedure here, but it makes no connection with the problem since method and problem pass one another by. In addition, such experimental ‘procedures’ appear to violate basic empiricist experimental tenets of repeatability and objectivity; it isn’t clear just what ‘repeatability’ can mean here since there seems no way of determining<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="block"/> what would constitute the ‘same’ in different cases, and the ‘results’ would also appear to be unavoidably subjective, based only on the reports of subjects and not amenable to any independent criteria of assessment.<marker type="block"/> The problem is not an empirical one; it just isn’t helpful to construe imaging, thinking etc. as internal ‘processes’ ‘in one’s head’. On this empirical model, ‘we have a definite concept of what it means to learn to know a process better’ (Wittgenstein 4 , § 308) and as I have already noted, we are thereby seduced into conflating a physical process (something in the brain, a ‘brain-state’) with an epistemic state (i.e. a state of consciousness). The explication of ‘imagination’ and its ‘mental’ cognates lies not in this direc- tion, however; they are not ‘objects’ with a place as such, in this particular empiricist ontological pantheon. Rather, they are important for the role they actually play in our conceptual framework; and to examine this role we need, not an empirical investigation into the ‘brain’ or some such action, but a conceptual investigation, which here means: we look at how such concepts are employed.<marker type="block"/> Ironically, there is some indirect empirical support for the view I am advocating at this point; one of the most interesting results of this approach as far as imagery is concerned is that it has brought out a hiatus concerning what subjects think they can ‘do’ with imaging. Although early work on this suggested that subjects appeared to be able to manipulate mental images with some facility 12 ] more recent studies have indicated that although subjects seemed to be able to ‘rotate’ and otherwise ‘manipulate’ certain kinds of ‘object’ via ‘mental images’ in some circumstances, other kinds of manipulation which seemed ostensibly no more difficult proved to be generally beyond their ‘imagistic’ powers[8]. Other related work has also indicated that the ‘visual’ aspect of mental imagery may not in fact be as ‘visual’ as is supposed 13 . Apart from my arguments here, these results also indicate the fallibility of our introspective claims regarding the phenomenalistic status our own mental states, particularly those to do with imaging and perception, and they underscore my contention that our problem with regard to research into imagery is partly at least a conceptual one which needs to be addressed first, if empirical research programmes in this domain are to be of any real use.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="70" page="9" column="1">12 Kosslyn, S M Image and mind Harvard University Press, Cambridge MA (1980)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="72" page="9" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="73" page="9" column="1">597</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="77" page="10" column="1">6</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="78" page="10" column="1">Rethinking imagery</h1>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="79" page="10" column="1">13 Finke, R A, Pinker, S and Farah, M ‘Reinterpreting visual patterns in mental imagery’ Cog- nitive Science 13 (1989) pp 51–78</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" page="10" column="1">We need to rethink the notions of imagery and imaging in order to develop them in more fruitful directions. To begin with, there can be no intelligible legislation for the use of signs which supposedly ‘refer’ to entities in an inner essentially private domain of the ‘mental’. To establish meanings for the use of language (signs) including e.g. ‘imaging’, ‘imagining’ and so <marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> forth, requires the establishment of techniques, ways of using such signs, together with the surroundings that would make them meaningful moves. Such techniques belong to the public domain of language use that we all share; and of course, we acquire those techniques gradually, by training, by education, from infancy, as we are inducted into the community of language-users. The acquisition of such techniques will also include, of course, those which allow us to talk eventually of ‘imagining’, or ‘imaging’ and a host of related ideas; but this does not mean that we can then use them to make public what, prior to this acquisition, was ‘private’. The very notion of ‘private’ to me is owed in this respect to the language we all share.<marker type="block"/> Secondly, language didn’t spring from a need to communicate an ‘inner something’; even though certain varieties of discourse such as those connected with imagery, imaging, the imagination and so on, do as it were, create the ‘logic space’ for talking of what is ‘in’ us, these forms of expression have to be learned, just like any others. And it is an important point that the paraphernalia of our mental lives are dependent upon the acquisition of not just one technique but many. We learn to talk, and in doing so we also learn to look, listen, attend, make observations, report, read, write, draw, imagine, pretend; and we also learn these, crucially, along with learning to stand, walk, run, balance, grasp, carry, find, hide, seek, chase, mime, play-act and so on. That is, we learn the techniques of language-use as embodied beings immersed in a host of physical activities intimately conjoined to the development and exercise of these techniques 14 . Thirdly, each of these techniques are interrelated; they have an indefinite number of interconnections. Roughly speaking, we learn them as a whole; one can only really significantly do any of these things if, no matter how primitively or schematically to start with, one has at least grasped the rudi- ments of most of them 15 . Such techniques interlock, and some of them build upon others. ‘Imagining’ etc. are forms of language-use that build on more primitive ones. Thus for example, if we are to teach someone to follow (understand) a story that begins: ‘Imagine that you are alone in the land of Oz and the Wicked Witch of the West is after you and you need to get to the Emerald City to find the Wizard...’ then we must first teach them more primitive, more basic forms of language-use. We could say: the imagined, the imaginary, is a domain we cannot enter until we have mastered a certain set of techniques; but these techniques themselves build upon others. Here, there are two key issues for understanding the function and role of imagery: the notion of a set of techniques the possession of which is a prerequisite for entry into a particular domain; and the notion that such techniques can ‘build’ upon more primitive or basic ones. We will examine these below.<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> 6. 1 Domains, pictures and imagery The notion of a domain that we can only enter by means of the acquisition of certain techniques is an important and useful one: we can illustrate it by means of the following: we might, for example, say that the picture is in its frame, the picture and frame are in my study. What is in the picture- frame is canvas, pigmented surface and so on; but what is in the picture, that is, what it pictures, brings us to the threshold of a domain we cannot enter unless we have grasped the concept of ‘picturing’, until we have understood the function of a picture as a representation device 16 . If we find this puzzling or surprising, then we should bear in mind that a picture bears much more resemblance to the other ordinary material objects that surround it than what it pictures. To be able to understand and use pictures we must first acquire the requisite techniques of usage and this we do partly by learning how to make pictures ourselves and also by attending to the many uses of pictures in our culture. The central point here, is that the capacity to see the content of pictures, what is ‘in’ them is a learned capacity, acquired, like other usages of symbols (and language more generally) through mastery of these techniques.<marker type="block"/> Similarly, we might say that the book is on the desk, and the desk is in my study; but what is in the book as an account, description, story etc. is not in the room. As with pictures, a consideration of what is in the book brings us to the threshold of a domain we cannot enter unless we have mastered certain techniques. Like the picture, the book cannot be entered into without the prior acquisition of the requisite techniques. In general we can state that the concept of ‘picturing’ may be applied to a wide range of representational devices, not only those of a visual kind such as pictures, diagrams, drawing, maps, graphs, models and so on but also those which communicate through the equally wide variety of notational symbols such as words, numbers and so on.<marker type="block"/> So much for the basic concept of ‘picturing’; I would emphasise that in what follows I will use the terms ‘picture’ or ‘picturing’ with the intention that these terms apply to this whole range of symbolisms, both visual and notational. Now, there are tie-ups between picturing, imaging, and imagining; for a start they share a common, more primitive substrate; that of being able to make observations, report and record in both verbal and written signs and symbols. As I have noted above, we acquire these techniques through a complex process of induction and enculturation into the society into which we are born, and we acquire them in a holistic way. In doing so, we gain entry to what we might call the primary conceptual field[15]. Mastery of this basic domain is a vital prerequisite to our entry<marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="block"/> into other domains; items in pictures or books may (although importantly, not necessarily) have their ‘originals’ in this domain.<marker type="block"/> The primitive techniques forming a substrate here function as a point-of- view making it possible to represent something. Indeed, they are the condition of being able to represent anything at all. We enter the primary conceptual field by mastering these techniques. What distinguishes these techniques from those of picturing or imaging, is that we can retreat from what is in pictures or books and contemplate the ‘originals’ which may have been used as ‘models’. But we cannot retreat in that sense from the primary field. However, as we’ll see, this distinction is important both to picturing and to imagery, and it forms the basis of much of their creative power. In order to illuminate these distinctions and also the tie-up between picturing and imagery, I will need to introduce three basic epistemological notions which are pivotal, both to understanding them, and to understanding the relationship between them. These are: epistemic transparency; epistemic stance; and epistemic metamorphism. I will explain each of these in turn.<marker type="block"/> 6. 2 Epistemic transparency In ideal conditions, say, we can regard the contents of reports (utterances in the presence of items etc.) in the primary conceptual field as typically reliable and accurate; we can call them informationally transparent in order to characterise this reliability. At a primitive stage of induction into our culture, i.e., as initiates or ab initio learners of such reporting techniques, we needn’t be aware of their representational function at all. We merely learn to use them reliably and this reliability is engendered, developed and refined through a gradual process of socially, culturally orientated con- ditioning and training.<marker type="block"/> But this does not capture the notion of transparency with respect to a picture’s picturing function; i.e., what is in the picture. For us to be able to see what is in the picture, it must become ‘transparent’ to us in a sense which transcends the transparency of the primary conceptual field. To do this one must grasp the use of the picture as a representational device, to be able to see what is in the picture, that is, what it pictures. In grasping this use of the picture, it becomes epistemically transparent and we have learned a new skill which is (logically) quite distinct from that of the ‘informationally reliable’ reportage of the primary conceptual field. This notion of epistemic transparency enables us to focus more explicitly on the distinction between items as they may appear in the primary conceptual field, and their possible counterparts as they may be represented in pictures. Note that these counterparts may not be literal representational<marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> ‘resemblances’ of their primary conceptual field originals at all; indeed, I think the distinction that this notion of epistemic transparency introduces here is fundamental for a more general appreciation of how it is possible for representation devices such as pictures and books to introduce and render intelligible symbolic, metaphoric modes of representation and also, vitally, the representation of items as fictional or imaginary.<marker type="block"/> 6. 3 Epistemic stance A picture must at least offer a (possible) point-of-view for it to function as a picture, if it doesn’t succeed in doing this then it fails as a picturing device. We can call this aspect of a picture’s functionality its epistemic stance. Now of course, some pictures may be set up to offer a completely unitary and unambiguous point-of-view; for example, an engineering drawing or a set of explicit written instructions. When we view such a picture it is intended (usually) that we only see it from one such possible point- of-view. But in order for a picture to function, it is not vital that it has a unitary epistemic stance as such. Indeed, many kinds of picture thrive on ambiguities; they offer the possibility of a diversity of points-of-view. Thus a viewer may contemplate the picture as representing different possibilities (differing points-of-view) and different viewers may also ‘see’ different things in the picture. Here we can see that there is thus a distinction to be made on the one hand between simply seeing the contents of a picture, and on the other, of grasping a potential multiplicity of ‘readings’ of the picture. In the latter case, we enter more fully into the representational subtleties of picturing. This kind of ‘ambiguity’, far from being an acciden- tal by-product of the techniques of picturing, has the potential to lead into entirely new domains; through this enhanced use of pictures we acquire the power to express what-might-be.<marker type="block"/> An important result of our acquiring the abilities to use picturing devices in these ways is that these techniques can in turn be focused back on the items in the primary conceptual field. What were, prior to the acquisition of the extended techniques of picturing, simply items to be reported on, can themselves become symbols representing something else, e.g. trees can represent knowledge, mountains can represent power and so on. There thus arises the possibility of a subtle interplay between ‘domains’ that the techniques of picturing allow, and which creates the possibility of an indefinite variety of modes of symbolisation using items both ‘in’ pictures and in the primary conceptual field as representational devices.<marker type="block"/> 6. 4 Epistemic metamorphism A potential multiplicity of points-of-view, offering the possibility of a multiplicity of epistemic stances leads to the possibility of growth points in<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> any picturing relation. What is pictured can lead to a new view precisely because of this possible multiplicity. We acquire the capacity to adopt differing epistemic stances as we learn the techniques of picturing; and this leads to what I will describe as epistemic metamorphism. This metamorphic property of picturing allows the possibility of seeing something entirely new ‘in’ the picture and through this we can develop the capacity both to ‘see’ and also to ‘reinterpret’ the picture in a potentially indefinite variety of ways. This is one of the most important features of picturing; in grasping this aspect of the use of pictures, we are able to employ the enormous inventive power that such techniques ultimately offer us. It is this power which lies at the heart of our usage of imagery and imagination. Epistemic metamorphism builds upon epistemic stance which in turn builds upon epistemic transparency. These, I suggest, are the fundamental epistemic factors and logical relationships extant in the employment of a wide variety of picturing devices; but only with them can we unlock what we think of as the power of the imagination.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="81" page="10" column="1">598</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="82" page="10" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="84" page="11" column="1">14 Johnson, M The body in the mind: the bodily basis of meaning, imagination and reason University of Chicago Press, Chicago IL (1987) 15 Sellars, W Empiricism and the philosophy of mind Harvard University Press, Cambridge MA (1997) (Originally published in Minnesota Studies in the Philosophy of Science Vol 1 (1956))</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="86" page="11" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="87" page="11" column="1">599</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="90" page="12" column="1">16 Aldrich, V ‘Mirrors pictures words perceptions’ Philosophy (1980) Vol 55(211)</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="92" page="12" column="1">600</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="93" page="12" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="98" page="13" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99" page="13" column="1">601</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="104" page="14" column="1">602</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="105" page="14" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="107" page="15" column="1">7</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="108" page="15" column="1">The tie-up between picturing and imagery</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" page="15" column="1">It should be clear that I am offering an explication of imagery and imaging etc. in terms of picturing; more precisely, in terms of the techniques, logical relationships and epistemological factors relating to picturing that I have been discussing. I cannot, for example, ‘imagine’ a move in chess or contemplate the possible outcomes of such a move if the game of chess does not exist; nor, vitally, can I do this without familiarity with the rules and moves of the game. Similarly, I cannot imagine a possible state of affairs, or contemplate possible changes in some domain without the resources of the representational techniques and picturing devices I have alluded to. Without these resources, there would be no possibility of our ‘imagining’ or ‘imaging’ anything. Indeed, I want to stress that, far from it being the case that such representational devices enable us to communicate our ‘imagery’ or other supposedly ‘inner’ phenomena, it seems evident to me that the situation is the other way round; the employment of imagery is itself parasitic upon the prior acquisition of these techniques. This offers us the opportunity to consider some useful results from this enquiry so far. <marker type="block"/> Firstly, it is not unhelpful to think of ourselves as ‘picturing devices’; that is, in acquiring the resources of language apposite to ‘imagination-talk’ or imagery, we are tacitly applying the techniques of ‘picturing’ to ourselves, which is to say that we can, in certain cases, use the techniques of picturing as, in effect, self-reportage[16]. We thus learn, in acquiring the picturing techniques I’ve discussed, to then ‘turn’ them upon ourselves so to speak. From learning to see what is ‘in’ some picture, we can learn to pass thence to a ‘seeing’ of what is ‘in’ us, image-wise, although it is important to<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="block"/> remember that we do not, epistemically speaking, stand in any relationship to our imagery; we do not describe our imagery, we report it. Our imagery is manifested only in the expressions we actually use, not in something ‘inner’ which we use these expressions to describe (Wittgenstein 7 § 630). So, in this specific sense, (there are other senses, but this need not detain us here) we can be thought of as ‘picturing devices’. Thus we can say; it is a logical (rather than a metaphysical) condition of picturing that there be picturers, and the notion of ‘picturer’ arises naturally out of the logic of picturing techniques. However, I would stress the qualification I’ve already made, which is that we should not therefore be tempted to suppose that in learning this particular use of ‘picturing’ we are rendering explicit what, prior to the acquisition of these techniques, was already in us.<marker type="block"/> Secondly, construing ourselves as picturing devices subject to, and constructed out of, the logical and epistemological apparatus I’ve outlined, also helps unravel some of the (traditional philosophical) obscurities related to first-person usage of imagery-terms (such as reporting on one’s imagery). Talk of what is ‘in’ us when we consider ourselves as picturing devices, borrows directly from the logic of ‘in’ with regard to picturing techniques. For the ‘I’ which has this imagery becomes, in terms of the account I’m offering, not a mysteriously unreachable entity forever ‘hid- den’ from others, but itself a construct, a logical result of the emergence and development of picturing techniques themselves. And since it is also a logical requirement (a necessary consequence) that this construct, the ‘I’ which ‘images’, has individuation and a specific location in space and time etc, then it is not difficult to see that it is also a resultant of much of the wider apparatus of our natural language out of which notions such as ‘individual’, ‘location’, ‘space’ and ‘time’ are themselves constructed. We can distinguish this view from the troublesome and ultimately incoherent notion of essentially private ‘inner’ states we examined earlier; we need to combat the (almost!) irresistible tendency to construe ‘imaging’ or ‘imagery’ as something intangible which takes place in a mysterious ‘medium’; this isn’t how it is at all. It helps here to always keep this in mind: you can’t do anything with ‘essentially private’ entities.<marker type="block"/> Thirdly, it should be emphasised that imagery-terms are themselves tools, part of the wider network of words, sentences, pictures, signs, notations, in short, language. With these tools is constructed a conceptual framework. In this sense, imaging is a doing, and not something intangible. Imagery, if it is to be of significance with respect to an activity such as designing, alludes to the thinkable, and this means: to the do-able. We cannot weigh things in the ‘image’ of a balance any more than we can look up a timetable ‘in the imagination’ (Wittgenstein 4 , § 255) If there is to be an outcome<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="block"/> here it must be subject to independent criteria, which means that design imagery, if it is to be usable, must make connections with what we do, with the techniques of picturing. Concepts pertaining to imaging, imagery and so on, are connected to these techniques, essentially so. One learns to ‘image’ or use the imagination as one learns to see a face better if one draws it, or as one works over a drawing, or a model, refining, and developing (Wittgenstein 8 , § 255). We should add here that the central criterion for the usability of a tool is its embeddedness in a technique, a way of usage. It is the significance of this embeddedness that we need to see if we want to get a better grasp of the role that imagery actually plays in an activity such as designing.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111" page="15" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112" page="15" column="1">603</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="116" page="16" column="1">604</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="117" page="16" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="119" page="17" column="1">8</region>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Conclusion">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="120" page="17" column="1">Conclusion</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126" page="17" column="1">I have argued that if the discourse we employ with respect to concepts such as imaging, imagery and other mental, psychological states could only ever be applied to ‘inner’ essentially private phenomena, then it would be impossible to make sense of it. If our ordinary everyday language is to have any use for us, it must refer to a domain we can all share. We have also seen that construing mental images as ‘objects’ and imagining as a kind of ‘process’ to be investigated within the empirical framework either of the physical sciences, or of empirical psychology leads to confusion. We are forced either to seek their elimination, or to ‘borrow’ an empirical investigative methodology whose application to the ‘mental’ leaves the logic of many of the common terms of our language, to say the least, obscure. We are trapped by a piece of misguided metaphysics (the ‘privacy of the mental’) and by the misapplication of an investigative methodology (empiricism). Such a ‘picture’ is a mere myth. However, we have also seen that it is possible to offer an alternative account of imagery which builds upon the techniques and resources of picturing, and have seen that such an account can lead to a more fruitful unpacking of the epistemological and logical factors relating to imagery. <marker type="block"/> If the concept of imagery and its cognates can be explicated in the ways I have demonstrated then this in turn has implications for empirical research programmes; although it has not been part of my analysis here to draw these out, it would be worth indicating what some of these might be. Firstly, we might expect that those who had some grounding in and grasp of the techniques I’ve discussed will themselves be more adept in the creative employment of imagery, and this could be the focus of empirical studies. (Purcell and Gero 17 offered some discussion of the possible shape of such a research programme.) Secondly, the acquisition of the resources of picturing techniques would become, in my analysis, an important factor in developing an ability for creative imagery and this has clear implications<marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> for design pedagogy through the teaching and learning of such techniques, which could be followed up through empirical studies. Thirdly, and in close relation to the last point, it should be clear that the epistemically significant concepts of transparency, stance, and metamorphism themselves have pedagogic implications, particularly with respect to teaching and learning, since the results, both of sensitising learners to these concepts, and of employing them more explicitly in design teaching programmes could become a focus for empirical enquiry. Finally I would draw attention to the holistic nature, as I have characterised it, of picturing and imagery and to the many strands of technique, visual, verbal, notational and symbolic out of which such complex abilities grow, as itself a ground for empirical studies focusing on the precise nature of the relationship between these many strands.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="122" page="17" column="1">17 Purcell, A T and Gero, J S ‘Drawings and the design process’ Design Studies 19(4) (1998) pp 389–431</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="124" page="17" column="1">The myths of imagery</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="125" page="17" column="1">605</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="127" page="18" column="1">606</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="128" page="18" column="1">Design Studies Vol 21 No. 6 November 2000</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
