<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>aae8a184720fa5655ffa50ddd3de004830a38217073b4df878ee49aba4aeda01</job>
    <base_name>62m6</base_name>
    <doi>10.1111/j.1468-2370.2010.00290.x</doi>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx1">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62m6.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62m6.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62m6.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="62m6.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">Reviews, Vol. 13, 153–176 (2011) DOI: 10.1111/j.1468-2370.2010.00290.x</outsider>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="3">Pluralism in Project Management: Navigating the Crossroads of Specialization and Fragmentation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group class="DoCO:ListOfAuthors">
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name id="4">Jonas Söderlund</name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">Department of Leadership and Management, BI Norwegian School of Management, 0442 Oslo, Norway Corresponding author email: <email id="5">jonas.soderlund@liu.se</email></region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="7" confidence="possible">Project management is a rapidly expanding subfield of management and organization studies. This paper seeks to make sense of this development and the current state of project management research. It reviews the literature published over the last five decades in 30 leading management and organization journals. In total, 305 articles were included in the data set. The paper proposes a categorization of the published articles into seven ‘schools of thought’: Optimization School, Factor School, Contingency School, Behaviour School, Governance School, Relationship School and Decision School. The schools vary in terms of their main focus and use of the project concept, major research questions, methodological approaches and type of theorizing. It is suggested that a better awareness on how to make use of the schools and the identified perspectives would stimulate cross-fertilization, unification and thus enhance a plural- istic understanding of projects and project management at the same time as it would prepare research to frame more accurately the problems of contemporary projects. In that respect, the paper offers ideas on how to navigate at the crossroads between specialization and fragmentation, between the search for novel topics and improvements of existing knowledge.</abstract>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="8" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">Making sense of fifty years of project management research</h1>
      </section>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" page="1" column="1">There is a strong relationship between scientific progress and pluralism, especially if the goal is to ‘get a reasonably adequate picture of the complex</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible" page="1" column="1">An earlier version of this paper was presented at the Academy of Management Conference in Anaheim in 2008. The paper has benefited from comments and help from workshop and conference participants and numerous colleagues in Scandinavia, the UK and the US. In particular, I am grateful for the valuable support and constructive comments from Erling S. Andersen, Karlos Artto, Elliot Bendoly, Floortje Blindenbach-Driesen, Mats Engwall, Lars Lindkvist, Rolf A. Lundin, Peter Morris, Ralf Müller, Johann Packendorff, Jeff Pinto, Anders Söderholm and Graham Winch. I also acknowledge the suggestions from the Associate Editor and four anonymous reviewers. © 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="11" page="1" column="2">ijmr_290 153..176</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="43" page="1" column="2">reality’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R129" id="12" class="deo:Reference">Knudsen 2003</xref>, p. 271). Similarly, pluralism could be viewed in light of Popper’s (1945) argument that the more open a scientific field is towards new ideas, the tougher the competition and, consequently, the better the chances for scientific breakthroughs. However, scientific fields, like project management, struggle with the balance between exploration and exploitation, between unification and focus and pluralism, diversity and openness, between the search for new topics, methods, and the capitalization and improvement of existing knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R160" id="13" class="deo:Reference">March 1996</xref>). As Knudsen (2003, p. 263, emphasis in original) put it: ‘fields with too little pluralism run the risk of being caught in a specialization trap, while fields with too much pluralism run the risk of being caught in a fragmentation trap’. Over the years, this challenge has been an often-debated topic in management and organization studies (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R185" id="14" class="deo:Reference">Pfeffer 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R240" id="15" class="deo:Reference">Van Maanen 1995</xref>) and is, perhaps, particularly pressing<marker type="page" number="2"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> for project management, given its recent fast-paced development and its historic origin within such diverse areas as engineering, operations research and organization theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117" id="20" class="deo:Reference">Johnson 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R145" id="21" class="deo:Reference">Levene 1996</xref>). In project management, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R172" id="22" class="deo:Reference">Morris (1994)</xref> clearly dem- onstrates, there is a long and strong tradition of research with a firm grounding in operations research and management science which dates back to the early 1950s. Since then, project management research has developed considerably and moved into other knowledge and application areas responding to the wider spectrum of the use of projects as organizational forms (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="23" class="deo:Reference">Ekstedt et al. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R246" id="24" class="deo:Reference">Whittington et al. 1999</xref>). On this development route, it has made use of a number of related disciplines: marketing; organization theory; strategic management; and political science, to name a few. Inspired by debates and studies in other subfields of management and organization studies, this paper suggests that an analysis and discussion of the ‘schools of thought’ might be a promising path to bring together unification and pluralism. Accordingly, it is an approach to avoid the aforementioned traps of specialization and fragmentation (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="25" class="deo:Reference">Daft and Buenger 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75" id="26" class="deo:Reference">Fredrickson 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R174" id="27" class="deo:Reference">Nag et al. 2007</xref>). To a certain extent, a categorization of research traditions may contribute to the sophistica- tion and further elaborations of existing knowledge and theories. It would also, if properly done, draw attention to new and evolving perspectives and ana- lytical frameworks. In other words, a categorization of contributions could lead the way to a healthy ‘cre- ative tension’ within the field of project management research (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R193" id="28" class="deo:Reference">Poole and Van de Ven 1989</xref>), and thus be essential for improving the linkages between project management and its related subfields in management and organization studies. These linkages are impera- tive, given the extensive scholarly interest in projects as cornerstones for new organizational forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="29" class="deo:Reference">Castells 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R246" id="30" class="deo:Reference">Whittington et al. 1999</xref>), loci for entrepreneurial and strategy formation processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R245" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Whittington et al. 2006</xref>) and organizational devices to deliver increasingly complex integrated customer solutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="32" class="deo:Reference">Davies and Hobday 2005</xref>). Indeed, the wide adoption of project-based structures makes project management, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R195" id="33" class="deo:Reference">Postrel (2007)</xref> comments, an important area of inquiry for management and organization studies in general. Theoretical pluralism is, however, not only essential to research, but may well also advance managerial and organizational practice. An awareness of multiple perspectives provides contrasting explanations and thereby stimulates manage-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> rial and organizational creativity. The combination of multiple perspectives and informed practice would then in the next step hopefully infuse a more insight- ful and penetrating research agenda (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R239" id="35" class="deo:Reference">Van de Ven 2007</xref>, p. 9). The main purpose of this paper is to present a categorization of the schools of thought which gives an account of the present state of theorizing in project management. Dividing a scientific field into different schools of thought would make us catego- rize contributions with strong similarity into one group (e.g. similar conception of phenomenon, key concepts and issues, base discipline, research methodologies), thus separating them from other groups. The prime reasons for using the school concept are twofold. First, so-called ‘schools overviews’ have offered instrumental and powerful analysis of research in related fields, such as that by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R169" id="36" class="deo:Reference">Mintzberg (1990)</xref> on strategic management (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R170" id="37" class="deo:Reference">Mintzberg et al. 1998</xref>). Second, the idea of school categorization has also recently gained considerable popularity within the project management community (Bredillet 2007; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R136" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Kwak and Anbari 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R213" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund 2002</xref>). Using this idea thereby facilitates a comparative analysis of the development of project management research relative to other management and organization subfields as well as to current debates among project management scholars. In relation to earlier school categorizations in project management, the present review relies on a more rigorous methodology and elaborate journal coverage (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R213" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund 2002</xref>) and, most importantly, has a specific focus on studies addressing the project level (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Bredillet 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R136" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Kwak and Anbari 2008</xref>). The paper is structured in the following way. The next section presents the methodology and data used for the literature review. Thereafter follows an account of the identified schools of thought that focus on a selected number of contributions and tra- jectories. The paper ends with comparisons, conclusions and implications.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="17" page="1" column="2">Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd, 9600 Garsington Road, Oxford OX4 2DQ, UK and 350 Main Street, Malden, MA 02148, USA</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="18" page="2" column="1">154</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="19" page="2" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="44" confidence="possible" page="2" column="2">Methodology</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="91" page="2" column="2">The paper focuses on articles published in high- ranked management and organization journals outside the conventional project management publications such as the International Journal of Project Management and Project Management Journal. Overviews of work published in these journals already exist, although they tend to centre on narrow <marker type="page" number="3"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> project management topics, such as risk management, project manager competencies, and planning techniques (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Betts and Lansley 1995</xref>; Crawford et al. 2006; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R128" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Kloppenborg and Opfer 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R192" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Pollack 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R228" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Themistocleous and Wearne 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R237" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Urli and Urli 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R255" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Zobel and Wearne 2000</xref>). In line with Leybourne (2007, p. 70), the review presented here instead addresses overall management and organization topics in projects and project management – a focus that the author believes is important for readers both within and outside the project management domain. The paper builds on a series of prior literature reviews and database investigations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Crawford et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Engwall 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Ford and Randolph 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R182" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Packendorff 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R209" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar and Dvir 2007</xref>; Söderlund 2002, 2004a,b). These reviews were analysed as a starting point for the study presented here. Based on panel discussions with leading scholars in project management, previously published literature reviews, and journal ranking lists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Collin et al. 1996</xref>; ISI Web of Science), it was decided to focus on 30 journals that were likely to publish empirical and theoretical work on project management, thus leaving out methodology, teaching and pure review journals from the sample (e.g. International Journal of Management Reviews, Organizational Research Methods and Academy of Management Learning &amp; Education). Besides mainstream management and organization journals, a selection of journals in related areas, such as technology management, innovation, operations management and product development, were added. A separate search for special issues on project management and adjacent areas was also made to identify those journals that publish project management work. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" id="61" class="deo:Reference">Table 1</xref> presents the journals included in the sample and documents a few patterns in the sample of articles from each journal. Papers were selected based on the following criteria: (1) published in one of the preferred journals; (2) focused on governance, management and organization of single projects (following Morris’s (1994) advice, articles dealing with early and/or implementation phases of projects were included); and (3) positioned within the realm of project management and/or project organization. Such positioning would normally be stated in the abstract, the introductory parts of the paper or in the conclusion section, often as a problem or challenge in terms of the management and organization of single projects. The abstracts were read and combined with keyword<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> investigations and, to ensure the accuracy of the literature search, related research reports were used to match the data set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R136" id="63" class="deo:Reference">Kwak and Anbari 2008</xref>; Packendorff 1995). This search created a total data set of 312 papers. After a preliminary analysis of the papers, it was decided to leave out seven papers, since the theoretical underpinnings were unclear or because the papers, after a more detailed analysis, did not match the initial criteria, which resulted in a final data set of 305 journal articles. In the subsequent phase, a brief summary was produced and between five and ten keywords were identified from each paper. The summary included the paper’s key ideas of project management, its base discipline and primary focus. Thereafter, the author analysed across the data set, which incorporated the different traditions and the diversity among the papers. The analysis started with an inductive examination of the papers based on key concepts and keywords. The first list of categories contained both categories that were relatively small (with two to three articles each) and larger categories (approximately 20 papers). Based on methodological recom- mendations, the number of categories was reduced through a deductive approach. The intention, based on Miller’s (1956) well-known idea, was to end up with approximately five to nine categories (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R170" id="64" class="deo:Reference">Mintzberg et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R171" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Morgan 1986</xref>). For purposes of presentation, the study has relied on compilations of keywords and citation analysis. The keywords are used primarily to identify similarities and differences across the schools, whereas the citation analysis is intended to identify examples of influential contributions within each school of thought. Every categorization effort needs to be based on a selected number of dimensions and variables. To fit the journal format, the scope was narrowed and focused on a limited number of dimensions, namely: influential contributions, sources of inspiration, primary ideas of projects and project management, empirical focus, key issues/questions, keywords and main research methodologies (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R169" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Mintzberg 1990</xref>). Bearing in mind that the idea in this paper is to advance theory development, the author believes that these dimensions are sufficient to identify and analyse pluralism within project management research. The study is dealing here with a delicate balancing act: the categorization scheme must provide room for a certain breadth of aspects and contributions, and, at the same time, be bounded to make it comprehensible and coherent. New schools will evolve, merge with existing ones, and old ones<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> will possibly cease to exist. Hence, the categorization presented here is by no means final and complete; it is to be seen as a tentative framework intended to stimulate discussion about the importance, purview and problems of research on projects and project management. Its meaning is also to relate project<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> management research better to the study of management and organization in general. A few delimitations had to be made. As mentioned earlier, the focus of attention is on project-centric studies. In the literature search carried out in 2008 covering papers published from 1954 to 2007, there<marker type="page" number="6"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> were many hits on ‘project’ and ‘project management’. Several articles were excluded from the data set because they dealt mainly with a different level of analysis (individuals or firms) or because they, for other reasons, did not specifically address the management and organization of projects. This generally implied that studies of the management of project- based firms (e.g. management of multiple projects, selection of projects, project portfolio management, project capabilities/competence) were not considered relevant for the present study (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Cooper et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R176" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Nobeoka and Cusumano 1997</xref>). Papers addressing narrow topics of project-based organizations, including innovation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R122" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Keegan and Turner 2002</xref>), human resource management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Bredin and Söderlund 2006</xref>) and knowledge transfer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R196" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Prencipe and Tell 2001</xref>), were also excluded, since their intention was principally to understand another domain of management than the management of projects. The prime focus of this review is accordingly on studies and articles that analyse single projects from a holis- tic and organizational point of view, which means that the literature review covers papers on governance, management and organizational structures and processes of single projects. Revisiting the so-called ‘fundamental questions of project management’ discussed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R214" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund (2004a)</xref>, the selected articles above all contribute to the understanding of why projects exist, how they differ, how they behave, the role of project management, and the determinants of success and failure of projects. In the following, it is suggested that the articles can be divided into seven distinct schools of thought: (1) Optimization School (logic-based, prescriptive research drawing on management science, optimization techniques and systems analysis); (2) Factor School (empirical research relying on descriptive statistics on the criteria and factors of project success and failure); (3) Contingency School (empirical research, case-study-based and survey- based research on the differences between projects, characteristics of projects and contextual dimensions); (4) Behaviour School (interpretative and descriptive research on organizational behaviour, processes and learning in projects); (5) Governance School (prescriptive research on governance and contract problems in projects); (6) Relationship School (descriptive case-study research on relations between actors in projects); and (7) Decision School (descriptive and interpretative research on politics and decision-making in projects). Below, the paper offers an overview of each of the schools and sum-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> marizes their respective developments and main findings. Thereafter, it turns to a comparative analysis eliciting the differences among the schools.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="46" page="2" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47" page="3" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="48" page="3" column="1">155</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="68" page="3" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="69" page="4" column="1">156</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="70" page="4" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="71" page="4" column="1">Table 1. Selected journals: patterns and comments (305 articles)</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="4">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Journal</th>
                  <th class="table"> No. of</th>
                  <th class="table"> Patterns and comments</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> articles</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 1. Academy of</td>
                  <td class="table"> 20</td>
                  <td class="table"> In AMJ there is a wide array of publications ranging from studies of decision-making in</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> complex projects, communication in R&amp;D projects, to studies of project team evolution. A</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> few shorter research notes were excluded from the sample.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 2. Academy of</td>
                  <td class="table"> 4</td>
                  <td class="table"> Most of the articles in the sample from AMR are relatively old. Two themes seem to have</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> attracted special attention: planning and matrix organization.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 3. Administrative</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8</td>
                  <td class="table"> No common theme was identified in the articles in the sample published in ASQ. However, a</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Science Quarterly</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> set of themes have attracted a lot of attention from other scholars on topics such as craft administration, product development processes, escalating commitment, group longevity and project performance, and temporary systems.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 4. British Journal of</td>
                  <td class="table"> 5</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers published in BJM do not have a strong common theme, although the papers in</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> various ways seem to take an interest in the processes and behaviour of projects. The articles are also all based on qualitative research, case studies being the most common approach.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 5. California</td>
                  <td class="table"> 12</td>
                  <td class="table"> In CMR are found some of the classics in project management and the main inspiration for the</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> notion of projects as temporary organizations. Many of the early articles on programme management, temporary systems and matrix management were published in this journal.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 6. Creativity and</td>
                  <td class="table"> 8</td>
                  <td class="table"> CIM is a rather new journal that has published several articles on subjects of relevance to</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Innovation</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> project management. However, many of the articles focus on aspects of individual work,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> including creativity and motivation. Accordingly, these papers were not included in the data set. The papers included in the data set discuss creativity and control in projects, and the impact of temporal contexts on management.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 7. European Management</td>
                  <td class="table"> 9</td>
                  <td class="table"> In the EMJ, one finds a set of articles on project success. Several short articles and empirical</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> reports were excluded from the sample. Also excluded were a few articles on project-based firms that primarily dealt with company-wide issues. Of the papers included in the data set, several have a governance orientation.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 8. European Management</td>
                  <td class="table"> 1</td>
                  <td class="table"> Given the success of the EURAM track on project management, it was expected that more</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> articles would be published in EMR dealing with project management/organization. However, in the end, only one of the articles matched the selection criteria.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 9. Harvard Business</td>
                  <td class="table"> 9</td>
                  <td class="table"> Papers are primarily about two topics, either practical approaches to the management of</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> projects (including rugby approaches, overlapping approaches, planning techniques, PERT), or as reports from failed projects (false economies, lessons learned). A number of practice-oriented papers and short notes were excluded from the sample. Some of the articles in the data set were also difficult to analyse because the theoretical foundation was not really made explicit (e.g., Gaddis 1959), and hence excluded from the sample.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 10. IEEE Transactions</td>
                  <td class="table"> 14</td>
                  <td class="table"> The bulk of papers in IEEE-EM deal with either critical success factors of projects and project</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> on Engineering</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> management or methods for optimizing project implementation. The papers have a rather</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> strong engineering or mathematical orientation. The author was only able to search issues between 1987 and 2007.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 11. Industrial Marketing</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers could be divided into two groups: one dealing with supplier–client relationships in</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> complex projects, the other dealing with project performance and project success. IMM has published a special issue that addresses project management issues.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 12. International</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers published in IBR generally look at the relationship aspects of projects, covering</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Business Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> topics such as owner involvement, network development, systems selling and project marketing. IBR has published a special issue on project marketing and systems selling in which several of the papers included were published.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 13. International Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2</td>
                  <td class="table"> The two papers in IJIM that have a project-centric focus deal with global innovation projects</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> of Innovation</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> and the importance of ‘project vision’. Both papers generally address the management</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> challenges of innovation projects.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 14. International Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6</td>
                  <td class="table"> In IJTM, a wide range of topics were found related to project management, from planning,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> of Technology</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> cross-functional integration to the practice of project management. It was difficult to identify</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> a common theme among the papers. However, the majority of papers deal with project management in new product development.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 15. International Studies</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7</td>
                  <td class="table"> Most papers have an organization theory orientation dealing with either cultural diversity or</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> of Management &amp;</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> complex decision-making.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"> Organization</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 16. Journal of</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> In JM, only three papers were found. No common theme could be identified, one paper deals</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> with cross-functional structures, one with critical success factors, and one with pacing and deadlines in projects. All papers identified have a high citation rate (89, 86, 27 respectively).</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="73" confidence="possible" page="4" column="1">Journal No. of Patterns and comments articles 1. Academy of 20 In AMJ there is a wide array of publications ranging from studies of decision-making in Management complex projects, communication in R&amp;D projects, to studies of project team evolution. A Journal few shorter research notes were excluded from the sample. 2. Academy of 4 Most of the articles in the sample from AMR are relatively old. Two themes seem to have Management Review attracted special attention: planning and matrix organization. 3. Administrative 8 No common theme was identified in the articles in the sample published in ASQ. However, a Science Quarterly set of themes have attracted a lot of attention from other scholars on topics such as craft administration, product development processes, escalating commitment, group longevity and project performance, and temporary systems. 4. British Journal of 5 The papers published in BJM do not have a strong common theme, although the papers in Management various ways seem to take an interest in the processes and behaviour of projects. The articles are also all based on qualitative research, case studies being the most common approach. 5. California 12 In CMR are found some of the classics in project management and the main inspiration for the Management Review notion of projects as temporary organizations. Many of the early articles on programme management, temporary systems and matrix management were published in this journal. 6. Creativity and 8 CIM is a rather new journal that has published several articles on subjects of relevance to Innovation project management. However, many of the articles focus on aspects of individual work, Management including creativity and motivation. Accordingly, these papers were not included in the data set. The papers included in the data set discuss creativity and control in projects, and the impact of temporal contexts on management. 7. European Management 9 In the EMJ, one finds a set of articles on project success. Several short articles and empirical Journal reports were excluded from the sample. Also excluded were a few articles on project-based firms that primarily dealt with company-wide issues. Of the papers included in the data set, several have a governance orientation. 8. European Management 1 Given the success of the EURAM track on project management, it was expected that more Review articles would be published in EMR dealing with project management/organization. However, in the end, only one of the articles matched the selection criteria. 9. Harvard Business 9 Papers are primarily about two topics, either practical approaches to the management of Review projects (including rugby approaches, overlapping approaches, planning techniques, PERT), or as reports from failed projects (false economies, lessons learned). A number of practice-oriented papers and short notes were excluded from the sample. Some of the articles in the data set were also difficult to analyse because the theoretical foundation was not really made explicit (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Gaddis 1959</xref>), and hence excluded from the sample. 10. IEEE Transactions 14 The bulk of papers in IEEE-EM deal with either critical success factors of projects and project on Engineering management or methods for optimizing project implementation. The papers have a rather Management strong engineering or mathematical orientation. The author was only able to search issues between 1987 and 2007. 11. Industrial Marketing 7 The papers could be divided into two groups: one dealing with supplier–client relationships in Management complex projects, the other dealing with project performance and project success. IMM has published a special issue that addresses project management issues. 12. International 10 The papers published in IBR generally look at the relationship aspects of projects, covering Business Review topics such as owner involvement, network development, systems selling and project marketing. IBR has published a special issue on project marketing and systems selling in which several of the papers included were published. 13. International Journal 2 The two papers in IJIM that have a project-centric focus deal with global innovation projects of Innovation and the importance of ‘project vision’. Both papers generally address the management Management challenges of innovation projects. 14. International Journal 6 In IJTM, a wide range of topics were found related to project management, from planning, of Technology cross-functional integration to the practice of project management. It was difficult to identify Management a common theme among the papers. However, the majority of papers deal with project management in new product development. 15. International Studies 7 Most papers have an organization theory orientation dealing with either cultural diversity or of Management &amp; complex decision-making. Organization 16. Journal of 3 In JM, only three papers were found. No common theme could be identified, one paper deals Management with cross-functional structures, one with critical success factors, and one with pacing and deadlines in projects. All papers identified have a high citation rate (89, 86, 27 respectively).</region>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="74" page="4" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="75" page="5" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="76" page="5" column="1">157</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T1">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="77" page="5" column="1">Table 1. Continued</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="1" page="5">
              <thead class="table">
                <tr class="table">
                  <th class="table"> Journal</th>
                  <th class="table"> No. of</th>
                  <th class="table"> Patterns and comments</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table.strange">
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                  <td class="table.strange"> articles</td>
                  <td class="table.strange"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 17. Journal of</td>
                  <td class="table"> 14</td>
                  <td class="table"> In JMS, the first paper on project management was found, published in 1970. The papers</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management Studies</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> published have a fairly strong organization theory perspective and cover a wide range of topics, including papers on critical success factors, matrix organization, political perspectives on projects, and critical perspectives on project management.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 18. Journal of Operations</td>
                  <td class="table"> 18</td>
                  <td class="table"> In JOM the first 15 volumes contained ten papers focusing on scheduling, forecasting and</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> priority rules. The most recent ten volumes have focused to a greater extent on critical success factors. Two papers had high citation scores (112 and 81).</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 19. Journal of Product</td>
                  <td class="table"> 6</td>
                  <td class="table"> Three of the papers have a focus on project success/product success and project management.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Innovation</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> The remaining papers address organizational structures and complexity. A few articles that</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> only focused on success factors for product development without a specific focus on projects were excluded from the sample.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 20. Long Range Planning</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2</td>
                  <td class="table"> One paper deals with project success, the other deals with planning approaches and work breakdown structures. Five practice-oriented papers were excluded from the sample.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 21. Management Science</td>
                  <td class="table"> 58</td>
                  <td class="table"> In MS, several papers on project management and project planning were identified. These papers have a strong operations research orientation, dealing with project scheduling, solving resource conflicts, project planning methods, etc. Several papers were excluded either because of a too narrow focus or due to mismatch in the level of analysis, including project portfolio management, multi-project scheduling, or a focus on project selection.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 22. Organization</td>
                  <td class="table"> 3</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers in Organization have a critical orientation and a strong organization theory background, carried out within a qualitative research paradigm.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 23. Organization Science</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers published in Organization Science have a strong organization theory origin. Papers are produced within two different traditions: one quantitative tradition and one case-study based/qualitative tradition. Several papers have touched upon inter-team co-ordination/ inter-departmental co-ordination.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 24. Organization Studies</td>
                  <td class="table"> 9</td>
                  <td class="table"> Learning and knowledge processes seem to be recurring themes in the papers published in Organization Studies. Several of the papers are published in the same special issue covering knowledge, learning and project organizing.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 25. R&amp;D Management</td>
                  <td class="table"> 15</td>
                  <td class="table"> A number of the papers deal with success factors in different types of development projects. Some papers cover relational aspects, including stakeholder management, governance, and collaboration. A number of papers were excluded from the sample because they were considered to be outside the scope of the present review, including project portfolio, and project valuation. The author had access to issues only between 1997 and 2007.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 26. Research Policy</td>
                  <td class="table"> 14</td>
                  <td class="table"> In RP, several influential papers were identified, ranging from success factors in projects and innovation projects to contextual analyses of projects.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 27. Scandinavian Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"> 11</td>
                  <td class="table"> The papers in SJM have a strong organization theory orientation. Many of the papers are</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> of Management</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> published in a special issue of selected papers from a project management conference. The theme of this special issue was ‘project management and temporary organization’.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 28. Sloan Management</td>
                  <td class="table"> 7</td>
                  <td class="table"> Two papers are clearly within the line of success factors and project management; the other</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Review</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> papers deal with managing uncertainty and models for project management. Several papers were not included because they primarily dealt with the firm-level, e.g. project portfolio and strategy.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 29. Strategic</td>
                  <td class="table"> 2</td>
                  <td class="table"> Two papers were included in the data set: one dealing with critical success factors, one focusing</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Management Journal</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> on knowledge integration in projects. Several papers were left out because they dealt primarily with company-wide issues, including multi-project strategies.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> 30. Technovation</td>
                  <td class="table"> 10</td>
                  <td class="table"> The majority of publications deal with project success, how to evaluate successful projects, and critical factors in projects. Most of the papers deal with innovation and new product development projects.</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="78" confidence="possible" page="5" column="1">Journal No. of Patterns and comments articles 17. Journal of 14 In JMS, the first paper on project management was found, published in 1970. The papers Management Studies published have a fairly strong organization theory perspective and cover a wide range of topics, including papers on critical success factors, matrix organization, political perspectives on projects, and critical perspectives on project management. 18. Journal of Operations 18 In JOM the first 15 volumes contained ten papers focusing on scheduling, forecasting and Management priority rules. The most recent ten volumes have focused to a greater extent on critical success factors. Two papers had high citation scores (112 and 81). 19. Journal of Product 6 Three of the papers have a focus on project success/product success and project management. Innovation The remaining papers address organizational structures and complexity. A few articles that Management only focused on success factors for product development without a specific focus on projects were excluded from the sample. 20. Long Range Planning 2 One paper deals with project success, the other deals with planning approaches and work breakdown structures. Five practice-oriented papers were excluded from the sample. 21. Management Science 58 In MS, several papers on project management and project planning were identified. These papers have a strong operations research orientation, dealing with project scheduling, solving resource conflicts, project planning methods, etc. Several papers were excluded either because of a too narrow focus or due to mismatch in the level of analysis, including project portfolio management, multi-project scheduling, or a focus on project selection. 22. Organization 3 The papers in Organization have a critical orientation and a strong organization theory background, carried out within a qualitative research paradigm. 23. Organization Science 11 The papers published in Organization Science have a strong organization theory origin. Papers are produced within two different traditions: one quantitative tradition and one case-study based/qualitative tradition. Several papers have touched upon inter-team co-ordination/ inter-departmental co-ordination. 24. Organization Studies 9 Learning and knowledge processes seem to be recurring themes in the papers published in Organization Studies. Several of the papers are published in the same special issue covering knowledge, learning and project organizing. 25. R&amp;D Management 15 A number of the papers deal with success factors in different types of development projects. Some papers cover relational aspects, including stakeholder management, governance, and collaboration. A number of papers were excluded from the sample because they were considered to be outside the scope of the present review, including project portfolio, and project valuation. The author had access to issues only between 1997 and 2007. 26. Research Policy 14 In RP, several influential papers were identified, ranging from success factors in projects and innovation projects to contextual analyses of projects. 27. Scandinavian Journal 11 The papers in SJM have a strong organization theory orientation. Many of the papers are of Management published in a special issue of selected papers from a project management conference. The theme of this special issue was ‘project management and temporary organization’. 28. Sloan Management 7 Two papers are clearly within the line of success factors and project management; the other Review papers deal with managing uncertainty and models for project management. Several papers were not included because they primarily dealt with the firm-level, e.g. project portfolio and strategy. 29. Strategic 2 Two papers were included in the data set: one dealing with critical success factors, one focusing Management Journal on knowledge integration in projects. Several papers were left out because they dealt primarily with company-wide issues, including multi-project strategies. 30. Technovation 10 The majority of publications deal with project success, how to evaluate successful projects, and critical factors in projects. Most of the papers deal with innovation and new product development projects.</region>
        </region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="81" page="5" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="82" page="6" column="1">158</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="83" page="6" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="92" confidence="possible" page="6" column="2">Optimization School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="118" page="6" column="2">In this category of research, such diverse fields as network planning research and systems analysis are found, of which the majority of papers have been published in Management Science and in IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management (for a detailed overview, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R225" id="93" class="deo:Reference">Tavares 2002</xref>). The contributions generally address the optimization of project implementation using mathematics, optimization theory and management science. The author has therefore chosen to label it the Optimization School (alternatives could have been Management Science, Planning or Systems Analysis). Judging from the 73 publications in the data set, this line of research was introduced quite early in the top-tier journals. Management Science published articles on project management and network planning in the early 1960s, and a range of papers were published in the 1960s on topics exploring PERT (Program Evaluation and Review Technique) and critical path planning, which also gained some interest in practitioner journals (for instance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R125" id="94" class="deo:Reference">King and Wilson 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R166" id="95" class="deo:Reference">Miller 1962</xref>). Since the early publications on project activity networks, PERT and CPM (Critical Path Method) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R127" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Klingel 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R147" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Levy et al. 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R183" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Parikh and Jewell 1965</xref>), more advanced methods and analyses followed. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, papers dealt with parallel strategies in development projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Abernathy and Rosenbloom 1969</xref>), project cost control, and different planning and programming solutions to the problem of optimal resource use and cost–time trade-offs (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39" id="100" class="deo:Reference">Cooper 1976</xref>). Subsequent articles contribute to the understanding of more complex problems and the management of yet more difficult projects by intro- ducing dynamic situations involving multi-pass, heuristic decomposition procedures for project scheduling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107" id="101" class="deo:Reference">Holloway et al. 1979</xref>) and project scheduling with continuously divisible constrained resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R241" id="102" class="deo:Reference">Weglarz 1981</xref>). Some contributions also extend the original PERT ideas by elaborating on Q-GERT modelling and simulation models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R226" id="103" class="deo:Reference">Taylor and Moore 1980</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92" id="104" class="deo:Reference">Gutierrez and Kouvelis (1991)</xref> use a stochastic activity completion time model to examine the effects of information release policies on subcontrac-<marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> tors of project activities. Similar contributions are presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="109" class="deo:Reference">Dumond and Mabert (1988)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Drexl (1991)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="111" class="deo:Reference">Elmaghraby and Kamburowski (1992)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Demeulemeester and Herroelen (1992)</xref>. A set of related papers were published in Management Science around this time (1988–95), with the overarching idea of developing techniques and models for formalized project management approaches, including network planning and PERT. The contributions within the research in the Optimization School share a common view on projects as complex activities to be planned by, more or less, advanced management-science techniques and models. The contributions tend to advocate an ana- lytic view of projects and project management. Writers also typically adopt a prescriptive and nor- mative stance, rather than a descriptive one (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R156" id="113" class="deo:Reference">Lucas 1971</xref>). Consequently, project management is largely defined as the application of the techniques to approach the complex scheduling/co-ordination problem of executing a project (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Bailetti et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="115" class="deo:Reference">Eppinger 2001</xref>). For instance, Liberatore and Titus (1983, p. 962) define project management as ‘the activities of screening, selecting, evaluating, budgeting, scheduling and controlling . . . projects’. Many of the papers refer to the history of project management found in the early days of management science and, in particular, the development of advanced project planning techniques and various structuring and breakdown methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R138" id="116" class="deo:Reference">Lanford and McCann 1983</xref>). A common assumption is that ‘successful management of . . . projects requires a careful planning, scheduling . . . of activities’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88" id="117" class="deo:Reference">Granot and Zuckerman 1991</xref>, p. 140). A great deal of attention is devoted to modelling and evaluation of projects combined with improvements in network models for project management (generalized networks, logical networks, overlapping activities and hammock activities). In recent years, research into this area has also focused on the limitations of the tools and techniques to deal with the growing complexity and speed of change.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="106" page="6" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="107" page="7" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="108" page="7" column="1">159</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="119" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Factor School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" page="7" column="1">A considerable body of project management research reflects the investigation of the criteria for project success and, naturally, also the factors that lead to either success or failure in projects and project management. Hence, a common interest revolves around the matters of how to determine what a successful <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> project is and what seems to cause project (management) success. The author has chosen to label this particular tradition of project management research the Factor School (alternatives could be Success School, Critical Success Factor School, see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R119" id="121" class="deo:Reference">Jugdev and Müller 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R213" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund 2002</xref>). In total, there were 64 papers included in the data set grouped within the Factor School. The research published in journals dates back to the late 1960s and early 1970s with a small number of articles in journals such as California Management Review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="123" class="deo:Reference">Avots 1969</xref>) and Academy of Management Journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R227" id="124" class="deo:Reference">Thamhain and Gemmill 1974</xref>). The majority of the publications were, however, published in the 1980s. The importance of examining the critical success factors is justified by the overwhelming failure of projects and the belief that the identification of these factors would profoundly improve project implementation in practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R187" id="125" class="deo:Reference">Pinto and Prescott 1990</xref>). This seems also to be the typical starting point for many articles within this tradition: e.g. why projects fail and what separates the low performers from the high performers (see, for instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="126" class="deo:Reference">Avots 1969</xref>). During the late 1980s, research developed rapidly, with a series of important publications in both practitioner-oriented journals, such as Sloan Management Review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R197" id="127" class="deo:Reference">Randolph and Posner 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R212" id="128" class="deo:Reference">Slevin and Pinto 1987</xref>) and well-known scholarly journals, such as the Academy of Management Journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R121" id="129" class="deo:Reference">Katz and Allen 1985</xref>), Administrative Science Quarterly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R120" id="130" class="deo:Reference">Katz 1982</xref>), Journal of Management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R188" id="131" class="deo:Reference">Pinto and Prescott 1988</xref>), Journal of Management Studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R187" id="132" class="deo:Reference">Pinto and Prescott 1990</xref>), Journal of Product Innovation Management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R140" id="133" class="deo:Reference">Larson and Gobeli 1988</xref>), Management Science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="134" class="deo:Reference">Clark 1989</xref>) and Strategic Management Journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="135" class="deo:Reference">Bryson and Bromiley 1993</xref>). A number of interesting developments are worth noting. One line of development encompasses an increasingly detailed empirical focus on particular types of projects and empirical contexts, most notably geographical regions, sectors and industries. Hence, research also becomes more fine-grained with regard to organizational conditions and task features. In addition, research covers a wider range of sectors and industries, such as pharmaceutical, elec- trical equipment manufacturing, IT, and oil and gas, sometimes in conjunction with a particular focus on geographical regions and/or nations. The second expansion relates to the nature of analysis with regard to its dynamics and specificity. Even though the majority of publications have a<marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> static orientation, in some publications one sees attempts to provide a dynamic view on projects and the variations in success factors across the project life cycle (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106" id="140" class="deo:Reference">Hoegl and Weinkauf 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R188" id="141" class="deo:Reference">Pinto and Prescott 1988</xref>). These studies typically span the early stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="142" class="deo:Reference">Ericksen and Dyer 2004</xref>), from the planning phases to the implementation and conclusion phases. In addition, some studies deal with the overall success factors, similar to the factors presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="143" class="deo:Reference">DeCotiis and Dyer (1977)</xref>, while others focus on a particular issue or problem, such as teamwork and team location (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90" id="144" class="deo:Reference">Grewal et al. 2006</xref>), decision-making influence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R121" id="145" class="deo:Reference">Katz and Allen 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R173" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Müller and Turner 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R227" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Thamhain and Gemmill 1974</xref>), group longevity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R120" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Katz 1982</xref>) and cross-functional co-operation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R190" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Pinto et al. 1993</xref>), yet still framing it as a problem relating to the management and organization of projects. For many years, research within the Factor School had a strict and narrow definition of success in terms of efficiency with regard to time, cost and quality dimensions. Over the years, however, this was broad- ened and led to an increased interest in value creation, long-term perspectives, and capability- building (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R207" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar et al. 2001</xref>), which generally signals a concern for separating efficiency from effectiveness measurements. Advancements pertaining to research methodologies are also discerned. The early studies generally rely on a limited data set or author experience with primarily anecdotal evidence. Over time, there has been more rigorous survey research, with large cross-sectional samples and a few in-depth case studies.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="137" page="7" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="138" page="8" column="1">160</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="139" page="8" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="152" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">Contingency School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="181" page="8" column="1">For several decades, project management research struggled to strike a balance between the elaborations of a theory of project management that was generic and general yet allowed for applications to different types of projects. One important stream of research tied to this involved contingency approaches and comparative analyses of projects and project management. The author has labelled it the Contingency School; primarily because it draws on contingency-inspired organization theory developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78" id="153" class="deo:Reference">Galbraith (1973)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="154" class="deo:Reference">Burns and Stalker (1961)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R143" id="155" class="deo:Reference">Lawrence and Lorsch (1967)</xref> (alternative labels could have been structural school, design school or situational school). In total, 42 papers were grouped as pertaining to the Contingency School.<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> The first paper in the sample is by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R164" id="157" class="deo:Reference">Middleton (1967)</xref> on different kinds of project organization. The author discusses the advantages and disadvantages of organizing by projects and identifies the various forms of project organization ranging from individual project organization, staff project organization, intermix project organization to aggregate organization. He argues that the establishment of a project organization should rest on an examination of the nature of the ‘job and its requirements’ and ‘scope of the project’. Several of the early contributions within the Contingency School continue on this line of thinking by addressing matrix organizations and matrix management, typically in R&amp;D settings (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R132" id="158" class="deo:Reference">Kolodny 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R236" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Tushman 1978</xref>). Some of the papers concentrate on the identification and comparison of different ‘project environ- ments’ and how these different environments require alternative approaches to project management, project control and project planning (see e.g. Griffiths and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91" id="160" class="deo:Reference">Pearson 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R178" id="161" class="deo:Reference">Nutt 1982</xref>, 1983). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R179" id="162" class="deo:Reference">Nutt (1983)</xref>, for instance, identifies 16 different environments and analyses how they relate to internal project attributes. The author typifies the identified environments based on the organization’s tendency to be centralized, cost conscious, qualitatively oriented and their mix of skills. A project management approach is proposed to meet the unique demands in each environment. Other papers adopt a more fine- grained approach by detailing the contingency factors for the design of project organization and project management, using task certainty and task interdependence (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="163" class="deo:Reference">Dailey 1978</xref>), sometimes in combination with analyses of specific kinds of projects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="164" class="deo:Reference">Debrabander and Edström 1977</xref>). This trajectory is also evident in papers throughout the 1980s and the 1990s, adding yet more contingency dimensions and more elaborate types of projects. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R155" id="165" class="deo:Reference">Løwendahl (1995)</xref> gives prominence to ‘project task uncertainty’ and ‘parent organization embeddedness’ in her study of an Olympic Games project, and Shenhar and colleagues published a series of papers in top-ranked journals on a ‘typo- logical theory’ (initially based on ‘technological uncertainty’ and ‘system scope’) of project management where contingency theory constitutes the prime theoretical foundation (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Dvir et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar 1998</xref>, 2001; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R208" id="168" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar and Dvir 1996</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R216" id="169" class="deo:Reference">Sommer and Loch (2004)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="170" class="deo:Reference">Pich et al. (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="171" class="deo:Reference">De Meyer et al. (2002)</xref> follow a similar path and suggest a categorization of four fundamental types of project uncertainties: variation, foreseen, unforeseen and<marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> chaos. To this end, they outline a contingency- influenced framework which contrasts types of project management logics and roles of project management (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="176" class="deo:Reference">De Meyer et al. 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R151" id="177" class="deo:Reference">Lindkvist et al. (1998)</xref> consider the significance of type of complexity in conjunction with ‘error problematic’ (as either ‘error detection’ or ‘error diagnostics’) to make sense of project management in time-compressed, large- scale product development projects. A similar, much- cited contribution is by Eisenhardt and Tabrizi (1995, p. 108), who contrast two models for achieving fast adaptation: the ‘compression model’ and the ‘expe- riential model’ with regard to different assumptions about certainty. Their paper contributes to the analysis and understanding of project management in ‘competitive, fast-paced situations’. Several other papers augment the progress of detailed analysis of contingency dimensions, especially with regard to further investigations of different types of projects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="178" class="deo:Reference">Chiesa 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="179" class="deo:Reference">Coombs et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R158" id="180" class="deo:Reference">Lundqvist et al. 1996</xref>). In sum, research within the Contingency School draws on a long and strong tradition in organization theory relating to a variety of contingency dimensions affecting organizational design and structure. In particular, papers illustrate the role of technologi- cal uncertainty, complexity and embeddedness for the design of project management and project organizations. Over time, papers have detailed the analysis with regard to the differences across types of projects as well as deeper investigations into specific contingency dimensions.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="173" page="8" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="174" page="9" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="175" page="9" column="1">161</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="182" confidence="possible" page="9" column="1">Behaviour School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="233" page="9" column="1">In the Behaviour School is found a diverse group of organization-theory inspired research on project organization, organizational behaviour and organization processes. The term ‘behaviour’ is chosen here to accommodate publications with an explicit focus on the organizational behaviour of projects, the processes of organizing, and the nature and organization of social interaction in projects. Accordingly, alternative labels could have been Process, Interaction, Learning or Organizing. In total, 64 papers were classified as being part of Behaviour School research. The first publications in the sample date back to the late 1960s and early 1970s. Here are found <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="183" class="deo:Reference">Wilemon and Cicero (1970)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80" id="184" class="deo:Reference">Gemmill and Wilemon (1970)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R249" id="185" class="deo:Reference">Wilemon and Gemmill (1971)</xref> and Wilemon<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> (1973) on the ‘ambiguities’ and ‘conflicts’ in project management. Among the first publications are also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R198" id="187" class="deo:Reference">Reeser (1969)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95" id="188" class="deo:Reference">Hammerton (1970)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R163" id="189" class="deo:Reference">Melcher and Kayser (1970)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="190" class="deo:Reference">Butler (1973)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R198" id="191" class="deo:Reference">Reeser (1969)</xref> examines the human problems in the ‘project form of organization’ and zeroes in on the ‘anxieties and frustrations’ of people working in a ‘projectized organization’, including the issues of phase-out and temporary relationships. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95" id="192" class="deo:Reference">Hammerton (1970)</xref> discusses the difficulties in projects associated with interdisciplinarity and motivation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R163" id="193" class="deo:Reference">Melcher and Kayser (1970)</xref> analyse an intensive case study of project management action and the troubles of building a team spirit and commitment in project settings. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="194" class="deo:Reference">Butler (1973)</xref> continues along these lines in his study of what he frames as ‘dysfunctional conflicts’ in project management. A number of articles within the Behaviour School consider the challenges and problems of ‘temporary organization’, inspired by the early work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Goodman and Goodman (1972, 1976)</xref>. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R157" id="196" class="deo:Reference">Lundin and Söderholm (1995)</xref> argue that projects have definite characteristics and thus a unique way of life and behaviour compared with permanent organizations. Several authors have adopted a similar dynamic view on projects and project organization. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82" id="197" class="deo:Reference">Gersick (1988, 1989)</xref> provides an interpretation of project teams working under deadline pressure. This research has also informed subsequent studies into the dynamics of projects, particularly regarding the effects of deadlines (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="198" class="deo:Reference">Chang et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="199" class="deo:Reference">Engwall and Westling 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R205" id="200" class="deo:Reference">Seers and Woodruff 1997</xref>). A number of other studies share a similar process- oriented scrutiny of projects as emerging phenomena that inherently change their direction and scope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R135" id="201" class="deo:Reference">Kreiner 1995</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R134" id="202" class="deo:Reference">Kreiner (1992)</xref> suggests that project behaviour follows the idea of a ‘theatre of passion’, where the unpredictability of human behaviour is an essential element of project management. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="203" class="deo:Reference">Engwall (2003)</xref>, although pointing out the importance of institutions and environments, focuses to a great extent on the ‘interior process’ of projects to estab- lish an evolutionary and process interpretation of project organization. Other studies are also found sharing the interest of enhancing the dynamic and behavioural interpretation of projects as organizational forms and processes. Some authors focus on the learning processes in projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="204" class="deo:Reference">Bourgeon 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="205" class="deo:Reference">Brady and Davies 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87" id="206" class="deo:Reference">Grabher 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R113" id="207" class="deo:Reference">Ibert 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R124" id="208" class="deo:Reference">Kim and Wilemon 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R204" id="209" class="deo:Reference">Scarbrough et al. 2004</xref>); others analyse the processes of knowledge sharing and knowledge integration<marker type="page" number="10"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109" id="214" class="deo:Reference">Hoopes and Postrel 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R114" id="215" class="deo:Reference">Ivory et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R175" id="216" class="deo:Reference">Newell et al. 2004</xref>). Here are also found studies dealing with the role of ‘boundary objects’ in projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="217" class="deo:Reference">Boland et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R202" id="218" class="deo:Reference">Sapsed and Salter 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R254" id="219" class="deo:Reference">Yakura 2002</xref>) and the development of trust in interdisciplinary and geographically dispersed projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="220" class="deo:Reference">Bechky 2006</xref>; Jarvenpaa and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R116" id="221" class="deo:Reference">Leidner 1999</xref>). In addition, some studies discuss human behaviour and culture in projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="222" class="deo:Reference">Dadfar and Gustavsson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R168" id="223" class="deo:Reference">Milosevic 2002</xref>), whereas other studies centre on the processes of creativity in projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="224" class="deo:Reference">Bech 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="225" class="deo:Reference">Ekvall 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108" id="226" class="deo:Reference">Holmquist 2007</xref>). An important feature of Behaviour School research is the general critique of the project form as an organizational solution and the dominant static and system-focused view of project management. This is apparent already in the first papers in the data set, and continues to be an important topic in the research published in the 1990s and the 2000s. For instance, some papers focus on particular problems in specific types of projects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Berggren 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97" id="228" class="deo:Reference">Hedlund and Ridderstråle 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R180" id="229" class="deo:Reference">O’Mahony 2003</xref>) and others offer a more general critique of the project form of organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102" id="230" class="deo:Reference">Hodgson 2002</xref>, 2004, 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R118" id="231" class="deo:Reference">Joyce 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R150" id="232" class="deo:Reference">Lindgren and Packendorff 2006</xref>). Research within the Behaviour School typically acknowledges the process and dynamic nature of projects, and investigates time pressure, trust- building, problem-solving, sense-making and learning dimensions to accommodate an analysis of the nature and process of the behaviour of projects.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="211" page="9" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="212" page="10" column="1">162</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="213" page="10" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="234" confidence="possible" page="10" column="1">Governance School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="259" page="10" column="1">In the Governance School, contributions are found that use an economics approach on projects and project management. The majority of papers include applications of either agency theory or transaction cost theory. Alternative labels for this school could be the Economics School or the Contract School. In total, 19 papers were grouped as belonging to the Governance School. Two of the first and most influential references in the Governance School discuss the problems of contracting and governance in the construction industry. The first paper in the data set is written by Stinchcombe (1959), who presents a comparative analysis of bureaucratic and craft administration for production. His study centres on market contracting versus bureaucratic control and the effects of variability in construction projects. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="235" class="deo:Reference">Eccles (1981)</xref>, another and<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> related influential paper, extends Stinchcombe’s investigation with a partial critique of his main finding. He examines subcontracting, and argues that subcontracting is better explained with reference to complexity, size and market extent. In both papers, the authority and administrative problems of projects are essential. The authors connect their analyses to the market–bureaucracy dichotomy and thereby touch upon contracting and transaction cost frameworks. Other papers in this research tradition similarly discuss problems pertaining to contracting and governance in projects. Early examples of contributions are four papers published in the Academy of Management Journal, namely <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R199" id="237" class="deo:Reference">Roman (1964)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84" id="238" class="deo:Reference">Goodman (1967)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R162" id="239" class="deo:Reference">Meinhart and Delionback (1968)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101" id="240" class="deo:Reference">Hodgetts (1969)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R199" id="241" class="deo:Reference">Roman (1964)</xref> discusses the problems of audit and performance evaluation in R&amp;D project management. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84" id="242" class="deo:Reference">Goodman (1967)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101" id="243" class="deo:Reference">Hodgetts (1969)</xref> zero in on the ‘authority problems’ of project organizations and, in view of that, examine the general question of why projects exist. Relying on a game theoretic interpretation, Meinhart and Delionback (1968) focus on the role of contracts and, in particular, the role of incentive contracts in project management. Recent contributions discuss the governance problems observed in projects in strategic alliances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83" id="244" class="deo:Reference">Gerwin and Ferris 2004</xref>), project alliances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="245" class="deo:Reference">Clegg et al. 2002</xref>), project-based international joint ven- tures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R111" id="246" class="deo:Reference">Hung et al. 2002</xref>), mutual organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R130" id="247" class="deo:Reference">Koenig and Thietart 1988</xref>) and complex consortia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R252" id="248" class="deo:Reference">Winch et al. 2000</xref>). Starting from a primary interest in the nature and particularities of construction projects as a case of craft administration, research within this line of research has developed to cover other types of projects, such as research projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="249" class="deo:Reference">Croisier 1998</xref>) and service development projects (van den <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="250" class="deo:Reference">Ende 2003</xref>). The transaction-cost-inspired research reflects an application of the Williamson theory in particularly complex empirical settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R251" id="251" class="deo:Reference">Williamson 1975</xref>), e.g. large-scale construction or offshore projects. The impact of transaction cost economics on the development of management theory is well documented, and hence it is perhaps no surprise that it has also been applied and used in project settings. A key theme revolves around the alternative forms of contracting and governance modes (Lorenzen and Frederiksen 2005; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R234" id="252" class="deo:Reference">Turner and Keegan 2001</xref>). Some of the research focuses on the relationship between project owners and project executers/administrators (see e.g.<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/>  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R235" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Turner and Müller 2004</xref>). Typically, these papers rely on agency theory to explore the difficulties in arran- ging for well-functioning interplay between projects and its external environment, including clients and project owners. Accordingly, there is an interest in understanding the differences in goal preferences and information asymmetry among the actors involved. The Governance School aims to analyse why projects exist and define the appropriate governing mechanisms of projects as a particular kind of administrative problem and complex transaction. In depicting project management largely as a macro- level concern and a strategic management issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R184" id="258" class="deo:Reference">Paul 1984</xref>), Governance School research investigates the overall and contractual aspects, the choice of project contracts and the forms of bilateral or trilateral governance to handle large-scale projects.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="254" page="10" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="255" page="11" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="256" page="11" column="1">163</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="260" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Relationship School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="283" page="11" column="1">The research within the Relationship School has several similarities to both the Governance School and the Behaviour School. However, research within this school draws on alternative theories taken primarily from the fields of inter-organizational relations and marketing. The majority of papers are published in Industrial Marketing Management and the International Business Review, i.e. journals that historically have had, for obvious reasons, a strong marketing origin. Recurrent themes in the papers are network formation and development ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R243" id="261" class="deo:Reference">Welch et al. 1996</xref>), stakeholder interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="262" class="deo:Reference">Elias et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R242" id="263" class="deo:Reference">Welch 2005</xref>), project networks (Hellgren and Stjernberg 1995), project marketing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="264" class="deo:Reference">Cova and Hoskins 1997</xref>) and relational interaction (Larson and Wikström 2007). In total, 19 papers were sorted into the Relationship School. Marketing research contributes to the field of project management by explaining how companies sell and market their projects, how clients buy projects, and how the early stages of a project can be seen as the management and organization of interactions between clients and the contractors. Important to this analysis is the observation of a lack of long- term relationships between the interacting partners, leading authors to discuss the ‘management of dis- continuity’ and its related co-operation problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93" id="265" class="deo:Reference">Hadjikhani 1996</xref>). Even though several studies adopt a process-oriented approach and analyse the formation of networks and relationships between<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> actors, they foremost address projects as complex networks of multiple actors. Studies emphasize, for instance, the high degree of uncertainty, the complex buying process, the long transaction duration and the double fragmentation of buying and selling centres (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R181" id="267" class="deo:Reference">Owusu and Welch 2007</xref>). Several articles address the importance of the early phases of projects as a means of understanding how projects are orga- nized during the implementation phase, what rules- of-the-game are set and what characterizes good co-operation and co-ordination in complex, inter- organizational projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="268" class="deo:Reference">Cova and Hoskins 1997</xref>). For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="269" class="deo:Reference">Cova et al. (1996)</xref> use sociograms to examine institutional and individual actors in the project environment, especially in order to identify the significant actors that are likely to have high influence on the progress of the project. Researchers, for that reason, highlight the complex negotiations and multipart sales processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R144" id="270" class="deo:Reference">Lemaire 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R167" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Millman 1996</xref>) and the importance of forming supplier and buyer alliances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="272" class="deo:Reference">Bansard et al. 1993</xref>). Similar types of network approaches are seen in studies on ‘project networks’, building on the paper by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98" id="273" class="deo:Reference">Hellgren and Stjernberg (1995)</xref>. In these publications, projects are viewed as dynamic networks of multiple actors and firms crossing organizational boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R217" id="274" class="deo:Reference">Staber 2004</xref>). Overall, managing the early phases of projects is typically addressed as a problem of organization and networking which requires appropriate managerial strategies, together with considerable time and resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="275" class="deo:Reference">Bansard et al. 1993</xref>). Accordingly, papers within this tradition typically emphasize the dynamic and social nature of projects. Authors document how firms can formulate projects in various ways, and how they work to influence the perception of projects. The Relationship School gives an alternative to the conventional static view of projects and stresses the relational embeddedness of projects and its social construction (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R211" id="276" class="deo:Reference">Skaates et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R218" id="277" class="deo:Reference">Starkey et al. 2000</xref>). Recent literature on project marketing appears to be as much an attempt to combine knowledge from different areas as it is a means of augmenting the understanding of the conduct in which projects are instigated, how they are built and how they are structured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="278" class="deo:Reference">Cova and Hoskins 1997</xref>). In summary, the Relationship School is largely devoted to research in the management of the early phases of projects, the identification of client needs, the dynamics of project networks, the formulation and formation of projects. Many of the studies rely on single case methodology, principally<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> investigating complex, industrial, international and inter-organizational projects.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="280" page="11" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="281" page="12" column="1">164</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="282" page="12" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="284" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Decision School</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="310" page="12" column="1">The Decision School is characterized by its principal interest in the early phases of projects. Here, scholars are generally occupied with two leading questions: Why are projects instigated, and why are certain decisions made that affect the termination or continuation of a project? In sum, 25 journal articles were grouped as belonging to the Decision School. One major interest in the Decision School is the efforts to explain why projects (or individual actors) that do not follow a rational (decision-making) model work successfully and why some projects that seem to be unwise get implemented despite objec- tive information on ‘bad economies’ ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="285" class="deo:Reference">Davis 1985</xref>). Thus, research examines the use of various strategies and actions during project realization, including ‘rapid-results’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R161" id="286" class="deo:Reference">Matta and Ashkenas 2003</xref>) and ‘outside views’ to deal with ‘over-optimism’ in project decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R154" id="287" class="deo:Reference">Lovallo and Kahneman 2003</xref>). In several ways, these strategies relate to ‘escalating commitment’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R201" id="288" class="deo:Reference">Ross and Staw 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R219" id="289" class="deo:Reference">Staw and Ross 1978</xref>) and the difficulties of terminating ongoing projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="290" class="deo:Reference">Balachandra et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89" id="291" class="deo:Reference">Green et al. 2003</xref>). The most influential publications are by Staw and Ross, published in Administrative Science Quarterly and in the Academy of Management Journal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R200" id="292" class="deo:Reference">Ross and Staw 1986</xref>, 1993; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R219" id="293" class="deo:Reference">Staw and Ross 1978</xref>). The analysis revolves primarily around the early decision processes in complex projects. Their notion of esca- lated commitment is an endeavour to understand the countervailing forces that make it difficult to with- draw from a project despite a poor economic result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R201" id="294" class="deo:Reference">Ross and Staw 1993</xref>, p. 703). Ross and Staw (1993, p. 701) ask the basic questions: ‘how do we get organizations moving, and how do we get them stopped once they are moving in a particular direc- tion?’ The authors argue that the escalation in complex projects/programmes involves the interplay of four sets of determinants: project, psychological, social and organizational determinants. It is also shown that ‘the more ambiguous and changing the economics of a project, the more difficult it will be for an organization to extricate itself from the selected course of action’ (p. 723). In other words, the studies by Staw and Ross bring to light the nature<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> of projects by investigating the role of self- justification and biased information processing in politicized environments. Several studies investigate the difficulties of decision-making in complex projects, including the use of economic calculations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115" id="296" class="deo:Reference">Jansson 1989</xref>), the adverse selection on evaluation decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96" id="297" class="deo:Reference">Harrison and Harrell 1993</xref>), and the politics surrounding projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="298" class="deo:Reference">Dehler 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79" id="299" class="deo:Reference">Gasper 1989</xref>). One important matter is how to make sense of risky projects that get out of control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="300" class="deo:Reference">Charalambos and Dexter 2004</xref>). Important in this line of research is the idea of ‘risk tolerance’ in project-driven organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R137" id="301" class="deo:Reference">Kwak and Scott LaPlace 2005</xref>) and the relevance of options thinking to understand decision-making in complex projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R152" id="302" class="deo:Reference">Lint et al. 2001</xref>). Others examine the role of decision-support systems for the management of projects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="303" class="deo:Reference">Asrilhant et al. 2004</xref>), while other studies concentrate on the political aspects of complex projects. These latter studies normally build further on the original ideas presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R219" id="304" class="deo:Reference">Staw and Ross (1978)</xref>. For instance, several papers address the reasons why software projects escalate and the associated problems with information flows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37" id="305" class="deo:Reference">Conlon and Garland 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R123" id="306" class="deo:Reference">Keil et al. 2003</xref>), whereas others zoom in on the troubles of reporting ‘bad news’ in complex, multi-actor projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R223" id="307" class="deo:Reference">Tan et al. 2003</xref>). Drawing on the notion of ‘future perfect thinking’, a few recent studies bring about the political aspects of public projects (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R191" id="308" class="deo:Reference">Pitsis et al. 2003</xref>) and the idea of projects as ‘political hybrids’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34" id="309" class="deo:Reference">Clegg and Courpasson 2004</xref>). Decision School research focuses primarily on the early stages of projects and underlines the value of in-depth analysis of single cases. Studies typically elicit the political processes inherent in public projects involving a great number of actors, encour- aging the analysis of the information flows, the escalation processes in projects, and the investigation of why good projects die and bad projects survive. Studies within this tradition tend to draw on classic research within psychology and organization theory, in particular, decision-making theories that contrast the rationalistic model of decision-making.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="311" confidence="possible" page="12" column="2">Embracing pluralism</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="339" page="12" column="2">Based on the above review of research on project management, a framework is suggested consisting of seven schools of thought that represent different traditions of research. The identification and categori- <marker type="page" number="13"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> zation of schools of thought in project management research lends support to the idea of theoretical pluralism. It also substantiates the observation that the study of projects and project management has gained increased attention from a wide range of disciplines, including operations research, organization theory, economics, psychology and industrial marketing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R213" id="316" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund 2002</xref>). In the following, the seven schools of thought are compared. To give more detail to the main attention of each school and their respective major influences, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" id="317" class="deo:Reference">Table 2</xref> presents examples of contributions based on citation analysis and selected keywords taken from the summary documents. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3" id="318" class="deo:Reference">Table 3</xref> presents an initial summary of the differences between the schools in terms of main focus and research approach and methodologies. As this table shows, project management research differs considerably, covering various topics with a focus on planning and scheduling of complex tasks, investigations of success factors to achieve project success, organizational structures, organization processes, governance of complex project transactions, formation of project networks and project investment decisions. Some disparity is also observed across the schools concerning their foci of analysis along the stages of the project life cycle. Some schools, such as the Decision School and Relationship School, tend to address the early stages and formation phases of projects, while other schools primarily examine the implementation phase, which, for instance, is the tendency among the bulk of studies in the Factor School and the Contingency School. Drawing on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="319" class="deo:Reference">Hambrick (1990)</xref>, one can also distin- guish differences in terms of the scholarly interest in the dynamic aspects of projects. Some schools treat projects primarily as a static phenomenon (Contingency School), while others adopt a more dynamic view on the development of projects (Behaviour School, Relationship School, Decision School). The former often presents projects from a snapshot view without giving details of its history and evolution. The latter, in contrast, seeks to elicit some of the dynamics involved in projects. Such interest is often seen in the use of longitudinal data or authors’ formulating explicit critique of conventional static interpretations of projects. Some diversity is also noted as to the respective schools’ interest in describing or prescribing, and whether the published papers are primarily based on inductive or deductive research approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="320" class="deo:Reference">Thomas 2006</xref>). For instance, most papers in the Factor School have a strong deductive approach, testing a particular<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> hypothesis, and a prescriptive orientation since ‘per- formance is a dependent construct’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94" id="322" class="deo:Reference">Hambrick 1990</xref>, 247), while Behaviour School research to a much greater extent reports on inductive and descriptive research with limited interest in formulating and testing hypotheses. Typically, a number of these studies embark on a longitudinal research agenda. Now turning to a comparison of how the schools have treated the idea of projects and project management, a few observations should be brought to the fore. First, one might say that a simple and clear-cut definition of projects and project management would be a difficult feat. Like other subfields of management, for instance strategic management (see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="323" class="deo:Reference">Cheaffee 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R174" id="324" class="deo:Reference">Nag et al. 2007</xref>), project management has its share of challenges, problems and opportunities. Looking at the seven schools, some overlap and shared ideas are discerned regarding project definitions, such as temporary, complex or interdisciplinary; at the same time, some interesting divergences are also discovered. In the analysis of the primary definitions of projects and the ideas of project management frequently adhered to, one has definitions of projects as complex sets of activities, complex tasks, organizational structures, organization processes, transactions, networks and large- scale investments. As a consequence, the schools give somewhat different explanations to the role and practice of project management, whether, for instance, the focus primarily is on planning, decision-making, design or network formation. From a theory-development standpoint, the schools hence have various foci and seek to answer, to some extent, different fundamental questions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R214" id="325" class="deo:Reference">Söderlund 2004a</xref>), ranging from the existence of projects, the variation among projects, how they behave, the role of project management, to, finally, the determinants of success and failure of projects. These questions are essential if one is to develop theories of projects and project management, and they are important for each of the schools to develop further, but also for the schools and the emerging perspectives to complement each other in future empirical investigations. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4" id="326" class="deo:Reference">Table 4</xref> presents a comparison of the key questions and the diverse project ideas. It also adds a summarizing ‘project management maxim’ to capture the role and function of project management portrayed in each of the identified schools. As documented in the categorization and analysis, the study elaborates on the polysemic nature of projects and thus acknowledges that projects come in different forms and have multiple meanings (cf. Bre-<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> dillet 2005a,b). Its polysemic nature probably stems from the empirical reality of contemporary projects where they are often, at the same time, considerable public investments and multifaceted organizational processes involving learning, emotions and tangled knowledge integration. Such complexities, one would assume, require a number of theoretical perspectives and research methodologies to be possible to grasp and understand. Hence, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4" id="338" class="deo:Reference">Table 4</xref> offers some substance to a critique of common descriptions of project management research to be discussed further below.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="313" page="12" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="314" page="13" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="315" page="13" column="1">165</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="328" page="13" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="329" page="14" column="1">166</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="330" page="14" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="331" page="14" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="332" page="15" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="333" page="15" column="1">167</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T3">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="334" page="15" column="1">Table 3. Schools of project management research: main focus and research approach</caption>
          <content>
            <table class="DoCO:Table" number="4" page="15">
              <thead class="table"/>
              <tbody>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> Main focus of analysis</td>
                  <td class="table"> Primary research approach and methodologies</td>
                  <td class="table"> Empirical context</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Optimization</td>
                  <td class="table"> Planning, breakdown techniques and scheduling</td>
                  <td class="table"> Logic-based, modeling, simulation,</td>
                  <td class="table"> Engineering,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"> of complex tasks</td>
                  <td class="table"> experiments, static/dynamic</td>
                  <td class="table"> R&amp;D</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Factor</td>
                  <td class="table"> Success factors and project outcomes/project</td>
                  <td class="table"> Surveys, quantitative cross-sectional analysis,</td>
                  <td class="table"> R&amp;D</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"> performance</td>
                  <td class="table"> regression analysis, deductive, static</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Contingency</td>
                  <td class="table"> Project organization design/structure</td>
                  <td class="table"> Surveys, multiple case studies, single case</td>
                  <td class="table"> R&amp;D</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> studies, deductive/inductive, static</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Behaviour</td>
                  <td class="table"> Project organization processes</td>
                  <td class="table"> Case studies, experiments, inductive,</td>
                  <td class="table"> Change,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> longitudinal, dynamic</td>
                  <td class="table"> development</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Governance</td>
                  <td class="table"> Governance of project organizations/</td>
                  <td class="table"> Case studies, deductive, static</td>
                  <td class="table"> Construction</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"> transactions</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Relationship</td>
                  <td class="table"> Management of the formation and development</td>
                  <td class="table"> Case studies, inductive, longitudinal, dynamic</td>
                  <td class="table"> Engineering,</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"> phase of projects</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                  <td class="table"> construction</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> Decision</td>
                  <td class="table"> The interplay among decision-makers in the</td>
                  <td class="table"> Case studies, longitudinal, deductive/inductive,</td>
                  <td class="table"> Public sector, IT</td>
                </tr>
                <tr class="table">
                  <td class="table"> School</td>
                  <td class="table"> (mainly) early stages of projects</td>
                  <td class="table"> dynamic</td>
                  <td class="table"></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </content>
          <region class="TableInfo" id="335" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Main focus of analysis Primary research approach and methodologies Empirical context Optimization Planning, breakdown techniques and scheduling Logic-based, modeling, simulation, Engineering, School of complex tasks experiments, static/dynamic R&amp;D Factor Success factors and project outcomes/project Surveys, quantitative cross-sectional analysis, R&amp;D School performance regression analysis, deductive, static Contingency Project organization design/structure Surveys, multiple case studies, single case R&amp;D School studies, deductive/inductive, static Behaviour Project organization processes Case studies, experiments, inductive, Change, School longitudinal, dynamic development Governance Governance of project organizations/ Case studies, deductive, static Construction School transactions Relationship Management of the formation and development Case studies, inductive, longitudinal, dynamic Engineering, School phase of projects construction Decision The interplay among decision-makers in the Case studies, longitudinal, deductive/inductive, Public sector, IT School (mainly) early stages of projects dynamic</region>
        </region>
        <region class="DoCO:TableBox" id="T4">
          <caption class="deo:Caption" id="336" page="15" column="1">Table 4. Schools of project management research: key questions, ideas and maxims</caption>
        </region>
        <region class="unknown" id="337" page="15" column="1">Key questions/issues investigated Dominant project idea Optimization School How to manage/plan a project? Complex set of activities Factor School What determines project success? Complex task Contingency School Why do projects differ? Organizational structure Behaviour School How do projects behave? Organizational process Governance School How are projects governed? Complex transaction Relationship School How are the early stages of projects Multi-actor network managed and how are projects formed? Decision School Why are projects instigated, why do Large-scale investment they continue to live?</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="340" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Rethinking or taking stock</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="361" page="15" column="1">Authors have stated that there is an ‘extraordinary silence’ on the theoretical side of project management and that ‘an explicit theory is the crucial and <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> single most important issue for the future’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R133" id="343" class="deo:Reference">Koskela and Howell 2002</xref>, p. 1). Similar opinions have been voiced by others in the domain of project management, who emphasize the need to decide on standard- ized definitions and that project management research must develop an overarching unifying theory to be recognized as a ‘proper academic disci- pline’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R230" id="344" class="deo:Reference">Turner 2006a</xref>, p. 1; see also, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R208" id="345" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar and Dvir 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R230" id="346" class="deo:Reference">Turner 2006a</xref>,b,c,d). A number of scholars even argue for the pressing need to ‘rethink project management’ (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R253" id="347" class="deo:Reference">Winter et al. 2006</xref>, p. 642). The present paper provides additional insights into and partial support for this rethinking agenda (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R253" id="348" class="deo:Reference">Winter et al. 2006</xref>, p. 642). The paper has shown that (1) pluralism offers various ‘theories of project management’ and alternative views on projects and their complexity; (2) research has, for several years, been interested in projects as social processes, organizational processes and decision-making processes;<marker type="page" number="16"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> (3) part of project management research has addressed a wide array of success criteria and value creation measurements; (4) there is an evolving plu- ralistic understanding of projects, which offers broad conceptualizations of projects and project management; and (5) theorists and reflective practitioners need to embrace this pluralism, and learn to live with multiple and sometimes competing explorations and explanations. In sum, based on this review, project management research today offers at least a minimum level of pluralism and multiple perspectives to illuminate the complex actuality of projects and project management practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="353" class="deo:Reference">Cicmil et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R203" id="354" class="deo:Reference">Sauer and Reich 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R250" id="355" class="deo:Reference">Williams 2005</xref>). The message is about embracing pluralism and learning to live with contradictions without losing focus and commonality. In that respect, project management as a scientific field needs to strike a balance between pluralist and unification strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R129" id="356" class="deo:Reference">Knudsen 2003</xref>). However, the primary role of the unification strategy is to set the agenda for research, to identify the important topics and questions, and to open up the arenas for sharing research results. Relating to the polysemic nature and multiple meanings of projects, this paper elicits a variety of conceptions and ideas of projects and project management. To some extent, these alternatives are competing; nevertheless, the existence of contrasting versions and definitions of projects are positive signs that are to be welcomed, and which, in the end, might facilitate the progress of research to the level of complexity almost matching that of projects themselves. Different ideas about projects can activate creative thinking about project management and aid fruitful knowledge exchanges with other subfields in management and organization studies. A few noteworthy examples already exist among the papers in the data set. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R208" id="357" class="deo:Reference">Shenhar and Dvir (1996)</xref> introduced a contingency theory and extended this idea in subsequent papers to test the theory on a larger sample in an attempt to explore successes and failures in project management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="358" class="deo:Reference">Dvir et al. 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R120" id="359" class="deo:Reference">Katz (1982)</xref> began with a study similar to other research in the Factor School, but his ideas later influenced follow-up studies in the Behaviour School and investigations into the salient features of projects as temporary organizations. These developments and school-crossings seem critical to producing theories that are sensitive to context yet still build on findings presented in earlier research. Schools are static, but schools develop; so do subfields. Although this paper offers a categorization of<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> project management research, it warns against narrow Balkanization both of the subfield, as such, becoming too distant from the study of management and organization, and schools locking themselves in to develop their own research agenda far from other scholars sharing the interest to develop knowledge about projects and project management. Building on what is known – ‘exploitation’ – is an important act of knowledge development; so is ‘exploration’. Exploitation can, however, be done in several ways: by elaborating further on the research carried out within a particular school; or by crossing schools and combining existing ideas developed in adjacent areas. In the author’s view, this is the best way to handle the balance of exploration and exploitation – between pluralism and unification – within management and organization, and the best way to strengthen the field of project management even further.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="342" page="15" column="2">Project management maxim ‘Optimizing project implementation by planning’ ‘Targeting project management by factors’ ‘Adapting project organization to contingencies’ ‘Shaping processes of project organization’ ‘Governing project organization/ transactions’ ‘Developing relationships and projects’ ‘Politicking and influencing decision-making processes’</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="350" page="15" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="351" page="16" column="1">168</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="352" page="16" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="362" confidence="possible" page="16" column="2">Putting the schools to work</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="370" page="16" column="2">Projects are becoming increasingly multifaceted, involving stakeholders with diverse interests, fast- changing technologies and distributed knowledge bases. As a result, they need to be examined from a number of different perspectives and theoretical lenses to frame accurately the problems facing their initiators, owners, designers and managers. At the same time, projects are vehicles for strategy development and implementation, regional development and places for work. Hence, the spectrum of problems confronting research becomes broader, which emphasizes the importance of connecting project management with other disciplines, such as strategy, economic geography and human resource management. To aid the world of practice, project management scholars would arguably have to provide solutions on how best to design structures which correspond to many challenges facing present-day projects, so that the relevant processes are initiated to take projects to fruition – be that behavioural, social or technical processes. The schools, however, suggest quite contrasting resolutions. Consider the determinants of success and failure – a popular theme in research on project management. Common in the explanations of failed projects in the Optimization School is the flawed use of plans and formalized planning techniques ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R149" id="363" class="deo:Reference">Liberatore and Titus 1983</xref>), while in the Factor School the reasons are addressed in a wider<marker type="page" number="17"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> management context, including top management attention, communication modes, teamwork, project manager skills, monitoring and feedback measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R187" id="368" class="deo:Reference">Pinto and Prescott 1990</xref>). In the Contingency School, the explanations are first and foremost sought in the design of the organization and its adapt- ability to particular contingencies, most notably the technical and environmental complexity and uncertainty. For the Decision School and the Behaviour School, the explanations are chiefly traced in human capacities to deal with information and the underlying reasons for commitments to particular courses of action and decision-making. Decision School research, conversely, tends to position the problem with regard to over-optimism and unrealistic expec- tations, making it nearly impossible for projects to succeed according to conventional success criteria. Finally, the Governance School and the Relationship School view failures predominantly in light of the institutional and inter-organizational environments, fragile governance mechanisms (Governance School) and/or the lack of important relationships with partners and other significant stakeholders (Relationship School). Determining which of the schools offer the best account depends on the focal situation, timing and the person conducting the analysis. Still, the schools and their different ideas of project management play an important role in enhancing understanding of the yet more complex projects of our time. Authors who claim that project management researchers should become a homogeneous group with a shared interest and view of reality with a common epistemology are not only downplaying the contributions of previous and recent research, but may, in fact, be hindering the advancement of in- genious thinking and creative tensions. By following the unification strategy too strongly, the project management community may run the risk of losing the important linkages between the field of project management and related management and organization studies. Thus, specialization wins at the expense of new findings, new ideas and relevance. By embracing pluralism, project management research may be better equipped to explore and explain the difficulties of generating, forming, managing and even killing projects – such analysis would benefit from a com- prehensive view on project processes and the use of multiple theories. As argued, embracing pluralism might lead us forward – to truly acknowledge the many exciting contributions within this fast-growing area of research. However, the schools, in conjunc-<marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> tion with the fundamental questions, discussed earlier, are central to being able to navigate in this land of research opportunities: to know where to start and where to head, what to build on and what to criticize. The schools of project management research presented here could play a part in turning the fragmentation trap where too many theories are produced at too high a speed into a focused creative tension among explanations with the capacity to provide complementary understandings and robust alternative models of project management.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="365" page="16" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="366" page="17" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="367" page="17" column="1">169</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="371" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="372" page="17" column="2">Abernathy, W.J. and Rosenbloom, R.S. (1969). Parallel strategies in development projects. Management Science, 15, pp. 486–505.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="373" page="17" column="2">Adler, P.S. (1995). Interdepartmental interdependence and coordination: the case of the design/manufacturing inter- face. Organization Science, 6(2), pp. 147–167.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="374" page="17" column="2">Adler, P.S. and Mandelbaum, A. (1995). From project to process management: an empirically-based framework for analyzing product development time. Management Science, 41, pp. 458–485.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="375" page="17" column="2">Alter, S. and Ginzberg, M. (1978). Managing uncertainty in MIS implementation. Sloan Management Review, 20(1), pp. 23–31.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="376" page="17" column="2">Asrilhant, B., Meadows, M. and Dyson, R. (2004). Exploring decision support and strategic project management in the oil and gas sector. European Management Journal, 22, pp. 63–73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="377" page="17" column="2">Avots, I. (1969). Why does project management fail? California Management Review, 12, pp. 77–82.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="378" page="17" column="2">Bailetti, A., Callahan, J. and DiPietro, F. (1994). A coordination structure approach to the management of projects. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 41, pp. 394–403.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="379" page="17" column="2">Balachandra, R., Brockhoff, K.K. and Pearson, A.W. (1996). R&amp;D project termination decisions: processes, communication, and personnel changes. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 13, pp. 245–256.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="380" page="17" column="2">Bansard, D., Cova, B. and Salle, R. (1993). Project marketing: beyond competitive bidding strategies. International Business Review, 2, pp. 125–141.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="381" page="17" column="2">Bech, N. (2001). Doors to leading projects: your new chance to understand and perform project leadership. Creativity and Innovation Management, 10, pp. 96–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="382" confidence="possible" page="17" column="2">Bechky, B.A. (2006). Gaffers, gofers, and grips: role-based coordination in temporary organizations. Organization Science, 17, pp. 3–21.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="383" page="17" column="2">Berggren, C. (2004). Global dreams – Local teams: rhetoric and realities of transnational innovation. International Journal of Innovation Management, 8, pp. 115–145.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="388" page="17" column="2">Betts, M. and Lansley, P. (1995). International Journal of Project Management: a review of the first ten years. <marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> International Journal of Project Management, 13, pp. 207–217.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="389" page="18" column="1">Boland, R.J., Lyytinen, K. and Yoo, Y. (2007). Wakes of innovation in project networks: the case of digital 3-D representations in architecture, engineering, and construction. Organization Science, 18, pp. 631–647.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="390" page="18" column="1">Bonner, J.M., Ruekert, R.W., Walker, O.C. Jr (2002). Upper management control of new product development projects and project performance. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 19, pp. 233–245.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="391" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bourgeon, L. (2002). Temporal context of organizational learning in new product development projects. Creativity and Innovation Management, 11, pp. 175–183.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="392" page="18" column="1">Brady, T. and Davies, A. (2004). Building project capabili- ties: from exploratory to exploitative learning. Organization Studies, 25, pp. 1601–1621.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="393" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bredillet, C. (2005a). From the editor: Where do we come from? What are we? Where are we going? Project Management Journal, 36, pp. 3–4.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="394" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bredillet, C. (2005b). From the editor. Project Management Journal, 36, pp. 3–4.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="395" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Bredillet, C. (2007). Exploring research in project management: nine schools of project management research (Part 1). Project Management Journal, 38, pp. 2–6.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="396" page="18" column="1">Bredin, K. and Söderlund, J. (2006). HRM and project inten- sification in R&amp;D-based companies: a study of Volvo Car Corporation and AstraZeneca. R&amp;D Management, 36, pp. 467–485.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="397" page="18" column="1">Bryson, J.M. and Bromiley, P. (1993). Critical factors affecting the planning and implementation of major projects. Strategic Management Journal, 14, pp. 319–337.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="398" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Burns, T. and Stalker, G.M. (1961). The Management of Innovation. London: Tavistock.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="399" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Butler, A.G. (1973). Project management: a study of organizational conflict. Academy of Management Journal, 16, pp. 84–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="400" page="18" column="1">Castells, M. (1996). The Rise of the Network Society. Oxford: Blackwell.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="401" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Chang, A., Bordia, P. and Duck, J. (2003). Punctuated equi- librium and linear progression: toward a new understanding of group development. Academy of Management Journal, 46, pp. 106–117.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="402" page="18" column="1">Charalambos, L.I. and Dexter, A.S. (2004). Turning around runaway information technology projects. California Management Review, 46, pp. 68–88.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="403" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Cheaffee, E.F. (1985). Three models of strategy. Academy of Management Review, 10, pp. 89–98.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="404" page="18" column="1">Chiesa, V. (2000). Global R&amp;D project management and organization: a taxonomy. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 17, pp. 341–359.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="405" page="18" column="1">Cicmil, S., Williams, T., Thomas, J. and Hodgson, D. (2006). Rethinking project management research: researching the actuality of projects. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 675–686.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="406" confidence="possible" page="18" column="1">Clark, K.B. (1989). Project scope and project performance: the effect of parts strategy and supplier involvement on</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="407" page="18" column="2">product development. Management Science, 35, pp. 1247–1263.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="408" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Clark, K.B. and Wheelwright, S.C. (1992). Organizing and leading ‘heavyweight’ development teams. California Management Review, 34, pp. 9–28.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="409" page="18" column="2">Clegg, S. and Courpasson, D. (2004). Political hybrids: Toc- quevillean views on project organizations. Journal of Management Studies, 41, pp. 525–547.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="410" page="18" column="2">Clegg, S.R., Pitsis, T.S., Rura-Polley, T. and Marosszeky, M. (2002). Governmentality matters: designing an alliance culture of inter-organizational collaboration for managing projects. Organization Studies, 23, pp. 317–337.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="411" page="18" column="2">Collin, S.-O., Johansson, U., Svensson, K. and Ulvenblad, P.-O. (1996). Market segmentation in scientific publications: research patterns in American vs European management journals. British Journal of Management, 7, pp. 141–154.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="412" page="18" column="2">Conlon, D.E. and Garland, H. (1993). The role of project completion information in resource allocation decisions. Academy of Management Journal, 36, pp. 402–413.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="413" page="18" column="2">Coombs, R., McKeekin, A. and Pybus, R. (1998). Toward the development of benchmarking tools for R&amp;D project management. R&amp;D Management, 28, pp. 175– 186.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="414" confidence="possible" page="18" column="2">Cooper, D.F. (1976). Heuristics for scheduling resource- constrained projects: an experimental investigation. Management Science, 22, pp. 1186–1194.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="415" page="18" column="2">Cooper, R., Edgett, S. and Kleinschmidt, E. (2001). Portfolio management for new product development: results of an industry practices study. R&amp;D Management, 31, pp. 361– 380.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="416" page="18" column="2">Cova, B. and Hoskins, S. (1997). A twin-track networking approach to project marketing. European Management Journal, 15, pp. 546–556.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="417" page="18" column="2">Cova, B., Mazet, F. and Salle, R. (1996). Milieu as a perti- nent unit of analysis in project marketing. International Business Review, 5, pp. 647–664.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="418" page="18" column="2">Crawford, L., Pollack, J. and England, D. (2006). Uncover- ing the trends in project management: Journal emphases over the last 10 years. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 175–184.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="419" page="18" column="2">Croisier, B. (1998). The governance of external research: empirical test of some transaction-cost related factors. R&amp;D Management, 28, pp. 289–298.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="420" page="18" column="2">Dadfar, H. and Gustavsson, P. (1992). Competition by effec- tive management of cultural diversity. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 22, pp. 81–92.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="421" page="18" column="2">Daft, R.L. and Buenger, V. (1990). Hitching a ride on a fast train to nowhere: the past and future of strategic management research. In Fredrickson, J. (ed.), Perspectives on Strategic Management. New York: Harper, pp. 81–103.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="422" page="18" column="2">Dailey, R.C. (1978). The role of team and task characteristics in R&amp;D team collaborative problem solving and prod- uctivity. Management Science, 24, pp. 1579–1588.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="423" page="18" column="2">Davies, A. and Hobday, M. (2005). The Business of Projects. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="427" page="19" column="1">Davis, D. (1985). New projects: beware of false economies. Harvard Business Review, 63, pp. 95–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="428" page="19" column="1">Davis, E.W. and Heidorn, G. (1971). An algorithm for optimal project scheduling under multiple resource con- straints. Management Science, 17, pp. 803–816.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="429" page="19" column="1">Davis, E.W. and Patterson, J. (1975). A comparison of heuristic and optimum solutions in resource-constrained project scheduling. Management Science, 21, pp. 944– 955.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="430" page="19" column="1">De Meyer, A., Loch, C. and Pich, M. (2002). Managing project uncertainty: from variation to chaos. Sloan Management Review, 43, pp. 60–67.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="431" page="19" column="1">Debrabander, B. and Edström, A. (1977). Successful information system development projects. Management Science, 24, pp. 191–199.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="432" confidence="possible" page="19" column="1">DeCotiis, T.A. and Dyer, L. (1977). The dimensions and determinants of project performance. Industrial Marketing Management, 6, pp. 370–378.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="433" page="19" column="1">DeFillippi, R. and Arthur, M. (1998). Paradox in project- based enterprise: the case of film making. California Management Review, 40, pp. 186–191.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="434" page="19" column="1">Dehler, G.E. (2003). Advocacy, performance, and threshold influences on decision to terminate new product development. Academy of Management Journal, 46, pp. 419–434.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="435" page="19" column="1">Demeulemeester, E. and Herroelen, W. (1992). A branch- and-bound procedure for the multiple resource- constrained project scheduling problem. Management Science, 38, pp. 1803–1818.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="436" page="19" column="1">Drexl, A. (1991). Scheduling of project networks by job assignment. Management Science, 37, pp. 1590–1602.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="437" page="19" column="1">Dumond, J. and Mabert, V. (1988). Evaluating project scheduling and due date assignment procedures: an experimental analysis. Management Science, 34, pp. 101–118.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="438" page="19" column="1">Dvir, D., Lipovetsky, S., Shenhar, A. and Tishler, A. (1998). In search of project classification: a non-universal approach to project success factors. Research Policy, 27, pp. 915–935.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="439" page="19" column="1">Eccles, R. (1981). Bureaucratic versus craft administration: the relationship of market structure to the construction firm. Administrative Science Quarterly, 26, pp. 449–469.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="440" page="19" column="1">Eisenhardt, K. and Tabrizi, B. (1995). Accelerating adaptive processes: product innovation in the global computer industry. Administrative Science Quarterly, 40, pp. 84–110.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="441" page="19" column="1">Ekstedt, E., Lundin, R.A., Söderholm, A. and Wirdenius, H. (1999). Neo-Industrial Organising: Renewal by Action and Knowledge Formation in a Project-Intensive Economy. London: Routledge.</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="442" page="19" column="1">Ekvall, G. (1993). Work: a longitudinal study of a product development project. Creativity and Innovation Management, 2, pp. 17–26.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="443" page="19" column="1">Elias, A., Cavana, R. and Jackson, L.S. (2002). Stakeholder analysis for R&amp;D project management. R&amp;D Management, 32, pp. 301–310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="445" page="19" column="1">Elmaghraby, S.E. and Kamburowski, J. (1992). The analysis of activity networks under generalized precedence <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> relations (GPRs). Management Science, 38, pp. 1245– 1263.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="446" page="19" column="2">van den Ende, J. (2003). Modes of governance of new service development for mobile networks: a life cycle perspective. Research Policy, 32, pp. 1501–1518.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="447" page="19" column="2">Engwall, M. (1998). The ambiguous project concept(s). In Lundin, R.A. and Midler, C. (eds), Projects as Arenas for Renewal and Learning Processes. Boston, MA: Kluwer Academic Publishers, pp. 25–36.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="448" page="19" column="2">Engwall, M. (2003). No project is an island: linking projects to history and context. Research Policy, 32, pp. 789–808.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="449" page="19" column="2">Engwall, M. and Westling, G. (2004). Peripety in an R&amp;D drama: capturing a turnaround in project dynamics. Organization Studies, 25, pp. 1557–1578.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="450" page="19" column="2">Eppinger, S.D. (2001). Innovation at the speed of information. Harvard Business Review, 79(1), pp. 149–158.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="451" page="19" column="2">Ericksen, J. and Dyer, L. (2004). Right from the start: exploring the effects of early team events on subsequent project team development and performance. Administrative Science Quarterly, 49, pp. 438–471.</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="452" page="19" column="2">Ford, R. and Randolph, A. (1992). Cross-functional structures: a review and integration of matrix organization and project management. Journal of Management, 18, pp. 267–294.</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="453" page="19" column="2">Fredrickson, J. (1990). Introduction: the need for perspectives. In Fredrickson, J. (ed.), Perspectives on Strategic Management. New York: Harper, pp. 1–8.</ref>
          <ref rid="R76" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="454" page="19" column="2">Fulkerson, D.R. (1961). A network flow computation for project cost curves. Management Science, 7, pp. 167–178.</ref>
          <ref rid="R77" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="455" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Gaddis, P.O. (1959). The project manager. Harvard Business Review, 37, pp. 89–97.</ref>
          <ref rid="R78" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="456" page="19" column="2">Galbraith, J.R. (1973). Designing Complex Organizations. Reading, PA: Addison-Wesley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R79" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="457" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Gasper, D.R. (1989). Toward a sociology of project assess- ment. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 19, pp. 28–52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R80" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="458" page="19" column="2">Gemmill, G. and Wilemon, D.L. (1970). The power spectrum in project management. Sloan Management Review, 12, pp. 15–25.</ref>
          <ref rid="R81" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="459" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Gersick, C. (1988). Time and transition in work teams: toward a new model of group development. Academy of Management Journal, 31, pp. 9–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R82" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="460" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Gersick, C. (1989). Marking time: predictable transitions in task groups. Academy of Management Journal, 32, pp. 274–309.</ref>
          <ref rid="R83" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="461" page="19" column="2">Gerwin, D. and Ferris, J.S. (2004). Organizing new product development projects in strategic alliances. Organization Science, 15, pp. 22–37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R84" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="462" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Goodman, R.A. (1967). Ambiguous authority definition in project management. Academy of Management Journal, 10, pp. 395–407.</ref>
          <ref rid="R85" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="463" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Goodman, L.P. and Goodman, R.A. (1972). Theater as a temporary system. California Management Review, 15, pp. 103–108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R86" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="464" confidence="possible" page="19" column="2">Goodman, R.A. and Goodman, L.P. (1976). Some management issues in temporary systems: a study of professional</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="468" page="20" column="1">development and manpower: the theater case. Administrative Science Quarterly, 21, pp. 494–501.</ref>
          <ref rid="R87" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="469" page="20" column="1">Grabher, G. (2004). Temporary architectures of learning: knowledge governance in project ecologies. Organization Studies, 25, pp. 1491–1514.</ref>
          <ref rid="R88" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="470" page="20" column="1">Granot, D. and Zuckerman, D. (1991). Optimal sequencing and resource allocation in research and development projects. Management Science, 37, pp. 140–156.</ref>
          <ref rid="R89" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="471" page="20" column="1">Green, S.G., Welsh, M.A. and Dehler, G.E. (2003). Advocacy, performance, and threshold influences on decision to terminate new product development. Academy of Management Journal, 46, pp. 419–434.</ref>
          <ref rid="R90" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="472" page="20" column="1">Grewal, R., Lilien, G. and Mallapragada, G. (2006). Loca- tion, location, location: how network embeddedness affects project success in open source systems. Management Science, 52, pp. 1043–1056.</ref>
          <ref rid="R91" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="473" page="20" column="1">Griffiths, D. and Pearson, A.W. (1973). Planning, control and organizational structure in research and development. Journal of Management Studies, 10, pp. 256–274.</ref>
          <ref rid="R92" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="474" page="20" column="1">Gutierrez, G.J. and Kouvelis, P. (1991). Parkinson’s law and its implications for project management. Management Science, 37, pp. 990–1001.</ref>
          <ref rid="R93" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="475" page="20" column="1">Hadjikhani, A. (1996). Project marketing and the management of discontinuity. International Business Review, 4, pp. 319–336.</ref>
          <ref rid="R94" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="476" page="20" column="1">Hambrick, D.C. (1990). The adolescence of strategic management, 1980–1985: critical perceptions and reality. In Fredrickson, J. (ed.), Perspectives on Strategic Management. Cambridge, MA: Ballinger, pp. 237–253.</ref>
          <ref rid="R95" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="477" page="20" column="1">Hammerton, J.C. (1970). Management and motivation. California Management Review, 12, pp. 51–56.</ref>
          <ref rid="R96" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="478" page="20" column="1">Harrison, P.D. and Harrell, A. (1993). Impact of ‘adverse selection’ on managers’ project evaluation decisions. Academy of Management Journal, 36, pp. 635– 642.</ref>
          <ref rid="R97" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="479" page="20" column="1">Hedlund, G. and Ridderstråle, J. (1995). International development projects: key to competitiveness, impossible or mismanaged? International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 25, pp. 158–184.</ref>
          <ref rid="R98" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="480" page="20" column="1">Hellgren, B. and Stjernberg, T. (1995). Design and implementation in major investments: a project network approach. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 11, pp. 377–394.</ref>
          <ref rid="R99" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="481" page="20" column="1">Henderson, J.C. and Lee, S. (1992). Managing I/S design teams: a control theories perspective. Management Science, 38, pp. 757–777.</ref>
          <ref rid="R100" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="482" page="20" column="1">Hobday, M. (2000). The project-based organization: an ideal form for management of complex products and systems? Research Policy, 29, pp. 871–893.</ref>
          <ref rid="R101" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="483" page="20" column="1">Hodgetts, R.M. (1969). Leadership techniques in project organization. Academy of Management Journal, 11, pp. 211–219.</ref>
          <ref rid="R102" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="484" page="20" column="1">Hodgson, D. (2002). Disciplining the professional: the case of project management. Journal of Management Studies, 39, pp. 803–821.</ref>
          <ref rid="R103" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="485" page="20" column="2">Hodgson, D. (2004). Project work: the legacy of bureaucratic control in the post-bureaucratic organization. Organization, 11, pp. 81–100.</ref>
          <ref rid="R104" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="486" page="20" column="2">Hodgson, D. (2005). Putting on a professional performance: performativity, subversion and project management. Organization, 12, pp. 51–68.</ref>
          <ref rid="R105" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="487" page="20" column="2">Hoegl, M. and Gemeunden, H.G. (2001). Teamwork quality and the success of innovative projects: a theoretical concept and empirical evidence. Organization Science, 12, pp. 435–449.</ref>
          <ref rid="R106" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="488" page="20" column="2">Hoegl, M. and Weinkauf, K. (2005). Managing task interde- pendencies in multi-team projects: a longitudinal study. Journal of Management Studies, 42, pp. 1287–1308.</ref>
          <ref rid="R107" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="489" page="20" column="2">Holloway, C.A., Nelson, R. and Suraphongschai, V. (1979). Comparison of a multi-pass heuristic decomposition procedure with other resource-constrained project scheduling procedures. Management Science, 25, pp. 862–872.</ref>
          <ref rid="R108" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="490" page="20" column="2">Holmquist, M. (2007). Managing project transformation in a complex context. Creativity and Innovation Management, 16, pp. 46–62.</ref>
          <ref rid="R109" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="491" page="20" column="2">Hoopes, D. and Postrel, S. (1999). Shared knowledge, ‘glitches,’ and product development performance. Strategic Management Journal, 20, pp. 837–865.</ref>
          <ref rid="R110" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="492" page="20" column="2">Huchzermeier, A. and Loch, C.H. (2001). Project management under risk: using the real options approach to evaluate flexibility in R&amp;D. Management Science, 47, pp. 85–101.</ref>
          <ref rid="R111" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="493" page="20" column="2">Hung, A., Naidu, G., Cavusgil, S. and Yam, R.C. (2002). An exploratory study of project based international joint ven- tures: the case of Chek Lap Kok Airport in Hong Kong. International Business Review, 11, pp. 505–522.</ref>
          <ref rid="R112" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="494" page="20" column="2">Iansiti, M. (1995). Shooting the rapids: managing product development in turbulent environments. California Management Review, 38(1), pp. 37–58.</ref>
          <ref rid="R113" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="495" page="20" column="2">Ibert, O. (2004). Projects and firms as discordant complements: organisational learning in the Munich software ecology. Research Policy, 33, pp. 1529–1546.</ref>
          <ref rid="R114" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="496" confidence="possible" page="20" column="2">Ivory, C.J., Alderman, N., Thwaites, A., McLoughlin, I. and Vaughan, R. (2007). Working around the barriers to cre- ating and sharing knowledge in capital goods projects: the client’s perspective. British Journal of Management, 18, pp. 224–240.</ref>
          <ref rid="R115" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="497" page="20" column="2">Jansson, D. (1989). The pragmatic uses of what is taken for granted: project leaders’ applications of investment calculations. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 19, pp. 49–63.</ref>
          <ref rid="R116" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="498" page="20" column="2">Jarvenpaa, S.L. and Leidner, T.E. (1999). Communication and trust in global virtual teams. Organization Science, 10, pp. 791–815.</ref>
          <ref rid="R117" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="499" page="20" column="2">Johnson, S.B. (1997). Three approaches to big technology: operations research, systems engineering and project management. Technology and Culture, 38, pp. 891– 919.</ref>
          <ref rid="R118" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="500" page="20" column="2">Joyce, W.F. (1986). Matrix organization: a social experi- ment. Academy of Management Journal, 29, pp. 536– 561.</ref>
          <ref rid="R119" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="504" page="21" column="1">Jugdev, K. and Müller, R. (2005). A retrospective look at our evolving understanding of project success. Project Management Journal, 36, pp. 19–31.</ref>
          <ref rid="R120" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="505" page="21" column="1">Katz, R. (1982). The effects of group longevity on project communication and performance. Administrative Science Quarterly, 27, pp. 81–104.</ref>
          <ref rid="R121" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="506" page="21" column="1">Katz, R. and Allen, T.J. (1985). Project performance and the locus of influence in the R&amp;D matrix. Academy of Management Journal, 28, pp. 67–87.</ref>
          <ref rid="R122" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="507" page="21" column="1">Keegan, A. and Turner, J.R. (2002). The management of innovation in project-based firms. Long Range Planning, 35, pp. 367–388.</ref>
          <ref rid="R123" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="508" page="21" column="1">Keil, M., Rai, A., Cheney Mann, J.E. and Zhang, G.P. (2003). Why software projects escalate: the importance of project management constructs. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 50, pp. 251–261.</ref>
          <ref rid="R124" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="509" page="21" column="1">Kim, J. and Wilemon, D. (2007). The learning organization as facilitator of complex NPD projects. Creativity and Innovation Management, 16, pp. 176–191.</ref>
          <ref rid="R125" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="510" page="21" column="1">King, W.R. and Wilson, T. (1967). Subjective time estimates in Critical Path planning: a preliminary analysis. Management Science, 13, pp. 307–320.</ref>
          <ref rid="R126" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="511" confidence="possible" page="21" column="1">Kirsch, L.J. (1996). The management of complex tasks in organizations: controlling the systems development process. Organization Science, 7(1), p. 121.</ref>
          <ref rid="R127" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="512" page="21" column="1">Klingel, A. (1966). Bias in PERT project completion time calculations for a real network. Management Science, 13, pp. 194–201.</ref>
          <ref rid="R128" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="513" page="21" column="1">Kloppenborg, T.J. and Opfer, W.A. (2002). The current state of project management research: trends, interpretations, and predictions. Project Management Journal, 33, pp. 5–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R129" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="514" page="21" column="1">Knudsen, K. (2003). Pluralism, scientific progress, and the structure of organization theory. In Tsoukas, H. and Knudsen, C. (eds), Oxford University Press Handbook on Organization Theory. Oxford: Oxford University Press, pp. 262–288.</ref>
          <ref rid="R130" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="515" page="21" column="1">Koenig, C. and Thietart, R.-A. (1988). Technology and organization: the mutual organization in the European aero- space industry. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 17, pp. 6–30.</ref>
          <ref rid="R131" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="516" page="21" column="1">Kolisch, R. (1996). Efficient priority rules for the resource- constrained project scheduling problem. Journal of Operations Management, 14, pp. 179–192.</ref>
          <ref rid="R132" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="517" page="21" column="1">Kolodny, H.F. (1979). Evolution to a matrix organization. Academy of Management Review, 4, pp. 543–553.</ref>
          <ref rid="R133" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="518" page="21" column="1">Koskela, L. and Howell, G. (2002). The underlying theory of project management is obsolete. Proceedings of the PMI Research Conference, Philadelphia: Project Management Institute.</ref>
          <ref rid="R134" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="519" page="21" column="1">Kreiner, K. (1992). The postmodern epoch of organization theory. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 22, pp. 37–52.</ref>
          <ref rid="R135" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="520" page="21" column="1">Kreiner, K. (1995). In search of relevance: project management in drifting environments. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 11, pp. 335–346.</ref>
          <ref rid="R136" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="521" page="21" column="2">Kwak, Y.H. and Anbari, F. (2008). Impact on Project Management of Allied Disciplines: Trends and Future of Project Management Practices and Research. Atlanta, GA: PMI.</ref>
          <ref rid="R137" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="522" page="21" column="2">Kwak, Y.H. and Scott LaPlace, K. (2005). Examining risk tolerance in project-driven organization. Technovation, 25, pp. 691–695.</ref>
          <ref rid="R138" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="523" page="21" column="2">Lanford, H.W. and McCann, T.M. (1983). Effective planning and control of large projects: using workbreak- down structure. Long Range Planning, 16, pp. 38– 50.</ref>
          <ref rid="R139" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="524" page="21" column="2">Larson, E. and Gobeli, D. (1987). Matrix management: contradictions and insights. California Management Review, 29, pp. 126–138.</ref>
          <ref rid="R140" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="525" page="21" column="2">Larson, E.W. and Gobeli, D. (1988). Organizing for product development projects. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 5, pp. 180–190.</ref>
          <ref rid="R141" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="526" page="21" column="2">Larson, E.W. and Gobeli, D.H. (1989). Significance of project management structure on development success. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 36, pp. 119–125.</ref>
          <ref rid="R142" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="527" page="21" column="2">Larson, M. and Wikström, E. (2007). Relational interaction processes in project networks: the consent and negotiation perspectives. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 23, pp. 327–352.</ref>
          <ref rid="R143" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="528" page="21" column="2">Lawrence, P.R. and Lorsch, J.W. (1967). Differentiation and integration in complex organizations. Administrative Science Quarterly, 13, pp. 1–47.</ref>
          <ref rid="R144" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="529" page="21" column="2">Lemaire, J.-P. (1996). International projects’ changing patterns: sales engineers’ changing role. International Business Review, 5, pp. 603–629.</ref>
          <ref rid="R145" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="530" page="21" column="2">Levene, R. (1996). The Origins of Project Management. International Encyclopedia of Business and Management, Vol. 5. London: Thomson Business Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R146" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="531" page="21" column="2">Levitt, R.E., Thomsen, J., Christiansen, T.R., Kunz, J.C., Jin, Y. and Nass, C. (1999). Simulating project work processes and organizations. Management Science, 45, pp. 1479– 1495.</ref>
          <ref rid="R147" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="532" page="21" column="2">Levy, F.L., Thompson, G.L. and Weist, J.D. (1963). The ABCs of the Critical Path Method. Harvard Business Review, 41(5), pp. 98–108.</ref>
          <ref rid="R148" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="533" confidence="possible" page="21" column="2">Leybourne, S. (2007). The changing bias of project management research: a consideration of the literatures and an application of extant theory. Project Management Journal, 38, pp. 61–73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R149" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="534" page="21" column="2">Liberatore, M. and Titus, G. (1983). The practice of management science in R&amp;D project management. Management Science, 29, pp. 962–974.</ref>
          <ref rid="R150" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="535" page="21" column="2">Lindgren, M. and Packendorff, J. (2006). What’s new in new forms of organizing? On the construction of gender in project-based work. Journal of Management Studies, 43, pp. 841–866.</ref>
          <ref rid="R151" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="540" page="21" column="2">Lindkvist, L., Söderlund, J. and Tell, F. (1998). Managing product development projects: on the significance of fountains and deadlines. Organization Studies, 19, pp. 931–951. <marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="column" number="1"/><marker type="block"/> Lint, O., Lint, O. and Pennings, E. (2001). An option approach to the new product development process: a case study at Philips Electronics. Preview. R&amp;D Management, 31(2), pp. 163–172.</ref>
          <ref rid="R153" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="541" page="22" column="1">Lorenzen, M. and Frederiksen, L. (2005). The management of projects and product experimentation: examples from the music industry. European Management Review, 2, pp. 198–211.</ref>
          <ref rid="R154" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="542" page="22" column="1">Lovallo, D. and Kahneman, D. (2003). Delusions of success: how optimism undermines executives’ decisions. Harvard Business Review, 81, pp. 56–63.</ref>
          <ref rid="R155" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="543" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Løwendahl, B. (1995). Organizing the Lillehammer Olympic winter games. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 11, pp. 347–362.</ref>
          <ref rid="R156" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="544" page="22" column="1">Lucas, R. (1971). Optimal management of a research and development project. Management Science, 17, pp. 679– 697.</ref>
          <ref rid="R157" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="545" page="22" column="1">Lundin, R.A. and Söderholm, A. (1995). A theory of the temporary organization. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 11, pp. 437–455.</ref>
          <ref rid="R158" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="546" page="22" column="1">Lundqvist, M., Sundgren, N. and Trygg, L. (1996). Remodularization of a product line: adding complexity to project management. Journal of Product Innovation Management, 13, pp. 311–324.</ref>
          <ref rid="R159" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="547" page="22" column="1">MacCormack, A., Verganti, R. and Iansiti, M. (2001). Developing products on ‘Internet Time’: the anatomy of a flexible development process. Management Science, 47, pp. 133–150.</ref>
          <ref rid="R160" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="548" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">March, J.G. (1996). Continuity and change in theories of organizational action. Administrative Science Quarterly, 41, pp. 278–287.</ref>
          <ref rid="R161" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="549" page="22" column="1">Matta, N. and Ashkenas, R.N. (2003). Why good projects fail anyway. Harvard Business Review, 81, pp. 109– 114.</ref>
          <ref rid="R162" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="550" page="22" column="1">Meinhart, W.A. and Delionback, L.M. (1968). Project management: an incentive contracting decision model. Academy of Management Journal, 11, pp. 427–434.</ref>
          <ref rid="R163" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="551" page="22" column="1">Melcher, A.J. and Kayser, T.A. (1970). Leadership without formal authority: the project group. California Management Review, 13, pp. 57–64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R164" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="552" page="22" column="1">Middleton, C.J. (1967). How to set up a project organization. Harvard Business Review, 45, pp. 73–82.</ref>
          <ref rid="R165" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="553" page="22" column="1">Miller, G.A. (1956). The magical number seven, plus or minus two: some limits on our capacity for processing information. Psychological Review, 63, pp. 81–107.</ref>
          <ref rid="R166" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="554" page="22" column="1">Miller, R.W. (1962). How to plan and control with PERT. Harvard Business Review, 40(2), pp. 93–104.</ref>
          <ref rid="R167" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="555" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Millman, T.F. (1996). Global key account management and systems selling. International Business Review, 5, pp. 631–645.</ref>
          <ref rid="R168" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="556" page="22" column="1">Milosevic, D.Z. (2002). Selecting a culturally responsive project management strategy. Technovation, 22, pp. 493– 508.</ref>
          <ref rid="R169" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="557" page="22" column="1">Mintzberg, H. (1990). Strategy formation: schools of thought. In Fredrickson, J. (ed.), Perspectives on Strategic Management. New York: Harper, pp. 105–236.</ref>
          <ref rid="R170" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="558" page="22" column="2">Mintzberg, H., Ahlstrand, B. and Lampel, J. (1998). Strategy Safari: The Complete Guide through the Wilds of Strategic Management. London: Prentice Hall.</ref>
          <ref rid="R171" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="559" page="22" column="2">Morgan, G. (1986). Images of Organization. London: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R172" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="560" page="22" column="2">Morris, P.W.G. (1994). The Management of Projects. London: Thomas Telford.</ref>
          <ref rid="R173" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="561" page="22" column="2">Müller, R. and Turner, R. (2007). The influence of project managers on project success criteria and project success by type of project. European Management Journal, 25, pp. 298–309.</ref>
          <ref rid="R174" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="562" page="22" column="2">Nag, R., Hambrick, D. and Chen, M. (2007). What is strategic management, really? Inductive derivation of a con- sensus definition of the field. Strategic Management Journal, 28, pp. 935–955.</ref>
          <ref rid="R175" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="563" page="22" column="2">Newell, S., Tansley, C. and Huang, J. (2004). Social capital and knowledge integration in an ERP project team: the importance of bridging and bonding. British Journal of Management, 15, pp. 43–57.</ref>
          <ref rid="R176" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="564" page="22" column="2">Nobeoka, K. and Cusumano, M.A. (1997). Multiproject strategy and sales growth: the benefits of rapid design transfer in new product development. Strategic Management Journal, 18, pp. 169–186.</ref>
          <ref rid="R177" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="565" page="22" column="2">Northcraft, G.B. and Wolf, G. (1984). Dollars, sense, and sunk costs: a life cycle model of resource allocation decisions. Academy of Management Review, 9, pp. 225–234.</ref>
          <ref rid="R178" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="566" page="22" column="2">Nutt, P.C. (1982). Hybrid planning methods. Academy of Management Review, 7, pp. 442–454.</ref>
          <ref rid="R179" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="567" page="22" column="2">Nutt, P.C. (1983). Implementation approaches for project planning. Academy of Management Review, 8, pp. 600– 611.</ref>
          <ref rid="R180" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="568" page="22" column="2">O’Mahony, S. (2003). Guarding the commons: how community managed software projects protect their work. Research Policy, 32, pp. 1179–1198.</ref>
          <ref rid="R181" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="569" page="22" column="2">Owusu, R.A. and Welch, C. (2007). The buying network in international project business: a comparative case study of development projects. Industrial Marketing Management, 36, pp. 147–161.</ref>
          <ref rid="R182" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="570" confidence="possible" page="22" column="2">Packendorff, J. (1995). Inquiring into the temporary organization: new directions for project management research. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 11, pp. 319– 334.</ref>
          <ref rid="R183" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="571" page="22" column="2">Parikh, S. and Jewell, W. (1965). Decomposition of project networks. Management Science, 11, pp. 444–459.</ref>
          <ref rid="R184" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="572" confidence="possible" page="22" column="2">Paul, S. (1984). The strategic management of development programs: evidence from an international study. International Studies of Management &amp; Organization, 14, pp. 133–166.</ref>
          <ref rid="R185" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="573" page="22" column="2">Pfeffer, J. (1993). Barriers to the advance of organizational science: paradigm development as a dependent variable. Academy of Management Review, 18, pp. 599–620.</ref>
          <ref rid="R186" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="574" page="22" column="2">Pich, M.T., Loch, C.H. and De Meyer, A. (2002). On uncertainty, ambiguity, and complexity in project management. Management Science, 8, pp. 1008–1023.</ref>
          <ref rid="R187" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="575" page="22" column="2">Pinto, J.K. and Mantel, S.J. (1990). The causes of project failure. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 37, pp. 269–276.</ref>
          <ref rid="R188" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="579" page="23" column="1">Pinto, J.K. and Prescott, J.E. (1988). Variations in critical success over the stages of in the project life cycle. Journal of Management, 14, pp. 5–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R189" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="580" page="23" column="1">Pinto, J.K. and Prescott, J.E. (1990). Planning and tactical factors in the project implementation process. Journal of Management Studies, 27, pp. 305–327.</ref>
          <ref rid="R190" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="581" page="23" column="1">Pinto, M.B., Pinto, J.K. and Prescott, J.E. (1993). Anteced- ents and consequences of project team cross-functional cooperation. Management Science, 39, pp. 1281– 1297.</ref>
          <ref rid="R191" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="582" page="23" column="1">Pitsis, T.S., Clegg, S., Marosszeky, M. and Rura-Polley, T. (2003). Constructing the Olympic dream: a future perfect strategy of project management. Organization Science, 14, pp. 574–590.</ref>
          <ref rid="R192" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="583" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Pollack, J. (2007). The changing paradigms of project management. International Journal of Project Management, 25, pp. 266–274.</ref>
          <ref rid="R193" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="584" page="23" column="1">Poole, M.S. and Van de Ven, A. (1989). Using paradox to build management and organization theories. Academy of Management Review, 14, pp. 542–578.</ref>
          <ref rid="R194" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="585" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Popper, K.R. (1945). The Open Societies and Its Enemies. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</ref>
          <ref rid="R195" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="587" page="23" column="1">Postrel, S. (2007). Do we need a project project? Blog post on the value of project management for strategy research, posted 6 June, 2007, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www" id="586">http://www</ext-link>. organizationsandmarkets.org</ref>
          <ref rid="R196" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="588" page="23" column="1">Prencipe, A. and Tell, F. (2001). Inter-project learning: processes and outcomes of knowledge codification in project-based firms. Research Policy, 30, pp. 1373– 1394.</ref>
          <ref rid="R197" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="589" page="23" column="1">Randolph, W.A. and Posner, B.Z. (1988). What every manager needs to know about project management. Sloan Management Review, 29, pp. 65–73.</ref>
          <ref rid="R198" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="590" page="23" column="1">Reeser, C. (1969). Some potential human problems of the project form of organization. Academy of Management Journal, 11, pp. 459–467.</ref>
          <ref rid="R199" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="591" page="23" column="1">Roman, D. (1964). Project management recognizes R&amp;D performance. Academy of Management Journal, 7, pp. 7–20.</ref>
          <ref rid="R200" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="592" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Ross, J. and Staw, B.M. (1986). Expo 86: an escalation prototype. Administrative Science Quarterly, 31, pp. 274– 297.</ref>
          <ref rid="R201" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="593" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Ross, J. and Staw, B. (1993). Organizational escalation and exit: lessons from the Shoreham nuclear power plant. Academy of Management Journal, 36, pp. 701–732.</ref>
          <ref rid="R202" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="594" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Sapsed, J. and Salter, A. (2004). Postcards from the edge: local communities, global programs and boundary objects. Organization Studies, 25, pp. 1515–1534.</ref>
          <ref rid="R203" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="595" page="23" column="1">Sauer, C. and Reich, B.H. (2007). What do we want from a theory of project management? A response to Rodney Turner. International Journal of Project Management, 25, pp. 1–2.</ref>
          <ref rid="R204" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="597" page="23" column="1">Scarbrough, H., Swan, J., Laurent, S., Bresnen, M., Edelman, L. and Newell, S. (2004). Project-based learning and the role of learning boundaries. Organization Studies, 25, pp. 1579–1600. <marker type="column" number="2"/><marker type="block"/> Seers, A. and Woodruff, S. (1997). Temporal pacing in task forces: group development or deadline pressure? Journal of Management, 23, pp. 169–187.</ref>
          <ref rid="R206" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="598" page="23" column="2">Shenhar, A.J. (1998). From theory to practice: toward a typology of project-management styles. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 45, pp. 33–48.</ref>
          <ref rid="R207" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="599" page="23" column="2">Shenhar, A. (2001). One size does not fit all projects: exploring classical contingency domains. Management Science, 47, pp. 394–414.</ref>
          <ref rid="R208" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="600" page="23" column="2">Shenhar, A. and Dvir, D. (1996). Toward a typological theory of project management. Research Policy, 25, pp. 607–632.</ref>
          <ref rid="R209" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="601" page="23" column="2">Shenhar, A. and Dvir, D. (2007). Project management research: the challenge and opportunity. Project Management Journal, 38, pp. 93–99.</ref>
          <ref rid="R210" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="602" page="23" column="2">Shenhar, A.J., Dvir, D., Levy, O. and Maltz, A.C. (2001). Project success: a multidimensional strategic concept. Long Range Planning, 34, pp. 699–725.</ref>
          <ref rid="R211" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="603" page="23" column="2">Skaates, M.A., Tikkanen, H. and Alajoutsijärvi, K. (2002). Social and cultural capital in project marketing service firms: Danish architectural firms on the German market. Scandinavian Journal of Management, 18, pp. 589–609.</ref>
          <ref rid="R212" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="604" page="23" column="2">Slevin, D.P. and Pinto, J.K. (1987). Balancing strategy and tactics in project implementation. Sloan Management Review, 29, pp. 33–41.</ref>
          <ref rid="R213" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="605" page="23" column="2">Söderlund, J. (2002). On the development of project management research: schools of thought and critique. International Project Management Journal, 6, pp. 20–31.</ref>
          <ref rid="R214" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="606" page="23" column="2">Söderlund, J. (2004a). Building theories of project management: past research, questions for the future. International Journal of Project Management, 22, pp. 183–191.</ref>
          <ref rid="R215" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="607" page="23" column="2">Söderlund, J. (2004b). On the broadening scope of the research on projects: a review and a model for analysis. International Journal of Project Management, 22, pp. 655–667.</ref>
          <ref rid="R216" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="608" page="23" column="2">Sommer, S. and Loch, C. (2004). Selectionism and learning in projects with complexity and unforeseeable uncertainty. Management Science, 50, pp. 1334–1347.</ref>
          <ref rid="R217" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="609" page="23" column="2">Staber, U. (2004). Networking beyond organizational boundaries: the case of project organizations. Creativity and Innovation Management, 13, pp. 30–40.</ref>
          <ref rid="R218" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="610" page="23" column="2">Starkey, K., Barnatt, C. and Tempest, S. (2000). Beyond networks and hierarchies: latent organizations in the UK television industry. Organization Science, 11, pp. 299– 305.</ref>
          <ref rid="R219" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="611" confidence="possible" page="23" column="2">Staw, B.M. and Ross, J. (1978). Commitment to a policy decision: a multi-theoretical perspective. Administrative Science Quarterly, 23, pp. 40–64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R220" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="612" page="23" column="2">Stinchcombe, A.L. (1959). Bureaucratic and craft administration of production. Administrative Science Quarterly, 4, pp. 168–187.</ref>
          <ref rid="R221" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="613" page="23" column="2">Takeuchi, H. and Nonaka, I. (1986). The new new product development game. Harvard Business Review, 64, pp. 137–146.</ref>
          <ref rid="R222" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="614" confidence="possible" page="23" column="2">Talbot, F.B. (1982). Resource-constrained project scheduling with time-resource tradeoffs: the nonpreemptive case. Management Science, 29, pp. 1197–1210.</ref>
          <ref rid="R223" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="618" page="24" column="1">Tan, B., Smith, H.J., Keil, M. and Montealegre, R. (2003). Reporting bad news about software projects: impact of organizational climate and information asymmetry in an individualistic and a collectivistic culture. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 50, pp. 64– 77.</ref>
          <ref rid="R224" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="619" page="24" column="1">Tatikonda, M.V. and Rosenthal, S.R. (2000). Successful execution of product development projects: balancing firmness and flexibility in the innovation process. Journal of Operations Management, 18(4), pp. 401–425.</ref>
          <ref rid="R225" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="620" page="24" column="1">Tavares, L.V. (2002). A review of the contribution of opera- tional research to project management. European Journal of Operational Research, 136, pp. 1–18.</ref>
          <ref rid="R226" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="621" page="24" column="1">Taylor, B.W. and Moore, L. (1980). R&amp;D project planning with Q-GERT network modeling and simulation. Management Science, 26, pp. 44–59.</ref>
          <ref rid="R227" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="622" page="24" column="1">Thamhain, H.J. and Gemmill, G.R. (1974). Influence styles of project managers: some project performance correlates. Academy of Management Journal, 17, pp. 216– 224.</ref>
          <ref rid="R228" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="623" page="24" column="1">Themistocleous, G. and Wearne, S.H. (2000). Project management topic coverage in journals. International Journal of Project Management, 18, pp. 7–11.</ref>
          <ref rid="R229" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="624" page="24" column="1">Thomas, J. (2006). Problematising project management. In Hodgson, D. and Cicmil, S. (eds), Making Projects Critical. London: Palgrave, pp. 90–107.</ref>
          <ref rid="R230" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="625" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. (2006a). Towards a theory of project management: the nature of the project. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 1–3.</ref>
          <ref rid="R231" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="626" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. (2006b). Towards a theory of project management: the nature of project governance and project management. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 93–95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R232" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="627" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. (2006c). Towards a theory of project management: the functions of project management. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 187–189.</ref>
          <ref rid="R233" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="628" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. (2006d). Towards a theory of project management: the functions of project management. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 277–279.</ref>
          <ref rid="R234" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="629" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. and Keegan, A. (2001). Mechanisms of governance in the project-based organization: roles of the broker and steward. European Management Journal, 19, pp. 254– 267.</ref>
          <ref rid="R235" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="630" page="24" column="1">Turner, J.R. and Müller, R. (2004). Communication and co-operation on projects between the project owner as principal and the project manager as agent. European Management Journal, 22, pp. 327–336.</ref>
          <ref rid="R236" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="631" page="24" column="1">Tushman, M.L. (1978). Technical communication in R&amp;D laboratories: the impact of project work characteristics. Academy of Management Journal, 21, pp. 624–645.</ref>
          <ref rid="R237" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="632" page="24" column="1">Urli, B. and Urli, D. (2000). Project management in North America, stability of the concepts. Project Management Journal, 31, pp. 33–43.</ref>
          <ref rid="R238" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="633" page="24" column="1">Vaaland, T.I. and Håkansson, H. (2003). Exploring inter- organizational conflict in complex projects. Industrial Marketing Management, 32, pp. 127–138.</ref>
          <ref rid="R239" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="634" page="24" column="2">Van de Ven, A. (2007). Engaged Scholarship: A Guide for Organizational and Social Research. New York: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R240" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="635" page="24" column="2">Van Maanen, J. (1995). Style as theory. Organization Science, 6, pp. 133–143.</ref>
          <ref rid="R241" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="636" page="24" column="2">Weglarz, J. (1981). Project scheduling with continuously divisible, doubly constrained resources. Management Science, 27, pp. 1040–1053.</ref>
          <ref rid="R242" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="637" page="24" column="2">Welch, C. (2005). Multilateral organizations and international project marketing. International Business Review, 14, pp. 289–305.</ref>
          <ref rid="R243" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="638" page="24" column="2">Welch, D., Welch, L. and Young, L. (1996). Network development in international project marketing and the impact of external facilitation. International Business Review, 5, pp. 579–602.</ref>
          <ref rid="R244" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="639" page="24" column="2">Wiest, J.D. (1981). Precedence diagramming method: some unusual characteristics and their implications for project managers. Journal of Operations Management, 1(3), pp. 121–130.</ref>
          <ref rid="R245" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="640" page="24" column="2">Whittington, R.A., Molloy, E., Mayer, M. and Smith, A. (2006). Practices of strategizing/organizing: broadening strategy work and skills. Long Range Planning, 39, pp. 615–629.</ref>
          <ref rid="R246" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="641" page="24" column="2">Whittington, R., Pettigrew, A., Peck, S., Fenton, E. and Conyon, M. (1999). Change and complementarities in the new competitive landscape: a European panel study, 1992–1996. Organization Science, 10, pp. 583–600.</ref>
          <ref rid="R247" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="642" page="24" column="2">Wilemon, D.L. (1973). Managing conflict in temporary systems. Journal of Management Studies, 10, pp. 282–296.</ref>
          <ref rid="R248" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="643" page="24" column="2">Wilemon, D.L. and Cicero, J.P. (1970). Project manager: anomalies and ambiguities. Academy of Management Journal, 13, pp. 269–282.</ref>
          <ref rid="R249" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="644" page="24" column="2">Wilemon, D.L. and Gemmill, G.R. (1971). Interpersonal power in temporary system. Journal of Management Studies, 8, pp. 315–328.</ref>
          <ref rid="R250" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="645" page="24" column="2">Williams, T. (2005). Assessing and moving on from the dominant project management discourse in the light of project overruns. IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, 52, pp. 497–508.</ref>
          <ref rid="R251" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="646" page="24" column="2">Williamson, O.E. (1975). Markets and Hierarchies. New York: Free Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R252" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="647" page="24" column="2">Winch, G., Clifton, N. and Millar, C. (2000). Organization and management in an Anglo-French consortium: the case of Transmanche link. Journal of Management Studies, 37, pp. 663–685.</ref>
          <ref rid="R253" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="648" page="24" column="2">Winter, M., Smith, C., Morris, P. and Cicmil, S. (2006). Directions for future research in project management: the main findings of a UK government-funded research network. International Journal of Project Management, 24, pp. 638–649.</ref>
          <ref rid="R254" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="649" page="24" column="2">Yakura, E.K. (2002). Charting time: timelines as temporal boundary objects. Academy of Management Journal, 45, pp. 956–970.</ref>
          <ref rid="R255" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="650" page="24" column="2">Zobel, A.M. and Wearne, S. (2000). Project management topic coverage in recent conferences. Project Management Journal, 31, pp. 32–37.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="385" page="17" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="386" page="18" column="1">170</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="387" page="18" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="424" page="18" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="425" page="19" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="426" page="19" column="1">171</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="465" page="19" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="466" page="20" column="1">172</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="467" page="20" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="501" page="20" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="502" page="21" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="503" page="21" column="1">173</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="537" page="21" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="538" page="22" column="1">174</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="539" page="22" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="576" page="22" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="577" page="23" column="1">Pluralism in Project Management</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="578" page="23" column="1">175</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="615" page="23" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="616" page="24" column="1">176</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="617" page="24" column="1">J. Söderlund</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="651" page="24" column="2">© 2010 The Author International Journal of Management Reviews © 2010 British Academy of Management and Blackwell Publishing Ltd.</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
